<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Baqiongshijinshibuzheng" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://sueyling:sueyling@data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/webdav/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
        <title>Baqiong Shi jinshi buzheng</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="zh">
        <title>八瓊室金石補正</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
        <title>Supplementary Corrigenda to the Epigraphica of Eight Gems Studio</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="zh" type="abbreviated">
        <title>八瓊</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="en" type="abbreviated">
        <title>Baqiong</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference" displayLabel="Baqiong shi jinshi buzheng">
        <title>Baqiong Shi jinshi buzheng</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <abstract>The present form of the well-known Supplementary Corrigenda to the Epigraphica of Eight Gems Studio (Baqiongshi jinshi buzheng 八瓊室金石補正), 
        was only compiled in 1925, but its information dates from the life time of its author, Lu Zengxiang 陸增祥 (1833-1889).  
        Lu Zengxiang begins his entry on Mount Gang with the rubbings of the inscriptions on Chicken Beak Rock. 
        The names of the signatories with the date (E) as well as the three Buddha names (D1) he transcribes in full. 
        Of the two sections of the sutra C1 and C2 he quotes the beginning and the end, but, as usual, he does not identify the text. 
        From the Lankāvatara sutra version A he quotes two sections  and from version B nine sections.  
        He notes that Ruan Yuan records none of these eleven sections, but that the rubbings, which he consults, must come from Mount Gang, 
        because the labels on them say so. Only a future visit can bring certainty, he notes. (LL)</abstract>
    <name xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#luzengxiang" type="personal">
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="family">Lu</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="given">Zengxiang</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">陸</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">增祥</namePart>
        <namePart type="date">1833-1889</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>This work gives for every inscription entry the measurements, the amount of columns,
        the location, a transcription and a commentary concerning older literature. For the Gangshan
        entries Lu Zengxiang remarks that although his eleven entries are not found in the older
        literature, he assumes that they all belong to Mount Gang because the notes on the rubbings
        say so. He is aware of the fact that the inscriptions on Mount Jian and Mount Tie are
        connected to those of Mount Gang, as was stated in Shanzuo jinshi zhi. Certainty about the
        location of the inscriptions can only be brought about a future visit.</abstract>
    <extension>130 <hi rend="italic">juan </hi>
        <foreign lang="zh">卷</foreign>
    </extension>
    <!--<physicalDescription>
        <extent>
            <detail type="fascicle">130</detail>
        </extent>
    </physicalDescription>-->
    <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>1925</dateIssued>
        <!--<dateOther>130 vols</dateOther>-->
    </originInfo>
    <tableOfContents>fascicles 12-16: 北魏, fascicles 17-19: 東魏, facsicles 20-22: 北齊, fascicle 23: 北周，
        facsicles 24-28: 隨, facsicles 29-78: 唐</tableOfContents>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="SKSLXB" type="host">
        <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
            <title>Shike shiliao xinbian</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo lang="zh">
            <title>石刻史料新編</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <part>
            <detail level="1" type="series">
                <number>1</number>
            </detail>
            <detail level="2" type="volume">
                <number type="start">6</number>
                <number type="end">8</number>
            </detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>6.3947</start>
                <end>8.6129</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
        <typeOfResource collection="yes"/>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>