<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Birnbaum1989a" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo lang="en">
        <title>Secret Halls of the Mountain Lords: The Caves of Wu-t’ai shan</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Birnbaum 1989a</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#birnbaum" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="en" type="family">Birnbaum</namePart>
        <namePart lang="en" type="given">Raoul</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>Birnbaum distinguishes four types of caves found at Mount Wutai: 1. dwelling caves; 2.
        paradise caves of the Mountain Lords; 3. manifestation caves; 4. Cave of Initiatory Rebirth
        1. For caves used as dwelling places on Mount Wutai, Birnbaum quotes T#2074: 51, 175b:
        大方廣佛華嚴經感應傳, an eighth century compendium of tales. 2. Most important among the paradise
        caves is Diamond Grotto 金剛窟. This cave was seen as the home of the Mountain Lord 山神.
        Birnbaum translates the story found in the Ancient Chronicle of Mount Clear and Cool 古清涼傳
        (by Huixiang 慧祥, T#2098; 51: 1092c-1100c; ca. 679) of Monk Xiangyun 祥雲 encountering the 山神
        on Mount Wutai, who says that he lives in Diamond Grotto. Birnbaum quotes the 水經注 (dating to
        309) by Li Daoyuan 麗道元 (d. 526; edited by Wang Xianqian 王先謙 in 1892) with the earliest story
        about people habiting Mount Wutai (also quoted in T#2098; 51: 1093a). Daoist cosmological
        views: grotto-heavens 洞天, discussed in the early sixth century revelations of the Zhengao 真誥
        (see Rolf A. Stein, Le monde en petit. Paris 1987, 289-290). When Buddhists took over the
        Mount Wutai territory, the Diamond Grotto was recognized as the home of Wenshu. Translation
        of quotation from the 古清涼傳 T#2098; 51:1094c-1095a. This text, in turn, quotes from the Map
        of Jetavana (Qihuan tu 祇洹圖; full title Zhong tianzhu Sheweiguo Qihuan Si tu jing 中天竺舍衛國祇洹寺圖經
        Illustrated Sutra of the Jetavana Monastery in Śrāvastī, Central India, T#1899;
        45:882b-896b), composed in 667 by Daoxuan 道宣. Diamond Grotto is taken over by the Buddhists
        by means of: 1. legitimation through appeal to antiquity (early Buddhas of the Auspicious
        Aeon); transfer of numinous power (numinous places have distinctive physiognomic features);
        3. grotto of a storehouse for treasures (musical instruments and sacred texts). At the time
        of the second major mountain monograph: 廣清涼傳 by Yan Yi 延一 (in the 1070s), Diamond Grotto as
        dwelling place of Wenshu was firmly established. Story of Buddhapāli who met Manjusri at
        Mount Wutai in 676, then returned to India to fetch a text, came back to Chang’an in 683,
        took the volume to Mount Wutai and was received by manjusri in Diamond Grotto (廣清涼傳, T#2099;
        51: 1111a-b). This story was already well known when Ennin 圓仁 came in the middle of the
        ninth century. Diamond grotto was also the place of the visions of the famous Pure Land
        Master Fazhao 法照 (story in T#2099, 51: 1114a-1115b) who founded Bamboo Grove Monastery 竹林寺.
        Then the story about the Monk Wuzhuo 無著, who failed to enter Diamond Grotto in time (T#2099,
        51: 1111b-1112c). The personal travel diary attributed to the Northern Song official Zhang
        Shangying 張商英, the Xu Qingliang zhuan 續清涼傳 (T#2100, 51: 1133a), says that Diamond Grotto
        connectes to Amitabha’s Pure Land in the West. T#2100, 51: 1105a: Diamond Grotto is linked
        to underground waterways. The Nārayāna Grotto 那羅延窟 is also a dwelling place of Manjusri. The
        name is derived from the Huayan jing, chapter ob dewelling places for bodhisattvas. Ennin
        visited the cave. Also T#2099, 51: 1126b. 3. Manifestation caves are the Cave of Guanyin 觀音洞
        (1984 last manifestation) and the Cave of Shancai 善財洞, the pilgrim hero of the Gandavyuha,
        since the Tang a chief attendant of Manjusri. Possibly influenced by the Cave of the
        Buddha’s Reflection at Nagarahāra. Since the middle of the ninth century cultic activities
        centered on Guanyin at Putuo Shan. "A significant factor underlying the initial inspiration
        to establish a cultic center at P’u-t’o Shanmay well have been the example of Wu-t’ai Shan."
        4. Birnbaum gives a report on his personal visit in the Cave of Initiatory Rebirth, also
        known as Cave of the Mother of Buddhas 佛母洞. </abstract>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#CdEA" type="host">
        <titleInfo lang="en">
            <title>Cahiers d’Extrême-Asie</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <date>1989</date>
            <detail type="volume">5</detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>115</start>
                <end>140</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>