<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Birnbaum2004" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd"><titleInfo lang="en"><title>Light in the Wutai Mountains</title></titleInfo><titleInfo type="reference"><title>Birnbaum 2004</title></titleInfo><name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#birnbaum" type="personal"><namePart lang="en" type="family">Birnbaum</namePart><namePart lang="en" type="given">Raoul</namePart><role><roleTerm>author</roleTerm></role></name><abstract>DH cave 159, west wall, Two Views of Wutai Mountain. Images appearing in balls of light.
    218: ... light associated with Wutaishan lends credibility to the powerful narrative put forth by Chinese Buddhists that these mountains are the earthly residence of a key figure of the Buddhist pantheon, Wenshu pusa. Narratives about these extraordinary phenomena thus are an important factor in the great shift in attitude that takes place in the mid-Tang period (by the mid-eighth century), in which Buddhists reconceive religious geography and begin to see China not as a borderland subordinate to the Indian Buddhist heartland, but as a central territory within the Buddhist world (footnote: see Birnbaum, Buddhist Encounters with the Wutai Mountains). The living bodies of buddhas and great sages may glow or emit flashes of
    219: light, and the replica bodies—the images and to represent these beings, to recreate their bodily forms—will do the same.
    220-221: description of the light experience (the experience of pure consciousness or luminous mind) of Hanshan Deqing (1546-1623) in 1575: the cooking pot had become covered with dust
    222: "... unusual experiences are reported at sites of power, such as the great pilgrimage mountains, and in the presence of objects of power, such as relics of accomplished persons of the past."
    </abstract><relatedItem xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#Kapstein2004" type="host"><titleInfo><title>The Presence of Light: Divine Radiance and Religious Experience</title></titleInfo><originInfo><issuance>monographic</issuance></originInfo><part><extent unit="page"><start>195</start><end>226</end></extent></part></relatedItem></mods>