<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Nattier2014" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo lang="en">
        <title>Now You Hear It, Now You Don’t: The Phrase ‘Thus Have I Heard’ in Early Chinese Buddhist Translations</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Nattier 2014</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#nattier" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="en" type="family">Nattier</namePart>
        <namePart lang="en" type="given">Jan</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>page 8: the formula 吾從佛聞如是 that occurs in T#701, T#500, T#212) was borrowed from Kang Mengxiang 康
        孟詳 (fl. 190-220), who produced a biography of the Buddha, the Zhong benqi jing 中本起經 (T#196).
        T701 is credited to An Shigao in the Taishō edition, but attributed to Dharmarakṣa by Sengyou.
        page 8, note 26: Jingying Huiyuan wrote three commentaries to the Bath-house Sutra (T#701): T#1764, T#1776, T#1793.
        page 17: This formula was subsequently adopted in just three other texts, two of which are sūtras (T500, Luoyun renru jing 羅云忍辱經; T701, Wenshi xiyu zhongseng jing 溫室洗浴眾僧經; and within the text, though not at the beginning, of T212, Chu yao jing 出曜經). None of these, however, can be dated with assurance to the period with which we are concerned. Their adoption of this usage, in fact—
        complete with the first-person pronoun wu 吾, which is highly unusual in this context—suggests that their renditions were not arrived at independently, but were borrowed directly from Kang Mengxiang’s work.</abstract>
    <language>
        <languageTerm>en</languageTerm>
    </language>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <relatedItem xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#Sen2014" type="host">
        <titleInfo lang="en">
            <title>Buddhism Across Asia. Networks of Material, Intellectual and Cultural Exchange. Volume 1</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>monographic</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>39</start>
                <end>64</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>