<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Nattier2007" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo lang="en">
        <title>Avalokiteśvara in Early Chinese Buddhist Translations: A Preliminary Survey</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Nattier 2007</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#nattier" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="en" type="family">Nattier</namePart>
        <namePart lang="en" type="given">Jan</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>185: “...the now-standard name Guanshiyin 觀世音(often abbreviated Guanyin 觀音) came into
        use only around the beginning of the fifth century CE.” The earliest names for the
        bodhisattva are in translation Kuiyin 窺) 音 in the Fa jing jing 法鏡經 Ugraparipṛcchā-(sūtra by
        An Xuan 安玄 and Yan Fotiao 嚴佛調 and in transcription Elouxuan 廅樓亘 in T#361, which probably
        goes back to the form *Avalokasvara . In early Chinese translations, Avalokasvara appears
        only as a member of the audience listening to the Buddha preaching, and plays an extremely
        minimal role. It becomes only an object of devotion in the two earliest translations of the
        larger Sukhāvatīvyūha, that by Lokakṣema (T #361) and by Zhi Qian (T#362). 198: Both
        translations “recommend that ordinary pratitioners who find themselves in difficulty should
        turn to them [i.e. Avalokasvara and Mahāsthāmaprāpta] for aid” In a second appearance of
        Avalokasvara in Zhi Qian’s translation, he receives his prediction (vyākarana) of his futur
        buddhahood from Buddha Amitābha. 200-201: Nattier translates T#361, 12:288b19-24 202:
        Avalokasvara as the successor of Amitābha Buddha “The most dramatic passage concerning
        Avalokasvara, however, occurs in a prose portion of the sūtra and is found in th
        etranslations of both Lokakṣema and Zhi Qian. For it is here that we are told that, after
        the death of Amitābha Buddha, Avalokasvara will succeed him as the reigning Buddha of
        Sukhāvati.” “With the exception of the name of the Buddha Amitābha—which is transcribed as
        Amituo 阿彌陀 throughout Lokakṣema’s version, but translated as Wuliang qingjing 無量清淨
        “Measureless Purity” by Zhi Qian—the wording of the two versions is virtually identical...”
        203: Nattier translates T#362, 12:309a14-24 2What we have here, in brief, is an account of
        the succession of one Buddha by another that is traditional in a certain sense, in that it
        adheres to the principle that there can only be one Buddha in any given world-system at a
        time. Thus Avalokasvara must remain a bodhisattva until after the death of Amitābha Buddha;
        only then can he [sic!] attain buddhahood himself.” “What is far from traditional, however,
        is the speed with which this takes place: Avalokasvara immediately attains buddhahood after
        the death of 204. Amitābha...” “...in Sukhāvatī the succession to the next Buddha is
        immediate. Amitābha’s land is thus presented as a “perpetual buddha-field” in the sense that
        the Dharma will never die out.” BUT: Other version of the Larger Sukhāvatīvyūha in Sanskrit,
        Tibetan and later Chinese versions, have “no reference to Amitābha’s final nirvāna; only the
        mentions of his immeasurably long lifespan...” This scenario “is profoundly continuous with
        what we find in another early Pure Land text, the Akṣobhyavyūha, which is also considered to
        have been translated by Lokakṣema or a member of his school(Achu foguo jing 阿閦佛國經, T313). In
        this scripture ... much attention is paid to Akṣobhya’s dramatic final nirvāna, and it is
        also clear that no other bodhisattva can attain buddhahood in this world after his death.
        Taken together, these scriptures suggest that an important turning point in the evolution of
        Pure Land thought took place when all references to the eventual extinction of Amitābha were
        eliminated, and only the discussion of his immeasurable lifespan remained. “ 205: “In the
        larger Sukhāvatīvyūha we are told that he [Avalokasvara] can serve as a refuge for people in
        this world who are in need of help, that he has been predicted to buddhahood (at least in
        Zhi Qian’s version), and that he will succeed to the position of presiding Buddha of
        Sukhāvatī after Amitābha’s death.” Conclusions: “...the inclusion of the larger
        Sukhāvatīvyūha within the corpus of Han-period translations...” “... Avalokasvara’s first
        significant appearance ... is in the larger Sukhāvatīvyūha-sūtra, translated during the late
        second century CE (if by Lokakṣema himself) or perhaps slightly later (if by another member
        of his school). This version was available in the first half of the third century to Zhi
        Qian, who used it .... as the basis for his own translation.” 206: “Nonetheless it seems
        clear that it was through the work of Dharmaraksa—specifically, through the twenty-third
        chapter of his Lotus Sūtra, the Guangshiyin wumen pin 光世音五門品—that this bodhisattva first
        gained widespread appeal in China. For though we have found small traces of the veneration
        of this bodhisattva under the name Elouxuan, it was as Guangshiyin that he first became to
        be widely worshipped in China.” </abstract>
    <language>
        <languageTerm>en</languageTerm>
    </language>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <relatedItem xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#Magee_Huang2007" type="host">
        <titleInfo lang="en">
            <title>Bodhisattva Avalokiteśvara (Guanyin) and Modern Society</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <name>
            <namePart lang="en" type="family">Magee</namePart>
            <namePart lang="en" type="given">William</namePart>
            <role>
                <roleTerm>editor</roleTerm>
            </role>
        </name>
        <name>
            <namePart lang="en" type="family">Huang</namePart>
            <namePart lang="en" type="given">Yi-hsun</namePart>
            <role>
                <roleTerm>editor</roleTerm>
            </role>
        </name>
        <originInfo>
            <dateIssued>2007</dateIssued>
            <publisher>
                <name type="corporate">Dharma Drum Publications</name>
            </publisher>
            <place>
                <placeTerm>Taipei</placeTerm>
            </place>
            <issuance>monographic</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>181</start>
                <end>212</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
  
</mods>