<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd" ID="Nattier1991">
    <titleInfo lang="en">
        <title>Once Upon a Future Time: Studies in a Buddhist Prophecy of Decline</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Nattier 1991</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="personal" ns2:href="#nattier">
        <namePart lang="en" type="family">Nattier</namePart>
        <namePart lang="en" type="given">Jan</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>on the relation of the Diamond Sutra and the Lotus Sutra with regard to moshi 末世
        thought. 33-34 The (Sanskrit) Diamond has four references to a "Five hundred After-years"
        period. In the first of these the Buddha’s disciple Subhuti asks (in the translation of
        Edward Conze) whether there will be any beings who will understand teachings such as those
        contained in this sutra "in the future period, in the last time, in the last epoch, in the
        last five hundred years, at the time of the collapse of the good doctrine" The Buddha
        replies that such beings will indeed exist, and goes on to describe the merits of these
        bodhisattvas. Three other passages are virtually identical in wording, conveying the same
        sense of anxiety concerning the “last five hundred years.” Kumarajiva renders these passages
        quite distinct from the Sankrit (note 18, p. 34) 如來滅後後五百歲 “after the Buddha’s extinction,
        during the five hundred after-years”（8.749a28&gt;, 來世後五百歲"in the future age, during the five
        hundred after-years”（8.750b5) 於後末世 “in the latter final age”（8.751al) 未來世 “in the future
        age” (8.751cl7). 35-37 parallel passages appar in the Lotus Sutra 36: In the Diamond Sutra
        we have little to go on, for in all four instances this passage appears suddenly, with no
        necessary connection to the surrounding text. One gets the impression, at least from the
        Sanskrit texts, that the composer of this sutra was merely repeating a set of stock phrases
        adopted from another source. p. 36, note 23: the Candragarbhasutra gained such influence
        (especially in East Asia) that its 2,500-year system was often read back into the Diamond
        Sutra, the Lotus Sutra, and other such works by commentators. note 24: It is noteworthy that
        these references to a period of five hundred years are not found in the rest of the
        Prajnaparamita sutras (in particular, those such as the Astasahasrika-prajnaparamita-sutra
        and the Ratnagunasamcayagatha, which are known to be older than the Diamond Sutra). p. 86:
        several of the sutras that in East Asia became most closely identified with the division of
        the Buddha’s Dharma into sequential periods —in particular, the Pure Land and Lotus sutras—
        do not apply a distinction between saddharma and saddhaima- pratirupaka to the teachings of
        Sakyamuni Buddha himself. The reading of these texts as if they contained such a distinction
        (supplemented by a third period otmo-fa, to be discussed below) is thus a contribution of
        later commentators, who in interpreting these texts through such a lens gave them an
        entirely new meaning. p. 97 on xiangfa in the Lotus, which does not appear in the same
        context as the moshi and eshi. </abstract>
    <relatedItem type="series">
        <titleInfo lang="en">
            <title>Nanzan Studies in Asian Religions<!-- 1--></title>
        </titleInfo>
        <part>
            <detail type="volume">
                <number>1</number>
            </detail>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
    <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>1991</dateIssued>
        <place>
            <placeTerm>Berkeley, CA</placeTerm>
        </place>
        <publisher>
            <name type="corporate">
                <namePart lang="en">Asian Humanities Press</namePart>
            </name>
        </publisher>
        <issuance>monographic</issuance>
    </originInfo>
</mods>