<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Nylan2010" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd"><titleInfo lang="en"><title>Wandering in the Ruins. The <hi rend="italic">Shuijing zhu</hi> Reconsidered</title></titleInfo><titleInfo type="reference"><title>Nylan 2010</title></titleInfo><name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#nylan" type="personal"><namePart lang="en" type="family">Nylan</namePart><namePart lang="en" type="given">Michael</namePart><role><roleTerm>editor</roleTerm></role></name><abstract>63: “This is also an essay about memory and loss”, “an essay about cultural identity”. “...about contexts, structures, and modes of discourse that appeared in the post-Han period of disunion.” “...Li’s work ... posits the existence of a fundamental and enduring unity that we might call an “empire of memory,” whose shadowy existence prevails through time, invisible to the naked eye and heedless of temporary political arrangements.”
        64: “...Li’s detailed verbal maps of no fewer than 1,252 rivers and waterways”
        “Historians, geographers, archaeologists, art historians, and historians of religion have culled material from Li Daoyuan’s “guidebook” for over a millennium, presuming the basic accuracy of its historical statements and attributing the vast majority of the discrepancies between the Commentary and various geographical treatises either to insufficient knowledge on Li’s part or to inadvertent interpolations and copyists errors after Li’s time.”
        “Li’s Shuijing zhu ... posits an empire that represents a collection of memories about the past—some of them faulty—that cluster around and haunt a range of sites, including steles, temples, boundary markers, stone chambers (leading to tombs?), inscribed stone coffins, local shrines, bronze inscriptions, and rock carvings, even when—or rather, especially when—these sites 
        65: are ruined or incomplete.” “That Li has crafted a supremely artful guide to people’s perceptions of the past—especially the distant past—is hardly the same thing as saying that he has transcribed extant records that he came across.”
        66: “...figures from myth and history-including immortals and gods are ranged side-by-side in such accounts with historical figures....”
        67: “for Li Daoyuan, the very best that individuals can aspire to is to tie their good names through tangible commemorative sites that mark the supreme majesty of the land-though those sites may perish.”
        68: “...readers are given meticulous measurements for the dimension of the Langya 琅邪 stele erected in the south by the First Emperor of Qin in the twenty-sixth year of his reign, when not a single line of the inscription praising
        the Emperor is quoted.”
        “Li attempts to transcend the realities of competition and war, conflict and division, in order to conjure the image of a unified tradition devoted to the common project of commemorating all that is worthy of remembering in the past. Even when there is “nothing to see,” Li Daoyuan makes us “see” the absence as part of the landscape and feel its effect on passersby.”
        70: “Li, we should remember, was living in a society that presumed the capacity of ritual enactments to unify people of vastly different tastes and backgrounds and to consecrate the countryside. Hence Li’s exhaustive catalogues of the major ritual centers he encounters, including the Eastern Han sites of the National Academy (Taixue 太學), Circular Moat (Biyong 辟雍); and Numinous Terrace (Lingtai 靈臺), the Stone Classics composed by Cai Yong and the transcription onto six slabs of  Wei Wendi’s 魏文帝 (r. 220–226) “Dian lun” 典論. Especially long and evocative are Li’s entries on the temples erected to the various Mountain Peak deities in China and his descriptions of the temples erected to the Sage, Confucius,...”
        77: “This essay has tried to introduce the alternative view that encounters between individuals and their geographies depend less upon their accumulated sensory receptions of the surrounding geography than upon their pre-existing conceptions about man’s place in time.”
        “Implicitly, this essay seeks to demonstrate that none of the three works should be regarded by modern researchers as altogether straightforward accounts of the distant past. As much as by what they omit to see and to mention as by their seemingly casual remarks, such books have shaped perceptions of “empire” and “authority” for moralists and skeptics alike over many generations.”
        94, note 3: “Usually nine years (515–524) are given as the date of compilation, but there is material in the book that dates well into the 530s, so we must imagine later editors and interpolators.”
    </abstract><relatedItem xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#Chan_Lo2010" type="host"><titleInfo lang="en"><title>Interpretation and Literature in Early Medieval China</title></titleInfo><name><namePart lang="en" type="family">Chan</namePart><namePart lang="en" type="given">Alan K. L.</namePart><role><roleTerm>editor</roleTerm></role></name><name><namePart lang="en" type="family">Lo</namePart><namePart lang="en" type="given">Yuet-Keung</namePart><role><roleTerm>editor</roleTerm></role></name><originInfo><dateIssued>2010</dateIssued><publisher><name type="corporate">State University of New York Press</name></publisher><place><placeTerm>Albany</placeTerm></place><issuance>monographic</issuance></originInfo><part><extent unit="page"><start>63</start><end>101</end></extent></part></relatedItem></mods>