<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="HanZhao2006" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
        <title>Qianxi Tang dai shideng—jianji yu Riben Jingdu Anxiang Si shideng de bijiao</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="zh">
        <title>淺析唐代石燈<hi rend="dash">──</hi>兼及與日本京都安祥寺石燈的比較</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
        <title>A Preliminary Analysis of Tang Stone Lanterns—Together with a Comparison with the
            Stone Lantern of Anshō-ji in Kyōto, Japan</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Han Zhao 2006</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#hanzhao" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">韓</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">釗</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>This article discusses surviving stone lanterns (without sutra/dharani texts) of the Tang and compares it with
        lanterns in Japan and Korea. The earliest surving stone lantern is from the Northern Qi, 
        in Tongzi Monastery (Tongzi Si 童子寺) in Taiyuan 太原. Han Zhao lists the following Tang
        stone lanterns:
        (1) Hebei Langfang 廊坊Longfu Si 隆福寺stone lantern. 3.4 m high, dated 668. 
        (2) Shanxi Changzi 長子Faxing Si 法興寺 stone lantern. 2.04 m high, dated 773. 
        (3) Xi’an Beilin bowuguan stone lantern with 7 tiers (originally 9 tiers). Originally from Shaanxi Qian Xian 乾縣 
        Xihu Cun 西湖村 Shiniu Si 石牛寺. 1.8 m high. A dragon coils around the lower part of the shaft below an octagonal basin.
        (4) Xi’an shi wenwu baohu kaogusuo stone lantern. Excavated in 1976 in Xi’an. 1.43 m high. Only the base and the shaft have remained. 
    A dragon coils around the latter.
    (5) Heilongjiang 黑龍江 Ningan 寧安 Xinglong Si 興隆寺 stone lantern. Bohai 渤海囯 kingdom (713–926). 6 m high. 
    Octagonal lantern top. Round lotus shaft. Octagonal lotus base.
    Han Zhao divides the surviving lanterns into two categories: "capital lanterns" 京畿型 and "provincial lanterns" 地方型.
    "Capital lantern" have coiling dragons (蟠龍石柱) as imperial symbols. No 3 and 4 belong to that category, as well as a stone lantern 
    allegedly brought from Tang China to Ansho-ji in Kyōto (https://anshouji.or.jp/about/detail/). 
    Stone lantern have come to Korea and Japan together with the Budhist teaching. Quite a few have survived from the 
    United Silla period in Korea. The largest one (慶州國立博物館), measuring 5 m in height, has an octagonal shaft on which nothing is written.
    In Japan, lanterns with an octagonal shaft disappear later. From the Kamakura 鐮倉 period (1192-1337) onwards, 
    lantern pillars with a hexagonal or square shaft were thriving.</abstract>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#" type="host">
        <titleInfo lang="zh">
            <title>西部考古</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
            <title>Xibu kaogu</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <detail type="volume">1</detail>
            <!-- <detail type="no"></detail>-->
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>453</start>
                <end>461</end>
            </extent>
            <date>2006</date>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>