<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Harrist2008" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo lang="en">
        <title>The Landscape of Words: Stone Inscriptions from Early and Medieval China</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Harrist 2008</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <subject>
        <hierarchicalGeographic>
            <province>Shandong</province>
        </hierarchicalGeographic>
        <topic/>
        <temporal>Northern Dynasties</temporal>
    </subject>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#harrist" type="personal">
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="family">Han</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="given">Wenbin</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">韓</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">文彬</namePart>
        <namePart lang="en" type="family">Harrist</namePart>
        <namePart lang="en" type="given">Robert E. Jr.</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>p. 24: The term moya, however, refers only to a
        particular medium-unquarried stone that remains in its original setting. Ancient
        theories of writing claim that the invention of Chinese characters was inspired by
        the discovery of patterns in nature-tracks of birds, markings on the backs of tortoises,
        or heavenly constellations.28 (: The classic formulation of this concept of the origins of writing appears in the "Postface"
        of Xu Shen’s "Shuowen jiezi xu," 2-3. See also Chaves, "Legacy of Ts’ang Chieh.") Although these concepts of how writing originated
        belong to the realm of myth, moya inscriptions do, in a sense, return writing
        to nature. Other supports for writing require manufacture or exacting preparation:
        bronze has to be cast, silk has to be woven, bamboo or wooden slips have to be
        trimmed, and the stone for a freestanding stele must be quarried and shaped. But
        inscriptions on cliffs or boulders, on surfaces that the landscape painter Guo Xi (ca.
        1000-ca. 1090) called "the bones of the earth," make use of material provided directly
        by nature itself,29 (Guo Si, "Linquan gaozhi," 639.) Not only were the surfaces for inscriptions free, but there was
        little regulation of access to sites where they accumulated.
        p. 276: To the list of characteristic embodiments of literati culture can be added, I
        believe, the <hi rend="italic">moya</hi> inscriptions that began to appear in large numbers during the Song
        period, especially in the twelfth and thirteenth centuries. Who visited scenic areas
        and historic sites? Literati in possession of the education and cultural sophistication
        to appreciate such excursions. By leaving behind their names at the sites they visited,
        these men signified to a public readership their participation in activities that defined
        their class, or the class with which they wished to be associated.</abstract>
    <originInfo>
        <place>
            <placeTerm>Seattle and London</placeTerm>
        </place>
        <publisher>
            <name type="corporate">
                <namePart lang="en">University of Washington Press</namePart>
            </name>
        </publisher>
        <dateIssued>2008</dateIssued>
    </originInfo>
</mods>