<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="He_Li1987" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://claudia:claudia@data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/webdav/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
        <title>Mianyang Bishui Si moya zaoxiang</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="zh">
        <title>綿陽碧水寺摩崖造像</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
        <title>Cliff Sculptures of Bishui Monastery in Mianyang</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>He and Li 1987</title>
        <!--<title>He Zhiguo and Li Qitang 1987</title>-->
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#hezhiguo" type="personal">
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="family">He</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="given">Zhiguo</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">何</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">志國</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#liqitang" type="personal">
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="family">Li</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="given">Qitang</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">李</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">其堂</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>碧水寺在綿陽市區涪江北岸的碧水崖邊，背依龟(龜?)山 Jade Water Temple is situated in the city of Mianyang on
        the northern bank of Fu River, Mount Gui in its back. The temple was built right in front of
        Mount Gui’s cliff; it has altogether 18 niches, 2 on the south wall, 16 on the west wall.
        The article gives a description of the sculptures of in niches 1, 4, 5, and 16, one by one,
        and of the Diamond sutra. Niche 1 contains Buddha Amitabha, Guanyin and Dashizhi.Niche 4
        same identification. Niche 5 contains altogether 44 figures; three of those are the main
        trias. Some of the remaining 41 figures have been substituted in clay. Originally, it should
        have been more than 41 subsidiary figures, but how many have been setroyed is hard to say.
        Main Buddha in niche 16 is also identified as Amitabha. Diamond sutra has more than 4000
        characters craved in grid, in kaishu. One fifth of the characters are already weathered.
        《綿陽縣誌。奇現》as text source. The sculptures are said to date in the Tang dynasty because its
        style is close to the sculpture in caves Wanfodong 万佛洞, Laolongdong 老龍洞 and 惠簡洞 Huijiandong
        in Longmen. The sculptures in niche 1 are likened to a Guanyin dated 681 (Gaozong Yonglong
        2)outside of Wanfodong 万佛洞. Besides, the sculptures of Bishuisi are similar to the Daoist
        figures of Yunüquan 玉女泉. Many of those carry votiv inscriptions; therefore it is known that
        they were made between 610 and 871. The 《綿陽縣誌。奇現》has the following report:
        大观元年(1107年)冬与表弟都奉郎李益侯。。。。观先辈郡守李同叔所建水阁院(即现碧水寺)。 北崖， 正观时令狐文轨施造经像，极工致，叹其历会昌以来渐暗淡，遂醵金彩绘，焕然生色。,
        testifying that in 1107 the niches of Bishuisi were restaurated.Gilding traces in niche 5
        are linked to this Song restoration. The 《綿陽縣誌。金刚》further has “字体秀逸，是隋唐间笔意“. Note that the
        《綿陽縣誌》either makes a mistake in transcribing the name of the alleged donor,狐文轨, or the Song
        donors made a mistake in transcribing this name’s second character. A more recent report
        (Yu_Wang2009)could identify the donor as 狐元軌 whose activities have been transmitted in
        several miracle stories among the Buddhist canon. The present report also gives a
        description of the stone cut Guanyin that is 3,13 m high. It was excavated in Kaiyuansi 開元寺
        and moved to Bishuisi. The 《綿陽縣誌》also has a report on the sculptures of Kaiyuansi saying
        that „有正观，总章，会昌等年号“. Therefore, the Bishuisi Guanyin is held to be a famous image of the
        Tang dynasty. Bishuisi was called 水阁院 during the Tang and Song dynasties. In 1800 (´Qing
        Jiaqing 5) a hall was built on top of the ruins, and during the renovation of 1806 (Jiaqing
        11) it received its present name.</abstract>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#SichuanWenwu" type="host">
        <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
            <title>Sichuan wenwu</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo lang="zh">
            <title>四川文物</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <date>1987</date>
            <detail type="no">3</detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>36</start>
                <end>38</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>