<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="FeiYong2021" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
        <title>Liuchao fojiao zaoxiang dui Chaoxian bandao ji Riben de yingxiang</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="zh">
        <title>六朝佛教造像對朝鮮半島及日本的影響</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="translated" lang="en">
        <title>The Impact of Buddhist Statuary of the Six Dynasties on the Korean Peninsular and
            Japan</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Fei Yong 2021</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <abstract>p. 292-293: In the middle of the 6th century, Buddhist statuary in the Shaanxi region
        clearly received influences from Southern China. A group of five standing Buddha statues of
        the Northern Zhou, excavated in 2004, and a statue excavated in 2007 are characterized in
        style as baoyi bodai yanhua shi 褒衣薄帶演化式 (loose gown with a wide girdle). Prototypes are
        among the Wanfo Si finds (wsz10, wsz1, wsz6, wsz3, wsz2, wsz4.) The author does not mention
        the fact that all these single Buddha statues show the same mudra, right hand raised in
        abhaya-mudrā 施無畏 (fearlessness), left hand showing variations of varada-mudrā 施愿印
        (wish-granting). The torso of a Northern Zhou statue excavated in Xi’an, Weiyangqu 未央區,
        north-west of Zhongcha Village 中查村, in November 2004, seems to hold a jewel in the left hand
        (fig. 5-93 on p. 244). Information on this statue in 中國社會科學院考古研究所.
        古都遺珍--長安城出土的北周佛教造像.文物出版社2010年版 (<ref type="biblio" target="GuduYizhen2010"/>). 
        p. 262: At the end of the 5th century, most Buddhas and bodhisattvas show 
        abhaya-mudrā 施無畏 (fearlessness) with the right hand, and varada-mudrā 施愿印
        (wish-granting) with the left. 
        
        如意珠  cintā-maṇi, a wish-granting jewel. Said to be obtained from the dragon-king of the sea, or
        the head of the great fish, Makara, or the relics of a Buddha</abstract>
    <name xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#feiyong" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">費</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">泳</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>2021</dateIssued>
        <place>
            <placeTerm transliteration="pinyin">Beijing</placeTerm>
            <placeTerm lang="zh">北京</placeTerm>
        </place>
        <publisher>
            <name type="corporate">
                <namePart transliteration="pinyin">Zhongguo shuju</namePart>
                <namePart lang="zh">中華書局</namePart>
            </name>
        </publisher>
        <issuance>monographic</issuance>
    </originInfo>
</mods>