<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Adamek2017" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
  <titleInfo lang="en">
    <title>Traces of the Sanjie (Three Levels) Movement at Baoshan</title>
  </titleInfo>
  <titleInfo type="reference">
    <title>Adamek 2017</title>
  </titleInfo>
  <name xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#adamek" type="personal">
    <namePart lang="en" type="family">Adamek</namePart>
    <namePart lang="en" type="given">Wendi Leigh</namePart>
    <role>
      <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
    </role>
  </name>
  <abstract> Introduction (p. 9–11) Backgrounds (p. 11–13) The “Final Age” Context of the
    Soteriologies of Lingyu and Xinxing (p. 14–15): “Significantly, Kumārajīva’s ... translation of
    the Diamond Sūtra in 401 led to the dissemination of its [Final Age] soteriology. This
    influential scripture provided a foundation for the argument that in the final Age, even the
    simplest practices have special significance. In it we find a kind of predestination doctrine
    that during the five hundred years after the Buddha’s death (hou wubai sui 後五百歲), those who
    cultivate the precepts and immediately give rise to faith in the scripture’s teachings are
    thereby proved to be those who have already cultivated the roots of virtue (p. 14) with numerous
    Buddhas, and are in effect already enlightened. Then the pratitioner is assured that men and
    women who recite and remember the Diamond Sūtra in the Final Age gain more merit than they could
    possibly comprehend.” Dazhusheng Cave and Lingyu (p. 16–17): “The scriptural selections carved
    inside and outside the cave include assurances of efficacy, and scripts for intense ritual
    practice. The passages seem to be centered on motivating practice through the difficult Final
    Age.” “We cannot be certain that Lingyu was solely responsible for the selection of texts at
    Dazhusheng. However, the carved references to the efficacy of repentance, the responsiveness of
    the Buddhas, and the ultimate dharmadhātu (realm of reality) signifying emptiness of defilement
    all correspond with Lingyu’s Dilun-based practice and teaching, as characterized in his Baoshan
    mortuary inscription and Xu gaoseng zhuan biography.” The Candragarbha-sūtra (p. 17–19):
    translated 566 in Ye by Narendrayaśas. The passage carved at Baoshan’s Dazhusheng Cave’s
    southwest inner wall by the door (T#397, 13: 363a25–b22) coincides with excerpts 26, 27, and 28
    carved at Jinchuanwan (Xinxing 3) from the Chapter on the Periodization of Jambudvīpa. The
    Confession-Repentance Liturgy (p. 20–26): “At Baoshan, the repentance liturgy known as the Lüe
    li qijie foming chanhui deng wen 略禮七階佛名懺悔等文 (Abridged Seven-Roster Buddhanāma and
    Confession-Repentance Text...) is inscribed at the farthest west of the lower register to the
    west (left) when one faces the Dazhusheng doorway from the outside. The apparent source of the
    confessional script is the Jueding pini jing 決定毗尼經 (Vinayaviniścaya-Upāliparipṛcchā-sūtra, Sūtra
    of the Inquiry of Upāli Regarding Determination of the Vinaya), a portion of which is closely
    reproduced. The wall includes two other scriptural sources with supplemental lists of Buddha
    names...” (p. 20). Translation of Chanhui wen carved : p. 21-22 (transcription will be given in
    her still unpublished book). “Moving toward the cave door from this liturgy and vow, there are
    more inscriptions that provide the practitioner with lists of names of the Buddhas of the ten
    directions beginning with Sumerupradīpaprabhāsa, the names of the thirty-five Buddhas of
    confession of the Jueding pini jing, and the names of the fifty-three Buddhas ... and the upper
    register has an additional list of twenty-five Buddha names from the Foming jing...” “Inside the
    cave ... the seven Buddhas of the past ... thirty-five Buddhas ...” (p. 22) “While Dazhusheng’s
    inscribed lists of Buddha names clearly correspond to “registers” in the liturgy, the names and
    images outside and inside the cave overspill the boundaries of any particular ritual structure,
    exhibiting duplications and substitutions.” (p. 24) “In the Baoshan context, Lingyu’s
    understanding of the way that repentance accesses Buddha-responsiveness and dharmadhātu is
    captured in a repentance poem (prayer) attributed to him in the fayuan zhulin ..., entitles
    Zongchan shi’e jiwen 總懺十惡偈文 (Verses on Comprehensive Repentance for the Ten Evil Deeds).” T53:
    918c23–919a27. (p. 25) Repentance and Sanjie Practice (p. 26–32) “The movement’s progenitor
    Xinxing may have been a student of Daoping, and thus could have been Lingyu’s fellow disciple.”
    (p. 26) “The Sanjie movement is perhaps most famous for its “inexhaustible treasury” (wujinzang
    無盡藏). Drawing on the Avataṃsaka notion of an “inexhaustible merit treasury” (wujin gongde zang
    無盡功德藏) compounded by the merit-transfer of the great bodhisattvas, Xinxing preached that access
    to the inexhaustible merit field was actualized by the devotee’s practice of universal and
    non-discriminatory giving.” (p. 27) “...some of the seventh-century Baoshan inscriptions for
    monks and nuns show their adherence to Sanjie-style asceticism, including corpse exposure.
    However, for ordinary practitioners the Sanjie program, centered on the practices of universal
    respect and universal giving.” (p. 28) p. 29--32 on Jinchuanwan is problematic, because Adamek
    knows the inscription on the west wall only from Zhang Zong (presentation at Columbia University
    2008), and he did not give a transcription of the carved text. That means that Adamek is not
    aware how short the surviving text portion is. She makes the following mistrake, as indicated on
    p. 31, note 84: "Zhang, Zhongguo Sanjiejiao shi, does not provide a transcription of the
    Jinchuanwan text, and there are over a hundred variants of the Qijie foming jing in the Dunhuang
    cache. I used Yabuki’s edition of S. 59 as a representative Sanjie version of the text..." “At
    Jinchuanwan cave we find a design with elements that clearly mark it as a Sanjie site, while
    echoing the foundational Buddha-name liturgy at Dazhusheng. ... The practice program enshrined
    at Jinchuanwan thus appears to be some seventy years later than Dazhusheng, and also postdates
    references to Sanjie-style practices in the Baoshan inscriptions.” (p. 29) “Like the Chanhui wen
    at Dazhusheng, Xinxing’s Qijie foming jing was centered on Buddha-name recitation of the
    thirty-five Buddhas from the Jueding pini jing. It also includes numerous other elements that
    echo the carvings at Dazhusheng.” (p. 30) “Xinxing’s liturgical complement to the Qijie foming
    jing is his Zhouye liushi fayuan fa 晝夜六時發願法 (Vows for the Six Periods of Day and Night; a.k.a.
    Lifo chanhui wen 禮佛懺悔文, Text of Repentance in Obeisance before the Buddhas), which further
    specifies the ritual sequence for each of the six daily periods.” (p. 31) “While drawing from a
    similar repertoire of texts as the Baoshan community and perhaps influenced by them, Xinxing
    provided a greater degree of elaboration and specificity regarding the structure and
    significance of Buddhanama repentance practice. ... Lingyu’s ... role in creating the site
    [Baoshan] is not mentioned in his 632 memorial niche. ... his involvement with Lingquan temple
    is only made explicit in the Xu gaoseng zhuan. In contrast, the later cave at Jinchuanwan was
    clearly designed as a repository of Xinxing’s teachings, both his own writings and his chosen
    sutras...” Proscriptions against Sanjie (p. 32–34) Relics and Forest Interment (p. 35–43): “The
    most dramatic link connecting Baoshan, Sanjie, and corpse exposure is the mortuary inscription
    for Xinxing’s disciple, Dhyāna Master Lingchen 靈琛” (629). Adamek gives a translation of the lost
    inscription after epigraphical sources (p. 40–42). Adamek opposes the claim made by Liu Shufen
    that 58 Baoshan inscriptions from the late sixth century point at corpse-exposure of former
    Sanjie monks and nuns (p. 38). Baoshan Inscriptions Describing Corpse Exposure (p. 44–56):
    Contains translations of inscriptions next to ash-body stupas 灰身塔 with enshrined mortuary
    images, namely of Dhyāna Master Jinggan 靜感(561–646), nun (p. 46–48) and Dharma Master Huixiu 慧休
    (547-646), monk (p. 48–55) Conclusions (p. 56–58): “Baoshan’s Sanjie connections are thus part
    of an eclectic assemblage that gives the place and its practicescape a distinctive identity,
    without being tied to any particular devotional cult, movement, or practice specialization.....
    four types of affirmation of especially dedicated practice in the memorials reviewed above. One
    is allusion to signature Sanjie practices. The second is description of making an image
    representing the deceased in a shrine for his or her relics. The third is description of the
    deceased’s practice of corpse exposure. The fourth is reference to the deceased as a “supernal
    appearance” (shenyi)” (p. 57) </abstract>
  <relatedItem xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#Poceski2017" type="host">
    <titleInfo lang="en">
      <title>Communities of Memory and Interpretation. Reimagining and Reinventing the Past in East
        Asian Buddhism</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <originInfo>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
    </originInfo>
    <part>
      <extent unit="page">
        <start>9</start>
        <end>68</end>
      </extent>
    </part>
  </relatedItem>
</mods>