<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="GeChengyong2017" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
        <title>Randeng qifu hu jiyue—Xi’an beilin cang sheng Tang Fojiao ‘randeng shitai zan’ yishu
            xinzhi</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="zh">
        <title>燃燈祈福胡伎樂<hi rend="dash">──</hi>西安碑林藏盛唐佛教‘燃燈石臺贊’藝術新知</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
        <title>Foreign Music for Lamp-Lighting Prayers—New Insights Into the Art of Buddhist ‘Stone
            Base Hymns of Lamp-Lighting’ of the High Tang Kept in the Forest of Steles in
            Xi’an</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Ge Chengyong 2017</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#gechengyong" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">葛</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">承雍</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>Lamp-lighting prayers are common rites of religious worship (Buddhism, Daoism,
        Zoroastrianism, Manichaeism) since the Northern Qi dynasty. In the 1950ies, a “lamp-lighting
        stone stand” 燃燈石臺 entered the collection of the Forest of Steles. It shows foreign
        musicians. Octagonal shaft, 1.2 m high. The original base and top are lost. Place of origin
        unknown. The title of the carved text is 燃燈石臺讚並序 , written by Li Xian 利憲, Prince of Ning 寧王.
        Transcription of the text given in simplified characters. The text names two palace
        officials as donors (府使蘇公, i.e. Su Sixu 蘇思勖, who died in 745, and Magistrate Tang 判官唐公). It
        is dated 大唐開元嵗次辛巳月直大火八日康申建 . 開元嵗次辛巳 is kaiyuan 29 (July 25, 741, if 月直大火 is the sixth month). 
        After the date, the names and
        occupational titles of 66 male musicians are given, followed by a dedication to the emperor,
        empress, the crown prince, the imperial princes, all military and civil officials, beings
        reborn in the six paths and all the people (兆庶). The titles and names of these 66 persons
        reveal that this is a heterogeneous group with members who had access to various parts of
        the palace, probably members of some kind of an association 社, maybe a lamp-lighting
        association 燃燈社. The author lists 8 stone lanterns (without the Azure Dragon lantern) and
        analyses in more detail the Langfang 廊坊 stone pillar (dated 688, the lantern on top is gone
        missing), which also features dancers and musicians. The eternal light pillar from Langfang
        has 16 niches with Buddha figures in 2 rows on the upper part of the shaft, and the lower
        part of the octagonal shaft features 6 figures in shallow relief dancing and making music.
        Then the author gives an excursion of what is known from manuscripts about Dunhuang Mogao ku
        Lantern festivals (with dance and music, P.3405, P.3461). At Dunhuang, there is also
        influence from Sogdian immigrants 粟特移民 who originally believed in Zoroastrianism 祆教. 
        
        The
        final part of the article is about the style of the pictorial representations on the Forest
        of Steles’ "lamp-lighting stone pillar." They are influenced by the art of the Eastern Roman
        empire (拂菻), which was transmitted by sketches/stencils 粉本. This influence is also
        documented in the Painting Catalog of the Xuanhe Era (Xuanhe huapu 宣和畫譜). The Forest of
        Steles has some steles from the kaiyuan era that clearly show this influence from the
        Eastern Roman empire, often in the depiction of lions. The author lists more examples for
        this influence, mostly beasts, whose depiction received influences also from legends
        circulating in India, Iran, and among the Sogdians. The lamp-lighting stone pillar under
        study features in its bottom part foreigners 胡人 making music and winged beasts 神靈動物. The
        tomb of donor Su Sixu 蘇思勖, who died in 745, was excavated in 1952. It featured an
        illustration of an orchestra and dancers. The tomb of Li Xian 利憲 also has scenes of music
        and dance 樂舞圖 on the east wall. </abstract>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#Wenwu" type="host">
        <titleInfo lang="zh">
            <title>文物</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
            <title>Wenwu</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <!--<detail type="volume"></detail>-->
            <detail type="no">1</detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>60</start>
                <end>75</end>
            </extent>
            <date>2017</date>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>