<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Gong_Zhang2017" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd"><titleInfo transliteration="pinyin"><title>Senglang yu Tai Shan fojiao shishi biannian</title></titleInfo><titleInfo lang="zh"><title>僧朗與泰山佛教史事編年</title></titleInfo><titleInfo type="translated" lang="en"><title>A Chronology of Historical Events around Senglang on Mount Tai</title></titleInfo><titleInfo type="reference"><title>Gong and Zhang 2017</title></titleInfo><abstract>This is a useful collection of quotations from the Buddhist canon related to the life of Zhu Senglang. However, as usual, the authors have not considered any research done outside of China, neither Japanese nor Western; they mainly quote Tang Yong­tong 1938.
        The authors propose a chronology of Senglang’ s life, saying that he moved to Tai Shan in 351, roamed the mountain together with the Daoist Master Zhang Zhong 張忠 until the latter’ s death, supposedly in 377, founding his own monastery afterward, named Langgong Si 郎公寺 between 376 and 383, held a meeting there with his contemporaries Dao’an (344–413) and Fahe ([330–348]–[385–434], and received lavish gifts from seven rulers competing over power of his time, before he died around the year 405.
        Critique: Contacts to the seven rulers are based on letters supposedly exchanged between Senglang and the kings; authenticity of these letters as preserved in Guang Hongming ji 廣弘明集, compiled in 645 by Daoxuan (道宣, 596–667) has been questioned by Zürcher 2007, 387, note 27, who suspects their “remarkable uniformity in style and wordings”. 
        The sources do not explicitly mention that Senglang ever invited Dao’an and Fahe to Mount Tai; this is the theory of Tang Yongtong. The biography of Fahe in Gaoseng zhuan says that a meeting was held in Jinyugu 金與谷, and it records a conversation between Dao’an and Fahe on top of a mountain. Yet Jinyugu 金與谷 is given as the name of the place where Senglang established ANOTHER (?) monastery, being located on a cliff northwest of Mount Tai  T#2059, 50: 354b8–9: 朗乃於金輿谷崑崙山中。別立精舍。猶是泰山西北之一巖也。 
        Xu Gaoseng zhuan by Daoxuan says that Shentong Si was established for Senglang by Murong De 慕容德 (r. 398–405) of the Southern Yan 南燕 dynasty.
        The Record of Miraculous Responses to the Three Jewels in China T#2106 mentions Langgongsi and Senglang with contradicting facts; the authors note these contradictions, but do not take the nature of this work as a collection of different sub-collections miracle stories in account. The Fayuan zhulin repeats the first occurrence in the Record of Miraculous Responses. In this case, the story is about the story on Seven Auspicious Images (story no. 4) on Mount Tai 西晉泰山七國金像瑞緣四,  T#2106, 52: 414a15-25, see Shinohara 1998, 149; 166, note 32; 172; 176-177. Shinohara speaks of a singular image, with the exception of 176-177, where he says "the golden images sent from seven kingdoms at Mt. Tai (Western Jin). Parallels: Fayuan zhulin, 53: 383c. Secondary source is Soper 1959, 86, 94.
    </abstract><name xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#gongweizhang" type="personal"><namePart lang="zh" type="family">公</namePart><namePart lang="zh" type="given">維章</namePart><role><roleTerm>author</roleTerm></role></name><name xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#zhangmei" type="personal"><namePart lang="zh" type="family">張</namePart><namePart lang="zh" type="given">梅</namePart><role><roleTerm>author</roleTerm></role></name><relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#Taishanxueyuanxuebao" type="host"><titleInfo lang="zh"><title>泰山學院學報</title></titleInfo><titleInfo transliteration="pinyin"><title>Tai Shan xueyuan xuebao</title></titleInfo><originInfo><issuance>continuing</issuance></originInfo><part><detail type="volume">39</detail><detail type="no">2</detail><extent unit="page"><start>14</start><end>20</end></extent><date>2017</date></part></relatedItem></mods>