<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Greene2008" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo lang="en">
        <title>Another Look at Early <hi rend="italic">Chan:</hi> Daoxuan, Bodhidharma, and the Three Levels Movement</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Greene 2008</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#greene" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="en" type="family">Greene</namePart>
        <namePart lang="en" type="given">Eric</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>Green gives a new interpretation of Daoxuan’s concluding summary to the section on
        "chan practitioners" (xichan 習禪), the Evaluation of the Chan Practitioners (Xichan lun 習禪輪)
        Unlike Hu Shi, Jan Yün-hua and Chen Jinhua (Chen Jinhua 2002), he does not think that
        Daoxuan praises Sengchou, in whose tradition he probably saw himself, but criticizes
        Bodhidharma. By closely analyzing Daoxuan’s vocabulary that he used for describing the
        meditation method of Bodhidharma, Greene is able to demonstrate that several terms that were
        said to hold a negative connotation (qiandang 遣蕩 as indicating the teaching of the
        middle-way 中道 instead of simply "discard and negate"; liangshe 両捨: abandonment of the two
        extreme position of existence and emptiness instead of "double-abandoning"; jueyan 絕言:
        refering to silent wisdom instead of merely "abstaining from the use of words"; er gui 二軌:
        two wheels of a cart in the sense of complementary; youze 幽賾: "recondite and mysterious"
        instead of "deep and complicated") are not meant negative at all, but are in accordance with
        technical terms for meditation Daoxuan uses in his Continuation of the Biographies of
        Eminent Monks elsewhere. As for the unidentified group of Chan pratitioners that Daoxuan
        openly criticizes, Green does not think that these are later pupils of Bodhidharma, but
        adherents of the Teaching of the Three Stages. In the final passage of his Evaluation of the
        Chan Practitioners, Daoxuan praises again the achievements of four famous monks, namely
        Huisi, Huiyuan, Sengchou and Sengshi. The fact that Bodhidharma is omitted from this list
        has been taken by Yanagida and Chen Jinhua as proof for an alleged rivalry between
        Bodhidharma’s lineage and the lineage of Sengchou, to which Daoxuan is counted. According to
        Greene, the underlying assumption of Yanagida and Chen that Bodhidharma’s followers had
        already established themselves as an important meditation group with a novel orientation
        (towards asceticism, manual labor and iconoclasm) is false and is due to the construction of
        so-called "proto-Chan" doctrines by modern Japanese scholars. Greene thinks that "there is
        thus no reason to think that Bodhidharma or his followers were famous or formed any kind of
        coherent group when Daoxuan was writing the Evaluation of the Chan Practitioners." (p. 78) </abstract>
    <relatedItem xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#ToungPao" type="host">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>T’oung Pao<hi rend="normal">, ser. 2, vol.</hi>
            </title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <date>2008</date>
            <detail type="volume">94</detail>
            <detail type="no">1–3</detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>49</start>
                <end>114</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>