<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Jiang_Shao2010" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://claudia:claudia@data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/webdav/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
        <title>Yingshan Xian Taipeng Shan shiku chubu yanjiu</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="zh">
        <title>營山縣太蓬山石窟初步研究</title>
        <!--<title>營山縣太蓬山石窟内容目錄</title>-->
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
        <title>A Preliminary Study of the Mount Taipeng Cave Shrines in Yingshan County</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Jiang and Shao 2010</title>
        <!--<title>Jiang Xiao­chun, Wu Hongjian and Shao Lei 2010</title>-->
    </titleInfo>
    <abstract>Taipeng Shan 太蓬山, located 47 km north-east of Yingshan County 營山縣, at 731 m above sea
        level. Most inscriptions are distributed across the eastern and western face of Touming
        Cliff (Touming yan 透明岩/巖). The authors give an overview on the research history of the most
        famous inscription of the site, the colophon by An Lushan 安祿山, dated to 713 (also the
        earliest date found at the site). In July 2008, the sites was surveyed, and the niches were
        numbered (again). Touming Cliff, Donghan Gate 東寒門 and Xihan Gate 西寒門 together count 104
        niches and more than 1470 sculpted images. Classification of types of caves/niches follows,
        and an overview on iconographical motifs is given. Niches K32 and K38 present Amitābha
        teaching to 52 bodhisattvas (weathered, bodhisattvas not countable).
        
        Buddhist inscriptions,
        five in total. K7: Diamond Sutra, illegible. 
        p. 60: K7. Diamond Sutra and  K8. Diamond Sutra, illegible and transcription and identification of the two phrases about the vajra beings: 第二奉请辟毒金刚，第三奉请黄随求金刚
       
        K9 (commonly
        named Dagu Cave 打鼓洞): fragments of a sutra text, illegible. K13: Diamond Sutra, ca. 5.000
        characters K53: Fragments of 妙法蓮華經普賢菩薩勸發品第二十八 (T.262 or T.264?) 方便陀羅尼…滿三…即于佛前而說咒曰…阿婆…帝二
        (T.262, 9: 61b5-27) 
        
        6 niches have votive inscriptions 造像題記:
        K13 (outside, on the left-hand
        side of the niche) 普濟寺碑記dated 907 (transcribed p. 60). Connection to the belief in the Ten Kings of Hell.
        K16 (located on the right-hand side of K13; outside the niche K16, to the
        left-and right-hand side on the cliff) right-hand side: 馮可振造像碑記dated 895 (well preserved,
        transcribed p. 61) Feng Kezhen donated the thousand-eyed and thousand-arms Guanshiyin
        千手千眼觀音像. Left-hand side: 修十王生七齋記, dated to 888 (transcribed p. 61) 
        K29 (below K28, below the
        four characters 晚霞晨暉, on the right-hand side of the outer niche frame) 安祿山題龕, dated 713
        (transcribed p. 62) 
        K36: fragments of an inscription, illegible 
        K45: fragments of
        inscriptions on the right- and left-hand side of the niche 
        
        南寒門K2: dated 1741 
        
        Visitor  inscriptions (in 4 places); and K29 has the poem 刺安祿山 by the retired scholar Yuan Jushi 遠居士
        of the Qing, followed by 安祿山題龕辯 by Zhu Shimin 朱時敏, dated 1229, who writes that the author of
        the former cannot be the famous An Lushan. 
        
        Chronology of the site: K1, K21, K22, K23 are the
        earliest, dated on style (mandorla) to Early Tang by comparison with Longmen, Middle Binyang
        Cave 賓陽中洞 (Bei Wei) . K43, K45; perhaps also Early Tang, comparable to Guangzuan Huangze Si
        cave 15, Guangyuan 劍閣櫎梁子 cave 2 and cave 6 . 
        Other cave clusters are also dated on style.
        The Rice Granary Path 米倉道 connected Taipeng Shan and Bazhong 巴中 
       
    </abstract>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#jiangxiaochun" type="personal">
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="family">Jiang</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="given">Xiaochun</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">蔣</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">曉春</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>

    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#shaolei" type="personal">
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="family">Shao</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="given">Lei</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">邵</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">磊</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract/>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#DunhuangYanjiu" type="host">
        <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
            <title>Dunhuang yanjiu</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo lang="zh">
            <title>敦煌研究</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <date>2010</date>
            <detail type="volume">122</detail>
            <detail type="no">4</detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>56</start>
                <end>67</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>