<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Juliano_Lerner2001" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo lang="en">
        <title>Monks and Merchants. Silk Road Treasures from Northwest China, Gansu and Ningxia,
            4th-7th Century</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Juliano and Lerner 2001</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#juliano" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="en" type="family">Juliano</namePart>
        <namePart lang="en" type="given">Annette L.</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#lerner" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="en" type="family">Lerner</namePart>
        <namePart lang="en" type="given">Judith A.</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <note>p. 153-155: Minature stupa or scripture stupa (jingta). Northern Liang dynasty (398-439),
        dated by inscription to 428. Found Jiuquan District, Gansu. Dark grey limestone with incised
        line drawing, Chinese text, and and low-relief sculpture. height: 44.6 cm. Gansu provincial
        Museum, Lanzhou. so-called Gao Shanmu stupa. By Gao Bao. 153: Fourteen scripture stupas,
        also called sutra pillars (jingta), have been discovered so far in the Gansu corridor and in
        the Turfan District of Xinjiang; most are housed in the collections of the Gansu Provincial
        Museum and of the Dunhuang, the Jiuquan, and the Wuwei Municipal Museums. Two from the
        Turfan District remain in Berlin’s Museum für Indische Kunst. Of the fourteen, sevn have
        dates ranging from 426 to 436, and nine bear names of the lay Buddhist donorswho
        commissioned them. All but two were made under the Northern Liang dynasty (398-439) during
        the thirty-year rule of Juqu Mengxun, an ardent Buddhist who also admired traditional
        Chinese culture. Probably votive in function, most scripture stupas have been found at sites
        of former temples; this kind of scripture stupa is found only in Gansu and Turfan and is not
        known in north-central China. The type dissappears from Gansu after the Northen Liang but
        survives briefly in Turfan with the remnant of that dynasty. </note>
    <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>2001</dateIssued>
        <place>
            <placeTerm>New York</placeTerm>
        </place>
        <publisher>
            <name type="corporate">
                <namePart lang="en">Harry N. Abrams</namePart>
            </name>
        </publisher>
        <issuance>monographic</issuance>
    </originInfo>
</mods>