<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="OnishiShuya1977" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo transliteration="romaji">
        <title>Kudara Futsuritsuzō to ikkō sanzon keishiki: Gatapu-ri haijishi shutsudo Kondō Futsuritsuzō o megutte</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="ja">
        <title>百濟佛立像と一光三尊形式<hi rend="dash">──</hi>佳塔里廢寺址出土金銅佛立像をめぐって<hi rend="dash">──</hi>
        </title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
        <title>Statue of Standing Buddha of Paekche Dynasty and <hi rend="italic">
                <foreign xml:lang="ja">Ikkō </foreign>Sanzon</hi> (Statue of Buddha Triad with One Halo) Style</title>
        <!--<title>Statue of standing Buddha of Paekche Dynasty and <hi rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="ja">Ikkō </foreign>Sanzon</hi> (statue of Buddha triad with one halo) Style</title>-->
    </titleInfo>
    <abstract>Regarding the transcription of 佳塔里 as Gatapu-ri:
        1) Until now, we have not discovered any source that mentions the japanese reading of 가탑리 佳塔里 [Gatap-ri]. Therefore, the rendering as Gatapu-ri was created by us ourselves.
        2) The Japanese transcription of Korean places follows this general rule: For contemporary materials, use a transcription based partly on Korean reading (i.e. from Hangul). For colonial era materials, use a transription based on Japanese reading (i.e. from Kanji/Hanja). 평양 平壌 [Pyongyang]: Pyon’yan (ピョンヤン) for comtemporary usage, Heijō (へいじょう) for colonial era materials. 경기도 京畿道 [Gyeonggi-do]: Kyongi-dō (キョンギ‐どう) for comtemporary usage, Keiki-dō (けいき‐どう)  for colonial era materials. See also p.23 in: https://www.eastasianlib.org/ctp/Subcommittees/sub_JpnRT/RT_Revision_Complete_Draft%20-%202018_Mar27.pdf.
        3) Since this is a text from 1977, we use the transcription for contemporary usage. If 佳塔里 would have been mentioned in colonial era materials, the reading would probably be Katō-ri(?) (かとう‐り). There are indeed several materials from the colonial era that mention 佳塔里. I have however, not found any materials that used Furigana in order to show the japanese reading of 佳塔里, therefore I cannot for 100% guarantee that Katō-ri is the correct rendering. Other japanese readings for 佳: Go-on: け (ke); Kan-on: かい (kai); Kan’yō-on: けい (kei).
        4) Normally, the reading of the korean reading 가탑리 has to be transcribed as follows: 가탑리 → Gatapri → Gatamni → ガタムニ → Gatamuni (Hangul → Revised Romanisation → Assimilation of consonants “pr” to “mn” → Rendering into Katakana → Transcription into the Hepburn-System). However, since this is a geographic name and ri 리/里 is an administrative unit, a hyphen is inserted between tap 탑 and ri 리; the assimilation of the consonants [pr → mn] will be ignored. See p.24 in: https://www.geschkult.fu-berlin.de/e/oas/korea-studien/files/romanization.pdf. Furthermore as in the other geographic cases such as in 京畿道 [Gyeonggi-do], we’ll add a hyphen into the japanese romanization as well. Therefore: 가탑리 → Gatapri → Gatap-ri → ガタプ‐リ → Gatapu-ri.
        5) We have rendered p-ri in Katakana as プリ (pu-ri) and not as ッリ (r-ri). For one, we have followed to ignore the assimilation of consonants as in the korean case when an hyphen is added. Furthermore, in japanese the combination of the two consontants p and r is rendered into pu プ and r+vowel in most of the cases (always?). See for example the japanese transcriptions of foreign terms with the combination of the two consonants “pr”, such as: epuron エプロン [Apron], konpuressā コンプレッサー [Compressor], Kipurosu キプロス [Cyprus], puraibēto プライベート [private], purintā プリンター [Printer], Puroisen プロイセン [Preußen], puroresu プロレス [Pro Wrestling], purosesu プロセス [Process], purezentēshon プレゼンテーション [Presentation], etc. or the multiple renderings of the river Dnieper (Днепр, Дніпро, Дняпро), such as Doniepuru-gawa ドニエプル川, Donepuru-gawa ドネプル川, Donyepuru-gawaドニェプル川, Donyēpuru-gawa ドニェープル川, Donipuro-gawa ドニプロ川.</abstract>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Ōnishi 1977</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#onishi_shuya" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="ja" type="family">大西</namePart>
        <namePart lang="ja" type="given">修也</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="romaji" type="family">Ōnishi</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="romaji" type="given">Shūya</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <relatedItem xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#Museum" type="host">
        <titleInfo transliteration="romaji">
            <title>Museum: Tōkyō kokuritsu hakubutsukan kenkyūshi,  </title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo lang="ja">
            <title>
                <foreign lang="en">
                    <hi rend="italic">Museum</hi>
                </foreign>：東京国立博物館研究誌</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <date>1977</date>
            <detail type="volume">
                <number>315</number>
            </detail>
            <extent unit="pages">
                <start>22</start>
                <end>34</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>