<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Ono2009" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo transliteration="romaji">
        <title>Kankoku Kunwi sekkutsu Amida nyoraizō no keishiki ni tsuite: Sho Tō-ki ni okeru Indo
            shōrai zuzō juyō no ichirei</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="ja">
        <title>韓国軍威石窟阿弥陀如来像の形式について<hi rend="dash">──</hi>初唐期におけるインド請来<!--図-->圖像受容の一例</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="translated" lang="en">
        <title>The Form of the Image of Amitābha Tathāgata in Gunwi Cave, Korea: One Example for an
            Indian Image Requested and Obtained Under the Early Tang Dynasty</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <abstract>On p. 137, the 50 Bodhisattvas of Wolong Shan 臥龍山, Sichuan are mentioned. 
        Pp. 137-139 is about the formation of Amitabha Buddha with earth-touching gesture.
        
        The Japanese
        transcription of Korean places follows this general rule: For contemporary materials, use a
        transcription based partly on Korean reading (i.e. from Hangul). For colonial era materials,
        use a transription based on Japanese reading (i.e. from Kanji/Hanja). 평양 平壌 [Pyongyang]:
        Pyon’yan (ピョンヤン) for comtemporary usage, Heijō (へいじょう) for colonial era materials. 경기도 京畿道
        [Gyeonggi-do]: Kyongi-dō (キョンギ‐どう) for comtemporary usage, Keiki-dō (けいき‐どう) for colonial
        era materials. See also p.23 in:
        https://www.eastasianlib.org/ctp/Subcommittees/sub_JpnRT/RT_Revision_Complete_Draft%20-%202018_Mar27.pdf.
        3) Since this is a text from 2009, we use the transcription for contemporary usage. If 軍威
        would have been mentioned in colonial era materials, the reading would probably be Gun’i (?)
        (ぐんい). According to the above rule, we take the Japanese reading from the Hangul 군위. Since
        the reading for 군위 is クヌィ, we choose the reading Kunwi. ぬぃ or ヌィ is almost never used in
        Japanese. The reading is probably nwi, but could also be ni.</abstract>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Ono Eiji 2009</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#ono_eiji" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="ja" type="family">小野</namePart>
        <namePart lang="ja" type="given">英二</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="hepburn" type="family">Ono</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="hepburn" type="given">Eiji</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#Waseda_kiyo3" type="host">
        <titleInfo lang="ja">
            <title>早稲田大学大学院文学研究科紀要：第三分冊　日本語日本文学　演劇映像学　美術史学　表象·<!--・-->メディア論　現代文芸</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo transliteration="romaji">
            <title>Waseda daigaku daigakuin bungaku kenkyūka kiyō: Dai 3-bunsatsu Nihongo Nihon
                bungaku, engeki eizōgaku, bijutsu shigaku, hyōshō, mediaron, gendai bungei</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <part>
            <detail type="volume">54</detail>
            <detail type="no">3</detail>
            <date>2009</date>
            <extent unit="pages">
                <start>131</start>
                <end>145</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
        <issuance>continuing</issuance>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>