<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="T_2871" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://claudia:claudia@data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/webdav/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo lang="zh">
        <title>大通方廣懺悔滅罪莊嚴成佛經</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
        <title>Extensive Sutra of Great Penetration 
            on Solemn Attainment of Buddhahood by Means of Repentance to Extinguish Sins</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
        <title>Datong fangguang chanhui miezui zhuangyan chengfo Jing</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>T#2871, 85</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <physicalDescription>
        <extent>
            <detail type="fascicle">1</detail>
        </extent>
    </physicalDescription>
    <originInfo>
        <edition/>
    </originInfo>
    <abstract>T 2871, abbreviated as Fangguang jing 方廣經. An apocryphal Chinese Buddhist text, originally lost, and reconstructed in the twentieth century on the basis of three Dunhuang manuscripts. Emperor Wen of the Chen dynasty 陳文帝 (r. 559–566) authored a text entitled “Confession Text [based upon] the Datong fangguang” 大通方廣懺文, preserved in the Guang hong ming ji T 2103.52.333c07–28, which is the earliest evidence for the existence of the text. The text is also listed in Fajingʼs 法經 catalogue of 591. We also have two extant manuscripts, dated 590 and 603. Thus, there is firm evidence that the text was compiled before the middle of the sixth century. The text contains long lists of names of the Buddha for recitation, each being preceded by namu 南無, guiming 歸命 or jishou 稽首; and claims for the great efficacy of the confession rites it lays out, including the power to wipe out the five ānantaryakarma and the sins of the icchantika. The specific rite entails taking the three refuges, and then paying homage to stūpas and all the minor divinities that fill all space; conducting rites of confession six times a day, and reciting the sutra itself three times a day. These practices must be continued for a period of seven days, without sleep. Ordinary practitioners must obtain a 'dream sign'  夢相 before they can be sure that their practice has been efficacious. A Tibetan version of the text exists also, P Kanjur 930–931. See Kuo Li-ying, Confession et contrition dans le bouddhisme chinois du Ve au Xe siècle (Paris: Publications de l'École française d'Extrême-Orient, 1994), 138–141. 〔大周刊定衆經目錄, 歷代三寶紀 〕 [Michael Radich]</abstract>
    <relatedItem xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="Taisho" type="host">
        <titleInfo lang="ja">
            <title>大正新脩大藏經.</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo transliteration="romaji">
            <title>Taishō shinshū daizōkyō</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo transliteration="romaji" type="abbreviated">
            <title>Taishō</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
            <title>New edition of the Buddhist canon in the Taishō era</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <name ns2:href="#takakusu" type="personal">
            <namePart lang="ja" type="family">高楠</namePart>
            <namePart lang="ja" type="given">順次郎</namePart>
            <role>
                <roleTerm>editor</roleTerm>
            </role>
        </name>
        <name ns2:href="#watanabe" type="personal">
            <namePart lang="ja" type="family">渡邊</namePart>
            <namePart lang="ja" type="given">海旭</namePart>
            <role>
                <roleTerm>editor</roleTerm>
            </role>
        </name>
        <physicalDescription>
            <extent>
                <detail type="volume">85</detail>
            </extent>
        </physicalDescription>
        <originInfo>
            <dateIssued>1924-1932</dateIssued>
            <dateIssued encoding="marc" point="start">1924</dateIssued>
            <dateIssued encoding="marc" point="end">1932</dateIssued>
            <place>
                <placeTerm>Tōkyō</placeTerm>
            </place>
            <publisher>
                <name type="corporate">
                    <namePart lang="ja">大正一切經刊行會</namePart>
                    <namePart transliteration="pinyin">Taishō issaikyō kankōkai</namePart>
                </name>
            </publisher>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <detail type="volume">
                <number>85</number>
            </detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>1338c22</start>
                <end>1345a30</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>