<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Kegasawa2020" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo lang="zh">
        <title>河北曲陽八會寺隋代刻經龕的全貌及其歷史地位</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
        <title>Hebei Quyang Bahui Si Suidai kejing kan de quanmao jiqi lishi diwei</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
        <title>A Complete View of the Sui Dynasty Sutra Carving Niches at Bahui Monastery, Quyang,
            Hebei and Their Historical Status</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Kegasawa 2020</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#kegasawa" type="personal">
        <namePart transliteration="romaji" type="family">Kegasawa</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="romaji" type="given">Yasunori </namePart>
        <namePart lang="ja" type="family">氣賀澤</namePart>
        <namePart lang="ja" type="given">保規</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>The topographical location of Bahui Si is important: It lies in between Dazhusheng Ku
        of Mount Bao (Lingyu) and Fangshan. Kegasawa visited Bahui Si in 2005 and 2008; see the
        respective Japanese publications. For some information of the former monastery close to
        today's Bahui Si, see the article by Liu Dunzhen 劉敦楨 (LiuDunzhen1935). Kegasawa assumes that the surrounding walls that protect the central shaft was build under the Song dynasty, as the ruins of the nearby monastery (documented by Liu Dunzhen) are also from this period.
    Kegasawa reconstructs the history of the monastery's rise and fall from the available sources (重修少容山八會寺文殊殿記). Ennin also mentions a visit to Bahui Si in his diary, but he does not describe the shaft with inscriptions.
    The arrangement of the texts on the sides of the central shaft is neat and orderly, and must have been based on a plan. (p. 13) Kegasawa imagines that a learned (cleric?) person oversaw this master plan. Because of this good planning, it should not have taken long to complete all carvings. This coincides with the evidence derived from the colophons. Kegasawa suggests kaihuang 10-20 as time span in which everything was finished. The donors came from the region, some held small posts as officials, and they were organized in association(s)=&gt;"行唐邑". 
    </abstract>
    <relatedItem xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#Xiayan2020" type="host">
        <titleInfo lang="zh">
            <title>中古中國的知識與社會</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
            <title>Zhonggu Zhongguo de zhishi yu shehuii</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo type="translated" lang="en">
            <title>Knowledge and Society in Medieval China</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <dateIssued>2020</dateIssued>
            <place>
                <placeTerm>Shanghai</placeTerm>
                <placeTerm lang="zh">上海</placeTerm>
            </place>

            <issuance>monographic</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>1</start>
                <end>24</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>

</mods>