<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Kiriya1997" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo transliteration="romaji">
        <title>Chūgoku ni okeru hokkekyō no sekkoku</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="ja">
        <title>中国における法華經の石刻</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="zh">
        <title>中國境内的法華經石刻</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
        <title>Stone Inscriptions of the ‘Lotus Sutra’ in China</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Kiriya 1997</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <abstract>Carving Buddhist sutras on stone in China could be understood as a combination of the
        tradition of carving Confucian Classics on stone and the Buddhist practice of copying and
        printing the Buddhist sutras. Lotus Sutra, especially the Chapter of the Universal Gate of
        the Bodhisattva Avalokiteśvara, has been one of the mostly carved Buddhist texts in China.
        The first part of the article – the extant examples of the carved Lotus Sutra - lists the
        known examples in respect of the date, place, type, content and historical documents. The
        second part – the thoughts and technology of carving Buddhist sutras in China – argues that
        the practice of carving sutras shows the reverence for the Chinese characters and the trust
        on the durability of the stone. The carved texts or Buddha names on the cliffs in open air
        have often a strong symbolic meaning, and in many cases the characters can be regarded as
        the replacements of Buddha statues. The carved texts, either key paragraphs or Buddha names
        or the title of the sutras also represent the whole corresponding text. The function of the
        carved texts in certain spatial environment in the Northern Qi Dynasty (550-577) might have
        been related with the practice of meditation. In a similar manner, the Chapter of the
        Universal Gate or the Buddha names from Lotus Sutra or even its title have been carved, and
        they might assume the same power as the whole text. The third part – the religious thoughts
        and the characteristics of the carved Lotus Sutra – discusses: a. the contents of the carved
        Lotus Sutras ranging from the whole text to just the title; b. the thoughts of preserving
        all the Buddhist texts and the Lotus Sutra in seven places with other Buddhist texts; c. the
        cult of the bodhisattva Avalokiteśvara and the related carved text. Abstract by Zhao Zhou </abstract>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#kiriya" type="personal">
        <namePart transliteration="romaji" type="family">Kiriya</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="romaji" type="given">Seiichi</namePart>
        <namePart lang="ja" type="family">桐谷</namePart>
        <namePart lang="ja" type="given">征一</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#AsaiEndo_kinen1997" type="host">
        <titleInfo transliteration="romaji">
            <title>Asai Endō sensei koki kinen ronbunshū: Nichiren kyōgaku no shomondai</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo lang="ja">
            <title>浅井円道先生古稀記念論文集：日蓮教學の諸問題</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <dateIssued>1997-02</dateIssued>
            <place>
                <placeTerm transliteration="romaji">Kyōto</placeTerm>
                <placeTerm lang="ja">京都</placeTerm>
            </place>
            <publisher>
                <name type="corporate">
                    <namePart transliteration="romaji">Heirakuji shoten</namePart>
                    <namePart lang="ja">平樂寺書店</namePart>
                </name>
            </publisher>
            <issuance>monographic</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>783</start>
                <end>816</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>