<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Kroll1983" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://claudia:claudia@data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/webdav/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo lang="en">
        <title>Verses from on High: The Ascent of T’ai Shan</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Kroll 1983</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#kroll" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="en" type="family">Kroll</namePart>
        <namePart lang="en" type="given">Paul W.</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>Samples of pre-Tang verses on Mount Tai:
        Lu Ji 陸機 (261–303): A Chant of Mount Tai
       Xie Lingyun 謝靈運 (385–433): Chant of Mount Tai
       the poetess Xie Daoyun 謝道韞 (Schwiegertochter von Wang Xizhi): Ascending the Mountain
        Du Fu 杜甫(712–770): Gazing afar at the Marchmount, written on a private excursion
        Lu Zhaolin 盧照鄰 (ca. 635–684) accompanied Tang Gaozong in 666: Songs for the Great Refection upon the Ascent for the feng.
        Zhang Yue 張說 (967–731) for Xuanzong in 725, composed 14 solemn songs for the rites, and an altar hymn for the feng sacrifice, Tang Xuanzong bestowed titles to Mount Tai and other mountains and landmarks in his empire.
        Cao Zhi 曹植 (192–232)： Combines in his poem Mount Tai as protector of the state with a place for Daoist transformation, i.e. Huangdi obtaining wings and becoming a transcendent
        The latter’s father, Cao Cao 曹操 (155–220): Three Cantos on the Pneuma Emerging, had already written on Mount Tai as a place where transcendents descend to earth
        
        Li Bo 李白 (701–762): Six poems, entitled Wandering on Mount Tai, in which he becomes a Daoist adept and finally, at night on the summit, turns into a transcendent, but just for one night. 
        Only two gentlemen of the Way seem to have been remembered for their association with Mount Tai: Xu Jun 許峻 (early second century), a master of divinatory practices, and Zhang Zhong 張忠 (first half of the fourth century), an expert in Daoist respiratory techniques, whom Zhu Senglang 竺僧朗 (ca. 315–400) follwed into the mountain in 351.</abstract>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#ToungPao" type="host">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>T’oung Pao<hi rend="normal">, ser. 2, vol.</hi>
            </title>
        </titleInfo>
        <!-- <titleInfo lang="zh">
            <title>通報</title>
        </titleInfo>-->
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <date>1983</date>
            <detail type="volume">69</detail>
            <detail type="no">4–5</detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>223</start>
                <end>260</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>