<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://claudia:claudia@www.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/webdav/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd" ID="Kuramoto2019">
    <titleInfo lang="ja">
        <title>『続高僧伝』智首伝と「故首律師高徳頌」の関係について</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo transliteration="romaji">
        <title>
            <hi rend="italic">Zoku kōsō den</hi> Chishu den to ‘ko Shurisshi Kōtoku shō’ no kankei ni tsuite</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
        <title>About the Relationsship between the Biography of Zhishou in the <hi rend="italic">Sequel to the Biographies of Eminent Monks</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Stele Praising the Vinaya Master and Eminent Monk Zhishou</hi>
        </title>
    </titleInfo>
    <abstract>Official English translation: The Relationship Between the Biography of Zhishou in the <hi rend="italic">Xu Gaoseng Zhuan</hi> and the ‘Monument Extolling the Vinaya Master and Eminent Monk Zhishou’</abstract>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Kuramoto 2019</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#kuramoto_shotoku" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="ja" type="family">倉本</namePart>
        <namePart lang="ja" type="given">尚德</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="romaji" type="family">Kuramoto</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="romaji" type="given">Shōtoku</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>This paper is part of my recent comparative research on the <i>Xu Gaoseng zhuan</i>
        and inscriptions. I discuss the relationship between the "Monument Extolling the Vinaya
        Master and Eminent Monk Zhishou" 智首律師高徳頌碑 (Zhishou monument) and the <i>Xu Gaoseng
            zhuan</i>’s biography of Zhishou. The Zhishou monument was built in the twelfth month of
        Xianqing 1 (656), over twenty years after his death in Zhenguan 9 (635). One of the reasons
        for its construction was that a plot was in the works to isolate Xuanzang, who was reigning
        over the Chang’an Buddhist world after returning to China and receiving the patronage of
        Taizong; he was seen by Gaozong and Wu Hou (later Wu Zetian) as part of a faction of
        Taizong’s former senior statesmen. The Zhishou monument was built at the gate of the
        Hongfu-si, where Zhishou had last resided. It became a place that highlighted the returning
        power of Zhishou’s disciples. This probably led to Zhishou’s top disciple, Daoxuan, becoming
        the senior monk at the Ximing-si in Xianqing 3 (658). Judging from the Zhishou monument
        text’s sequential composition and use of similar words and phrases, it is highly likely that
        it drew from the <i>Xu Gaoseng zhuan</i> (first version: ca. Zhenguan 19, 645). However, the
            <i>Xu Gaoseng zhuan</i> mentions this monument. It appears that this was added when this
        collection of biographies was revised after Daoxuan became the senior monk at the
        Ximing-si.</abstract>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#Indogaku_Bukkyogaku_kenkyu" type="host">
        <titleInfo lang="ja">
            <title>印度學佛敎學硏究</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo transliteration="romaji">
            <title>Indogaku Bukkyōgaku kenkyū</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
            <title>Journal of Indian and Buddhist Studies</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <detail type="volume">67</detail>
            <detail type="no">2</detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>746</start>
                <end>751</end>
                <!--<start>226</start>
                <end>231</end>-->
            </extent>
            <date>2019</date>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>