<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://claudia:claudia@www.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/webdav/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd" ID="Kuramoto2011b">
 <titleInfo lang="ja">
  <title>中國における觀音信仰の展開の一樣相―『觀世音十大願經』と「觀世音佛」</title>
 </titleInfo>
 <titleInfo transliteration="romaji">
  <title>Chūgoku ni okeru Kannon shinkō no tenkai ichi yōsō<hi rend="dash">──</hi>‘Kanseon ju
   daigankyō’ to ‘Kanseonbutsu’</title>
 </titleInfo>
 <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
  <title>One Aspect of the Evolution of the Guanyin Cult in China: The Sutra of the ‘Ten Great Vows
   of Guanshiyin’ and the ‘Buddha Guanshiyin’</title>
 </titleInfo>
 <titleInfo type="reference">
  <title>Kuramoto 2011b</title>
 </titleInfo>
 <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#kuramoto_shotoku" type="personal">
  <namePart lang="ja" type="family">倉本</namePart>
  <namePart lang="ja" type="given">尚德</namePart>
  <namePart transliteration="romaji" type="family">Kuramoto</namePart>
  <namePart transliteration="romaji" type="given">Shōtoku</namePart>
  <role>
   <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
  </role>
 </name>
 <abstract>Kuramoto traces the story of how Guanyin is going to become a Buddha in the following
  sources: A: T#157, 03 悲華經 B: T#371, 12 觀世音菩薩授記經 C: 觀世音三昧經 (apokryph), lost, listed in 法經錄 or 眾經目錄
  (one version of it is T#2148, 55:180c-218), in Dunhuang manuscripts 北 8280, 北 8281, S 4338.
  Guanshiyin receives vyakarana from Sakyamuni, and will be called 正法明如來。 D: 觀世音十大願經 or 弘猛海慧經
  (apokryph). The first born son of the king by the name of 善光 makes ten great vows in front of
  空王觀世音佛, and vows to become 觀世音佛 in the future. C and D are clearly different from A and B, which
  are in conformity with the well-known transmission of Guanyin becoming the successor of Amitabha.
  Kuramoto mentions Dunhuang manuscript S.0795 “觀世音佛名”, which repeats the name of Guanshiyinfo 2530
  times. Then he gives in his list A nine votive inscriptions which refer to Guanshiyinfo, the
  earliest dating to the year 495. His list B has the three Shandong inscriptions of this name at
  Hongdingshan, Culaishan, and Taoshan. List C contains two more examples (from 532 and 541) of
  Buddha figures that are called 觀世音像 in the inscription. In the Shandong inscriptions, Guanshiyinfo
  is cut close to Amituofo, therefore it must refer to Guanshiyin as successor of Amitabha as
  described in the 觀世音菩薩授記經. This is true only with respect of the two names Buddha Amitabha and
  Buddha Guanshiyin following after each other. At Beixiangtangshan in Daye cave 大業洞 from the Sui,
  the name Guanshiyin pusa is carved after the seven Buddha of the past (including Sakyamuni) and
  the future Buddha Maitreya. This sequence is also mirrored in the sculpted figures of the opposite
  wall. 涉县木井寺武平四年（573）碑: The 遺教經 carved on this stele contains the “ten great vows of Guanshiyin”
  (大悲觀世音) 八會寺經龕 : The east side of the southern niche gives the ten great vows under the heading of
  弘猛慧海經觀音願 Conclusions: The idea found in Pure Land Buddhism that Guanyin becomes a Buddha after
  Amitabha is propagated in the 悲華經 and 觀世音菩薩授記經. The role of Guanyin as a saviour is found in the
  apocryphal scriptures 觀世音三昧經 and 觀世音十大願經. Especially in the last scripture, 空王觀世音佛 is a different
  Buddha. In front of him, the bodhisattva takes ten vows. These are found on stelae and in Bahuisi,
  and as Daye cave in Northern Xiangtangshan has shown, these vows are the ground on which Guanyin’s
  position as saviour in the succession of Sakyamuni is based. </abstract>
 <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="" type="host">
  <titleInfo lang="ja">
   <title>龍谷大学アジア仏教文化研究センター ワーキングペーパー</title>
  </titleInfo>
  <titleInfo transliteration="romaji">
   <title>Ryūkoku daigaku ajia bukkyō bunka kenkyū sentā wō kingu pēpā</title>
  </titleInfo>
  <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
   <title>Ryukoku University Research Center for Buddhist Cultures in Asia - Working Papers</title>
  </titleInfo>
  <originInfo>
   <dateIssued>2011</dateIssued>
   <place>
    <placeTerm transliteration="romaji">Kyōto</placeTerm>
    <placeTerm lang="ja">京都</placeTerm>
   </place>
   <publisher>
    <name type="corporate">
     <namePart transliteration="romaji">Ryūkoku daigaku ajia bukkyō bunka kenkyū sentā</namePart>
     <namePart lang="ja">龍谷大学アジア仏教文化研究センター</namePart>
     <namePart lang="en">Ryukoku University Research Center for Buddhist Cultures in Asia</namePart>
    </name>
   </publisher>
   <issuance>continuing</issuance>
  </originInfo>
  <part>
   <detail type="no">10-1</detail>
   <extent unit="page">
    <start>1</start>
    <end>16</end>
   </extent>
   <date>2011</date>
  </part>
 </relatedItem>
 <classification edition="#Kuramoto2016">reprint</classification>
 <relatedItem xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#Kuramoto2016" type="host">
  <note>reprint</note>
  <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#kuramoto_shotoku" type="personal">
   <namePart lang="ja" type="family">倉本</namePart>
   <namePart lang="ja" type="given">尚德</namePart>
   <namePart transliteration="romaji" type="family">Kuramoto</namePart>
   <namePart transliteration="romaji" type="given">Shōtoku</namePart>
   <role>
    <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
   </role>
  </name>
  <originInfo>
   <issuance>monographic</issuance>
  </originInfo>
  <part>
   <extent unit="page">
    <start>457</start>
    <end>471</end>
   </extent>
  </part>
 </relatedItem>
</mods>