<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Kuramoto2016a" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://claudia:claudia@data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/webdav/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
        <title>Cong kejing kan Yecheng fojiao: yi Xiaonanhai shiku yu Bei Xiangtangshan shiku wei
            zhongxin</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="zh">
        <title>從刻經看鄴城佛教：以小南海石窟與北響堂山石窟為中心</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
        <title>Buddhism in the Capital Ye as Seen from Engraved Sutras: With a Focus on the
            Xiaonanhai Caves and the Northern Mount Xiangtang Caves</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Kuramoto 2016a</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#kuramoto" type="personal">
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="family">Kuramoto</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="given">Shōtoku</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">倉本</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">尚德</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>For the southern cave at Northern Mount Xiangtang, Kuramoto constructs a sequence of Buddhist practice as followes: the texts inscribed on the boulder dated to 566 (天統二年) imply the keeping of precepts and the taking of vows for non-retrogression on the bodhisattva path; the texts carved on the pillars imply invocation of Buddha names in repentence rites; the texts carved inside the ground floor of the cave imply veneration of the Buddha image; the texts carved on the first floor of the cave imply taking refuge in Buddha wisdom and Buddha nature, and protection of the buddhadharma.
        Kuramoto identifies the Northern Qi as the time when large-sacle sutra inscriptions (大規模的刻經) were made. As prototypes, he names the Confucian classics (Xiping canon), Bingling cave 169 未曾有經, the Northern Liang votive stupas (research by Inamoto Yasuo 稲本泰生 2009), the Bo'ai County cliff carvings in Henan (509), and the Shayu cliff carvings in Heshun County in Shanxi (529). The stone classics of the Han and Wei came from Luoyang of the Eastern Wei in 546 to Yecheng (research by Kiriya Seiichi 桐谷征一 1996: <ref type="biblio" target="Kiriya1996">188-189; 207-208, note 14</ref>).   
        Background: the "Nirvana School" flourished in the South, and arrived in the North, where the main concern was how to put in practice the idea that "all beings, even icchantica, possess Buddhahood." "一切衆生悉有佛性" "闡提成佛" The translation of the Daśabhūmikaśāstra (Shidi lunjing 十地經論, T.1522)(allegedly written by Vasubandhu) was ordered by Emperor Xuanwu 北魏宣武帝 of the Northern Wei, and done by Bodhiruci 菩提流支 (and Ratnamati 勒那摩提). This translation was studied fervently by some of the best scholars of this time, including Huiguang 慧光, Fashang 法上, and Jingying Huiyuan 净影寺慧遠 (523年—592年).
        In the three-level panjiao system of the Dilun school, the highest status (通宗 or 圓宗) held the Nirvana Sutra, the Huayan jing, the 大集經, and the Srimaladevi. The Nirvana Sutra counted as "gradual" teaching 漸教, and the Huayan as "sudden" teaching 頓教. The 大集經 and the Srimaladevi counted as "perfect" teaching 圓教 because of their benjue 本覺 doctrine.
    While former studies concentrated on identifying the sources of the stone texts, Kuramoto aims at comparing the texts carved at Xiaonanhai and at Northern Mount Xiangtang with regard to doctrinal similarities and distinctions.
    In 551, Emperor Wenxuan calls Sengchou to his court to bestow bodhisattva precepts on him, and in 552, he made him abbot of Yunmen Monastery 雲門寺. The ruins of Yunmen Monastery have not been discovered, but there is a chance it may have been located close to Xiaonanhai. Wenxuan also made Sengchou abbot of Shiku dasi 石窟大寺, which was the monastery near the imperial cave shrines at Northern Mount Xiangtang.
    Due to its small size, the middle cave at Xiaonanhai is believed to have served as a meditation cave (only). The epitaph of Bhikṣu Sengxian 比丘僧賢, who appears in the second votive inscription (XNH_4), was discovered. Thus we know that he was promoted to  昭玄大統 (Head of the Order/Major Superintendent at the State Bureau of Buddhist Monastic Affairs) and died in 570 (see article by Takuma Nobuyuki 田熊信之 2010). The calligrapher, Sengxian 僧纖, should have been a disciple of Sengchou residing at 雲門寺. 
    Former studies have stressed the connection between Xiaonanhai and Dazhusheng Ku, but Kuramoto holds that the connection between Xiaonanhai and Northern Mount Xiangtang is much more relevant.
    According to Inamoto Yasuo 稲本泰生, the selection of the two verses carved on the rear wall of the cave (XNH_6 with T.1509, 25: 87c11–12, and XNH_7 with T.374, 12: 450a16; 451a1) represents the idea of "upgrading" (yueji 越級) towards attaining Buddhahood, because the recitation of these verses enabled Śākyamuni in former incarnations to become a Buddha even before Maitreya.
    Kuramoto relates "彌勒為天衆説法時間" to Maitreya in Tusita Heaven, but he identifies Śākyamuni as turner of the three wheels in Deer Park, probably in the context of the selected jātaka verses. On the opposite wall, he only mentions the inscriptions with the different gardes of rebirth, skipping the descriptive phrases of Pure Land features.
    The entrance wall has no cartouches, only the illustration of Vimalakīrti and Mañjuśrī.
    Following YenChuanying1998, 400-401, Kuramoto identifies the sources of all four verses (XNH_2) taken from the Buddhāvataṃsaka. Because of the modifications of the fourth verse,  it was believed that the cave is a place where Vairocana dwells. Ding 1988, Yen 1998, and Inamoto 2000 thus identified the Buddha image on the rear wall as Vairocana, while 勝木言一郎 1996,  LiYuqun1997,  李 1999,  謝 XieZhenfa2006 opted for Śākyamuni. Kuramoto himself argues for Śākyamuni. The Dilun school thought that Vairocana is 報身 Buddha in the Huayan jing, and Śākyamuni is 化身 Buddha in the Nirvana Sutra and Da zhidu lun (Prajna Sutras). Therefore, the Buddha on the rear wall next to the verses from these sutras must be Śākyamuni. Compared to the configurations of Dazhusheng Ku--Vairocana on the rear, Maitreya and Amitābha on the side walls, identified in inscriptions--the jātakas of Śākyamuni's former incarnations do not befit Vairocana at Xiaonanhai. Moreoevr, the usual iconography of Vairocana includes representations of the six paths of rebirth on his body.
    When Sengchou embellished the pictorial program of the cave, he should have thought of the main Buddha as Śākyamuni, and thus added the jātakas. In addition, the combination of Vairocana, Maitreya and Amitābha is unknown in the art of the Northern Qi, while there are many examples of steles combining Śākyamuni, Maitreya, and Amitābha.
    Kuramoto's transcription of XNH_3 is incomplete. He abbreviates the middle part, which is heavily weathered on the stone. Śākyamuni, Maitreya, and Amitābha is also the sequence of contemplation found in the Nirvana Sutra after the si nianchu passage (?).
    Kuramoto identifies the final part of XNH_3 as six vows taken by Ajatasatru. The reasons as to why these six vows were added to the si nianchu passage are the same as those found at Northern Mount Xiangtang.
    Kuramoto identifies 念佛，念法，念僧 as the first three of the 六念 from the 梵行 Chapter of the Nirvana Sutra (the other three are 念戒，念施，念天). He thinks that 念佛，念法，念僧 matches the content of Ajatasatru's second vow. After Zhiyi's 菩薩戒義疏 (T.1811, 40: 569a9), 念三寶 before repenting makes the Three Jewels appear in front of oneself: 《菩薩戒義疏》卷1：「令起心念三寶，如在目前。」
    Kuramoto gives context for both verses in XNH_4 (T#374, 12: 497b9–10 and T#374, 12: 426c26–27). He sees a connection to the life of Sengchou, who once converted a hunter who then became a monk (T. 2060, 50: 555a4-5 《續高僧傳》卷16〈3 習禪〉：「青羅獵客執刀
    剪髮。」). Moreover, it is known that Sengchou made use of verses when preaching. Kuramoto assumes that Sengchou use the verse T#374, 12: 426c26–27 when he converted the hunter.
    East cave at Xiaonanhai: the interior is similar to that of the middle cave, but the rear wall has no jātakas, but figures of donors (monks and lay women). East wall: Maitreya reborn below and teaching. Date: a bit later than the middle cave. Exterior wall: Śākyamuni and Duobao Fo sitting in their stupa, Vairocana and two assistants in a smaller niche nearby. This iconography was influenced by Dilun doctrine. This composition type must date to 560-570. The twelve meditating Buddha figures around the stupa are supposed to represent 化佛 from the ten directions. The votive inscription on the base of the stupa is transcribed (see also Yen Chuan-ying). It mentions 十方化佛來 to where Śākyamuni and Duobao Fo sit. West of this scene (at the left-hand side) is a smaller niche. Below the central Buddha is an inscription identifying him as Vairocana. Therefore, the bodhisattvas should be Samantabhadra and Mañjuśrī. The figures resemble those carved in the 560s on the Lou Rui Huayan Stele at Bao Shan Lingquan Si. Here, all three of them are identified in cartouches.
    Below this group are two twin niches. In between them the following inscription: 釋迦□□□
    /于佛及法僧 深起清净信/信敬三寶故 能發菩提心. The legible part corresponds to T.278, 9: 433a12-13 於佛及法僧，深起清淨信，信敬三寶故，能發菩提心。
    The impact of Dilun doctrine: They understood Duobao Fo as a 法身佛 according to the vow this Buddha took to appear after his parinirvana wherever the Lotus Sutra is preached. He could do so because 自身他身法身平等無差別. (Śākyamuni is 化身, Vairocana is 報身佛). This is the message of the exterior wall: 法身平等，三寶常住.
    In sum, Xiaonanhai is not about Vairocana, but about Śākyamuni, and its doctrines resemble those manifested at Northern Mount Xiangtang. The motive of Duobao Ta 多寶塔 ist also found in the upper tier of the southern cave there.
    Southern Cave at Northern Mount Xiangtang:
    Boulder dated 566 with Excerpts from the <hi rend="italic">Mahāparinirvāṇa-mahāsūtra</hi> (T#374, 12: 533b19-534b7) and from the <hi rend="italic">Sutra of Queen Śrīmālā of the Lion’s Roar</hi> (T#353, 12: 218a6–7): The content of the text passages left out in the stone text (533b20-25; 533b29-c9; 533c10-13; 533b29-533c13 (?) ) is found in the Śrīmālā Sutra. The first vow of Queen Śrīmālā is added to these excerpts, while the excerpts themselves do not contain her vows 2 and 3. The three vows of the Queen represents all vows taken by all bodhisattvas. Perhaps her first vow stand here as pars pro toto for all vows.
        Before Queen Śrīmālā took these 3 great vows, she received her vyakarana from the Buddha, and then took ten vows. The tenth of these vows constitutes that the paramita of bodhisattva practice are the True Dharma 正法. The carved excerpts reflect the differences between the southern Nirvana school and the northern Nirvana school (whatever these are).
        p. 16: The texts inscribed on the boulder are an intentional combination of passages. 
        The selection of texts carved by Tang Yong reflects his personal fortune and preferences. The Sutra spoken by Bo is about the Teacher of the State 國師, Chancellor 宰相 Bo 孛, in line with his own aspirations at court. We know that he was a follower of Maitreya, as he once donated a golden Maitreya image (T.2110, 52: 516a25-27: 晉昌王唐邕。造眾義莊嚴大寧國寺。鑄彌勒金像一軀。)
        
        Pillars: the table on p. 18 transcribes the surviving inscriptions on the pillars and identifies the Taisho references. Kuramoto (p. 19) sees a close relationship to the texts carved on the boulder dated 天統二[年] (566) and thus believes the pillars were carved under the Northern Qi. Pillar 1: T.1161, 20: 664ab (觀藥王藥上二菩薩經) recommends the following sequence: 藥王藥上二菩薩/Buddhas of the ten directions/seven Buddhas of the Past/Fifty-Three Buddhas/Thousand Buddhas of the present kalpa/Thirty-Five Buddhas/numberless Buddhas of the ten directions. Kuramoto then gives the sequence as found at Dazhusheng Ku of Lingyu, and in Dunhuang manuscripts S.59 and BD00216, titled 七階佛名, and thus sets out to reconstruct the program of the texts carved on the pillars and their sequence.
        
        The sequence at Northern Mount Xiangtang must have been pillars 1, 2, 3. He argues that the first panel to read was the south-west panel, and the south panel the final panel. On pillar 3, the Twenty-Five Buddha names start there. On the south side panel only the character 樂 remains of a verse that should have been either "諸行无常，是生滅法。生滅滅已，
        寂滅為樂。(T.374, 12: 450a16; 451a1)" or "如來證涅槃，永斷於生死。若能至心聽，常得无量樂。(T#374, 12: 497b9–10)," as the character 樂 is found as the last character only in these two verses in the 七階佛名 (S.59 and BD00216). Thus, the reading sequence started on the south-western panel and ended on the south panel, running in clockwise direction. He reconstructs that pillar 1 and the now lost pillar 2 should have had the Buddhas of the Ten Directions, the Seven Buddhas of the Past, and the Fifty-Three Buddha names. 
        The content of pillar 2, which starts with the quote T.374, 12: 411b28–411c1, is also found at Xiaonanhai, and matches that on the boulder dated 天統二[年] (566). 
        Pillar 3 starts with the Twenty-Five Buddha names, and the second Buddha name from T.426, 14: 70c21–22. After the first Buddha name, the explanation 柬方燃燈界有佛名寳集若人聞名者超世六十劫<!--(T.440, 14: 159c20–21)--> was carved, the content of which accords with the excerpts carved on the boulder dated to 566 (no retrogression on the bodhisattva path, qick attainment of Buddhahood). The second Buddha name from T.426, 14: 70c21–22, 帝寳幢摩尼勝光如來, is also found on the Guanyin Sutra Stele 觀音經碑 from Mujin Si 木井寺 dated to 571. The verse (T.353, 12: 217a24–25) carved on the north-west side was spoken by Queen Śrīmālā before she received vyakarana from the Buddha (her rebirth as 普光如來); it thus represents a guarantee for the attainment of Buddhahood.
        Kuramoto believes (p. 22) that the texts carved on the boulder dated 566 and those carved on the pillars were composed under the guidance of the same monk. First, vows are taken in front of (?) the boulder, then Buddha names were invoked and repentance was done while circumabulating (?) the pillars.
        
        The verses taken from the Sutra of Immeasurable Meaning (T.276, 9: 384c29–385b21) spoken by 80,000 bodhisattvas in praise of the Buddha‘s body on the entrance wall of the inner cave should have been carved at the same time when Southern Cave was made. These verses are also found at other sites (see Mizuno_Nagahiro1937, 61,  and XieZhenfa2006, 383-387).
        The Verses on the Vow for Rebirth 願生偈 (Wuliangshou jing lun: T.1524, 26: 230c13–231b6) carved on the southern outside wall of the porch attest to the upcoming Amitabha belief, as does the sculpture group of the main altar inside the inner cave, which have been identified as Amitabha, Avalokitesvara, and Mahasthamaprapta.
        Text carved at both sides of the stupa dome (above cave 1 雙佛洞, located above cave 3): 
        Three Buddha names taken from T.447, 14: 376a23–24 and the Names of the 12 Kinds of Scriptures (T.675, 16: 674b22–25): The three Buddha names follow in T.675 after the name of Sakyamuni and his predecessors. They thus represent the continuation of the buddhadharma into the future. After the Names of the 12 Kinds of Scriptures follows: 歸命真覺藏識海. Kuramoto notes that in his commentary on the Shidi lun 十地論義疏 (T.2799), Fashang defines "真實決定" (T.2799, 85: 765c8-9: 真實決定者。自體真覺性離緣得也。體非分別，離諸妄想，故云出世間也。) "藏識海" is taken from T.670, 16: 484b11: 藏識海常住, and is also connected to Dilun. According to [Tiantai de 天臺的!] Huisi [teacher of Zhiyi], 藏識 is the same as Buddha nature or tathagatagarbha. Therefore, 歸命真覺藏識海 means "taking refuge in Buddha nature".
        The Ten Epithets of the Buddha (大聖十號) and the prājñāpāramitā spell 般若神咒, followed by 稽首常住<supplied>大</supplied>寳海: The missing character is 大 after ZhangZong2013a, 91. Kuramoto notes that the phrase also appears in Huayanjing T.278, 9: 500c-501a.
        The inscriptions carved at both sides of the stupa dome thus represent the Buddha Jewel and the Dharma Jewel of the Three Jewels (p. 24).
        常住<supplied>大</supplied>寳海 (after the Ten Epithets) symbolizes the Buddha Jewel, and 覺藏識海 (after the Ten Classes of Scriptures) symbolizes the Dharma Jewel. Both terms are Dilun terminology. Therefore, these inscriptions must have been composed under the guidance of a Dilun master. 
        Inside cave 1 (雙佛洞), Sakyamuni sits next to Duobao Fo, like outside the eastern cave at Xiaonanhai.
        A similar composition is also found at Lingquan Si in Lingyu's  靈裕 (518–605) Pagoda, which carries inscriptions (see Adamek 2021, 421-432, especially 429-431, in the inscription dated 632). 
        The sequence of texts is (p. 24): boulder dated 566 (taking vows), pillars (for repentance), veneration of the Buddha image (cave 3), taking refuge in Buddha wisdom, Buddha nature, protection of the Dharma, continuation of the Dharma (stupa dome).
        In his conclusions, Kuramoto holds that the texts at the Southern Cave of Northern Mount Xiangtang (including the boulder dated 566) were all composed under the guidance of the same monk(s). He also stresses the doctrinal affinity of the texts there and those at Xiaonanhai, but there are also distinctions.
        While the Northern Wei cherished the Guanyinjing, there was a shift in practice under the Northern Qi towards taking vows, keeping Mahayana precepts, and invoking Buddha names. The common thread at Xiaonanhai and Northern Mount Xiangtang is the belief that all beings possess Buddha nature, and a practice oriented towards shortening the time span for achieving Buddhahood.
        On the basis of "all beings possess Buddha nature," such issues were also discussed by other patriarchs: Daochuo (Pure Land); Xinxing (Sanjie jiao); Zhiyi (Tiantai); Huike (Chan), and thus the Budhist schools developed (and were transferred to Japan). 
        
    
    
    </abstract>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#Shijingyanjiu2016" type="host">
        <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
            <title>Shijing yanjiu. Di yi ji</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo lang="zh">
            <title>石經研究第一輯</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <dateIssued>2016</dateIssued>
            <issuance>monographic</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>241</start>
                <end>265</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>