<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="YenChuanying1998" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
        <title>Investigation of the Iconography of the Meditation Caves of the Northern Qi Dynasty:
            from the Xiaonanhai Cave to the Caves of Mount Xiangtang</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="zh">
        <title>北齊禪觀窟的圖像考──從小南海石窟到響堂山石窟</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
        <title>Bei Qi changuanku de tuxiang kao: cong Xiaonanhai shiku dao Xiangtang Shan
            shiku</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Yen Chuan-ying 1998</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#yenchuanying" type="personal">
        <namePart transliteration="taiwan" type="family">Yen</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="taiwan" type="given">Chuan-ying</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">顔</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">娟英</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>In this article, Yen Chuan-ying examines Xiao Nanhai and the caves 1 and 2 at Southern Mount Xiangtang in an effort to point out doctrinal similarities. She transcribes and identifies all carved texts, and then elaborates on the doctrinal background for the selected text passages. She also tries to connect the pictorial program of the caves to the inscriptions. For example, she relates the "四念處" text to the representations of jātakas at Xiaonanhai (p. 401), and the visualizations as described in the 觀經 (9 grades of rebirth illustrations) to Buddhāvataṃsaka doctrines (p. 407). She also traces the concept of a Pure Land in the Vimalakirtinirdesa and in the Buddhāvataṃsaka (p. 409). This approach can be misleading, for example, when she constructs a relation between Buddhāvataṃsaka doctrine and the passage from T.232 carved in cave 2 at Southern Mount Xiangtang (p. 426), as she does not take into account phases of construction. (The T.232 passage may have been added later to cave 2 at Southern Mount Xiangtang, or by a different group of donors, compared to the inscription of the Huayan Jing chapters in cave 1.)
        I
        
        
        Xiangtang Shan is close to the 滏口 (Fukou) Pass (xing 陘), the pass through the Taihang
        Mountains that is closest to the Northern Qi capital Ye. Northern Mount Xiantang
        (constructed 550-559) lies on the western slope of this mountain, and Southern Mount
        Xiangtang (founded 565) on the southern slope. Xiaonanhai lies on the southern slope of
        Mount Guigai in Shanying Cun 善應村 in Anyang. It lies in a valley along the waterway that connected Henan and Shanxi.
        
        All three caves at Xiaonanhai are described in full. The reliefs inside the eastern cave are similar to those inside the middle cave (Maitreya in the east and the Pure Land in the West), but they are not as detailed. Therefore, scholars believe that the eastern cave was created after the middle cave. It has an interesting depiction on the outside wall, featuring Śākyamuni and Prabhūtaratna sitting side-by-side inside Prabhūtaratna's stūpa to listen to the Lotus Sutra being preached. Vairocana appears in a nearby smaller niche.
        The western cave might be unfinished. There are sculpted images inside, but no relief carvings. Outside this cave are rows of 40 male donor figures in a 10 x 4 grid.
        
        Middle cave:
        Yen Chuan-ying transcribes all the text carved inside and outside the middle cave, with the exception of the Nirvana Sutra passage dubbed Four Bases of Mindfulness 《四念處》 (T.374, 12: 433c26-434b23). (Note by CW: The middle part of the text is severely weathered and can thus not be transcribed with certainty; therfore, all authors so far avoided transcribing it.) 
        She identifies all carved text, even the fourth verse taken from the Buddhāvataṃsaka (T.278, 9: 441b26–27: “拘那牟尼惠無礙，諸吉祥中最無上，彼佛曾來如此室，是故此地最吉祥。”), although she does not say so. She rather considers this verse a "new composition", but she notes that the carved text exchanges the name of Kanakamuni with Vairocana Buddha (therefore she must refer to T.278, 9: 441b26–27 without saying so).  
        Just like Michael Radich, she gives contexts for all jātakas of the selected passages, with the exception of the jātaka she names “讚佛功德,” (this corresponds to T. 1509,  25: 87c11–12, not identified by Yen), while Michael names it “jātaka on seeing the glorious Buddha in a cave.” In her overall analysis of the carved Nirvana Sutra passages and the Buddhāvataṃsaka verses, Yen stresses doctrinal commonalities of both sutras, and how these are brought to the fore in the text selection at Xiaonanhai Middle Cave.
        
        According to the information derived from the Stele Inscription on the Caves of Mount Fu 釜山石窟之碑 (Sui; 581–618), the caves at Southern Mount Xiangtang were begun in 565 (天統元年) by monk Huiyi 慧義 of Huanyan Si, and from 573 onwards patronized by Gao Anagong 高啊那肱 (died 580). 
        In cave 1, the chapters 4-7 (in scrolls 5-6) of the Huayan jing were carved. (The chapters 3-4 were planned for the right-hand side wall, but never finished). Together with the contents of chapter 8 (賢首品) at Xiaonanhai (represented by verses 2 and 3), this constitutes the entire second (of nine) assemblies of the Huayan jing, named 普光法堂會.
        In her section on "donors" (p. 426-427), she tries to identify some of the individuals named in the inscriptions, and also shows the connection between the twin caves at Southern Mount Xiangtang and Little Mount Xiangtang (Shuiyu Si), Western Cave.
        
        
        
        
    </abstract>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <relatedItem xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#TohoGakuho" type="host">
        <titleInfo transliteration="romaji">
            <title>Tōhō Gakuhō</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo lang="ja">
            <title>東方學報</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <date>1998</date>
            <detail type="volume">70</detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>375</start>
                <end>440</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>