<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Andrews2016" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd"><titleInfo lang="en"><title>The Temple of the Prince who Torched his Body and the Making of Mount Wutai</title></titleInfo><titleInfo type="reference"><title>Andrews 2016</title></titleInfo><name xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#andrews" type="personal"><namePart lang="en" type="family">Andrews</namePart><namePart lang="en" type="given">Susan</namePart><role><roleTerm>author</roleTerm></role></name><abstract>Andrews re-examines the first gazetteer devoted to Mount Wutai, the Ancient Chronicle of Mount Clear and Cool 古清涼傳 (by Huixiang 慧祥, T#2098; 51: 1092c-1100c), already treated in BIRNBAUM 1989a, but she gives a more detailed and more convincing analysis. This scripture fashioned an ancient past for the Temple of the Prince Who Torched his Body 王子燒身寺 on the central peak in the seventh century. T#2098; 51: 1094c: The prince burnt his body n the site of an ancient Asoka stupa. His eunuch-servant Liu Qianzhi 劉謙之 restores his body by recitation of the Avatamsakasutra in this place. Liu writes a commentary in 600 volumes. The Gu Qingliang zhuan is much closer to the YanYi’s (998?-1072) Guang Qingliang zhuan 廣清涼傳 than to Zhang Shangying’s 張商英 Continued Chronicle of Mount Clear and Cool (Xu Qingliang zhuan 續清涼傳; T#2100. On this scripture see Robert Gimello, Chang Shang-ying on Wu-t’ai Shan. In Pilgrims and Sacred Sites in China, ed. by Susan Naquin and Chün-fang Yü, Berkeley: University of California Press 1992). Although they have no zhi 志 in their titels, the Gu Qingliang zhaun and the Guang Qingliang zhuan both are proto-gazetteers 原始方志 (Bingenheimer). The Gu Qingliang zhuan is divided into five chapters. Chapter three: Ancient and Present Superior Traces 古今勝跡; chapter four: Pilgrims Who Experienced Efficacious Responses 遊禮感通. "In compiling the gazetteer, as this example shows, Huixiang brought together narratives forwarding a range of visions of Mount Wutai that worked in concert to enhace its overall prestige."
        Scriptural sources playing a role in the emergence of Mount Wutai as an object of devotion: Huayan jing, translated by Buddhabhadra in ca. 420; Mañjuśrī dharma ratnagarbha dharani sutra (Wenshi shili fabaozang tuoluoni jing 文殊師利法寶藏陀羅尼經, translated by Bodhirucie (672?-727), the Mañjuśrī parinirvana sutra (Wenshu shili ban niepan jing 文殊師利般涅槃經; see David Quinter in Asia Major 23.2 (2010), 97-128). 
        Avatamska sutra interpolation appearing in Buddhabhadra’s and Siksananda’s translation: T#278, 9: 590a; T#279, 9: 241b: Mañjuśrī dwells at Mount Qingliang...
        Accounts of encounters with Mañjuśrī ... put forward a vision of the locale that accords with scriptural tellings of its significance.
        The Gu Qingliang zhaun presents en eclectic vision of the mountain’s significance. While it is tempting to read this diversity as evidence of the historical confluence of autochthonous and Buddhist traditions at Mount Wutai, ... examining the versions of the narrative .... reveals that ... the Gu Qingliang zhuan creates rather than describes the past. ... The Gu Qingliang zhuan suggests that sixth-century Mount Wutai was a center of Mañjuśrī devotion. Taking Huixiang’s text at face value, we would conclude that Northern Qi patronage facilitated the formation of Mount Wutai as a place of Mañjuśrī veneration in the sixth century. Stories promoting the efficacy of chanting the Avatamsake sutra are all set during the reign of Emperor Xiaowen of the Northern Wei (r. 471-499), rather than the Northern Qi period.... The tale about the restoration of the eunuch’s male member ... was essentially a narrative extolling the Avatamsake sutra. Proponents of the Wutai cult subsequently grafted it onto the lore of the Wangzi Shaoshen Tenple, changing the story from one celebrating a text into one framing Mount Wutai as a place of healing visions.... the Gu Qingliang zhuan created rather than described history. Then Andrews provides scriptural examles for the Northern Qi prince’s auto-cremation before a relic mound. ... it may be that the precedent for the auto-cremation of rulers lies outside Buddhism altogether. ... the story of the Northern Qi prince’s self-immolation called to mind autochthonous models of ritual disfiguring of the body studied by Schafer.
        ...the Wangzi Shaoshen Temple founding legend is equally an example of the role the relic cult played in the making of new religious territory. ... the idea that visions of bodhisattvas and buddhas could heal their viewers had a significant pre-seventh-century history. ... The devotee’s sincerity together with the bodhisattva’s power ... bring about recovery when combined with the recitation of a potent text. ...considered Wutai a realm of curatives.
        
        Tansen Sen, Buddhism, Diplomacy, and Trade: emergence of Mount Wutai as an objects of pan-Asian devotion. Before: borderland complex (Forte), then creation of a local sacred landscape, then pan-Asian sacred landscape, then Indian monks make pilgrimages to Mount Wutai. [International pilgrimage centers like Mount Wutai supercede local networks like the 98 character passage!]
        Mount Wutai’s creation as a pilgrimage center of regional, national, and international importance. The writing and rewriting of the Wangzi Shaoshen Temple’s past extended the site’s newfound importance as Mañjuśrī’s dwelling place and a hub of the Buddhist world into the Northern Qi period, and further, to the time of Aśoka. ...framed the site as a worthy focus of imperial attention during the very same period in which ruler Tang Gaozong (r. 650-683) and his consort Wu Zetian (r. 684-705) ... started to be involved there.
        Huize’s 會賾 Longshuo era (661-663) expedition: Instructed by the throne to investigate holy traces 聖跡 ... Huize submitted a report of the favorable omens jiaxiang 佳祥 he witnessed and circulated a map of the mountain. ... The reference to Aśoka’s activities ... provided a model for court patronage of the place.
        Emperoro Wen of the Sui became a model for Empress Wu Zetain, who also promoted a relic-cult...
        Ennin’s ninth-century Nittō guhō junrei gyōki and Yanyi’s eleventh-century Guang Qingliang zhuan establish that at least by the ninth century, Mount Wutai residents and visitors believed that Wu Zetian had been active at the site.
        The mountain’s association with Mañjuśrī attracted powerful patrons including Tang Gaozong and Wu Zetian ... enhanced the sense that they were cakravartin rulers of singularly central Buddhist realms.
        The Gu Qingliang zhuan brings together, first, the account of an unnamed layman’s self-immolation; second, the story of Aśoka’s 84,000 relic mounds; and finally, the tale of an unnamed sixth-century eunuch’s healing.
        The writing and rewriting of the past, this study shows, constituted one means through which trritories werde constructed as holy centers. [It’s all about historiography!]
        
    </abstract><relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#JCBS" type="host"><titleInfo lang="en"><title>Journal of Chinese Buddhist Studies</title></titleInfo><originInfo><issuance>continuing</issuance></originInfo><part><date>2016</date><detail type="volume">29</detail><extent unit="page"><start>91</start><end>127</end></extent></part></relatedItem></mods>