<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Campany1991" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd"><titleInfo lang="en"><title>Notes on the Devotional Uses and Symbolic Functions of Sūtra Texts as Depicted in Early Chinese Buddhist Miracle Tales and Hagiographies</title></titleInfo><titleInfo type="reference"><title>Campany 1991</title></titleInfo><name xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#campany" type="personal"><namePart lang="en" type="family">Campany</namePart><namePart lang="en" type="given">Robert F.</namePart><role><roleTerm>author</roleTerm></role></name><abstract>Campany first lists 
        Devotional Uses: 1. Recitation, 2. Collection. Preservation, and Display: Sūtra as Sacred Commodity, 3. Texts Worn on the Body: The Sūtra as Amulet,
        (on p. 37-38, the story of Xing Huaimingwho who wore the Guanshiyin sutra on his head (T#2122, 53:459b)4. Inviolable Texts: 
        Miraculous Punishment for Desecration of Sūtras;
        then 
        Literary Uses: The Sūtra Text as Symbol: Miraculous Sūtra Recitals by Women as Symbols for the Revelatory Transmission of Dharma, 2. Sūtra as Symbols and Embodiments of the Bodhisattvas’s Responsive Compassion,
        3. The Sūtra as a Metonymic Symbol of Buddhist Norms
        Conclusions:
        54: .. much depends on how they are used, on the functional place they fill in a system of roles and relationships, and how they are perceived, received, and socially constituted. 
        Little importance is attached to the texts as vessels of doctrinal meaning; much importance is attached to the veneration in which the texts are held, .... 
        And this veneration, even when it takes the form of recitation, is not essentially a literary act but an act of faith and of certain quality of mind. ... 
        Yet .... it is the contents of the sūtra texts themselves that set up this functional way of appropriating them. .... many of the sūtras mentioned in the tales 
        teach the efficacy of acts of veneration to themselves, acts such as possession, copying, reciting, wearing, hearing, and making offerings.
        Appendix: Primary Texts and Editions Used, with Dates; Abbreviations; Explanations of Citation Methods 
    </abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><relatedItem xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#JIABS" type="host"><titleInfo><title>Journal of the International Association of Buddhist Studies</title></titleInfo><originInfo><issuance>continuing</issuance></originInfo><part><date>1991</date><extent unit="vol">14</extent><extent unit="no">1</extent><extent unit="page"><start>28</start><end>72</end></extent></part></relatedItem></mods>