<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="ChenHuaiyu2022" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
   
   
    <titleInfo lang="zh">
        <title>中古時期敦煌燃燈文與石燈銘文比較研究</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
        <title>Zhonggu shiqi Dunhuang randeng wen yu shideng mingwen bijiao yanjiu</title>
    </titleInfo>
   <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
        <title>A Comparative Study of Stone Lantern Inscriptions and Lantern-Lighting Texts from Dunhuang in the Middle Ages</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Chen Huaiyu 2022</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#chenhuaiyu" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">陳</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">懷宇</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>Everything that is known about stone lanterns is based either on inscriptions found on surviving specimen, or on Dunhuang manuscripts. From Dunhuang, we have lantern-lighting texts written in both Tibetan and Chinese, which were used in assemblies/maigre feasts 齋會 or in festivals 節慶. Stone lantern pillars have survived in Shanxi, Shaanxi, Hebei, Henan and Shandong (not the parallel to stone sutras!!!). Their inscriptions display the character of memorial monuments 紀念碑性.
    Chen Huaiyu writes much better Chinese than English, yet his Chinese vocabulary is drenched with American academic terminology (he holds a doctorate from Princeton). 
    Stone lanterns  flourished mainly under the Tang, and declined from the ninth century onwards. On the other hand, the lantern-lighting texts from Dunhuang date to the ninth and tenth centuries. “Lantern-lighting text” 燃燈文 is found as headings on liturgical texts among Dunhuang manuscripts. Inscribed stone lanterns, on the other hand, are usually titled “Lantern Praise”  燈讚 or “Lantern Eulogy” 燈頌.  Stone lanterns are are a symbol for the Dharma body of the Buddha. A comparison of stone lantern inscriptions and liturgical lantern-lighting texts (as promised in the title of the present article) reveals the complexity 複雜性 of the issue under study. However, both text groups represent a common cultural heritage 文化遺產, on which is build a common Buddhist identity 體身份.
    He mentions that the idea of an inexhaustible lamp 無盡燈 has come from the Avatamsaka 華嚴. Stone lantern have developed since the Northern dynasties (earliest surviving specimen!) and have probably been influenced from Zoroastrianism 祆教 and from Daoist light rituals 道教燈儀. He elaborates on connections with Buddha Dīpaṃkara 燃燈佛/然燈佛 and on the traditions of offering lamps 供燈, turning the body into a lamp (as a torch--burning for the Buddha) 身燈, inexhaustible lamp 無盡燈, and “lighting lanterns” the 放燈. Rituals of “lighting lanterns” have evolved into “lantern-lighting assemblies.” An important narrative for lantern-lighting rituals is the story of the poor woman Nandā-dīpa 難陀燈, whose donation of oil kept the eternal light 長明燈 burning so that it could not be blown out by Maudgalyāyāna (賢愚經; The Beggar Woman Named ‘Relying on Joy’).
    Chen Huaiyu discusses Dunhuang manuscripts S.1441 v-6 (titled 燃燈文), which refers to Buddha Dīpaṃkara (燃燈佛 and 定光佛).
    Then he quotes several lantern pillar texts (Langfang pillar, Shanxi Dai Xian 觀音寺燈臺頌, a pillar erected by Su Sixu 蘇思勖 (died 745) in 741 (kaiyuan 29) from Chang’an (see GeChengyong2017), and an inscription from 795 mentioned in epigraphical sources and titled 保唐寺毗沙門天王燈幢讚並序. Next, he quotes from manuscript P.T.45VI. He stresses the memorial character of all these inscription (and he translates 紀念碑性 as "monumentality," and I do not understand why). I did not read his utterances on "Buddhist ideology and society." His conclusions on the belief in Buddha Dīpaṃkara includes the little enlightening statement that, under Guiyijun rule in Dunhuang, the Buddhist worldview 佛教宇宙觀 of merit charity 功德施捨 was oriented from the upper social strata to the lower, and in Central China, it was vice versa, from the lower social strata towards the upper.</abstract>
    <language>
        <languageTerm>en</languageTerm>
    </language>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#ShijieZongjiaoYanjiu" type="host">
        <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
            <title>Shijie zongjiao yanjiu</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo lang="zh">
            <title>世界宗教研究</title>
        </titleInfo>
       
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <!--<detail type="volume"></detail>-->
            <detail type="no">7</detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>41</start>
                <end>47</end>
            </extent>
            <date>2022</date>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>