<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="ChenHuaiyu2015" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
 <title>A Study of the Meaning of Tang Dynasty Stone Lanterns</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="zh">
        <title>唐代石燈名義考</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
        <title>Tang dai shideng mingyi kao</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Chen Huaiyu 2015</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#chenhuaiyu" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">陳</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">懷宇</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>In the introduction to this article, Chen Huaiyu quotes his earlier publications. 1.
        唐代的佛教燈臺，燈樓與燈幢: He quotes from Ye Changchi’s Yu shi 語石 and from ChenMingda1960. He refers to
        LiuShufen2008b and criticizes her for calling lantern pillars dengchuang 燈幢, because most self-designations found on such pillars read dengtai 燈臺. Apart from the examples already referred to by Liu Shufen, he adds more dengtai examples from the Tang. He also mentions dengtai from Sichuan (p. 68).
        In sum, Chen Huaiyu collects in this article every single Tang  lantern pillar/tower/base that has survived or is known from epigraphical and other text sources (for example, Ennin’s diary). Whenever available, he quotes the inscriptions carved on these pillars. He does he same for Daoist lanterns and lanterns in Korea and Japan. He concludes that the majority of the inscriptions refer to the respective monuments as dengtai 燈臺. Also found is denglou 燈樓, but dengchuang 燈幢 is very rare and seems to be connected to the cult of Bishamen. Some specimen are referred to as huatai 花臺 with reference to their lotus base. In his opinion, the earliest surviving dengtai might be from the Northern Qi (Shanxi Taiyuan Long Shan Tongzi Si 太原龍山童子寺), but this lantern is heavily weathered and does not seem to have an inscription or date. He also argues that the earliest dengtai of the Tang is the lantern found at Lingyan Si dated to 650 (yonghui 1 永徽元年). However, he obviously never saw the lantern himself, and only quotes the short artcle by Zhang Zong on Mount Tai (ZhangZong2003b_Taishan). Our photographs of this weathered pillar reveal that it has two inscriptions: One with 25 Buddha names, followed by the date of 650. The second is a longer text (maybe a "praise"?), in which are found as self-designation "this Buddha pillar" 是佛幢 and "eternal light" 長明燈. This text is signed by 大沙門靈智 and several names of 清信士, but has no date. As a consequence, Chen’s argument that "dengtai" is the original and earliest designation for this type of monument does not hold. In terms of chronology, denglou might be the earliest, dengtai the most frequent, and Chen does not even consider 長明燈樓. He also mentions a report found in a gazetteer which implies that in 585, some Buddhist followers donated a "longchuang" 龍幢 for the emperor etc. in Zezhou, Jincheng shi in Shanxi 山西晉城市澤州.
    Although Chen collects a lot of material, maybe everything available, his conclusions are not very reasonable, and he seems a bit helpless when he quotes from Buddhist scriptures to say somethig about lamp-lighting rites.</abstract>
    <language>
        <languageTerm>en</languageTerm>
    </language>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#" type="host">
        <titleInfo lang="zh">
            <title>唐宋歷史評論</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
            <title>Tang Song lishi pinglun</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <detail type="no">1</detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>56</start>
                <end>94</end>
            </extent>
            <date>2015</date>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>