<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="ChenHuaiyu2014" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo lang="en">
        <title>Multiple Traditions in One Ritual: A Reading of the Lantern-Lighting Prayers in
            Dunhuang Manuscripts</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Chen Huaiyu 2014</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#chenhuaiyu" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">陳</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">懷宇</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>randeng wen 燃燈文 lantern-lighting prayers in Dunhuang manuscripts; zhaiwen 齋文 texts for
        feasts 
        
        In "redefining the
        lantern-lighting prayers", the author attempts to define this genre without sucess: In sum,
        short prescriptive (he does not know this word) texts on lighting lanterns are found in many
        rituals; here, he only considers rituals focusing on lighting lamps alone, and these are in
        Dunhuang always connected to New Year celebrations. The author translates P.2058 (6), bad
        translation, and gives an "analysis". He translates (part of?) P.2588. He says that S.2850
        and P.3269, which are titled "lantern-lighting prayers" are no such prayers at all. "Three
        traditions in the Latern-lighting prayers": Lamp as a symbol of wisdom; "body lantern" 身燈 in
        the context of self-mutilation; display of lamps 放燈 in festivals. Chen refers randomly to
        Buddhist sutras, hinting at stories and meanings, without text references ( I doubt he
        understands these texts), in an attempt to explain some of the terms found in the two
        lantern-lighting prayers he "translated". He translates a prayer from P.2341v from the time
        of the Tibetan occupation, 781–848) in Dunhuang (dedicated to king Khri-Ide-srong-brtsa, r. 815–841). 
        In sum: Chen Huaiyu focuses on three prayers in Dunhuang
        manuscripts ( P.2058 (6), P.2588, P.2341v) from the 9th-10th century (Guiyijun 歸義軍 period, 851–ca. 1000), which he wants to translate and to understand, but he has no idea how to work
        with texts, or how to annotate a translation. It is unclear why he chose these texts, and
        what his intentions are in translating them. He "compares" prayers "written in Tibetan (1 prayer) and
        Chinese (2 prayers)" without quoting the primary texts, or giving translations. It is unclear to me if
        he is able to read Tibetan at all.</abstract>
    <language>
        <languageTerm>en</languageTerm>
    </language>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <relatedItem xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#Sen2014" type="host">
        <titleInfo lang="en">
            <title>Buddhism Across Asia. Networks of Material, Intellectual and Cultural Exchange.
                Volume 1</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>monographic</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>233</start>
                <end>257</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>