<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Wang_Lei2009" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://claudia:claudia@data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/webdav/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
        <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
                <title>Sichuan Tangdai moya zaoxiang zhong bufen ruixiang de bianshi</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo lang="zh">
                <title>四川唐代摩崖造像中部分瑞像的辨識</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
                <title>Identification of Elements of Miraculous Images in Tang Dynasty Votive Sculptures on Polished Cliffs in Sichuan</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo type="reference">
                <title>Wang Jianping and Lei Yuhua 2009</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#wangjianping" type="personal">
                <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="family">Wang</namePart>
                <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="given">Jianping</namePart>
                <namePart lang="zh" type="family">王</namePart>
                <namePart lang="zh" type="given">劍平</namePart>
                <role>
                        <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
                </role>
        </name>
        <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#leiyuhua" type="personal">
                <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="family">Lei</namePart>
                <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="given">Yuhua</namePart>
                <namePart lang="zh" type="family">雷</namePart>
                <namePart lang="zh" type="given">玉華</namePart>
                <role>
                        <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
                </role>
        </name>
        <abstract>Aśoka images are images of Buddha Śākyamuni said to have been made by king Aśoka.
                The earliest of these images in China date back to the Jin dynasty, but they have
                been produced at least until the Tang dynasty, when Gaozong in 659 decreed that an
                Aśoka image in his likeness was made (T#2106, 52:407a18-19). These images have a
                clearly discernable iconography, and their style preserves influences of the art of
                Gandhara. Wang and Lei examine first Chinese text sources about Aśoka images (mainly
                found in Huijiao’s 慧皎Gaosengzhuan 高僧傳, Daoxuan’s道宣(596-667) Xu gaosengzhuan, and his
                Assembled Records of Response of the Three Jewels in the Spiritual Realm (i. e.
                China) (Ji shenzhou sanbao gantong lu集神州三寶感通錄, T#2106, 52: 404-435). For
                illuminating the legends around the Aśoka images, Wang and Lei quote in detail from
                the biographies of monk Huida 慧達 (T#2059, 50:409b29-c3), monk Tanyi 曇翼 , monk
                Huiyuan 慧遠 , monk Sengming 僧明 (T#2060, 50:692a03-694a14) and monk Mingyu 明馭 (T#2060,
                50: 674b29-c22, who send the renshou relics to Chongfansi in Jizhou 济州崇梵寺, where an
                Aśoka image was housed). The most famous of all Aśoka images is that of Changgansi
                長干寺. Its story is found in the Assembled Records of Response of the Three Jewels in
                the Spiritual Realm (T#2106, 52:414a26-c17). This is the image that was finally
                taken from Changgansi to Daxingshansi 大興善寺 in Chang’an when the Sui dynasty was
                established. From these records, the authors like to extract the following
                historical facts: Five monks from the western regions travelled to India and
                received an Aśoka image. On their way to the capital Ye they got in trouble and hid
                it on a river bank. Therefore, the dissemination route of the Aśoka image runs from
                India via the western regions, entering the Central Plains of China and eventually
                spreading down the Lower Yangtzi area. Furthermore, the Aśoka image developed in
                several stages: First, a bronze lotus pedestal was added, and in the first year of
                Xian’an era (371) the image was completed with a halo that Liang Wudi supplemented
                with seven apsaras and two bodhisattvas. During the era Zhide (583-586), a square
                pedestal was added, and a brocade hat (?) 锦帽 on top of the crown made of seven
                jewels 七宝冠. Under Sui Wendi, a sitting image was made on the basis of the standing
                one. According to a report in X#1623, 87:244c7-9, monk Tanyi came to Sichuan, where
                an Aśoka icon performed the miracle of shedding tears in times of famine. In Xi’an
                lu in Chengdu, an Aśoka image was unearthed that is dated by its votive inscription
                to the year 551. Seven more statues or parts of them from the Xiao and Liang of the
                Southern Dynasties to the Northern Zhou dynasty can be found in Wanfosi. The
                iconography of the Aśoka images is characterized by a very high usnisa, moustache,
                almond shaped eyes, a kasaya covering both shoulders, U-shaped folds of the kasaya,
                the left hand holding a stack of folding, the right hand showing the mudra of
                fearlessness. The authors relate these images to the art of Gandhara, and identify
                more images of this type in Longmen (west hill, Tangzidong 唐字洞,upper part of west
                wall, donation of nun Jingming of Jingfusi 唐代净福寺比丘尼净命with inscription; and on the
                cliff above Huijiandong惠简洞 a niche with two standing figures to the left and right),
                and in Dunhuang (cave 323, inner cave, south wall, mural of东晋杨都金像出渚的感应事迹), as well
                as one in Bazhong (巴中南龕83號窟).</abstract>
        <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#Dunhuangxuejikan" type="host">
                <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
                        <title>Dunhuangxue jikan</title>
                </titleInfo>
                <titleInfo lang="zh">
                        <title>敦煌學輯刊</title>
                </titleInfo>
                <originInfo>
                        <issuance>continuing</issuance>
                </originInfo>
                <part>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <detail type="no">1</detail>
                        <extent unit="page">
                                <start>81</start>
                                <end>93</end>
                        </extent>
                </part>
        </relatedItem>
</mods>