<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="WuHung2008" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo lang="en">
        <title>
            <hi rend="italic">Ji</hi>: Traces in Chinese Landscape and Landscape Painting</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Wu Hung 2008</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#wuhung" type="personal">
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="family">Wu</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="given">Hung</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">巫</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">鴻</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>original meaning of 跡/迹 is footprint. Legend About Yu’s footprints 禹迹 preserved in a hymn in Zuo zhuan, fourth year of the Duke of Xiang 襄四. 古迹 old trace, 遺迹 leftover trace are standard terms for ancient sites of historical interest. a guji or yiji is an integral element of a timeless landscape, but it is always a fragment of the past. Ji transforms nature into human works and vice versa.
    1. 神迹 divine traces as ambiguous signs of supernatural power
    2. 古迹 historical traces as subjects of antiquarian interest
    3. 遺迹 remnant traces as loci of political memory and expression
    4. 勝迹 famous historical sites as meeting places of elite and popular culture; renowned places.
    zu 1.: traces of the hands and feet of the Divine Giant 巨靈 remain on Mt. Hua, the sacred mountain in the west, when he broke the mountain apart into two. Also Cang Jie 倉頡, the creator of writing, who invented Chinese characters from observing the traces of the footsteps of birds. (A genealogy of ancient rulers 帝王世紀, Explaining the graphs nd analyzing the characters 說文解字, and other sources). Different representations of such divine traces: perfectly discernable and isolated, based on literary accounts, not empirical observation; and as an integral feature of the landscape.
    zu 2. as an example, he gives the King Yu Stele 禹王碑 or Goulou Stele 岣嶁碑 (supposedly carved on a natural cliff), already mentioned in stories from the first to the fourth centuries. Han Yu 韓愈 (768-824) was looking for it in vain. Zhu Xi 朱熹 (1130-1200) and Zhang Shi (1132-1180) 張栻 were looking for it in the winter of 1167, also in vain. It is mentioned and described in the Records of Famous Places 與地記勝 by Wang Xiangzhi 王象之 (1163-1230), completed in 127. It was duplicated and erected at Yuelu Shan 岳麓山 near Changsha 長沙 in Hunan, and that duplicate was again duplicated several times. Traditional claim for Yu’s authorship, the text is in tadpole script (kedou wen 蝌蚪文), a type of Daoist writing?. Antiquarianism (jinshi xue 金石學) since the mid-eleventh century transformed divine traces into historical traces. 
    zu 4: Mount Tai as a "memory site" commemorating numerous historical personages and events. </abstract>
    <relatedItem xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#CdEA" type="host">
        <titleInfo lang="en">
            <title>Cahiers d’Extrême-Asie</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <date>2008</date>
            <detail type="volume">17</detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>167</start>
                <end>192</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>