<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="McBride2005" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo lang="en">
        <title>Dhāraṇī and Spells in Medieval Sinitic Buddhism</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>McBride 2005</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#mc_bride" type="personal">
        <namePart type="family" lang="en">McBride</namePart>
        <namePart type="given" lang="en">Richard D.</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>He discusses 1. Jingying Huiyuan (523-592) who analysed dhāraṇī in his Mahayana
        Compendium Dasheng yizhang 大乘義章 (T#1851, 26 fasc.) Following Dharmaksema’s (known as "Great
        Spell Master"大咒师) translation of the Bodhisattva-bhumi (Pusa dichi jing 菩萨地持经), Huiyuan
        classified dhāraṇī in four groups: dharma (fa tuoluoni 法陀罗尼), meaning (yi tuoluoni 義陀罗尼),
        spell technique (zhoushu tuoluoni 咒术陀罗尼) and acquiescence (ren tuoluoni 忍陀罗尼). This taxonom
        was later also employed by Bodhiruci (fl. 508-527) and Xuanzang (ca. 600-664). Dharma and
        meaning dhāraṇī are associated with hearing, completely maintaining, and not forgetting the
        Buddhadharma, the Buddhist teaching. These two types of dhāraṇī may best be thought of as
        “codes.” Spell-technique dhāraṇī, he explains, rely on spiritual efficacy (shenyan ) and are
        something bodhisattvas produce to dispel all adversity. Acquiescence dhāraṇī, the final
        type, allow a bodhisattva to maintain his place on the bodhisattva path. ... Thus, to
        Huiyuan, the acquisition of dhāraṇī, including magic spells and incantations, is a natural
        outgrowth of a bodhisattva’s religious cultivation, particularly samadhi or meditative
        absorption, and is a mark, ornament, or adornment of a bodhisattva’s spiritual attainment.
        The ability to work wonders is presented as a sign of a true bodhisattva. Prior to his death
        in 592, Jingying Huiyuan commanded his disciples that twice a day, before the morning and
        afternoon lecture assemblies, the entire congregation of monks and others participating in
        the lecture should chant the Prajñaparamita or Perfection of Wisdom spell (bore poluomi zhou
        ) fifty times (T 2060, 50.492c18.). This probably refers to the spell found at the end of
        Kumarajiva’s translation of the Heart Sutra. 2. Daoshi (ca. 596-683), produced a Buddhist
        “encyclopedia” called A Grove of Pearls in the Garden of the Dharma (Fayuan zhulin). Two
        fascicles treat dhāraṇī. </abstract>
    <relatedItem xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#JIABS" type="host">
        <titleInfo lang="en">
            <title>Journal of the International Association of Buddhist Studies</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <date>2005</date>
            <detail type="volume">28</detail>
            <detail type="no">1</detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>85</start>
                <end>114</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>