<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd" ID="Muramatsu2021-note">
    There are various translation for the two terms <hi rend="italic">dang lu </hi>當壚 and Huji 胡姬 into English, which we can both read in Li Bai’s another poetry with the title 前有一樽酒行二首:
    <p>春風東來忽相過，金樽淥酒生微波。</p>
    <p>落花紛紛稍覺多，美人欲醉朱顏酡。</p>
    <p>青軒桃李能幾何，流光欺人忽蹉跎。</p>
    <p>君起舞，日西夕。</p>
    <p>當年意氣不肯傾，白髮如絲嘆何益。</p>
    <p/>
    <p>琴奏龍門之綠桐，玉壺美酒清若空。</p>
    <p>催弦拂柱與君飲，看朱成碧顏始紅。</p>
    <p>胡姬貌如花，當壚笑春風。</p>
    <p>笑春風，舞羅衣，君今不醉將安歸？</p>
    
    Edward H. Schafer writes on <ref type="biblio" target="Schafer1963a">27</ref>:
    <p>The zither plays “The Green Paulownias at Dragon Gate,”</p>
    <p>The lovely wine, in its pot of jade, is as clear as the sky.</p>
    <p>As I press against the strings, and brush across the studs, I’ll drink with you, milord;</p>
    <p>“Vermilion will seem to be prase-green” when our faces begin to redden.</p>
    <p>That Western houri with features like a flower——</p>
    <p>She stands by the wine-warmer, and laughs with the breath of spring</p>
    <p>Laughs with the breath of spring, </p>
    <p>Dances in a dress of gauze!</p>
    <p>“Will you be going somewhere, milord, <hi rend="italic">now,</hi> before you are drunk?”</p>
    In the footnote n125 on p. 284 he further writes:
    “[...] ‘Western houri’ is <hi rend="italic">hu chi</hi> [<hi rend="italic">hu ji</hi>], which in Chinese connotes a beautiful lass, with gracious manners, of Western or Northern, probably Iranian, origins. [...]”. See: <ref type="biblio" target="Schafer1963a"/>
    
    Charlie Ng and Phoebe Poon translated the terms as “This exotic lady” and “At the wine table”, see <ref type="biblio" target="Zhangfa2016">132</ref>, while Kidder Smith and Mike Zhai wrote “A Turkic singing girl” and “[tends] the wine pot”. See <ref type="biblio" target="Smith-Zhai2021">21</ref>.
    
    Meanwhile, Owen in <ref type="biblio" target="Owen1981"/> writes “Turkish wench” and “bar”.
    
    <p><ref type="biblio" target="Owen1981">130</ref></p>
    
    <p>Ballad of Youth (second of two)</p>
    <p>A young man of Five Barrows suburb</p>
    <p>east of the Golden Market,</p>
    <p>Silver saddle and white horse</p>
    <p>cross through wind of spring.</p>
    <p>When fallen flowers are trampled all under,</p>
    <p>where is it he will roam?</p>
    <p>With a laugh he enter the tavern</p>
    <p>of a lovely Turkish wench.</p>
    <p>[08045]</p>
    
    <p>少年行二首之二</p>
    <p>五陵年少金市東</p>
    <p>銀鞍白馬度春風</p>
    <p>落花踏盡遊何處</p>
    <p>笑入胡姬酒肆中</p>
    
    
    
    
    <p><ref type="biblio" target="Owen1981">369</ref></p>
    
    <p>4. Ho [Hu] 胡 (a general appellation for Central Asians, Turks, Tartars, etc.) were often associated with tavern keeping (e.g., 02628) but Li Po’s line speciafically echoes lines from Hsin Yen-nien’s [Xin Yannian 辛延年] “Officer of the Guard” [Yulin lang] 羽林郎 (CHs 2.15b):</p>
    
    <p>Relying on our general’s power,</p>
    <p>We tease the Turk of the tavern.</p>
    <p>The Turkish wench is just fifteen,</p>
    <p>On a spring day she stands alone at the bar.</p>
    
    <p>依倚將軍勢</p>
    <p>調笑酒家胡</p>
    <p>胡姬年十五</p>
    <p>春日獨當壚</p>
        
        Since Ishida writes in his sub-chapter that he interprets the Huji 胡姬 in most of the cases meaning Iranian peoples (Sogdians), possibly living among, or already inter-mixed with, Mongol-Turkic peoples in the Northwest, I would suggest we don’t use the exclusive form “Turkish” or “Turkic singing”, but stick to Schafer’s broader term “Western”.
</mods>