<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="LaiFei2003a" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
        <title>Seng’an kejing kaoshu</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="zh">
        <title>僧安刻經考述</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
        <title>On the Investigation of Seng’an’s Engraved Sutras</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Lai Fei 2003</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <subject>
        <hierarchicalGeographic>
            <province>Shandong</province>
            <province>Hebei</province>
            <province>Henan</province>
        </hierarchicalGeographic>
        <topic>stone scriptures</topic>
        <name>Seng’an Daoyi</name>
        <temporal>Northern Dynasties</temporal>
    </subject>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#laifei" type="personal">
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="family">Lai</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="given">Fei</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">賴</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">非</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>Following Kiriya2003a, Lai Fei presents an even more detailed, hypothetical biography
        of Seng’an Daoyi. P. 99 contains his defense for reading the name of the monk as "Seng’an
        Daoyi". He follows Zhang Weiran 張偉然 and Xu Hongguo. He first discusses inscription sites and
        their associated donor names, then the chronology of the sites visited by Seng’an (p.
        115-119): Point of departure: Mount Hongding, region of Chongfan Monastery, Mount Yi, Mount
        Tao, Mount Shuiniu, Yanzhou. P. 115: Lai Fei estimates an age of more than 40 years when
        visiting Mount Hongding, and more than 60 years when writing Mount Ge. Travelling to Ye in
        the west: Da kong wang fo and 無垢佛 、 彌勒佛、獅子佛、明炎佛 at Northen Mount Xiangtang (Lai Fei rejects
        Seng’an as writer of Tang Yong stele). Lai Fei thinks that Seng’an did not take part in Tang
        Yong’s project, but only wrote the Buddhanames in 572. From 572-574, he then wrote sutra
        passages and Da kong wang fo at Southern Mount Xiangtang. Return to the east: In 575, he
        came back with Lady Zhao, whom he had met at the capital when being invited by Tang Yong,
        and created Mount Jian. Fourth phase of propagation of the Dharma with support by members of
        the upper social strata: Mount Tai in 576, which remained unfinished because of persecution
        under Zhou Wudi. Lai Fei believes that this persecution was not as severe as the histories
        want us make believe. In 579, Seng’an wrote Mount Tie, and in 580 Mount Ge. When Mount Gang
        was created, he had probably already died. p. 119-120: These four phases can be arranged in
        two large phases, with Mount Jian as turning point, i.e., before and after 575. The sites
        are different in size, contents (Buddhanames and sutra passages), collaborators,
        calligraphic style, and intention (禪宋 and 護法) p. 120-124 table showing inscriptions by
        Seng’an at the Shandong sites (and steles) and at Northern and Southern Mount Xiangtang,
        passages carved, Seng’an’s signatures and his alleged collaborators. p. 124-131: Explanation
        of the distinctions concerning size, contents, collaborators, calligraphic style, and
        intention within the two phases, before and after 575. </abstract>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#SDSKYS_bwg2003" type="host">
        <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
            <title>Beichao moya kejing yanjiu (xu)</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo lang="zh">
            <title>北朝摩崖刻經研究（續）</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <dateIssued>2003-12</dateIssued>
            <place>
                <placeTerm transliteration="others">Hong Kong</placeTerm>
                <placeTerm lang="zh">香港</placeTerm>
            </place>
            <publisher>
                <name type="corporate">
                    <namePart transliteration="pinyin">Tianma tushu youxian gongsi</namePart>
                    <namePart lang="zh">天馬圖書有限公司</namePart>
                </name>
            </publisher>
            <issuance>monographic</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>92</start>
                <end>134</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>