<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="LeiYuhua1998" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://claudia:claudia@data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/webdav/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
        <title>Sichuan zaoqi fojiao tanyuan</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="zh">
        <title>四川早期佛教探源</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
        <title>An Investigation into Early Buddhism in Sichuan</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Lei Yuhua 1998</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#leiyuhua" type="personal">
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="family">Lei</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="given">Yuhua</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">雷</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">玉華</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>1.It is generally assumed that Buddhism entered the Central Plains of China via the
        Western Regions, and from there came to Sichuan via Guangyuan, proceeding to Dazu. This is
        called the northern route to Sichuan, but there might have been other routes as well. The
        earliest Buddhist site in Sichuan is the Tiancheng cave 天成窟at Qianfoya 千佛崖 in Guangyuan 广元.
        The bodhisattva figures there resemble the sculpture of the Wei dynasty at Maijishan 麦积山 and
        Gongxian 巩县. Some scholars believe that Buddhist art entered Shaanxi through the Hexi
        corridor, and was transmitted from Shaanxi to Guangyuan first, then to other places in
        Sichuan.Recent excavations in Chengdu (商业街，西安路) have unearthedearly Buddhist sculptures with
        a style very different from those sculptures of Guangyuan that were introduced from the
        north. A Maitreya Buddha from Xi’an lu resembles in style paintings from the Southern
        Dynasties in the style of 秀骨清象 (elegant bones, clear appearance). The sculptures from the
        Southern Dynasties discovered in Chengdu are also not entirely alike the contemporaneous
        sculpture from the Central Plains. 2. There are many more differneces between the Chendu
        sculptures excavated in Xi’an Lu and Luoyang sculpture. The iconographic motives are more
        diversified in Chengdu, including Maitrya, Amitayus, Śākyamuni and Prabhūtaratna, and Three
        Buddhas not referring to the three times, but to the three directions or trikaya. In fact,
        when the Northern Wei dynasty transferred the capital to Luoyang in 494, one reason for
        doing so was to be closer to Han culture, and the model of this culture was held to be the
        Chinese South. 3. Before Northern Buddhism entered Sichuan via Guangyuan, Buddhism was
        already flourishing in Sichuan. 4. Even though there is no doubt that the Buddhist teaching
        reached China via Central Asia and the Silk Road, since ancient times, at least two more
        routes connected India with China: The southeastern sea route, and the southwestern Sichuan
        - India route (蜀 - 身毒道). The southwestern route existed already before the Han dynasty,
        maybe even in the 5th century BCE, and connected ancient India with the states of Chu 楚, Wu
        吳, and Shu 蜀, from today’s Sichuan to Yunnan and then to India. Under the Qin 秦 dynasty,
        already two roads existed between Sichuan and Yunnan, the Bo 僰 route, and the Qingyi 青衣道
        route. The sea route betweenWu and India already existed before the Han dynasty, and the
        connection between Sanxia 三峽 (east of Chengdu) and Chu/Wu can be traced back to the late
        Neolithic. Monk Faxian 法顯, who travelled to India in 399, returned on the searoute in 412,
        when he landed in Shandong and made his way from there to Jiankang 健康 (today’s Nanjing). It
        can be assumed that Buddhism had already reached Sichuan from the east or south before it
        was introduced via the northern route. 5. Lei Yuhau goes on to list objects with early
        Buddhist representations (stone sculpture, money trees, ceramics, painted bricks) in
        Sichuan. Leshan has to be taken as the eastermost point of the southwestern India - Sichuan
        route. But also in neighboring Hubei in Ezhou 鄂州 (the ancient city of Wuchang 武昌城) Buddhsit
        motivs are found on bronze mirrors. From here, Buddhism spread into Jiangsu and Zhejiang, as
        excavations of tombs from the Six Dynasties have shown. From that time, no Buddhist
        artefacts are found in the north of China. Therefore it can be assumed that from the end of
        the Eastern Han to the Jin dynasty, Buddhism flourished first in the western parts of
        Sichuan, Hubei, Jiangsu and Zhejiang, and developed its own characteristics.The art of cave
        temples and its related styles were introduced later from the north.</abstract>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#SichuanWenwu" type="host">
        <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
            <title>Sichuan wenwu</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo lang="zh">
            <title>四川文物</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <date>1998</date>
            <detail type="no">5</detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>39</start>
                <end>42</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>