<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="LeiYuhua2005b" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://claudia:claudia@data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/webdav/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
        <title>Sichuan moya shike zhong de Emituofo yu wushi’er pusa</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="zh">
        <title>四川摩崖石刻中的阿彌陀佛與五十二菩薩</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
        <title>Buddha <foreign lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Surrounded by 52 Bodhisattvas Carved on Polished
            Cliffs in Sichuan</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Lei Yuhua 2005b</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#leiyuhua" type="personal">
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="family">Lei</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="given">Yuhua</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">雷</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">玉華</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <!--<name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#wangxiaomeng" type="personal">
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="family">Wang</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="given">Xiaomeng</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">王</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">小蒙</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>editor</roleTerm>
        </role>-->
    <!--</name>-->
    <abstract>Lei Yuhua distinguishes four types of representations of Amitābha’s Pure Land: 
        Type A
        consists of Buddha Amitābha and two standing bodhisattvas, sometimes with additional
        disciples, heavenly kings, and guardians (盛唐, Guangyuan 广元 cave 89). 
        
        Type B represents
        Buddha Amitābha with two bodhisattvas standing or sitting, surrounded by many smaller
        bodhisattva figures sitting on lotuses (Bazhong 巴中 southern caves 33, 62, western caves 37;
        also in Tongjiang 通江, Wangcang 旺苍, and Zitong 梓潼.  Zhenguan to Kaiyuan eras, 627-741). 
        
        Type C has two subtypes: 
        C1 has Buddha Amitābha and two bodhisattvas with heavenly buildings to the
        left and right from the middle of the 8th century (Bazhong western cave 53); 
        C2 is the fully developed Western Paradise with heavenly architecture, trees, lotus pond, birds, musical
        instruments, and the 16 visualizations of queen Vaidehi from the middle of the 8th century
        to the Southern Song dynasty (Dazu 大足 Beishan 北山 Fowan 佛湾 cave 245, Baoding 宝顶 Dafowan 大佛湾
        cave 18).
        
        On type B: The earliest sculptures of this type are found in Guangyuan Qianfoyan
        千佛崖 and Huangzesi 皇泽寺 from the late Northern Dynasties. They also show the influence of the
        Southern Dynasties (Chengdu). During the Tang dynasty, this motif flourished in Guangyuan,
        and also in Bazhong, in a particular large scale. These two sites are situated along two
        important routes linking Sichuan to Chang’an and Luoyang; the 金牛道 and 米仓道. The 金牛道 connected
        Chang’an with Sichuan; the 米仓道 the Central Plain with Bazhong. Therefore it is assumed that
        Sichuan received the impact of Chang’an and Luoyang, but it is so far unclear which
        influences came from Chang’an, which from Luoyang. In Longmen, more than 71% of all images
        represent Amitābha and bodhisattva Guanyin. In Longmen, there is one representation of
        Amitābha with 52 bodhisattvas which dates to the era Gaozong (ca. 660-683) [she doesn’t say
        where exactly in Longmen; should be Wanfodong]. There are a few differences between these
        representations in Longmen and those in Sichuan. Some features of the Longmen
        representations that show up there since the Kaiyuan era are found earlier in Sichuan.
        Therefore, Lei concludes that the Sichuan examples are not influenced by Longmen [she does
        not consider that vice versa, Sichuan might have influenced Longmen], but rather by
        Chang’an. 
        For evidence she relates to Binxian Dafosi, where some examples of lotus thrones
        interconnected by stems can be found [she probably relates to Qianfodong, but these also
        date later than the Sichuan examples]. Another characteristic of the Sichuan sculptures are
        the extremely reluctant jewellery; this points more to Chang’an than to the richly
        embellished bodhisattva statues of Luoyang. After the Kaiyuan era, representations of the
        Western Pure Land in Sichuan belong to type C. </abstract>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#KaoguYuWenwu" type="host">
        <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
            <title>Kaogu yu wenwu</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo lang="zh">
            <title>考古與文物</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <date>2005</date>
            <detail type="no">2</detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>76</start>
                <end>79</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
    <classification edition="#ChengduKaoguyanjiu_1">reprint</classification>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#ChengduKaoguyanjiu_1" type="host">
        <note>reprint</note>
        <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
            <title>Chengdu kaogu yanjiu 1</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo lang="zh">
            <title>成都考古研究（一）</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <dateIssued/>
            <issuance>monographic</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>649</start>
                <end>654</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>