<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="LiSisheng1991" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://claudia:claudia@data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/webdav/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
        <title>Yi Fo wushi pusa he pusa zhuang Fo</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="zh">
        <title>一佛五十菩薩和菩薩裝佛</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
        <title>One Buddha and Fifty Bodhisattvas and the Buddha Jeweled like a Bodhisattva</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <abstract>Official English translation: “One Buddha and Fifty Bodhisattvas and the Decoration of Bodhisattvas”, taken from CNKI.</abstract>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Li Si­sheng 1991</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <abstract>Official English translation: “One Buddha and Fifty Bodhisattvas and the Decoration of Bodhisattvas”</abstract>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#lisisheng" type="personal">
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="family">Li</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="given">Sisheng</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">李</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">巳生</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <!--<name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#yangxiong" type="personal">
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="family">Yang</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="given">Xiong</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">楊</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">雄</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>editor</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>-->
    <abstract>Both motifs, One Buddha and Fifty Bodhisattvas and the Buddha Dressed like a Bodhisattva flourished during the Wu Zetian era. When the motif of  One Buddha and Fifty Bodhisattvas started to decline, the motif of the Buddha Dressed like a Bodhisattva started to rise.
        As source for the motif of one Buddha and fifty bodhisattvas, Li Sisheng quotes the story in Ji Shenzhou sanbao gantong lu T#2106, 52: 421a17–b3, and he also refers to the biography of Huihai 惠海 （541–609）in Xu gaoseng zhuan T#2060, 50: 515c6–516a6, who is said to have received from a certain monk Seng Daoquan 僧道詮 from Qizhou 齊州 a "figure of Amitāyus arriving" with the information that "the Indian Bodhisattva Wutong of Kukkuṭa Monastery rode through the air to Sukhāvatī to portray the appearance of the Buddha." Huihuai is said to have revered the image sincerely to the end of his life, receiving auspicious signs from it.(T#2060, 50: 515c14–19: 忽有齊州僧道詮。齎畫無量壽像來云。是天竺雞頭摩寺五通菩薩。乘空往彼安樂世界圖寫尊儀。既冥會素情深懷禮懺。乃覩神光炤爍。慶所希幸。於是模寫懇苦。願生彼土。沒齒為念。).  Li Sisheng lists occurrences for this motif in Sichuan for Tongjiang, Bazhong, Danleng, Mianyang and Dazu, and additional occurrences in Dunhuang (Mogao cave 332) and Longmen (Wanfo Cave, Jingshan cave, Gaoping jun wang cave). He notes a wide range of variation of this motif, which goes back to Indian samples of the fifth and sixth centuries (which have not survived).  
        Moreover, the motif of One Buddha and Fifty Bodhisattvas is a forerunner of Amitabha paradises. In Tantric Buddhism, Amitāyus presides Sukhāvatī in the west as one of the four Buddhas. He is also part of many kinds of mandalas. </abstract>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#DunhuangYanjiu" type="host">
        <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
            <title>Dunhuang yanjiu</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo lang="zh">
            <title>敦煌研究</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <dateIssued/>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <date>1991</date>
            <detail type="no">2</detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>49</start>
                <end>58, 119–123</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>