<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="LiuHui2003" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
        <title>Tai Shan Daimiao kao</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="zh">
        <title>泰山岱廟考</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="translated" lang="en">
        <title>A Study of the Dai Temple at Mount Tai</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Liu Hui 2003</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#liuhui" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">劉</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">慧</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>p. 138: 磚 brick When digging a groove for the installation of a lightning arrester at
        Renan Gate 仁安門 in January 1985, about 150 cm below ground level, architectural remains came
        to light. p. 139: Different kinds of 瓦當 eaves-tiles were found, among them four tiles with
        lotus decor. Diameters vary from 13-15 cm. Beads and lotus leaves. 瓦當 eaves-tiles are also
        called 筒瓦頭 (hanging edge of a dripping tile) p. 141: In August 1984, eaves-tiles with lotus
        decor were found at Shentong Monastery 神通寺. Those with eight lotus leavea resemble those
        unearthed in Daimiao. ( see 王建浩，山東濟南神通寺殿堂遺址的清理。 考古， 1996 年， 第1期。) At the same site in
        Shentong Si a large-size gutter 大型滴水 was found, p. 142: which is very similar to a gutter 滴水
        found in October 2002 in Daimiao, when work was undertaken on the road at the north side of
        Xihua Gate 西華門. Its decor is from the Tang. Other eaves-tiles found at Ren’an gate date to
        the Han dyansty, providing evidence that buildings stood there already a long time ago. This
        must have been the Lower Tempel 下廟 of the three tempels 三廟 already mentioned in the 水經注,
        with trees from the time of han Wudi. Continuation of construction is given until the High
        Tang. </abstract>
    <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>2003</dateIssued>
        <place>
            <placeTerm transliteration="pinyin">Jinan</placeTerm>
            <placeTerm lang="zh">濟南</placeTerm>
        </place>
        <publisher>
            <name type="corporate">
                <namePart transliteration="pinyin">Qi Lu shushe</namePart>
                <namePart lang="zh">齊魯書社</namePart>
            </name>
        </publisher>
    </originInfo>
</mods>