<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="LiuShufen1997" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo lang="zh">
        <title>經幢的形制、性質和來源<hi rend="dash">──</hi>經幢研究之二</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
        <title>Jingchuang de xingzhi, xingzhi he laiyuan: jingchuang yanjiu zhi er</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
        <title>The Shape, Nature, and Origin of Sutra Pillars: Studies in Sutra Pillars, Part 2</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Liu Shu­fen 1997</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <abstract>In her section on lantern pillars 燈幢 (p. 691-692), Liu Shufen only quotes from epigraphic sources. She does not write which of these pillars, if any, is still extant. She defines lantern pillars 燈幢 as lantern platforms/towers 燈臺 that imitate sutra pillars 經幢. (Actually, 燈幢 and 燈臺 are usually both translated into English as "lantern pillars.") They combine the purpose of illumination with the supernatural powers of dharani pillars [quote from <ref type="biblio" target="Jinshicuibian">juan 66, page 8</ref>]. On lantern pillars, the <hi rend="italic">Glorious Buddha Crown <foreign xml:lang="sa">Dhāraṇī</foreign>
        </hi> 尊勝咒 was "often" carved [she quotes <ref type="biblio" target="Jinshicuibian">juan 66, page 9-10</ref> for one example dated to 748, and <ref type="biblio" target="Baqiongshijinshibuzheng">juan 47, page 4</ref>, for another dated to 752].
        On some lantern pillars, the Sutra Spoken by the Buddha on the Merit of Donating Lamps was carved. Liu quotes one example from epigraphic literature, <ref type="biblio" target="Jinshicuibian"> juan 66, page 15-16</ref>, an octagonal pillar dated to 759, with this sutra and the Glorious Buddha Crown Dhāraṇī. Then she refers to The Qinglong Si pillar of 831 by Du Wenxiu, quoting the excavation report published in 1989.
        Some lantern pillars are shaped like stone pillars, but have no sutra or dhāraṇī texts carved on them. Liu gives as example the lantern pillar in Kaihua Si 開化寺 in Yuanshi Xian 元氏縣 in Henan, donated by Zhao Yongan 趙永安 and others and dated to 752.
    </abstract>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#liushufen" type="personal">
        <namePart type="family">Liu</namePart>
        <namePart type="given">Shufen</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">劉</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">淑芬</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#ZYY_lishiyuyan_yjs_jikan" type="host">
        <titleInfo lang="zh">
            <title>中央研究院歷史語言研究所集刊</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
            <title>Zhongyang yanjiuyuan lishi yuyan yanjiusuo jikan</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <date>1997</date>
            <detail type="volume">68</detail>
            <detail type="no">3</detail>
            <extent>
                <start>643</start>
                <end>786</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>