<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="LiuYuantang2013" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
        <title>Zhonghuang Shan Bei Qi kejing jingzhu he kanke shijian bianxi</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="zh">
        <title>中皇山北齊刻經經主和刊刻時間辨析</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
        <title>A Discussion of the Donors and the Date of the Stone Carvings at Mount Zhonghuang from the Northern Qi Dynasty</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Liu Yuan­tang 2013</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#liuyuantang" type="personal">
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="family">Liu</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="given">Yuantang</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">劉</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">元堂</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <!--<name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#lvxiaoxiang" type="personal">
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="family">Lü</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="given">Xiaoxiang</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">吕</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">小鄉</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>editor</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>-->
    <abstract>This is a summary of the available secondary literature on the date and donor of Mount Zhonghuang. The author discusses four assumptions:
        1. Emperor Wenxuan (文宣帝 r. 550–559) of the Northern Qi was the donor; the project was started at the end of the tianbao era 天保 (550–559). The edition of the the 4th year of the Jiaqing 嘉慶 reign (1799) of the <hi rend="italic">She County Gazetteer</hi> 《涉县志》(Shexianzhi_Jiaqing_1799, juan 1, 6–7) has a report in the first juan that reads:
        “唐王山，縣西二十里，一名唐王嶠[jiao4]，後唐莊宗伐梁時常過此，因名。山下舊有北齊時離宫，傳載文宣帝高洋，自鄴詣晉陽，往来山下，起離宫以備巡幸，於此山腰見數百僧行過，遂開三石室，刻諸尊像。
        及天保末，又使人往竹林寺取經函，勒之岩壁，今山上經像現存。世傳唐文宗駐蹕處者誤。上有媧皇廟，香火特盛。”
        “Mount Tang Wang, located twenty li west of the county town, also called Peak Tang Wang, is named after Emperor Zhuangzong 莊宗 (r. 923–926) of the Later Tang 後唐 (923–937), who passed through this place when he attacked the [Later] Liang (907–923). At the foot of the mountain is a palace (for the initerant court) of the Northern Qi. Tradition has it that Gao Yang, the Emperor Wenxuan (r. 550–559), when travelling from the [lower capital] Ye to the [upper capital] Jinyang, passed by the foot of the mountain; [therefore], a palace was erected to provide [a residence] during his imperial tours. When [the emperor] saw that several hundreds of monks once passed by the mountain waist, he had three stone chambers opened and sculptures carved. At the end of the tianbao era, he also sent a messenger to Zhulin Monastery to fetch sutra cases [in order to] carved the texts on the cliffs. On the mountain, the sutras and sculptures are still extant. [The story that] circulates among common people that is was a resting place for the Tang Emperor Wen (r. 826–840) is wrong. On top of the mountain, the Empress [Nü]wa Temple is located, where the burning of incense is especially abundant.” 
        This assumption is voiced by WangXuezhong1991.
        2. The donor is Tang Yong, the carving started at the end of the tianbao era 天保 (550–559) and stopped during the tiantong 天統 era (565–570)。 Voiced by Fan Shouming 范壽銘 (1871–1922) in his Xun Yuan jinshi ba wei  循園金石跋尾 (Xunyuanjinshibawei), 卷下. He thought that the term “令王” found in a damaged votive inscription for a sculpture at the entrance to the cave refers to Tang Yong (who is 令 and 王): 
        “邕遷尚書令，封晋昌王，在武平之初，則此三洞佛經为天統閒刻無疑。” [Tang] Yong was promoted Director of the Department of State Affairs, and appointed Prince of Jinchang at the beginning of the wuping era (570–575). There is no doubt that these three caves were carved during the tiantong 天統 era (565–570)
        3. The donor is Tang Yong, and the carving was completed at the end of the tiantong 天統 era (565–570): Voiced by Li Yuqun (LiYuqun1997, 449, 474) and Lai Fei (LaiFei2000b, 7). 
        Li Yuqun thinks that the report about Emperor Wenxuan (Gao Yang) opening the caves in the <hi rend="italic">She County Gazetteer</hi> is the result of a far-fetched connection made by the compilers of the gazetteer to the <hi rend="italic">Record on the Restoration of the Hall of the Buddhas of the Three Ages</hi> 《重修三世佛殿記》of 1159 (正隆四年) at Northern Mount Xiangtang.
        He also notes the connection between Tang Yong and his wife, Lady Zhao, one of the donors at Mount Jian (dated 575). He concludes that all great sutra were completed on Mount Zhonghuang in 575. The votive inscription and sutra text for the deceased Lady Zhao
        (小山梁趙妃母刻經) was carved between 575 and 576. 
        Lai Fei argues that, as it took Tang Yong 4 years to complete his project at Northern Mount Xiantang, it must have taken at least 5 years to complete the carvings at Mount Zhonghuang. Therefore, Lai dates the Mount Zhonghuang carvings to 570–575.
        4. The donors is Tang Yong, the carving started at the end of the tianbao era 天保 (550–559) and stopped sometime between the end of the tiantong 天統 era (565–570) and the beginning of the wuping era (570–575). Voiced by Ma Zhongli (MaZhongli2003, 259), who ascribes Mount Zhonghuang and the Northern and Southern Mount Xiangtang to Tang Yong.
        MaZhongli2006b, 43: 中皇山摩崖佛经...开始于北齐“天保末年”，终于北齐天统末年至武平初年，
        I. The donor is Gao Yang:
        This is based on the report in <hi rend="italic">She County Gazetteer</hi> 《涉县志》(Shexianzhi_Jiaqing_1799, juan 1, 6–7).
        However, there is a very similar report found on the stele titled <hi rend="italic">Record on the Restoration of the Hall of the Buddhas of the Three Ages</hi> 《重修三世佛殿記》of 1159 (正隆四年).
        The stele is in Changle Monastery 常樂寺 at Northern Mount Xiangtang (photographs at stonesutras1/Images/Hebei/Xiangtangshan/Bei Xiangtang/Changle Temple/IMG_0109 to IMG_0128 and IMG_0134). The report reads:
        “文宣帝常自鄴都詣晉陽，往来山下，故起離宫已備巡幸。於此山腰見數百僧聖僧行道，遂開三石室，刻諸尊像，因建此寺。
        初名石窟寺，後主天統閒改智力，宋嘉祐中复更名常樂寺...”
        “Because Emperor Wenxuan (r. 550–559) often traveled from the [lower capital] Ye to the [upper capital] Jinyang, [thus] passing by the foot of the mountain, a palace was erected to provide [a residence] during his imperial tours. When [the emperor] saw several hundreds of holy monks practicing the Way on the mountain waist, he had three stone chambers opened [there] and had sculptures carved. Thus, this monastery was founded. It was first named Stone Cave Monastery (Shiku Si), but Emperor Houzhu 後主 (r. 565–576) changed it to Zhili [Monastery] during the tiantong 天統 era (565–570). During the jiayou era (1056–1063) of the Song, it was re-named Changle Monastery.”
        It has been suggested that the record in the <hi rend="italic">She County Gazetteer</hi> has been taken from the Changle Monastery Stele. The History of the Northern Qi 北齊書 in its present version does not mention a palace for imperial tours on Mount Tang Wang (Mount Zhonghuang); therefore, the gazetteer report was copied from the stele.  
        Li Yuqun (LiYuqun1997, 449) suggests that the compilers of the gazzetteer related the Mount Xiangtang report to the Peak Tang Wang. 
        However, Ma Zhongli (MaZongli1991) refutes Li Yuqun's suggestion by pointing out that (1) there should have been many palaces for imperial tours 離宫 along the way 
        (2) there are also three caves at Mount Zhonghuang
        (3) the History of the Northern Qi 北齊書 neither mentions the palace at Mount Zhonghuang nor the one at Northern Mount Xiangtang.
        Therefore, the author (Liu Yuantang) lends credibility to the report of the <hi rend="italic">She County Gazetteer</hi>. Additional arguments by the author: 
        (1) Recently, we know that Northern Mount Xiangtang was begun during the final years of the Eastern Wei (534–550) and finished under the Northern Qi. Li Yuqun (or does he mean TangZhongming2004, 25?) suggests three phases: 534–547; 549–560; 561–565. Therefore, the <hi rend="italic">Record on the Restoration of the Hall of the Buddhas of the Three Ages</hi> is not reliable [der Autor hat keine Ahnung vom Genre!]. (2) Yu shi juan 1: “高齊之初，镌山腹寫一切經” relates to Mount Zhonghuang.(MaZhongli2006b) Taiping huanyu ji [Universal Geography of the Taiping (976-983) Era]《太平寰宇记》(Taiping_hyj2007) and the 《郡国志》(now lost) quoted therein are reliable. (3)Juan 16 of the Wu’an Xian Gazetteer 《武安縣志》 (乾隆四年, 1739) provides evidence for the existence of an imperial palace of Gao Yang at Northern Xiangtang Shan: “今故邑人大司寇胡礪常樂寺碑文云: 文宣自鄴都詣晉陽，往来山下⋯⋯刻諸尊像。《齊志》又云: 文宣天保末，常使人駱駝往竹林寺取經函。相傳竹林寺即在常樂寺旁，則是高洋勒經於崖壁，開鑿石室、供佛像無疑也⋯⋯”。The text of the <hi rend="italic">Changle Monastery Stele of the Supervisor/Head of the Townspeople Past and Present, Kou Huli</hi>, reads: “Gao Yang, the Emperor Wenxuan (r. 550–559), when travelling from the [lower capital] Ye to the [upper capital] Jinyang, passed by the foot of the mountain; ... he had sculptures carved. The <hi rend="italic">Records of the Qi</hi> [an earlier incarvation of the Bei Qi shu, now lost] say: At the end of the tianbao era, he often sent messengers on camels to Zhulin Monastery to fetch sutra cases. It is transmitted that Zhulin Monastery was located close to Changle Monastery. Therefore, [Changle Monastery] is without doubt [the place] where Gao Yang had sutras carved on the cliffs, opened stone chambers, and donated Buddhist images.”
        We know that it was Tang Yong who carved sutras at Northern Xiangtang Shan, not Gao Yang. This report should refer to the carvings at Mount Zhongshan. It fits the entry in the 1799 She County gazetteer about Mount Tangwang 唐王山. (4) The scope of the Mount Zhonghuang carving project of several thousand characters was too expensive even for high ministers (such as Tang Yong) at the Northern Qi court. Therefore, it should be a project of Gao Yang, who once said to Sengchou: “from now on, We will divide the [annual] state revenue into three parts, that is to say, one to be given to the country, one for Our Own use, and then one for the Three Jewels (the Buddhist institutions).” (LL in Shandong 1, 26) 今以國儲分為三分，謂供國、自用及以三寶。(T.2060, 50: 554b24–26)
        II. The donor is Tang Yong
        first voiced by Fan Shouming 范壽銘 (1871–1922) in his Xun Yuan jinshi ba wei  循園金石跋尾 (Xunyuanjinshibawei, 14476–14477); Preface 1922), 卷下, under the entry 涉縣摩崖佛經跋. Liu Yuantang quotes Fan at length, and then dismantles his arguments (p. 46: "...该跋存有诸多错误或不能使人信服的地方。").
        
        Conclusions, p. 47: 综上所述，中皇山刻经“经主是唐邕说”缺乏令人信服的证据，由此推断出的刻经时间也不足为信。“经主为高洋，刻经于天保末年”说具有较高
        的可信度。但它毕竟是《涉县志》的“传载”，不能以此为定论。这个问题的彻底解决还有待于新材料
        的发现。In sum, the “Tang Yong is the donor thesis” lacks convincing evidence, and the date of the carving inferred from this thesis is also unreliable.
        The thesis that Gao Yang (文宣帝 r. 550–559) was the donor, and that the inscription were carved at the end of the tianbao era (550–559) has a relatively high probability.
        However, because this thesis appears as a “transmitted report” in the <hi rend="italic">She County Gazetteer</hi> (of the 4th year of Jiaqing, 1799), it cannot be taken as a definite conclusion. A complete solution to this problem awaits the discovery of new materials. </abstract>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#GuoxueChazuo" type="host">
        <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
            <title>Nanjing yishu xueyuan xuebao</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo lang="zh">
            <title>南京藝術學院學報</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <date>2013</date>
            <detail type="no">3</detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>44</start>
                <end>47</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>