<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Sano2017" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo transliteration="romaji">
        <title>Zui-Tō ni okeru Bukkyō meikai yugyōtan no henka: Enra ō to <hi rend="italic">Kongō kyō</hi> soshite sōsaku no hōga</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="ja">
        <title>隋唐における仏教冥界遊行譚の変化：閻羅王と金剛経そして創作の萌芽</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
        <title>Changes in Buddhist Stories about Visits to the Underworld in the Sui and Tang Dynasties: King Yama, the <hi rend="italic">Diamond <foreign xml:lang="ja">Sūtra</foreign>
            </hi>, and the Birth of Fiction</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Sano 2017</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#sano" type="personal">
        <namePart transliteration="romaji" type="family">Sano</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="romaji" type="given">Seiko</namePart>
        <namePart type="family">佐野</namePart>
        <namePart type="given">誠子</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>Einleitung 93–95: frühester Auftritt von Yama im Luoyang qielan ji (T#2029) von 547, übersetzt Wang Yi-tung 73–76. Only meditation and chanting sutras is acceptable.
        1. King Yama erscheint in Reisen durch die Hölle-Geschichten return-from-death narratives 冥界遊行譚 95–98: 
        Faxian erwähnt Yama in seinem Reisebericht.
        Chu sanzang jiji (T#2145, 55: 107a26–c22) by Sengyou, juan 15: 白法祖 Bo Fazu. Also read in Chinese as Bai Fazu. Also called Bo Yuan 帛遠, Bo Fazu 帛法祖, and Bo Yuan (Bai Yuan) 白遠. A Chinese monk originally from Henei 河內. Worked translating in Chang’an 常安 between 290 and 306. Is said to have read the 首楞嚴經 sutra to Yama: 《出三藏記集》卷15：「後少時有一人。姓李名通死而更蘇云。見祖法師在閻羅王處為王講首楞嚴經云。講竟應往忉利天。」(CBETA, T55, no. 2145, p. 107, b29–c2)
        Also in Gaoseng zhuan by Huijiao, T#2059, 50: 327b16–18.
        
        Liu Sahe 劉薩荷 (Huida 慧達): Mingxiang ji 冥祥記 by Wang Yan 王琰, assembled around 490 (story 45) and Fayuan zhulin (juan 86): Liu Sahe meets Guanshiyin in the earth prison, who tells him: "The sutras are venerable texts, fords of transformative instruction. The merit attached to the [Prajnaparamita sutra is foremost; that of the Surangama [sutra] is next. For persons of goodness, the place where [these] sutras are recited and chanted will become a [space of] diamonds 若有善人讀誦經處。其地皆為金剛, but the many beings who have only eyes of flesh cannot perceive this. If you can recite [them] diligently, you will not fall into the earth prisons. The final version of the Prajnaparamita [sutra] and the alms bowl of the Tathagata will later reach the Han land in the east. If you can establish one act of merit with respect to this sutra or this bowl, you will receive rebirth in the heavens as recompense and will obtain manifold quantities of merit." (Campany 2012, 151) 《法苑珠林》卷86：「又曰。經者尊典化導之津。波羅蜜經功德最勝。首楞嚴亦其次也。若有善人讀誦經處。其地皆為金剛。但肉眼眾生不能見耳。能勤諷持不墮地獄。[4]波若定本及如來鉢。後當東至漢地。能立 一善於此經鉢。受報生天倍得功德。所說甚 廣。略要載之。」(CBETA, T53, no. 2122, p. 920, a9–15)
        [4]波＝般【宋】【元】【明】【宮】。
        (Campany 2012, 121, footnote 282: The otherworld official known as Taishan fujun 太山府君 (a title, not a person’ s name-the office was filled by successive appointees, here including an ancestor of the story’ s (no. 26) protagonist!) had long been indigenously conceived of as overseeing the summoning and registration of the newly dead.)
       Während im Ming xiang ji noch Taishan fujun vorkommt, wird im Xu gaoseng zhuan von Daoxuan nur noch Yama erwähnt. Dann wird Taishan fujun in apokryphen Schriften durch Yama ersetzt. Koexistenz von Taishan fujun und Yama im Ming bao ji tale 19: Gjertson 1989, 196–202: Sui Renqian who is supposed to die to fill a vacancy in the hell bureaucracy. A friendship with a ghost saves him. He goes to see Taishan fujun on Mount Tai. Explanation of the administration of hell, with Yama as emperor, Taishan fujun as Department of the Affairs of State. In the end, the commissioning of a Buddhist image can prolong his life, though he is not a Buddhist.
       Tale 2 in Ming bao ji, Gjertson 160–161, also in  《法華傳記》卷6：「云我是泰山府君閻羅王。」(CBETA, T51, no. 2068, p. 74, b4–5)
       2. King Yama and sutra recitation, the appearance of the Diamond Sutra 98–103
       Daoxuan’ s Xu gao seng zhuan: Erstes Auftreten eines Mönches 釋明濬, der Diamond Sutra rezitiert, und von Yama angehalten wird, mehr zu rezitieren (T#2060, 50: 65b26–c4).
       Retribution tales 應驗譚 of the Six dynasties: Guanshiyin zur Rettung aus Not, Diamond Sutra in travels to hell narratives for the prolongation of life. Unter Kaiser Xuanzong 唐玄宗 (r. 712–756), the Diamond Sutra was copied with the intent of prolonging life. 
    Xiao Yu <foreign xml:lang="zh">蕭瑀</foreign> (574–647), courtesy name Shiwen, posthumously known as Duke Zhenbian of Song, was an imperial prince of the Western Liang dynasty who later became an official under the Sui and Tang dynasties.) promoted the Diamond Sutra most ferociously already under the Sui.
    3. Further evolution (extension) of return-from-death narratives under the Sui and Tang 103–107
    T#2083: 《釋門自鏡錄》(For a discussion of the authorship and date of this work, see <ref type="biblio" target="ChenJinhua2007">21, 37</ref>, who proposes that it was written sometime between 698 and 704) 卷2, Daoxiang biography 釋道相 T#2083, 51: 819c25–820b28.
    Sanjiejiao 
    Notes 107–110
    Abstract 111
    </abstract>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#" type="host">
        <titleInfo transliteration="romaji">
            <title>Nagoya daigaku bungakubu kenkyū ronshū: Bungaku</title>
            <!--<title>Nagoya daigaku bungakubu kenkyū ronshū. Bungaku</title>-->
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo lang="ja">
            <title>名古屋大学文学部研究論集·文学</title>
            <!--<title>名古屋大学文学部研究論集. 文学</title>-->
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo type="translated" lang="en">
            <title>The Journal of the Faculty of Letters, Nagoya University: Literature</title>
            <!--<title>The Journal of the Faculty of Letters, Nagoya University. Literature</title>-->
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <date>2017</date>
            <detail type="volume">63</detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>93</start>
                <end>111</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
    <!--<classification edition="#Sakurabe1975a">reprint</classification>
   <!-\- <relatedItem xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#Sakurabe1975a" type="host">
        <note>reprint</note>
        <titleInfo transliteration="romaji">
            <title>Bukkyōgo no kenkyū zōho</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo lang="ja">
            <title>仏教語の研究 増補</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
            <title>Extended Research on Buddhist Terminology</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#sakurabe" type="personal">
            <namePart transliteration="romaji" type="family">Sakurabe</namePart>
            <namePart transliteration="romaji" type="given">Hajime</namePart>
            <role>
                <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
            </role>
        </name>
        <originInfo>
            <dateIssued>1997</dateIssued>
            <place>
                <placeTerm>Kyōto</placeTerm>
                <placeTerm lang="ja">京都</placeTerm>
            </place>
            <publisher>
                <name type="corporate">
                    <namePart transliteration="romaji">Buneidō</namePart>
                </name>
                <namePart lang="ja">文栄堂</namePart>
            </publisher>
            <issuance>monographic</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>88</start>
                <end>98</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>-\->-->
</mods>