<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Schopen1975" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo lang="en">
        <title>The Phrase ‘<hi rend="italic">
                <foreign lang="sa">sa pṛthivīpradeśaś caityabhūto
                    bhavet </foreign>
            </hi>’ in the <hi rend="italic">
                <foreign lang="sa">Vajracchedikā:</foreign>
            </hi> Notes on the Cult of the Book in <foreign lang="sa">Mahāyāna</foreign>
        </title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Schopen 1975</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#schopen" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="en" type="family">Schopen</namePart>
        <namePart lang="en" type="given">Gregory Robert</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>From the response to Schopen by Drewes 2007: p. 4: Previous scholars tended to take
        the word bhūta in the compound to indicate a comparison and thus, like Conze, to read
        passages like the Vajracchedikā’s as stating merely that places where people do things with
        sūtras are like caityas. Schopen argues that this interpretation makes little sense and that
        the term caityabhūta in these passages refers to actual caityas which serves as early
        Mahāyāna cult sites. Altogether, Schopen analyses six caityabhūta passages and several other
        passages that seem to be modeled on them in light of related material from a range of South
        Asian Buddhist texts. From his analysis he draws a remarkably specific picture of the nature
        and history of the cult of the book. ... p. 6: What is perhaps most notable about Schopen’s
        argument in support of these theses is that the only evidence that he cites for the
        existence of Mahāyāna book shrines is his caityabhūta passages and their variants. A key
        question, then, is whether or not these passages make reference to shrines. What I will try
        to suggest is that they do not, and that they are in fact similes or metaphors, as scholars
        before Schopen tended to think.</abstract>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#IndoIranianJournal" type="host">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>Indo-Iranian Journal</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <detail type="volume">17</detail>
            <detail type="no">3–4</detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>147</start>
                <end>181</end>
            </extent>
            <date>1975</date>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
    <classification edition="#Schopen2005a">reprint</classification>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#Schopen2005a" type="host">
        <titleInfo lang="en">
            <title>Figments and Fragments of Mahāyāna Buddhism in India: More Collected
                Papers</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>monographic</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>25</start>
                <end>62</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>