<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Senchakushu1998" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo lang="en">
        <title>Hōnen’s Senchakushū. Passages on the Selection of the Nembutsu in the Original Vow
            (Senchaku hongan nembutsu shū <foreign lang="zh">選擇本願念佛集</foreign>)</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Senchakushu 1998</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#senchakushu_translation" type="corporate">
        <namePart lang="en">Senchakushū English Translation Project</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>editor</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>Introduction, p. 24: Hōnen interpreted the expression “takes firm hold of his name” to
        mean the recitation of the nembutsu. For Hōnen, the recited nem- p. 25: butsu became the
        basis for reconciling the Wu-liang-shou-ching’s foregrounding of the original vow with the
        Kuan wu-liang-shou ching’s emphasis on the contemplative practice. By reading the above
        passage of the A-mi-t’o ching in this way, he was able to interpret it in light of the other
        two sūtras. The sūtra states, “Buddhas in all six directions, that is, north, south, east,
        west, up, and down, all confirm that Amida Buddha’s teaching is true.” Hōnen read this
        passage to mean that this sūtra absolutely affirms that the nembutsu was the only assured
        way to the Pure Land. Hōnen felt the main purport of the sūtra consists of the buddhas of
        the six directions giving witness only to the practice of the nembutsu for gaining birth in
        the Pure Land and not giving witness to the various practices in other sūtras regarding
        birth in the Pure Land. This is called senchaku shōjō or “selection by all buddhas of the
        six directions witnessing the authenticity of the nembutsu.” Translation (p. 137-138): 13.
        Passages Attesting That the Nembutsu Plants Many Good Roots, While the Miscellaneous
        Practices Plant But FEW The A-mi-T’o ching (Amida Sūtra) says:.... Shan-tao, interpreting
        those passage says:... The following is my opinion: The words “It is impossible to be born
        in that land by means of the virtue of few good roots” mean that it is difficult to be born
        in that land through all the other miscellaneous practices. For that reason [Shan-tao says],
        “It may be difficult to be born there by means of the miscellaneous good practicesthat
        correspond to people’s varying capacities. The phrase “few good roots” is in contrast with
        the notion of “many good roots.” Thus, the miscellaneous good practices plant few good
        roots, while the nembutsu plants many. This is why Lung-shu’s Ching-t’u wen (Passages
        Concerning the Pure Land) says: The characters of the A-mi-t’o ching carved in stone in the
        city of Hsiang-yang written by Ch’en Jen-ling in the Sui dynasty were graceful, and many
        people prized and enjoyed them. [In this version of the sūtra one finds] after the words
        “with a single and undistracted mind” the following passage of twenty-one characters that
        are left out of the text handed down to us today: “By upholding the name, one’s sins are
        extinguished. This is the karmic result of the virtue of many good roots.” Here one can see
        that the meaning is not just one of “many” versus “few.” There is also the meaning of
        “great” versus “small”: that is to say, the miscellaneous practices represent small
        goodness, while the nembutsu represents great goodness. There is also the connotation of
        “superior” versus “inferior”: the miscellaneous good practices are an inferior goodness,
        while the nembutsu is a superior goodness. One should understand the meaning.</abstract>
    <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>1998</dateIssued>
        <place>
            <placeTerm transliteration="romaji">Tōkyō and Honolulu</placeTerm>
        </place>
        <publisher>
            <name type="corporate">
                <namePart lang="en">Sōgō Bukkyō Kenkyūsho, Taishō University and University of
                    Hawaiʻi Press</namePart>
            </name>
        </publisher>
    </originInfo>
</mods>