<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Shao_Ma2019" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
        <title>Shi dengchuang chubu yanjiu</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="zh">
        <title>石燈幢初步研究</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
        <title>A Preliminary Investigation of Stone Lantern Pillars</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Shao Lei and Ma Yujiao 2019</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#shaolei" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">邵</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">磊</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm><!--男-->
        </role>
    </name>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#mayujiao" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">馬</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">玉姣</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm><!--女-->
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>A very basic article on stone lantern pillars that are also called 石燈幢，石燈臺，石燈籠，石燈塔.
    Lamps are one of the six gifts for the Buddha (燃燈，凃香，香花，飲食，净水). The authors start with the use of light in the paleolithikum. 
    Then they explore sutra pillars 經幢, which started under Tang Gaozong. The most popular Buddha Crown Dhāraṇī (T.967) on these pillars was only translated in 683 by Buddhapāli 佛陀波利. In 776, Emperor Daizong decreed that all monks and nuns recite the Buddha Crown Dhāraṇī.  This Dhāraṇī was first written on cloth and  flewn on high pillars. later, such 經幢 were also made of stone for better durability. Stone lanterns have a double function of bringing light and of presenting an object for veneration. Inside the lantern chamber 燈室 at the top, candles or lamp oil can be placed.  The authors give a brief description of the Langfang 廊坊 pillar (3.5 m high), the lantern chamber of which is missing. With its date of 688, it is the earliest (?) known pillar at present. The authors differentiate between stone lanterns 石燈 and stone lantern pillars 石燈幢 (with texts), both of which have different functions.
    Stone pillars consist of  four parts: a top part in the shape of a precious gourd 寳葫蘆, the lantern chamber, the lantern pillar or body, and Sumeru base. At last, the authors give a brief introduction into the function of stone lantern pillars for the deliverance of the dead, for lighting up the night (also with electricity), and as cultural relics.</abstract>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#" type="host">
        <titleInfo lang="zh">
            <title>長江文明</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
            <title>Changjiang wenming</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <detail type="volume">33</detail>
            <detail type="no">1</detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>20</start>
                <end>25</end>
            </extent>
            <date>2019</date>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>