<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Shinohara1999" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo lang="en">
        <title>Literary Construction of Buddhist Sacred Places: The Record of Mt. Lu by Chen Shunyu</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Shinohara 1999</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#shinohara" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="en" type="family">Shinohara</namePart>
        <namePart lang="en" type="given">Koichi</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>
        <hi rend="italic">Record of Mount Lu</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Lu Shan ji </hi>
        <foreign xml:lang="zh">廬山記</foreign> compiled by Chen Shunyu <foreign xml:lang="zh">陳舜愈</foreign>
        around 1072. 937: "literary essays describing the mountains are combined with collections of verses
        and inscriptions." Conclusion 962–963: Constructing Mount Lu as a Buddhist sacred site by the presence
        of a missionary monk, in this case Huiyuan 慧遠 (334–416). Two strategies: Dragon Spring Temple:
        negotiation with local deities, “a place with extraordinary natural features marking passages with
        supernatural realms” Donglinsi: “bringing distinctly Buddhist sacred objects from outside the
        mountain, thus establishing the presence of the Buddha and his teaching in this site”. “The famous
        Aśoka image that miraculously responded to Huiyuan’s prayer to come to Mt. Lu was over time
        transformed into Mañjuśrī who lives on the mountain, in the same way this bodhisattva is said to
        reside at Mt. Wutai.” 943: This account of Huiyuan’s arrival and his temples draws heavily on
        Huijiao’s biography of Huiyuan in the Biographies of Eminent Monks. Huiyuan founded Dragon Spring
        Temple, and also Donglingsi Temple 東林寺, where the Terrace of the Buddha’s Shadow and a miraculous
        Asoka image are located. 945: “The Donglingsi temple is presented not as a place where a local deity
        appeared but as a place where extraordinary Buddhist objects were brought from outside and placed.”
        947: “Donglinsi is here presented as a Buddhist sacred place by means of a rhetorical strategy very
        different from that used in presenting the Dragon Spring temple.”</abstract>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <relatedItem xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#AsiatischeStudien" type="host">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>Asiatische Studien, Études Asiatiques</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <date>1999</date>
            <detail type="volume">53</detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>937</start>
                <end>964</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>