<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Shinohara2004" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
        <titleInfo lang="en">
                <title>Stories of Miraculous Images and Paying Respect to the Three Jewels: A Discourse on Image Worship in Seventh-Century China</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo type="reference">
                <title>Shinohara 2004</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <name xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#shinohara" type="personal">
                <namePart lang="ja" type="family"/>
                <namePart lang="ja" type="given"/>
                <namePart transliteration="romaji" type="family">Shinohara</namePart>
                <namePart transliteration="romaji" type="given">Koichi</namePart>
                <role>
                        <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
                </role>
        </name>
        <abstract>Shinohara discusses "the discourse on image worship [that] developed gradually and
                in a variety of separate and disconnected directions over a long period in Buddhism"
                on the basis of works by Daoxuan (596-667) and Daoshi (dates unknown): The <hi rend="italic">Jade Forest in the Dharma Garden</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Fayuan zhulin</hi>, T. 2122, 53) and the <hi rend="italic">Essential
                        Teachings of Scriptures</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Zhujing yaoyi</hi>, T. 2123,
                54] by Daoshi, as well as “Paying respect to monks and images” (<hi rend="italic">sengxiang zhijing</hi>) in Daoxuan’s vinaya commentary, <hi rend="italic">Sifenlü shanfan bujue xingshi chao</hi> (T. 1804). He concludes that "image
                worship, or paying respect to images, is highlighted as a crucial element in a
                defense of the autonomy of the Samgha" that was threatened again by two Tang
                emperors. "Taizong’s edict requiring monks and nuns to ”pay respect” (or “pay
                homage,” zhijing) to parents and the ruler was issued in 631, although it was
                quickly withdrawn in 633... In 662, Gaozong issued an order to have the matter of
                requiring monks and nuns do reverence (<hi rend="italic">zhibai</hi>) to the
                emperor, the empress, the crown prince, and parents be publicly debated (T. 2108:
                52.455ab; T. 2103: 52.284a)." He tries to reconcile the fact that in Daoshi’s longer
                anthology <hi rend="italic">Jade Forest in the Dharma Garden lots of miracle stories
                        about wonder-working icons are included, while in the shorter anthology <hi rend="italic">Essential Teachings of Scriptures</hi> mainly
                        quotations from the <hi rend="italic">Guanfo sanmei[hai] jing</hi> (<hi rend="italic">The Ocean-like Samādhi of Buddha Meditation</hi>, T.
                        643: 15.688b, 688c-689a)</hi> dealing with visualizations and mental images
                are presented. He seems to be irritated about the fact that in the <hi rend="italic">Essential Teachings of Scriptures</hi> "image worship is conceived of
                simply as a preliminary step in the practice of Buddha visualization, and the
                linkage between image worship and the defense of the Samgha is no longer visible." I
                propose that for his <hi rend="italic">Essential Teachings of Scriptures</hi>,
                Daoshi thought that only the mental practice of Buddha visualization would be
                appropriate. As Daoxuan had pointed out in his vinaya commentary earlier, paying
                respect to images was not considered the highest form of “seeing the Buddha". That
                was seeing the Dharma body by means of contemplation on emptiness, like Subhuti did
                when he surpassed the nun Utpalavarnā in paying respect to the Buddha
                (須菩提觀諸法空是為見佛法身。得真供養供養中最。非以致敬生身為供養也) according to the <hi rend="italic">Dazhidulun</hi>.</abstract>
        <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
        <originInfo>
                <issuance>monographic</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <relatedItem xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#Granoff_Shinohara2004" type="host">
                <titleInfo>
                        <title>Images in Asian Religions: Texts and Contexts</title>
                </titleInfo>
                <originInfo>
                        <issuance>monographic</issuance>
                </originInfo>
                <part>
                        <extent unit="page">
                                <start>180</start>
                                <end>222</end>
                        </extent>
                </part>
        </relatedItem>
</mods>