<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Shinohara1998" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
        <titleInfo lang="en">
                <title>Changing Roles for Miraculous Images in Medieval Chinese Buddhism: A Study of
                        the Miracle Image Section in Daoxuan’s <hi rend="italic">Collected
                                Records</hi>
        </title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo type="reference">
                <title>Shinohara 1998</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <name xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#shinohara" type="personal">
                <namePart lang="en" type="family">Shinohara</namePart>
                <namePart lang="en" type="given">Koichi</namePart>
                <role>
                        <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
                </role>
        </name>
        <abstract>Shinohara examines 50 miracle stories contained in T#2106 (T#2106, 52: 404a7–435a19)
                Despite the early dates indicated within the texts, the miraculous image stories
                themselves can only rarely be further traced back than the <hi rend="italic">Biographies of Eminent Monks</hi> by Huijiao; however, Shinohara assumes
                that they still have a long history behind them.<note>
            <ref type="biblio" target="Shinohara1998">142</ref>.</note> The merging of stories
                about so-called Asoka images into monk’s biographies is a well-known
                                phenomena<note>
            <ref type="biblio" target="Shinohara1998">143</ref>.</note> Miraculous image stories highlight the close relationship
                between the ruler and the monastic community. The role and function of image stories
                underwent significant changes in new political environments. Images “said to have
                been sent or brought from distant imaginary kingdoms” may refer to the idea of Asoka
                images, as “early Asoka image stories probably influenced the evolution of some of
                the other miraculous image stories in medieval China”<note>
            <ref type="biblio" target="Shinohara1998">150–151</ref>.</note> Out of the total of 50
                image stories, 19 contain closing statements indicating how long the images or the
                monasteries where they are kept have been in existence.<note>19 out of the For a
                        list see <ref type="biblio" target="Shinohara1998">174, note
                        63</ref>.</note> “the close relationship between the emperor and miraculous
                images (“royal images”) appears to have declined under the Tang.”<note>
            <ref type="biblio" target="Shinohara1998">162</ref>.</note>
    </abstract>
        <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
        <relatedItem xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#Davis1998" type="host">
                <titleInfo>
                        <title>Images, Miracles, and Authority in Asian Religious
                                Traditions.</title>
                </titleInfo>
                <originInfo>
                        <issuance>monographic</issuance>
                </originInfo>
                <part>
                        <extent unit="page">
                                <start>141</start>
                                <end>188</end>
                        </extent>
                </part>
        </relatedItem>
</mods>