<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Shinohara1988" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
        <titleInfo lang="en">
                <title>Two Sources of Chinese Buddhist Biographies: Stupa Inscriptions and Miracle Stories</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo type="reference">
                <title>Shinohara 1988</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <name xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#shinohara" type="personal">
                <namePart lang="en" type="family">Shinohara</namePart>
                <namePart lang="en" type="given">Koichi</namePart>
                <namePart lang="ja" type="family">篠原</namePart>
                <namePart lang="ja" type="given">亨一</namePart>
                <role>
                        <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
                </role>
        </name>
        <abstract>148–181 : on Liu Sahe/Huida’s biographies and miracle stories. The earliest
                datable material is the miracle story about Huida in the Mingxiang ji. Huijiao seems
                to have been aware of this story and presented a summary of it in his biographies.
                Hui-chiao’s biography centering around stories about Asoka stupas and images,
                however, is primarily based on other sources. Daoxuan’s biography mentions both the
                miracle story in Mingxiang ji, similar but not identical, and the Gaoseng zhuan
                summary of that story, and Huijiao’s earlier biography. The main part of Daoxuan’s
                Huida biography is based on materials from other sources. The story of Liu
                Sahe/Huida was widely known in connection with the legend of Asoka stupas. See, for
                exampe, the Liang shu. It parallels certains themes in the accounts of Mingxiang ji
                and Gaoseng zhuan biography. Miracle stories associated with Asoka stupas and Buddha
                images included in Huida’s biography appear in Daoxuan’s Ji shenzhou sanbao gantong
                lu (664). The Mingxiang ji version says that Huida lived in the capital city at the
                end of the T’ai-yuan period (376–396). 169: The treatment of the four miracle
                stories in the Kao-seng chuan biography of Hui-ta in these two later sources shows
                that at least by the seventh century Liu Sa-he’s name was associated only with the
                Asoka stupa stories, and that the Asoka image stories circulated without any
                reference to this monk.</abstract>
        <relatedItem xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#Granoff_Shinohara1988" type="host">
                <titleInfo lang="en">
                        <title>Monks and Magicians: Religious Biographies in Asia</title>
                </titleInfo>
                <originInfo>
                        <issuance>monographic</issuance>
                </originInfo>
                <part>
                        <extent unit="pages">
                                <start>119</start>
                                <end>228</end>
                        </extent>
                </part>
        </relatedItem>
</mods>