<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="SQSW" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
        <title>Shiquan shuwu jinshi tiba</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="zh">
        <title>石泉書屋金石題跋</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
        <title>Colophons to Epigraphica from the Stone Well Studio</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="zh" type="abbreviated">
        <title>石泉</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="en" type="abbreviated">
        <title>Shiquan</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference" displayLabel="Shiquan shuwu jinshi tiba">
        <title>Shi­quan shu­wu jin­shi ti­ba</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#lizuoxian" type="personal">
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="family">Li</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="given">Zuoxian</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">李</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">佐賢</namePart>
        <namePart type="date">1807-1876 </namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#chenzhu" type="personal">
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="family">Chen</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="given">Zhu</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">陳</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">洙</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>
        A few decades later, Li Zuoxian 李佐賢 (1807-1876) gives a more complete and detailed account in his Shiquan shuwu jinshi tiba 石泉書屋金石題跋 
        (Colophons to Epigraphica from the Stone Well Studio). He enumerates thirteen inscriptions on Mount Gang, eight of which are sections of 
        the two Lankāvatara sutra versions. For five of these he transcribes the complete text. Li Zuoxian is the first who reads the 
        columns in their proper sequence, and he corrects Ruan Yuan on this point. He also notes their relative spatial positions,
        but he does not understand the overall sequence of the sections, and he mentions ten scattered characters from sections that he thinks are unfinished.(LL)
        
        Concerning Mount Gang, Li Zuoxian describes in detail "thirteen sections" 十三段 of
        inscriptions. Section 1 corresponds to all inscriptions of the north side of Chicken Beak
        Rock (GS_E1, GS_D1.1, GS_D1.2, GS_D1.3); section 2 corresponds to the east side of Chicken
        Beak Rock (GS_C1); section 3 corresponds to the south side of Chicken Beak Rock (GS_C2);
        section 4 corresponds to GS_A5; section 5 corresponds to GS_B24; section 6 corresponds to
        GS_B31.2; section 7 corresponds to GS_A3; section 8 corresponds to GS_B7; section 9
        corresponds to GS_A4; section 10 corresponds to GS_B30; section 11 corresponds to GS_B25,
        section 12 corresponds to GS_B26. After the four last mentioned characters there are only
        "63 damaged characters that do not form a section". East of those, he mentions GS_B28.
        Afterwards, there are ten more "damaged characters" that do not form a section. Li Zuoxian
        complains that Ruan Yuan recorded only sections 1,2,3,8 and 10, and that other sources are
        even more lacking. Altough Li Zuoxian did not realize how to read the text segments in
        sequence, he is the first who paid attention to the reading direction of each text segment,
        and made some effort to understand the spatial relations between the text segments. 
        
        In 1839 道光己亥,
        Li Zuoxian visited Mount Tie. In the article he describes the site, compares the records of
        Ruan Yuan with what he saw, equals the calligraphic style to that in Jingshiyu on Taishan. 
        In addition to the sutra text and the Stone Hymn, he also
        found three characters (曹都惟) at the east side of the sutra text which correspond to the
        colophon by Li Ju’ao 李巨敖 (Tie 6), of which he only saw three columns. In this case Ruan Yuan’s record
        must be right, saying that the colophon consisted of 4 columns. Li Zuoxian also records the
        three colophons on the southern slope [Tie_3, Tie_4, Tie_5]. After that, he records three
        more lines of colophons without realizing that these belong to the remain of the colophon on
        the eastern slope [Tie_6]. Obviously, he has seen these lines only in rubbings, and not on
        the rock. He goes on comparing his findings with Ruan Yuan’s records and states that the
        former did not record the colophons found by him on the southern and eastern slope. Then he
        lists all remaining characters recorded by Ruan Yuan, remarking that he did not see any of
        them.Thus he did not understand that three of these inscriptions were part of the sūtra
        text, and that one (the齊囗任城 colophon) actually belonged to the aforementioned colophon by
        Li Ju’ao [Tie_6] on the southern slope.
        Li Zuoxian <foreign xml:lang="zh">李佐賢</foreign> (1807-76) also travelled to the inscription site of Mount Jian. 
        In his <hi rend="italic">Colophons to Epigraphica of Stone Spring Studio</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Shiquan shuwu jinshi tiba</hi>
        <foreign xml:lang="zh">石泉書屋金石題跋</foreign>) from 1839 he 
        describes how his friend Meng Yushan introduced him to the place, and how they “touched the rock to distinguish characters and recorded the text.”<note>
            <ref type="biblio" target="SQSW">2, 19: 14193-14194</ref>.</note> Li Zuoxian 
        said that the inscriptions were arranged in four sections. His first section differs from Qian Tai’s first section only 
        in including JS 3. 
        The second section contained JS 8, 10, and 11, and for the third he gave only JS 12. He said that quarry workers must have 
        already destroyed the texts carved in the fourth section. In comparing his findings with Ruan Yuan’s publication, 
        he points out several mistakes of the latter, but excuses these with the incomplete rubbings 
        Ruan Yuan had to rely on. Furthermore, he regrets that two inscriptions listed by Ruan Yuan are no longer seen on the rock, 
        and he expresses his wish to preserve the inscriptions by recording 
        them for generations to come (fig. <ptr target="Version-4-lizuoxian.jpg"/>) (CW).</abstract>
    <extension>1 <hi rend="italic">juan </hi>
        <foreign lang="zh">卷</foreign>
    </extension>
    <!--<physicalDescription>
        <extent>
            <detail type="fascicle">1</detail>
        </extent>
    </physicalDescription>-->
    <originInfo>
        <dateOther>Postscript 1911</dateOther>
    </originInfo>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#SKSLXB" type="host">
        <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
            <title>Shike shiliao xinbian</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo lang="zh">
            <title>石刻史料新編</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>monographic</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <typeOfResource collection="yes"/>
        <part>
            <detail level="1" type="series">
                <number>2</number>
            </detail>
            <detail level="2" type="volume">
                <number>19</number>
            </detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>14189</start>
                <end>14198</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>