<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Shuijingzhujiaozheng" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
        <title>
            <hi rend="normal">Shuijing zhu</hi> jiaozheng</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="zh">
        <title>《水經注》校證</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="translated" lang="en">
        <title>Collated Edition of the <hi rend="italic">Annotated Classic of Waterways<!--Commentary on the Waterways Classic--></hi>
        </title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Shui­jing zhu jiao­zheng</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <abstract>Nylan 2010, 94, note 3: “Li’s work was intended as a “commentary” on an earlier third-century B.C.E. work, the Shuijing. Usually nine years (515–524) are given as the date of compilation, but there is material in the book that dates well into the 530s, so we must imagine later editors and interpolators. That Li’s work must have greatly expanded the scope of the original can be seen from its detailed comments not only upon rivers and waterways, but also land routes, famous products, antiquities, personalities, and dialects. Li Daoyuan’s classic also contains the world’s first inventory of 300 stele inscriptions, not to mention descriptions of numerous other sites of memory, including twenty instances of rock art. Li quotes from well over four hundred books, many of which are now lost.”
        Wilkinson 2015, 200: Shuijing 水經 (Classic of waterways). Conventionally attributed to Sang Qin 桑欽, third century BCE, but now thought to have been written in the third century CE. The earliest work devoted to rivers. It contains an inventory of 137 rivers and waterways and survives thanks to its expansion in the important commentary by Li Daoyuan 酈道元 (d. 527), the Shuijing zhu 水經注 (Commentary to Classic of waterways), ca. 515–24. Li’s work is 20 times the length of the original. It contains not only detailed notes on 1,252 rivers and waterways but also (as the narrative follows the course of each river) on land routes, famous products, antiquities, prominent people, dialects, and strategic passes. There are references to no fewer than 15,000 place names (with explanations of the origins of over 1,000 of them) and the world’s first notice of some 20 rock art sites. He quotes from 477 books, many since lost, and records about 350 stone inscriptions; Shuijing zhushu 水經注疏. Yang Shoujing 楊守敬 (1839–1915) and  Xiong Huizhen 熊會貞 (d. 1936), commented; Duan Xizhong 段熙仲, punctuated and collated. ...”</abstract>
    <name xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#lidaoyuan" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">酈</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">道元</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#chenqiaoyi" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">陳</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">橋驛</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>commentator</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>2013</dateIssued>
        <place>
            <placeTerm transliteration="pinyin">Beijing</placeTerm>
            <placeTerm lang="zh">北京</placeTerm>
        </place>
        <publisher>
            <name type="corporate">
                <namePart transliteration="pinyin">Zhonghua shuju</namePart>
                <namePart lang="zh">中華書局</namePart>
            </name>
        </publisher>
        <issuance>monographic</issuance>
    </originInfo>
</mods>