<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Strickmann1990" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo lang="en">
        <title>The Consecration Sūtra: A Buddhist Book of Spells</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Strickmann 1990</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#strickmann" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="en" type="family">Strickmann</namePart>
        <namePart lang="en" type="given">Michel</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>1. The Value of Apocryphal Sūtras for Sinology: "... including the Jen-wang ching (Book of Benevolent Kings), Fan-wang ching (Book of Brahmā’s Net), 
        and the Ta-sheng Ch’i-hsin lun (Treatise on the Awakening of Faith According to the Mahāyāna. These three texts alone provided the foundations, 
    respectively, for the Buddhist protection of the state, the internal legislation of the religious life, and an advanced philosophical analysis." ...
    "Like their Indian prototypes, these extended compositions presented themselves as authentic products of supramundane omniscience and dominion—but in this case, 
    the machinery of authority was set in motion by Chinese clerics and was directed to an audience of their countymen."... "Yet it should also be clear, that 
    in terms of "authenticity" there is little to choose between a sūtra written in fourth-century Kashmir and one in fourth-century Ch’ang-an."
    "... the importance of Chinese apocryphal sūtras may be proportionate to their distance from their nominal source. They offer a wide view of the acculturation 
    and synthesis of Indian Buddhist elements on foreign soil."
    2. Dhāraṇī-sūtras in Chinese Buddhism: "...dhāraṇī-sūtras, or books of spells or incantations.... offer close analogies to contemporary Taosit writings. ...They were 
    intended as the basis for rituals—efficient texts, we could call them—and we must envisage them as circulating among persons to whose needs they corresponded, lay persons as well as monks and nuns."
    "In fact, the Book of Consecration’s twelfth and final book is a version of the Bhaiṣajyaguru-sūtra made in 457, and Ōmura assigned the work as a whole to the second half of the fifth century."
    ... "Ōmura  Seigai has already demonstrated from Chinese souirces how mantras and dhāraṇīs were early confounded and intermingles in Buddhist practice, the term "spirit-spell" (shen-chou) being used for both."
    3. Structure and Contents of the Book: "Several features confer on the Book of Consecration exceptional significance in the history of Buddhism: 1. It includes 
    the earliest surviving Chinese version of the highly influential Bhaiṣajyaguru-sūtra. ... 4. It is one of the first Buddhist texts to contain directives for acquiring 
    merit on behalf of dead anchestors—a practice that was soon to become one of the most characteristic features of East Asian Buddhism."
    "The Book of Consecration (Kuan-ting ching) is a collection of twelve individual sūtras, each contained in a single fascicle (chüan)."
    "Although this work may belong with the composite dhāraṇī anthologies of its time, it is my belief—against modern Japanese scholarly opinion—that it is a unified whole, 
    written with an intelligible purpose." ... "The final two books appropriately provide information on last things—rites of transcendence and rebirth in the paradises 
    of the ten directions."
    4. Buddhist Apocalyptic and the Scripture’s Origin and Destiny: "... a bhikṣu named Universal Succor .... will happen upon a grotto in which he will discover 
    a jeweled casket. On opening it he will find the text of the Book of Consecration incised in letters of purple gold on tablets of sandalwood. He will do homage to 
    the text and then begin to recite it and practice the rites prescribed therein." "An ultimate disappearance of scripture is also the climax of a dramatic 
    apocalypse composed in fifth-century Chiang-nan, the Fo-shuo fa mieh-chin ching (Book on the Extiction of the Dharma; T 396).... [gives summary of contents]...
    "Hidden in a cavern until the destined moment, it is thus apparently the earliest example of a "discovered" scripture, a class of Buddhist writings that has until 
    now been better known from the Tibetan tantric traditions .... the Book of Consecration presents itself as a comprehensive manual of practice for the end of the dharma..."
    5. The Authorship of the Scripture: "According to Seng-yu, the original collection comprised the first nine books only; the final three books were a later addition. [T#2145, 55:31a25-29]
    The twelfth book, however, he separated from the others and placed in a class apart. It is found in his section on doubtful or fabricated scriptures, where he 
    describes it as follows: "In the time of the Sung emperor Hsiao-wu ti, in the first year of the Ta-ming reign-period (457), the bhikṣu Hui-chien of the Lu-ye ssu in Mo-ling 
    made up this work on the basis of the [authentic Bhaiṣajyaguru-]sūtra. It concludes with a rite for prolonging life, and this has caused it to circulate 
    very widely in the world." 《出三藏記集》卷5：「灌頂經一卷(一名藥師琉璃光經或名灌頂拔除過罪生死得度經)
    右一部。宋孝武帝。大明元年。魅陵鹿野寺比丘慧簡。依經抄撰(此經後有續命法所以偏行於世)。」(CBETA, T55, no. 2145, p. 39, a21)
    6. Taoism: The Demonic Religion of the Last Age: "...the author of the Book of Consecration is anxious to unmask the pretensions of the Taoists themselves: their 
    matter is derived from Buddhism, their inspiration is demonic..." "The first several chapters of the Book of Consecration provided Chines proto-Tantric devotees 
    with comprehensive Buddhist "registers" of guardian deities who would accompany them through life’s vicissitudes—battalions and regiments of a sort they would have 
    known from Taoism." "In a pardonable fashion with the demonic, we have said all too little about the rites of salvation with which our scripture concludes. 
    Such material appears in Books Eleven and Twelve. The eleventh book describes ten paradises, one in each of the ten directions....The twelfth and final book 
    also contrasts Amitābha’s region with the vision it presents to the Master of Pharmaka’s Buddha-realm in the East. These descriptions document the popularity 
    that Amitābha’s cult had attained by the mid-fifth century..."
    7. Socio-Economic Background: "Having noted our author’s derogatory comments on the costly pledge-offerings that accompanied Taoist scriptural transmission, ..."
    "... references in his text to gift-giving and donations to the Saṃgha. Such references abound in the eleventh book.....pious descendants must always 
    take care to assure an adequate supply for their progenitor’s rebirth." [quotes translated passages from chapter eleven for support]
    8. Indigenious Religion in the Book of Consecration: "... the Book of Consecration gives a broad survey of the major types of religious phenomena 
    to be observed in fifth-century Chiang-nan, and our author is careful to distinguish them all from one another. Despite his polemic bias, there is no 
    casual confusion here beteween Taoist priests and practices and the exorcists and rites of ordinary Chinese religion.."
    9. The Legitimation of Apocryphal Texts: Eschatology and Political Dissidence: "...the class of Buddhist texts to which the Book of Consecration belongs, 
    along with its parallel Taoist scriptures, was intended for a period of cosmic and social crisis. They consequently share a common protective 
    or therapeutic function.." [For an example of a apocryphal scripture that failed official recognition, Strickmann quotes the story of Miaoguang’s 
    Book of the Adornments of the Family of Sarvajñatā [Omniscience] from Chusanzang jiji, T#2145, 55:40b-c] "The author of a new Buddhist scripture 
    was clearly risking a good deal, at least in 510, when an imperial bodhisattva ruled in Chien-k’ang. Liang Wu-ti (r. 502-549) took his role as 
    Buddhist monarch very seriously, and it is clear that his high normative Buddhist dispensation imposed far closer controls on scriptural innovation 
    than had hitherto been current. ... no new Taoist scriptures appeared under the Liang until an extensive series of relevations burst on the scene 
    very shortly after the Buddhist emperor’s death in 549." "...strict Buddhist textual cataloguing, with sections opened for "suspect" (i) scriptures and 
    "falsifications" (wei), really began during Wu-ti’s reign." "Otherworldly texts  had long counted among potential dynastic talismans; such had been the 
    original function of the Han Confucian "apocrypha" (ch’an wei), and by the fifth century, at least, Buddhist and Taosit masters, too, were encouraged 
    to draw textual support for the reigning dynasty from their own resources of sacred literature.""Beyond their intrinsically auspicious, talismanic 
    function, scriptures might be written to buttress imperial authority in other ways—inaugurating rites to protect the state..... fifth-century apocrypha 
    owe their remarkable success to their usefulness from the official point of view." [examples for] "...scriptural tempering in a monarch’s best interests..."
    "A lengthy interpolation was made in the text of the Śrīgupta-sūtra as translated by Narendrayaśas (517-589)..... The interpolated passage states 
    that Candraprabha will be born as ruler of the Sui, Ta-hsing by name... Some hundred years later, a significant interpolation was made in the text 
    of the Pao-yü ching (Ratnamegha-sūtra), translated by Dharmaruci in 693, expanding that text’s prophecy concerning a female monarch as a retrospective 
    justification of Wu Chao’s assumption of imperial power in 690." "Perhaps the most spectacular success of all must be credited to the Taoist who, in 1116,  
    wrote and presented to Hui-tsung an enormous scripture, commonly known as the Book of Salvation (Tu-jen ching; HY 1), celebrating that ruler’s 
    theophany. The work was accepted with enthusiasm and set the head of the first printed canon; it still opens the Taoist canon today."
    </abstract>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#Buswell1990" type="host">
        <titleInfo lang="en">
            <title>Chinese Buddhist Apocrypha</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>monographic</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>75</start>
                <end>118</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>