<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/rest/db/schema/stone.xsd">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>N.N.</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <!-- Titel und Kürzel des Bandes in @n -->
                <title n="sichuan_volume4" xml:lang="en">Sichuan Volume 4</title>
                <title n="sichuan_volume4" xml:lang="zh">四川省第四卷</title>
                <!-- Ordnungsnummer für Kapitelreihenfolge in @n -->
                <biblScope unit="chapter" n="7"/>
            </seriesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date/>
                <respStmt>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:id="Site_WFY_Section_Da_Cave66">
        <body>
            <div type="cave" xml:lang="en">
                <head type="cave">Cave <hi rend="bold">66</hi>
                </head>
                <div>
                    <head>Description</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Overview</head>
                        <p> This is the largest and tallest cave in section D, and in the Grove
                            overall. It is completely filled with chapters from the <hi rend="italic">Great <foreign xml:lang="sa">Parinirvāṇa</foreign>
                                Sutra</hi> (<hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mahāparinirvāṇa-sūtra</foreign>
                            </hi>, <hi rend="italic">Da
                                banniepan jing </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">大般涅槃經</foreign>;
                            hereafter: <hi rend="italic">Nirvana Sutra</hi>). In addition, two
                            sculptured niches have been carved near the floor on wall d. Colophons
                            record, that a monk sponsored the sutra texts and a female disciple one
                            of the relief sculptures (fig. <ptr target="WFY_cave66d_niches_DSC6567.jpg"/>).
                            <!--A movement in the rock has pushed a part of wall d forward and sideways about the width of a column, so that the columns appear to be continuous but actually are not.-->
                        </p>
                        <p/>
                        <p/>
                        <p/>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Location</head>
                        <list>
                            <item>Southern slope, section D. Ca. 415 cm above present walkway, today
                                only accessible by ladder. </item>
                            <item>Situated above the tiny niche <hi rend="bold">63</hi> and between
                                niche <hi rend="bold">62</hi>, to the west, and the large Buddha
                                figure <hi rend="bold">64</hi> to the east. Cave <hi rend="bold">59</hi> and cave <hi rend="bold">66</hi> frame the niche <hi rend="bold">62</hi> on both sides and seem to form one group
                                (fig. <ptr target="section_D_DSC0952.jpg"/>). Because the cliff is
                                bulging forward at this point, the two sutra caves <hi rend="bold">59</hi> and <hi rend="bold">66</hi> converge within the
                                mountain. At their rear, the wall between them is very thin (fig.
                                    <ptr target="Section_D_map.svg"/>). On the cliff face the
                                distance between the two caves is ca. 340 cm.</item>
                            <item>Direction: wall f 352˚.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Shape</head>
                        <p>Box shape with open front. The rectangular ground plan widens toward the
                            rear; the rear wall and its base are slightly concave. </p>
                        <p>The threshold extends outward ca. 37 to 48 cm; one stone step remains at
                            its eastern edge, and beneath it is a stone support, possibly for a
                            beam.</p>
                        <p>A base between 20 cm and 27 cm high, and 2 cm to 8 cm deep, runs along
                            the foot of the three walls except for the two figure niches.</p>
                        <p>The horizontal ceiling extends outward above the open front, where it is
                            supported on both sides by the upper parts of the walls that splay
                            outward.</p>
                        <figure rend="left" n="figure" xml:id="cave66_map.svg">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">
                                <hi rend="bold">66</hi>號窟平面圖。雷魯卡根據馬本漢和王平國田野繪圖製作</head>
                            <head>Ground plan of cave <hi rend="bold">66</hi>; drawing by Lukas
                                Ledderose after field map by MB and MS </head>
                            <graphic url="cave66_map.svg"/>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Measurements</head>
                        <list>
                            <item>Wall d: Height at the front 318 cm, at the rear 317 cm, width 331
                                cm.</item>
                            <item>Wall e: Height at midpoint 316 cm, width 296 cm.</item>
                            <item>Wall f: Height at the front 312 cm, at the rear 322 cm, width 314
                                cm.</item>
                            <item>Width of opening 238 cm.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>State of preservation</head>
                        <p>A natural crack in the left corner of wall e in cave <hi rend="bold">59</hi> finds its continuation in the rear of cave <hi rend="bold">66</hi>, where it runs down in the area of columns 112–131 through
                            the entire wall d, and over the floor toward the eastern corner of the
                            entrance. From the top of wall d the same crack runs over the ceiling to
                            the center of wall f and then down that wall. On a sunny day, some light
                            used to spill through the crack shared by caves <hi rend="bold">59</hi>
                            and <hi rend="bold">66</hi>. The crack has now been sealed. </p>
                        <p>There were vertical cracks in the rock before engraving began that were
                            taken into account by the engravers. In segment 12-B of wall d, for
                            instance, they left free space of ca. five characters in length in
                            column 114, and another of ca. 21 characters in column 115. At some time
                            after the engravings had been completed, shifts in the mountain or even
                            an earthquake caused these cracks to widen. In segment 11-D a crack had
                            opened to the width of one column between columns 112 and 113; in
                            segment 12-C, the engravers originally left a space of ca. 5 characters
                            in column 116, but 19 characters have flaked off in the adjacent column
                            117; in segment 12-D, columns 114 and 115, one can observe how the upper
                            part of the wall has moved outward and sideways, to about the width of
                            one column; in segment 13-A, a horizontal hole in the wall, about six
                            characters in height (continuing into segment 14-A) was taken into
                            account by the carvers; yet above it, in segment 13-A, another deep
                            crack has caused the upper part of the wall to shift sideways. The
                            mountain continues to move; in segment 13-B, in column 126, the crack
                            split the two characters, <hi rend="italic">jijin</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">飢饉</foreign>, both halves are visible in the rubbing
                            made in the 1980s, but the left halves had been covered with cement,
                            when the photograph was taken in 2012. The shifts have been indicated in
                            the illustratios of segments 11-D, 12-D, 13-A, and 13-B. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="Site_WFY_Section_Da_Cave66_d_en">
                    <head>Wall d</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Layout</head>
                        <list>
                            <item>The front edge is damaged. The polished area, 296 x 320 cm, begins
                                at the entrance and directly under the ceiling; it ends at the
                                corner with rear wall e, and 20–27 cm above the floor.</item>
                            <item>The rectangular field of script, ca. 276 x 320 cm, begins ca. 4 cm
                                from the entrance and 14 cm below the ceiling; it ends 22 cm above
                                the floor and 12–15.5 cm from the rear wall. </item>
                        </list>
                        <p>In the lower right quadrant of the wall, the columns of the sutra text
                            form a horizontal line above the two niches (fig. <ptr target="WFY_cave66d_niches_DSC6567.jpg"/>). These measure 96 cm in
                            height, and together they have a total width of 150 cm. Niche <hi rend="bold">66-1</hi> shows the familiar group of seven figures. In
                            the center, a Buddha sits on an elevated lotus throne flanked by two
                            lions. The niche behind him, surmounted by an ogival frame, is filled by
                            a pointed halo under a canopy between two <hi rend="italic">bodhi</hi>
                            trees, carved in low relief. Also in the niche, on both sides of the
                            Buddha, stand his two disciples, the one to the Buddha’s right holding a
                            sutra scroll, and two bodhisattvas. Of the two guardian figures outside
                            of the niche below, the one next to the entrance has been cut off, by a
                            vertical incision for a threshold. Next to it, on part of an outer stone
                            frame, a mantra<!--dhāraṇī--><!-- formula--> in one column, 22.9 x 3.2
                            cm, is engraved: <foreign xml:lang="sa">Oṃ ārolik,
                                svāhā</foreign><!--<hi rend="italic">an a lu le ji sa he</hi>
                            -->
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">唵阿嚧勒繼，娑訶</foreign>!<note>For the romanization and explanation see
                                    <ref type="biblio" target="Giebel2001">152, 201</ref>. For a
                                concise introduction of the formula, its various transliterations
                                and further references see <ref type="biblio" target="WangTsuiling2011">252–253</ref>.
                                <!--The original formula <hi rend="italic">an a lu le ji sa po he</hi> “<foreign xml:lang="zh">唵阿嚧勒繼薩婆訶</foreign>” is seen in <hi rend="italic">Xiatang Huiyuan chanshi guanglu </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">瞎堂慧遠禪師廣録</foreign>, see R 120: 907b3. The carved transliteration is most close to “<foreign xml:lang="zh">唵阿嚧勒繼，薩嚩訶</foreign>” or “<foreign xml:lang="zh">唵阿嚧勒繼，薩婆訶</foreign>” that is transmitted in the Chan literature. -->
                            </note>
                            To its right the character <hi rend="italic">zhi </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">之</foreign> and other graffiti characters have been
                            incised (fig. <ptr target="WFY_cave66d_niches_colophon2.jpg"/>). <figure rend="left" n="figure" xml:id="WFY_cave66d_niches_colophon2.jpg">
                                <head xml:lang="zh">
                                    <hi rend="bold">66</hi>號窟<foreign xml:lang="en">d</foreign>壁像龕外框上神咒。2012年拍攝</head>
                                <head>Mantra
                                    carved at outer stone frame of cave <hi rend="bold">66</hi>;
                                    photograph taken in 2012</head>
                                <graphic url="WFY_cave66d_niches_colophon2.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </p>
                        <p>In niche <hi rend="bold">66-2</hi> two bodhisattvas with lavishly
                            ornamented garments stand side by side on lotus pedestals. Their heads
                            have been broken off. </p>
                        <p>In the narrow space between the two niches, <hi rend="bold">66-1</hi> and
                                <hi rend="bold">66-2</hi>, are the standing bodhisattva figure and
                            the seated Buddha figure with the dedicatory inscription.<note>See
                                above, “The Heroic Section D,” colophons, p. <ptr type="infra" target="colophon_66"/>.</note>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <table rend="box">
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <table rend="innerboxSecond">
                                        <head>Field of Script</head>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="1">Frame</cell>
                                            <cell n="1">horizontal lines at upper and lower
                                                edges</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="2">Grid</cell>
                                            <cell n="2">vertical lines</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="3">Horizontal rows</cell>
                                            <cell n="3">none</cell>
                                        </row>
                                    </table>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <table rend="innerboxSecond">
                                        <head>Columns</head>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="4">No. of columns</cell>
                                            <cell n="4">146</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="1">Width of ten columns</cell>
                                            <cell n="1">20.2–20.5 cm</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell>Space between columns</cell>
                                            <cell>ca. 0.1–1.1 cm</cell>
                                        </row>
                                    </table>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <table rend="innerboxSecond">
                                        <head>Characters</head>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell><!--<graphic/>-->Characters per column</cell>
                                            <cell>up to column 78: ca. 113; from column 79 on: ca.
                                                157</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="2">Length of ten characters</cell>
                                            <cell n="2">16.5–18.2 cm</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell>Space between characters</cell>
                                            <cell>ca. 0.3–1.5 cm </cell>
                                        </row>
                                    </table>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <table rend="innerbox">
                                        <head>Sample</head>
                                        <row n="1">
                                            <cell n="1">Characters</cell>
                                            <cell>Column/No.</cell>
                                            <cell n="1">Height (cm)</cell>
                                            <cell n="1">Width (cm)</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="2">
                                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">九</foreign>jiu </cell>
                                            <cell n="2">146/87</cell>
                                            <cell n="2">1.0</cell>
                                            <cell n="2">1.2</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="3">
                                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">部</foreign>bu </cell>
                                            <cell n="3">146/88</cell>
                                            <cell n="3">2.0</cell>
                                            <cell n="3">1.7</cell>
                                        </row>
                                    </table>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>State of preservation</head>
                        <p>Generally good; the surface is fairly even. The incision for the
                            threshold near the entrance, which has obliterated the guardian figure
                            of niche <hi rend="bold">66-1</hi>, has a width of 9–10 cm. Above it, a
                            rectangular hole, 176–186 cm above the floor, cuts into columns 3–8; two
                            rectangular holes, 100–108 cm above the floor, cut into columns 15–17,
                            and at the upper edge of the field of script into columns 11–15. The
                            area to the right of the upper hole is damaged. Two smaller natural
                            holes, 202–206 cm and 251–257 cm above the floor, cut into columns 82–84
                            and 86–89. The carvers took those into account. A man-made hole above
                            columns 80–84, under the ceiling, does not affect the field of script.
                            Flaked off areas extend 21 cm to the left and 24 cm to the right of the
                            long crack coming down from the ceiling in the rear area. Some
                            characters are still visible. This vertical crack is crossed at ca.
                            244–262 cm above the floor by a deep horizontal natural crevice,
                            beginning ca. 8 cm from wall e and extending ca. 100 cm into the cave.
                            The crack then turns down diagonally and peters out; it was taken into
                            account by the carvers. A black surface tarnishes the lower half of the
                            wall. <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="WFY_cave66d_niches_DSC6567.jpg">
                                <head xml:lang="zh">
                                    <hi rend="bold">66</hi>號窟<foreign xml:lang="en">d</foreign>壁像龕。2010年拍攝</head>
                                <head>Image niches on wall d in
                                    cave <hi rend="bold">66</hi>; photograph taken in
                                    2010</head>
                                <graphic url="WFY_cave66d_niches_DSC6567.jpg" height="125mm"/>
                            </figure>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Text Markers</head>
                        <p/>
                        <table rend="textmarker">
                            <row>
                                <cell>Column 1:</cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh"> [大般涅槃經]卷第五</foreign>; refers to the
                                    beginning of scroll 5, which is the beginning of part 2 of
                                    chapter 4, entitled <hi rend="italic">Rulaixing pin
                                        </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">如來性品</foreign> of the <hi rend="italic">Nirvana
                                    Sutra</hi><!--<hi rend="italic">Great <foreign xml:lang="sa">Parinirvāṇa</foreign> Sutra</hi> (<hi rend="italic">
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mahāparinirvāṇa-sūtra</foreign>
                                    </hi>, <hi rend="italic">Da banniepan jing </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">大般涅槃經</foreign>; hereafter:<hi rend="italic">Nirvana Sutra</hi>) -->.
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Column 1:</cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">尒時迦葉菩薩白佛言</foreign>; First characters
                                    of the sutra text in this cave. The text continues here from
                                    cave <hi rend="bold">59</hi>. </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Column 79:</cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">大般涅槃經卷第五</foreign>; refers to the end
                                    of scroll 5 of the <hi rend="italic">Nirvana Sutra</hi>, which
                                    coincides with the end of part 2 of chapter 4, entitled <hi rend="italic">Rulaixing pin </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">如來性品</foreign>.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Column 79:</cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">大般涅槃經卷第六如來性品第四之三</foreign>; refers to
                                    the beginning of scroll 6 of the <hi rend="italic">Nirvana
                                        Sutra</hi>, which coincides with the beginning of part 3 in
                                    chapter 4, entitled <hi rend="italic">Rulaixing pin
                                        </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">如來性品</foreign>.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Column 133:</cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">大般涅槃經卷第六</foreign>; refers to the end
                                    of scroll 6 of the <hi rend="italic">Nirvana Sutra</hi>, which
                                    coincides with the end of part 3 in chapter 4, entitled <hi rend="italic">Rulaixing pin </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">如來性品</foreign>.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Column 134:</cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">[大般涅槃經]卷第七<!--[如來性品第四之四]--></foreign>;
                                    refers to the beginning of scroll 7 of the <hi rend="italic">Nirvana Sutra</hi>, which coincides with the beginning of
                                    part 4 in chapter 4, entitled <hi rend="italic">Rulaixing pin
                                        </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">如來性品</foreign>.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Column 146:</cell>
                                <cell>Last column, ends with:<foreign xml:lang="zh">
                                        ……微妙清淨猶如滿月若有說言如來[雖為一]</foreign>. </cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="Site_WFY_Section_Da_Cave66_e_en">
                    <head>Wall e</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Layout</head>
                        <list>
                            <item>A polished area, 284 x ca. 290 cm, begins at the corner with wall
                                d, directly under the ceiling; it ends 22–27.5 cm above the floor
                                and ca. 6 cm from wall f. </item>
                            <item>The horizontal rectangular field of script, ca. 178 x 285 cm,
                                begins 12 cm from wall d and 11 cm below the ceiling; it ends 23–30
                                cm above the floor, and 13 cm from wall f; the lower edge is
                                approximately horizontal. </item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <table rend="box">
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <table rend="innerboxSecond">
                                        <head>Field of Script</head>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="1">Frame</cell>
                                            <cell n="1">none</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="2">Grid</cell>
                                            <cell n="2">none</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="3">Horizontal rows</cell>
                                            <cell n="3">none</cell>
                                        </row>
                                    </table>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <table rend="innerboxSecond">
                                        <head>Columns</head>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="4">No. of columns</cell>
                                            <cell n="4">129</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="1">Width of ten columns</cell>
                                            <cell n="1">22 cm </cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell>Space between columns</cell>
                                            <cell>ca. 0.1–1.5 cm</cell>
                                        </row>
                                    </table>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <table rend="innerboxSecond">
                                        <head>Characters</head>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell><!--<graphic/>-->Characters per column</cell>
                                            <cell>uneven, 169 in column 106</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="2">Length of ten characters</cell>
                                            <cell n="2">17.5 cm </cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell>Space between characters</cell>
                                            <cell>ca. 0.1–0.5 cm </cell>
                                        </row>
                                    </table>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <table rend="innerbox">
                                        <head>Sample</head>
                                        <row n="1">
                                            <cell n="1">Characters</cell>
                                            <cell>Column/No.</cell>
                                            <cell n="1">Height (cm)</cell>
                                            <cell n="1">Width (cm)</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="2">
                                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">世</foreign>shi </cell>
                                            <cell n="2">2/74</cell>
                                            <cell n="2">1.1</cell>
                                            <cell n="2">1.6</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="3">
                                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">佛</foreign>fo </cell>
                                            <cell n="3">4/80</cell>
                                            <cell n="3">1.9</cell>
                                            <cell n="3">2.1</cell>
                                        </row>
                                    </table>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>State of preservation</head>
                        <p>Generally good. The surface is uneven. A long horizontal crack with deep
                            crevices, ca. 119–126 cm above the floor, reaches from columns 21 to 81.
                            It was already present when the text was engraved, and the carver took
                            it into account. Across the entire wall, a black tinge reaches 50–100 cm
                            from the floor. There are traces of drips above an arc-shaped area under
                            the ceiling. The last quarter of the wall to the left is moist. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Text Markers</head>
                        <p/>
                        <table rend="textmarker">
                            <row>
                                <cell>Column 1:</cell>
                                <cell>begins with: <foreign xml:lang="zh">一經律說如恒河沙等義味……</foreign>;
                                    continuation from wall d, part 4 in chapter 4, entitled <hi rend="italic">Rulaixing pin </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">如來性品</foreign> in scroll 7 of the <hi rend="italic">Nirvana
                                        Sutra</hi>. </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Column 52:</cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">大般涅槃經卷第七</foreign>; refers to the end
                                    of scroll 7 of the <hi rend="italic">Nirvana Sutra</hi>, which
                                    coincides with the end of part 4 in chapter 4, entitled <hi rend="italic">Rulaixing pin </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">如來性品</foreign>.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Column 52:</cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">大般涅槃經如來性品之五 卷第八</foreign>; refers to
                                    the beginning of scroll 8 of the <hi rend="italic">Nirvana
                                        Sutra</hi>, which coincides with the beginning of part 5 in
                                    chapter 4, entitled <hi rend="italic">Rulaixing pin
                                        </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">如來性品</foreign>.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Column 102:</cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">大般涅槃經卷第八</foreign>; refers to the end
                                    of scroll 8 of the <hi rend="italic">Nirvana Sutra</hi>, which
                                    coincides with the end of part 5 in chapter 4, entitled <hi rend="italic">Rulaixing pin </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">如來性品</foreign>.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Column 102:</cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">大般涅槃經如來性品之六 卷第九</foreign>; refers to
                                    the beginning of scroll 9 of the <hi rend="italic">Nirvana
                                        Sutra</hi>, which coincides with the beginning of part 6 of
                                    chapter 4, entitled <hi rend="italic">Rulaixing pin
                                        </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">如來性品</foreign>. </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Column 129:</cell>
                                <cell>the last column, ends with: <foreign xml:lang="zh">作如是言所有方等大乘經典</foreign>; to its right, after the end of the
                                    last column follow: <foreign xml:lang="zh">佛頂尊勝</foreign>.
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="Site_WFY_Section_Da_Cave66_f_en">
                    <head>Wall f</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Layout</head>
                        <list>
                            <item>The polished area, 295 x 325 cm, begins in the corner with wall e
                                and below the ceiling; it ends 18–26 cm above the floor and extends
                                ca. 34 cm beyond the field of script toward the entrance.</item>
                            <item>The field of script measures 277 x 278 cm and begins at a distance
                                of 16 cm from the corner with wall e, and 11–16 cm below the
                                ceiling; the upper horizontal edge is irregular; it ends 25–30 cm
                                above the floor and 20–70 cm from the entrance. The lower edge
                                wavers slightly.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>No text was engraved in the upper right corner. The first 12 columns
                            begin 234 cm above the floor, columns 13–14 are 239 cm above the floor,
                            columns 15–19 are 252 cm above the floor, columns 16–20 are 255 cm above
                            the floor, and columns 21–22 are 260 cm above the floor. Thereafter all
                            columns begin 286 cm above the floor.</p>
                        <p>In the upper central part, several areas remain empty, with no text being
                            engraved, save for one or two characters: <hi rend="italic">yi
                                </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">一</foreign> , <hi rend="italic">ren
                                </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">人</foreign> , <hi rend="italic">shisan
                                </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">十三</foreign> , <hi rend="italic">zuoda
                                </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">作大</foreign>.</p>
                        <!--<p>The lower edge of the field of script wavers slightly.</p>-->
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>State of preservation</head>
                        <p>Generally good. The surface is fairly even. As in wall d, an incision for
                            a former threshold, 9–10 cm wide, has been made near the entrance. Three
                            superimposed man-made holes also correspond to those on wall d. One
                            hole, 94–101 cm above the floor, cuts into columns 127–128; another
                            hole, 170–179 cm above the floor, is outside of the field of script, and
                            the third hole, also outside the field of script, is directly beneath
                            the ceiling.</p>
                        <p>A horizontal crack from ca. 90 cm to 100 cm above the floor forms holes,
                            the deepest ones from column 6–25, 44–56 and 75–82; a shallow horizontal
                            incision, caused by geological layers, ca. 160 cm above the floor,
                            extends from the entrance to column 15; the long crack, which runs
                            around the entire cave, begins in wall f in the center beneath the
                            ceiling and comes down diagonally, having created a large flaked area on
                            either side, especially where it meets the lower horizontal incision.
                            The rear part of the wall is covered with a <!--blackish-->dark
                            patina.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <table rend="box">
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <table rend="innerboxSecond">
                                        <head>Field of Script</head>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="1">Frame</cell>
                                            <cell n="1">none</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="2">Grid</cell>
                                            <cell n="2">none</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="3">Horizontal rows</cell>
                                            <cell n="3">none</cell>
                                        </row>
                                    </table>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <table rend="innerboxSecond">
                                        <head>Columns</head>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="4">No. of columns</cell>
                                            <cell n="4">129</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="1">Width of ten columns</cell>
                                            <cell n="1">21.5–25.0 cm</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell>Space between columns</cell>
                                            <cell>ca. 0.2–1.7 cm</cell>
                                        </row>
                                    </table>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <table rend="innerboxSecond">
                                        <head>Characters</head>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell><!--<graphic/>-->Characters per column</cell>
                                            <cell>uneven, 141 in column 125</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="2">Length of ten characters</cell>
                                            <cell n="2">17.0–19.5 cm</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell>Space between characters</cell>
                                            <cell>ca. 0.2–1.5 cm </cell>
                                        </row>
                                    </table>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <table rend="innerbox">
                                        <head>Sample</head>
                                        <row n="1">
                                            <cell n="1">Characters</cell>
                                            <cell>Column/No.</cell>
                                            <cell n="1">Height (cm)</cell>
                                            <cell n="1">Width (cm)</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="2">
                                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">闡</foreign>chan </cell>
                                            <cell n="2">1/71</cell>
                                            <cell n="2">2.0</cell>
                                            <cell n="2">1.8</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="3">
                                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">大</foreign>da </cell>
                                            <cell n="3">1/77</cell>
                                            <cell n="3">1.2</cell>
                                            <cell n="3">1.3</cell>
                                        </row>
                                    </table>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Text Markers</head>
                        <p/>
                        <table rend="textmarker">
                            <row>
                                <cell>Column 1:</cell>
                                <cell>[<foreign xml:lang="zh">悉是天魔波旬所說……</foreign>]; continuing from
                                    wall e (not visible).</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Column 22:</cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">大般涅槃經卷第九</foreign>; refers to the end
                                    of scroll 9 of the <hi rend="italic">Nirvana Sutra</hi>, which
                                    coincides with the end of part 6 of chapter 4, entitled <hi rend="italic">Rulaixing pin </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">如來性品</foreign>. </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Column 23:</cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">大般涅槃經如來性品之餘 卷第十</foreign>; refers to
                                    the beginning of scroll 10 of the <hi rend="italic">Nirvana
                                        Sutra</hi>, which coincides with the beginning of part 7,
                                    which is the remainder of chapter 4, entitled <hi rend="italic">Rulaixing pin </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">如來性品</foreign>.
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Column 42:</cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">[大般涅槃經一切大眾]所問品第五</foreign>; refers to
                                    the beginning of chapter 5, entitled <hi rend="italic">Yiqie
                                        dazhong suowen pin </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">一切大眾所問品</foreign> in scroll 10 of the <hi rend="italic">Nirvana Sutra</hi>. </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Column 78:</cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">大般涅槃經卷第十</foreign>; marks the end of
                                    scroll 10 of the <hi rend="italic">Nirvana Sutra</hi>, which
                                    coincides with the end of chapter 5, entitled <hi rend="italic">Yiqie dazhong suowen pin </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">一切大眾所問品</foreign>. </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Column 79:</cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">大般涅槃經現病品第六 十一</foreign>; refers to the
                                    beginning of scroll 11 of the <hi rend="italic">Nirvana
                                        Sutra</hi>, which coincides with the beginning of chapter 6,
                                    entitled <hi rend="italic">Xianbing pin </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">現病品</foreign>. </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Column 111:</cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="z">大般涅槃經聖行品第七</foreign>; refers to the
                                    beginning of chapter 7 entitled <hi rend="italic">Shengxing pin
                                        </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh"> 聖行品</foreign> in scroll 11 of
                                    the <hi rend="italic">Nirvana Sutra</hi>.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Column 129:</cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">大般涅槃經卷第十一</foreign>; refers to the end
                                    of scroll 11 of the <hi rend="italic">Nirvana Sutra</hi>, which
                                    coincides with the end of chapter 7, entitled <hi rend="italic">Shengxing pin </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">聖行品</foreign>.
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Column 129:</cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">普州安岳縣沙門僧義造涅槃經一龕[永]為[供]養</foreign>;
                                    refers to the votive inscription by Renunciant Sengyi.</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="Site_WFY_Section_Da_Cave66_discussion_en">
                    <head>Discussion</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="biblio" target="Pengjiasheng1988">7, 13</ref>
                        <note>
                            <p>Peng Jiasheng provides, basing himself on the material given by Hu
                                Wenhe <foreign xml:lang="zh">胡文和</foreign>, measurements of the
                                dimensions of the three walls of the cave and computes its volume as
                                28.416 cubic meters. He identifies the carved scrolls and chapters
                                of the <hi rend="italic">Nirvana Sutra</hi> on walls d, e, and f,
                                with the exception of chapter 7, <hi rend="italic">Shengxing pin
                                    </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh"> 聖行品</foreign>, in scroll 11. He
                                describes the preservation of the walls as “very good <foreign xml:lang="zh">完好</foreign>”. He further refers to the colophon
                                by Renunciant Sengyi <foreign xml:lang="zh">沙門僧義</foreign>, and says
                                that it is not clear whether this monk donated only the parts of the
                                    <hi rend="italic">Nirvana Sutra</hi> carved in cave <hi rend="bold">66</hi>, or all parts of this sutra carved at the
                                Grove. In any case, he must have been one of the main donors at the
                                site.</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="biblio" target="Howard1988">41–42</ref>
                        <note>
                            <p>Angela Falco Howard, a pioneer who was the first to discuss the Grove
                                in English, notes and translates colophons in caves <hi rend="bold">59</hi> and <hi rend="bold">66</hi>. She emphasizes the
                                connection between the monumental sculpture of the Reclining Buddha
                                and the <hi rend="italic">Nirvana Sutra</hi> that is so prominent in
                                the Grove and suggests possible “ties with the Southern Buddhist
                                tradition of coastal China, where the <hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Nirvana Sūtra</foreign>
                                </hi> had been
                                especially studied and venerated.” She further notes that “the <hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Avataṃsaka
                                    Sūtra</foreign>
                                </hi> . . . and the <hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkāvatāra Sūtra</foreign>
                                </hi> . . . are
                                both conspicuously absent” in the Grove, as are “the <hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Yogācāra</foreign>
                                </hi>
                                texts which Xuanzang . . . translated.”</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="biblio" target="Caodan1990">51</ref>
                        <note>
                            <p>Cao mentions the colophon by Renunciant
                                Sengyi<!-- <foreign xml:lang="zh">沙門僧義</foreign>-->. </p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="biblio" target="Huwenhe1992">9</ref>
                        <note>
                            <p>Although published later, this study was the basis for <ref type="biblio" target="Pengjiasheng1988">7</ref>. Therefore, the
                                measurements of the three dimensions of the cave, the locations of
                                the texts, including the lack of chapter 7, <hi rend="italic">Shengxing pin </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh"> 聖行品</foreign>, in
                                scroll 11, are the same as in Peng. However, Hu Wenhe transcribes
                                the colophon by Renunciant Sengyi here completely.
                                <!--Hu Wenhe sets out the measurements of the three dimensions of the cave
                                (as does <ref type="biblio" target="Pengjiasheng1988">7</ref>), but he does not compute its volume.
                                Hu adopts the same locations of the texts as given by Peng Jiasheng<!-\-<ref type="biblio" target="Pengjiasheng1988"/>-\->, omitting chapter 7, <hi rend="italic">Shengxing pin </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh"> 聖行品</foreign>, in scroll 11. He transcribes the colophon by Renunciant Sengyi<!-\- <foreign xml:lang="zh">沙門僧義</foreign>-\->.-->
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="biblio" target="Dengzhijin1993">36–37, 39</ref>
                        <note>
                            <p>Deng Zhijin points out that all walls in this cave are covered with
                                texts taken from the <hi rend="italic">Nirvana Sutra</hi>. He gives
                                a description of niche <hi rend="bold">66-1</hi> on wall d with
                                measurements, and enumerates some of the chapters and scrolls carved
                                on walls d and f. He provides a transcription of the colophon by
                                Renunciant Sengyi on wall f. </p>
                            <p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="biblio" target="HuWenhe1994">68</ref>
                        <note>
                            <p>Hu Wenhe repeats the information given in <ref type="biblio" target="Huwenhe1992">9</ref>. </p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="biblio" target="Li_Deng1997">42–43</ref>
                        <note>
                            <p>Li Liang and Deng Zhijin give measurements, list number of columns on
                                each wall, compute number of characters, identify sutra and
                                chapters, date the cave to the Tang period and suggest a <hi rend="italic">kaiyuan</hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">開元</foreign>
                                era (713–741) date on stylistic grounds for the two niches on wall
                                d. </p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="biblio" target="ChengduKaoguFaxian2008">379–381, 406–407</ref>
                        <note>
                            <p>The editors of the Chengdu Municipal Institute of Cultural Relics and
                                Archaeology provide detailed descriptions of the architecture of the
                                cave, including measurements of all walls, and an analysis of their
                                chronology. The two niches, with their sculptures, are described in
                                great detail; all colophons are transcribed. The editors tabulate
                                the column numbers for each scroll and give references to the texts
                                in the <hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="ja">Taishō</foreign>
                                </hi> edition.</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="biblio" target="Cao_Yu2009">12–13</ref>
                        <note>
                            <p>Cao and Yu give measurements of the walls, their surface areas, and,
                                based on rubbings, the number of extant characters, wall d: 23,542;
                                wall e: 20,382; wall f: 21,930. They identify the scrolls and
                                chapters of the <hi rend="italic">Nirvana Sutra</hi> carved in this
                                cave, and also provide a transcription of the votive inscription by
                                Sengyi. </p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="biblio" target="LeeSonyaS2009">50–52, 54–55</ref>
                        <note>
                            <p>See the Discussion to cave <hi rend="bold">59</hi>.</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="biblio" target="Qin_Zhang_Lei2015">84–88; 123–124; 350–411</ref>
                        <note>
                            <p>The authors give a detailed description of the location and
                                architecture of the cave, as well as of the niches and their
                                sculptures. The position of the texts of the sutra scrolls and
                                damaged areas are indicated in measured drawings of the walls. The
                                engraved sutra text is transcribed, albeit without punctuation;
                                differences with the <hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="ja">Taishō</foreign>
                                </hi> edition are indicated. </p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <ref type="biblio" target="Dengxingliang2016">76, 88–89, 109</ref>
                        <note>
                            <p>Deng Xingliang gives a general description of the cave with
                                measurements, and a description of the two image niches on wall d,
                                also with measurements. He provides a transcription of the votive
                                inscription by Sengyi. He lists all chapters and scrolls of the <hi rend="italic">Nirvana Sutra</hi> carved on walls d, e, and f,
                                indicating the column numbers where they start and end, and he also
                                quotes the relevant text passages carved at the beginning and end of
                                each such chapter or scroll. For his general remarks on the <hi rend="italic">Nirvana Sutra</hi> as carved at the Grove, see
                                cave <hi rend="bold">59</hi>, Discussion. </p>
                            <p>Drawing attention to the votive inscription by Sengyi <foreign xml:lang="zh">僧義</foreign> from Anyue County <foreign xml:lang="zh">安岳縣</foreign> in Pu Prefecture <foreign xml:lang="zh">普州</foreign> in cave <hi rend="bold">66</hi>;
                                further citing the inscription in cave <hi rend="bold">59</hi> by Li
                                She <foreign xml:lang="zh">李涉</foreign> [Deng reads Li Sha <foreign xml:lang="zh">李沙</foreign>] from Changjiang County <foreign xml:lang="zh">長江縣</foreign> in neighboring Sui Prefecture
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">遂州</foreign>, and the colophon in section
                                C by Yang Yi <foreign xml:lang="zh">楊義</foreign> from Lezhi County
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">樂至縣</foreign> in Pu Prefecture <foreign xml:lang="zh">普州</foreign>, Deng concludes that the donors at
                                the Grove came from the region of Pu Prefecture. </p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="cave" xml:lang="zh">
                <head type="cave">
                    <hi rend="bold">66</hi>號窟</head>
                <div>
                    <head>描述</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>概述</head>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="bold">66</hi>號窟是<foreign xml:lang="en">D</foreign>區乃至整個卧佛院最高大的洞窟，窟内壁面刻滿《大般涅槃經》。另有兩造像龕開鑿於<foreign xml:lang="en">d</foreign>壁底部。題記表明，佛經由一位僧人施刻，造像之一由清信女供養（<ptr target="WFY_cave66d_niches_DSC6567.jpg"/>）。<!--岩體運動將<foreign xml:lang="en">d</foreign>壁部分壁面向前推移了寬約一行經文的位置，造成部分經文錯行。-->
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>位置</head>
                        <list>
                            <item>位於南崖，<foreign xml:lang="en">D</foreign>區，高於現今步道約415厘米，現今僅可通過梯子進入。 </item>
                            <item>位於<hi rend="bold">63</hi>號小龕上方，西側<hi rend="bold">62</hi>號龕與東側<hi rend="bold">64</hi>號大佛之間。<hi rend="bold">59</hi>號窟和<hi rend="bold">66</hi>號窟從兩側將<hi rend="bold">62</hi>號龕夾拱在中間，三者似構成一完整組合（<ptr target="section_D_DSC0952.jpg"/>）。因崖面在此處前凸，<hi rend="bold">59</hi>號窟與<hi rend="bold">66</hi>號窟於山體内部聚攏。兩經窟後端相連，之間的牆體極薄，但崖面窟口間距離約爲340厘米（<ptr target="Section_D_map_ZH.svg"/>）。</item>
                            <item>
                                <foreign xml:lang="en">f</foreign>壁方向：352 ˚。</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>形制</head>
                        <p>敞口方形窟。長方形平面，後端漸寬；後壁及其底部略内凹約37－48厘米；東緣尚存一級石階，其下有石槽，可能用於安放木梁。</p>
                        <p>除二造像龕所在位置之外，三壁底部有一周高20－27厘米、深2－8厘米的牆基。 平頂延伸至敞開的窟口外，兩側由外伸的側壁上部支撐。</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>尺寸</head>
                        <list>
                            <item>
                                <foreign xml:lang="en">d</foreign>壁：前端高318厘米，後端高317厘米，寬331厘米。</item>
                            <item>
                                <foreign xml:lang="en">e</foreign>壁：中部高316厘米，寬296厘米。</item>
                            <item>
                                <foreign xml:lang="en">f</foreign>壁：前端高312厘米，後端高322厘米，寬314厘米。</item>
                            <item>窟口：寬238厘米。</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>保存狀况</head>
                        <p>位於<hi rend="bold">59</hi>號窟<foreign xml:lang="en">e</foreign>壁與<foreign xml:lang="en">f</foreign>壁轉角處的自然裂隙延伸至<hi rend="bold">66</hi>號窟後端，該裂隙在<hi rend="bold">66</hi>號窟<foreign xml:lang="en">d</foreign>壁第112－131行刻經所在位置，貫穿整個壁面，并越過窟内地面延伸至窟口東角。該裂隙又自<foreign xml:lang="en">d</foreign>壁上緣穿過窟頂，在中間部位貫穿整個<foreign xml:lang="en">f</foreign>壁。陽光充足時，甚至可以看到光綫穿過<hi rend="bold">59</hi>號窟和<hi rend="bold">66</hi>號窟共同的這道裂隙。該裂隙現已填補水泥。</p>
                        <figure rend="left" n="figure" xml:id="cave66_map_ZH.svg">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">
                                <hi rend="bold">66</hi>號窟平面圖。雷魯卡根據馬本漢和王平國田野繪圖製作</head>
                            <head>Ground plan of cave <hi rend="bold">66</hi>; drawing by Lukas
                                Ledderose after field map by MB and MS </head>
                            <graphic url="cave66_map_ZH.svg"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>在刻經之前，岩體已出現縱向裂縫，刻經者將其列入考量。例如在<foreign xml:lang="en">d</foreign>壁12-B區（同圖版代碼），爲避開裂縫，第114行有五字左右，第115行有二十一字左右的空間未書寫刻字。刻經完成後某一時間，山體移動或是地震導致了裂縫加寬。在11-D區，第112行與第113行之間出現了一條一行寬的裂縫；在12-C區，第116行原初即有5字左右的空間未刊刻，而相鄰的第117行則有19個刻字剥落；在12-D區，觀察第114行和第115行可見，牆體上部向外移位，并且側移大概一行寬的距離；在13-A區，牆上有一處横向的孔洞，刻經者在此處跳過約6字的空間（一直延伸到14-A區）；然而孔洞上方，另一處深縫導致了13-A區牆體上部的側移。山體持續移動；於13-B區的第126行，裂縫通過“飢饉”二字的正中間，左右兩半仍皆可見於20世紀80年代的拓片，然2012年拍攝的照片顯示，左半部分已被水泥掩蓋。所述移位已標示於本卷圖版<foreign xml:lang="en">11-D</foreign>、<foreign xml:lang="en">12-D</foreign>、<foreign xml:lang="en">13-A</foreign>以及<foreign xml:lang="en">13-B</foreign>。</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="Site_WFY_Section_Da_Cave66_d_zh">
                    <head>
                        <foreign xml:lang="en">d</foreign>壁</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>佈局</head>
                        <list>
                            <item>壁面前端殘損。打磨區面積爲296×320厘米，直接始於窟口及窟頂，延伸至與<foreign xml:lang="en">e</foreign>壁相接轉角處以及地面上方20－27厘米處。</item>
                            <item>刻經面呈長方形，尺寸約爲276×320厘米，始於距窟口4厘米、窟頂下方14厘米處，結束於距後壁12－15.5厘米、地面上方22厘米處。</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>壁面右下方的各行刻經下緣在兩座像龕上方齊齊止住<!--壁面近窟口四分之一處，刻經面下緣水平對齊，止於二造像龕上方-->（<ptr target="WFY_cave66d_niches_DSC6567.jpg"/>）。像龕高96厘米，總寬150厘米。<hi rend="bold">66-1</hi>號龕爲常見的一鋪七尊像組合。正中爲一佛陀<!--釋迦牟尼佛-->，趺坐於蓮花臺座上，座下兩側各有一獅子。佛陀身後有桃形頭光，正對龕楣尖拱之下。頭光上覆華蓋，兩側各淺浮雕一菩提樹。龕内主尊兩側脇侍二弟子和二菩薩，其中佛陀右側弟子手捧經卷。龕外下方雕二力士，近窟口處的一尊被用於安裝門檻的縱向凹槽破壞。在凹槽外側的石框上，刻有一行22.9×3.2厘米的神咒：“唵阿嚧勒繼，娑訶！”
                                    <note>有關此神咒涵義及羅馬拚音，見羅爾夫・基柏<ref type="biblio" target="Giebel2001">第152頁和第201頁</ref>。有關此神咒的精簡介紹、不同的漢字音譯以及參考文獻，見王翠玲<ref type="biblio" target="WangTsuiling2011">第252－253頁</ref>。</note>神咒右側有“之”字以及其他塗鴉刻字（<ptr target="WFY_cave66d_niches_colophon2.jpg"/>）。</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="bold">66-2</hi>號龕内造二菩薩，各立於蓮座之上，服飾華麗，頭部皆殘失。</p>
                        <p>在<hi rend="bold">66-1</hi>號龕和<hi rend="bold">66-2</hi>號龕之間的狹面上，雕鑿有一尊菩薩立像和一尊帶有供養題記的坐佛像。<note>見本卷雷德侯（<foreign xml:lang="en">Lothar Ledderose</foreign>）《壯麗的<foreign xml:lang="en">D</foreign>區》一文“題記”部分，<ptr type="infra" target="colophon_66_zh"/>。</note>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>保存狀况</head>
                        <p>大體完好。壁面相當平整。近窟口處的門檻凹槽寬9－10厘米，破壞掉一尊<hi rend="bold">66-1</hi>號龕力士像。其上方有一矩形鑿孔，距窟内地面176－186厘米，鑿入第3－8行刻經；另有二矩形鑿孔，一個距地面100－108厘米，鑿入第15－17行經文，另一個位於刻經面上緣，鑿入第11－15行經文。上方鑿孔外側的壁面殘損。此外還有兩個較小的天然孔洞，在距地面202－206
                            厘米和251－257厘米處，分别切隔第 82－84 行和
                                86－89行經文。工匠在刻經時將其考慮在内。窟頂下方、第80－84行經文上方，有一人工鑿孔，但未對刻經面造成影響。在壁面後端自窟頂延伸下來的長裂隙左、右兩側，分别有寬21厘米和24厘米的區域風化剥落。一些文字仍可辨識。有一條很深的横向天然裂隙，在距離地面244－262厘米左右的地方與上述縱裂隙相交，該裂隙始於距<foreign xml:lang="en">e</foreign>
                            壁8厘米處，長約100厘米。之後裂隙斜向下方，然後逐漸消失；刻經工匠亦將其納入考量。壁面下半部覆蓋有黑色污斑。</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>佛經標識</head>
                        <p/>
                        <table rend="textmarker">
                            <row>
                                <cell>第1行</cell>
                                <cell>［大般涅槃經］卷第五；標識《大般涅槃經》第五卷的開始，即第四品“如來性品”第二部分的開始</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>第1行</cell>
                                <cell>尒時迦葉菩薩白佛言……；該窟刻經的首幾字，承接<hi rend="bold">59</hi>號窟經文。</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>第79行</cell>
                                <cell>大般涅槃經卷第五；標識《大般涅槃經》第五卷的結束，即第四品“如來性品”第二部分的結束。</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>第79行</cell>
                                <cell>大般涅槃經卷第六如來性品第四之三；標識《大般涅槃經》第六卷的開始，同時也是第四品“如來性品”第三部分的開始。</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>第133行</cell>
                                <cell>大般涅槃經卷第六；標識《大般涅槃經》第六卷的結束，即第四品“如來性品”第三部分的結束。</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>第134行</cell>
                                <cell>［大般涅槃經］卷第七；標識《大般涅槃經》第七卷的開始，即第四品“如來性品”第四部分的開始。</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>第146行</cell>
                                <cell>末行，結束於“……微妙清淨猶如滿月若有說言如來［雖為一］”。</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <table rend="box">
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <table rend="innerboxSecond">
                                        <head>經文</head>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="1">邊框</cell>
                                            <cell n="1">上、下緣有水平綫</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="2">界格</cell>
                                            <cell n="2">有縱格綫</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="3">横排</cell>
                                            <cell n="3"> 無</cell>
                                        </row>
                                    </table>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <table rend="box">
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <table rend="innerboxSecond">
                                        <head>行</head>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="4">行數</cell>
                                            <cell n="4">146</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="1">十行寬度</cell>
                                            <cell n="1">20.2－20.5厘米</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell>行距</cell>
                                            <cell>約0.1－1.1厘米</cell>
                                        </row>
                                    </table>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <table rend="innerboxSecond">
                                        <head>文字</head>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell><!--<graphic/>-->每行字數</cell>
                                            <cell>第78行之前：約113字<!--（第46行）-->；第79行起：約157字<!--（第116行）--></cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="2">十字高度</cell>
                                            <cell n="2">16.5－18.2厘米</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell>字距</cell>
                                            <cell>約0.3－1.5厘米</cell>
                                        </row>
                                    </table>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <table rend="innerbox">
                                        <head>舉例</head>
                                        <row n="1">
                                            <cell n="1">刻字</cell>
                                            <cell>行/字</cell>
                                            <cell n="1">高（厘米）</cell>
                                            <cell n="1">寬（厘米）</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="2">
                                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">九</foreign>jiu </cell>
                                            <cell n="2">146/87</cell>
                                            <cell n="2">1.0</cell>
                                            <cell n="2">1.2</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="3">
                                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">部</foreign>bu </cell>
                                            <cell n="3">146/88</cell>
                                            <cell n="3">2.0</cell>
                                            <cell n="3">1.7</cell>
                                        </row>
                                    </table>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="Site_WFY_Section_Da_Cave66_e_zh">
                    <head>
                        <foreign xml:lang="en">e</foreign>壁</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>佈局</head>
                        <list>
                            <item>打磨區尺寸約爲284×290厘米，直接始於與<foreign xml:lang="en">d</foreign>壁相接轉角處及窟頂之下，延伸至距<foreign xml:lang="en">f</foreign>壁約6厘米處及地面上方22－27.5厘米處。</item>
                            <item>刻經面呈横長方形，尺寸約爲178×285厘米，始於距<foreign xml:lang="en">d</foreign>壁12厘米、窟頂下方11厘米處，結束於距<foreign xml:lang="en">f</foreign>壁13厘米、地面上方23－30厘米處。下緣近乎水平。</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>保存狀况</head>
                        <p>大體完好。壁面不甚平整。距地面約119－126厘米的地方，有一條横向長裂隙，其兩側形成若干較深的小裂縫，切隔第21－81行經文。該裂隙在經文刊刻之時已經存在，刻經者將其列入考量。在整個壁面範圍内，黑色污斑自底部延伸至地面上方50－100厘米處。在窟頂下面的一個弧形區域上方，可見水滴痕迹。東側四分之一壁面較潮濕。</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <table rend="box">
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <table rend="innerboxSecond">
                                        <head>經文</head>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="1">邊框</cell>
                                            <cell n="1">無</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="2">界格</cell>
                                            <cell n="2">無</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="3">横排</cell>
                                            <cell n="3"> 無</cell>
                                        </row>
                                    </table>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <table rend="innerboxSecond">
                                        <head>行</head>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="4">行數</cell>
                                            <cell n="4">129</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="1">十行寬度</cell>
                                            <cell n="1">22厘米</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell>行距</cell>
                                            <cell>約0.1－1.5厘米</cell>
                                        </row>
                                    </table>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <table rend="innerboxSecond">
                                        <head>文字</head>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell><!--<graphic/>-->每行字數</cell>
                                            <cell>不等。169字（第106行） </cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="2">十字高度</cell>
                                            <cell n="2">17.5厘米</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell>字距</cell>
                                            <cell>約0.1－0.5厘米</cell>
                                        </row>
                                    </table>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <table rend="innerbox">
                                        <head>舉例</head>
                                        <row n="1">
                                            <cell n="1">刻字</cell>
                                            <cell>行/字</cell>
                                            <cell n="1">高（厘米）</cell>
                                            <cell n="1">寬（厘米）</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="2">
                                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">世</foreign>shi </cell>
                                            <cell n="2">2/74</cell>
                                            <cell n="2">1.1</cell>
                                            <cell n="2">1.6</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="3">
                                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">佛</foreign>fo </cell>
                                            <cell n="3">4/80</cell>
                                            <cell n="3">1.9</cell>
                                            <cell n="3">2.1</cell>
                                        </row>
                                    </table>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </div>
                    <?cb?>
                    <div>
                        <head>佛經標識</head>
                        <p/>
                        <table rend="textmarker">
                            <row>
                                <cell>第1行</cell>
                                <cell>始於“一經律說如恒河沙等義味……”；承接d壁《大般涅槃經》第七卷第四品“如來性品”第四部分經文。</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>第52行</cell>
                                <cell>大般涅槃經卷第七；標識《大般涅槃經》第七卷的結束，即第四品“如來性品”第四部分的結束。</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>第52行</cell>
                                <cell>大般涅槃經如來性品之五 卷第八；標識《大般涅槃經》第八卷的開始，同時也是第四品“如來性品”第五部分的開始。</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>第102行</cell>
                                <cell>大般涅槃經卷第八；標識《大般涅槃經》第八卷的結束，即第四品“如來性品”第五部分的結束。</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>第102行</cell>
                                <cell>大般涅槃經如來性品之六 卷第九；標識《大般涅槃經》第九卷的開始，同時也是第四品“如來性品”第六部分的開始。</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>第129行</cell>
                                <cell>末行，結束於“作如是言所有方等大乘經典”。其右側有“佛頂尊勝”四字。</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="WFY_caves66-69_DSC_0055.jpg">
                            <head xml:lang="zh"> 位於<hi rend="bold">65</hi>號窟與<hi rend="bold">66</hi>號窟之間的<hi rend="bold">64</hi>號龕立佛像。2010年拍攝</head>
                            <head>Standing Buddha figure in niche <hi rend="bold">64</hi>, between
                                caves <hi rend="bold">65</hi> and <hi rend="bold">66</hi>;
                                photograph taken in 2010</head>
                            <graphic url="WFY_caves66-69_DSC_0055.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="Site_WFY_Section_Da_Cave66_f_zh">
                    <head>
                        <foreign xml:lang="en">f</foreign>壁</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>佈局</head>
                        <list>
                            <item>打磨區尺寸爲295×325厘米，直接始於<foreign xml:lang="en">f</foreign>壁與<foreign xml:lang="en">e</foreign>壁相接轉角處及窟頂之下，延伸至窟口刻經面外大約34厘米處及地面上方18－26厘米處。</item>
                            <item> 刻經面尺寸爲277×278厘米，始於距<foreign xml:lang="en">e</foreign>壁16厘米左右、窟頂下方11－16厘米處，結束於距窟口20－70厘米、地面上方25－30厘米處。上緣不規則。下緣略有起伏。</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>壁面右上角未刊刻經文。前12行刻經始於地面上方234厘米處，第13、14行始於239厘米處，第15－19行始於252厘米處，第16－20行始於255厘米處，第21、22行始於260厘米處。之後的經行皆始於地面上方286厘米處。</p>
                        <p>壁面上部中間區域，有若干空白處，除“一”“人”“十三”及“作大”零星幾個刻字之外，未刊刻經文。</p>
                        <!--<p>刻經面下緣略有起伏。</p>-->
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <table rend="box">
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <table rend="innerboxSecond">
                                        <head>經文</head>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="1">邊框</cell>
                                            <cell n="1">無</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="2">界格</cell>
                                            <cell n="2">無</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="3">横排</cell>
                                            <cell n="3"> 無</cell>
                                        </row>
                                    </table>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <table rend="innerboxSecond">
                                        <head>行</head>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="4">行數</cell>
                                            <cell n="4">129</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="1">十行寬度</cell>
                                            <cell n="1">21.5－25.0厘米</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell>行距</cell>
                                            <cell>約0.2－1.7厘米</cell>
                                        </row>
                                    </table>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <table rend="innerboxSecond">
                                        <head>文字</head>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell><!--<graphic/>-->每行字數</cell>
                                            <cell>不等。141字（第125行） </cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="2">十字高度</cell>
                                            <cell n="2">17.0－19.5厘米</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell>字距</cell>
                                            <cell>約0.2－1.5厘米</cell>
                                        </row>
                                    </table>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <table rend="innerbox">
                                        <head>舉例</head>
                                        <row n="1">
                                            <cell n="1">刻字</cell>
                                            <cell>行/字</cell>
                                            <cell n="1">高（厘米）</cell>
                                            <cell n="1">寬（厘米）</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="2">
                                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">闡</foreign>chan </cell>
                                            <cell n="2">1/71</cell>
                                            <cell n="2">2.0</cell>
                                            <cell n="2">1.8</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell n="3">
                                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">大</foreign>da </cell>
                                            <cell n="3">1/77</cell>
                                            <cell n="3">1.2</cell>
                                            <cell n="3">1.3</cell>
                                        </row>
                                    </table>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>保存狀况</head>
                        <p>大體完好。壁面相當平整。與<foreign xml:lang="en">d</foreign>壁相同，近窟口處也有一條9－10厘米寬的門檻凹槽。其上方的三個人工鑿孔亦與<foreign xml:lang="en">d</foreign>壁鑿孔位置對應。第一個鑿孔距地面94－101厘米，鑿入第127和128行經文；
                            第二個距地面170－179厘米，位於刻經面外側；第三個緊挨窟頂，同樣在刻經面外。</p>
                        <p>地面上方90－100厘米左右之處有一條横向裂隙，形成若干孔洞，其中最深者位於第6－25行、第44－56行以及第75－82行刻經處。另有一條地質層形成的横向淺裂隙，距地面160厘米左右，自窟口延伸至刻經第15行處。前述貫穿整個洞窟的長條裂隙，在<foreign xml:lang="en">f</foreign>壁始於壁面頂部的中間位置，之後斜向穿過壁面，裂隙兩側範圍大面積剥落，長條裂隙與横向淺裂隙相交處尤爲嚴重。後端壁面覆蓋有黑色污斑。 </p>
                        <figure rend="left" n="figure" xml:id="WFY_cave66_DSC_0258.jpg">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">
                                <hi rend="bold">66</hi>號窟窟口。2010年拍攝</head>
                            <head>Entrance to cave <hi rend="bold">66</hi>; photograph taken in 2010 </head>
                            <graphic url="WFY_cave66_DSC_0258.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                    <?cb?>
                    <div>
                        <head>佛經標識</head>
                        <p/>
                        <table rend="textmarker">
                            <row>
                                <cell>第1行</cell>
                                <cell>［悉是天魔波旬所說……］，不可見，承接e 壁經文。</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>第22行</cell>
                                <cell>大般涅槃經卷第九；標識《大般涅槃經》第九卷的結束，即第四品“如來性品”第六部分的結束。</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>第23行</cell>
                                <cell>大般涅槃經如來性品之餘<space n="1"/>卷第十；標識《大般涅槃經》第十卷的開始，同時也是第四品“如來性品”第七部分即剩餘部分的開始。</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>第42行</cell>
                                <cell>［大般涅槃經一切大眾］所問品第五；標識《大般涅槃經》第十卷第五品“一切大眾所問品”的開始。</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>第78行</cell>
                                <cell>大般涅槃經卷第十；標識《大般涅槃經》第十卷的結束，即第五品“一切大眾所問品”的結束。</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>第79行</cell>
                                <cell>大般涅槃經現病品第六 十一；標識《大般涅槃經》第十一卷的開始，同時也是第六品“現病品”的開始。</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>第111行</cell>
                                <cell>大般涅槃經聖行品第七；標識《大般涅槃經》第十一卷第七品“聖行品”的開始。</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>第129行</cell>
                                <cell>大般涅槃經卷第十一；標識《大般涅槃經》第十一卷的結束，即第七品“聖行品”的結束。</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>第129行</cell>
                                <cell>普州安岳縣沙門僧義造涅槃經一龕［永］為［供］養；標識刻經供養題記。 </cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="Site_WFY_Section_Da_Cave66_discussion_zh">
                    <head>討論</head>
                    <bibl> 彭家勝<ref type="biblio" target="Pengjiasheng1988">第7和13頁</ref>
                        <note>
                            <p>彭家勝測量了三方壁面的尺寸，并計算出洞窟體積爲28.416
                                    立方米。他辨識出除第十一卷第七品“聖行品”之外的<foreign xml:lang="en">d</foreign>、<foreign xml:lang="en">e</foreign>和<foreign xml:lang="en">f</foreign>壁所刻《大般涅槃經》卷品。他將各壁保存狀况描述爲“完好”。他亦提及沙門僧義題記，但未確定僧義僅捐資刊刻了<hi rend="bold">66</hi>號窟的《涅槃經》，還是施刻了整個卧佛院的《涅槃經》。彭認爲，無論如何，僧義是此處刻經址主要的供養人之一。</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl> 何恩之<ref type="biblio" target="Howard1988">第41－42頁</ref>
                        <note>
                            <p>作爲研究卧佛院的先驅者之一，何恩之是第一位以英文討論卧佛院的學者。她記録并翻譯了<hi rend="bold">59</hi>號窟與<hi rend="bold">66</hi>號窟的題記。她也强調宏偉的卧佛像與卧佛院内佔據重要地位的《大般涅槃經》之間的聯繫，并提出其或許與“中國沿海地區南方佛教特别尊崇和研習《大般涅槃經》的傳統有關”。她進一步指出，在卧佛院“未刊刻《華嚴經》《楞伽經》以及玄奘翻譯的唯識佛典是很顯目突出的”。</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl> 曹丹<ref type="biblio" target="Caodan1990">第51頁</ref>
                        <note>
                            <p>曹丹提及沙門僧義題記。</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl> 胡文和<ref type="biblio" target="Huwenhe1992">第9頁</ref>
                        <note>
                            <p>雖然出版較晚，胡文和此研究是彭家勝<ref type="biblio" target="Pengjiasheng1988">第7頁</ref>的基礎。因此，此處給出的洞窟三維測量尺寸和經文刊刻位置皆同上述彭家勝之文，包括漏掉了第十一卷第七品“聖行品”。不過，胡文和此處完整地迻録了沙門僧義題記。<!--胡文和給出了洞窟的三維測量尺寸（同彭家勝<ref type="biblio" target="Pengjiasheng1988">第7頁</ref>），但未計算體積。他採用彭家勝提供的經文刊刻位置，同樣漏掉了第十一卷第七品“聖行品”。他迻録了沙門僧義題記。-->
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl> 鄧之金<ref type="biblio" target="Dengzhijin1993">第36－37和39頁</ref>
                        <note>
                            <p>鄧之金指出本窟各壁刻滿《涅槃經》經文。他描述了<foreign xml:lang="en">d</foreign>壁<hi rend="bold">66-1</hi>號龕并給出尺寸，同時列舉<foreign xml:lang="en">d</foreign>壁和<foreign xml:lang="en">f</foreign>壁刊刻的部分卷品，且移録了<foreign xml:lang="en">f</foreign>壁沙門僧義題記。</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl> 胡文和<ref type="biblio" target="HuWenhe1994">第68頁</ref>
                        <note>
                            <p>胡文和重申了胡文和<ref type="biblio" target="Huwenhe1992">第9頁</ref>的信息。 </p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl> 李良和鄧之金<ref type="biblio" target="Li_Deng1997">第42－43頁</ref>
                        <note>
                            <p>作者給出了測量尺寸，列出各壁經文行數，計算刻經字數并辨識經品名。作者認爲該窟乃唐代所開，并根據<foreign xml:lang="en">d</foreign>壁二龕的造像風格將其年代進一步判定爲開元時期（713－741）。</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl> 成都考古發現<ref type="biblio" target="ChengduKaoguFaxian2008">第379－381和406－407頁</ref>
                        <note>
                            <p>成都市文物考古研究所的編者提供了洞窟建築形制方面的詳盡記録，包括所有壁面的測量尺寸以及斷代分析。編者還詳細描述了窟内兩座造像龕，迻録了所有題記，以表格形式列出各卷刻經壁面所處行數，并且註明《大正藏》對應經本。
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl> 曹丹和于春<ref type="biblio" target="Cao_Yu2009">第12－13頁</ref>
                        <note>
                            <p>作者測量了壁面尺寸，基於拓片現存字數，認爲<foreign xml:lang="en">d</foreign>壁、<foreign xml:lang="en">e</foreign>壁和<foreign xml:lang="en">f</foreign>壁分别爲23542、20382和21930字。作者辨識出本窟刊刻的《涅槃經》卷品，亦迻録了沙門僧義的供養題記。</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl> 李琛妍<ref type="biblio" target="LeeSonyaS2009">第50－52和54－55頁</ref>
                        <note>
                            <p>見<hi rend="bold">59</hi>號窟討論。</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl> 秦臻、張雪芬和雷玉華<ref type="biblio" target="Qin_Zhang_Lei2015">第84－88、123－124和350－411頁</ref>
                        <note>
                            <p>作者詳細描述了洞窟位置、建築形制和造像龕，并繪製壁面實測圖標示經卷位置和殘損區域。作者迻録刻經，但未標句讀，并指出刻文與《大正藏》版本之間的差異。</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl> 鄧星亮<ref type="biblio" target="Dengxingliang2016">第76、88－89和109頁</ref>
                        <note>
                            <p>鄧星亮描述了洞窟整體情况并給出測量數據。他也對<foreign xml:lang="en">d</foreign>壁上兩座造像龕進行描述并提供測量數據。作者迻録了沙門僧義的供養題記，并列舉了<foreign xml:lang="en">d</foreign>壁、<foreign xml:lang="en">e</foreign>壁和<foreign xml:lang="en">f</foreign>壁上刊刻的《涅槃經》卷品，并分别給出各卷品起始的行數。此外，作者還援引各卷品首尾的相關文段。有關作者對卧佛院所刻《涅槃經》的觀點，見<hi rend="bold">59</hi>號窟“討論”部分。 綜合考慮<hi rend="bold">66</hi>號窟窟内普州安岳縣僧義的供養題記，和<hi rend="bold">59</hi>號窟内來自附近遂州長江縣李涉（作者讀作李沙）的題記以及<foreign xml:lang="en">C</foreign>區普州樂至縣楊義的題記，作者認爲卧佛院的供養人均來自普州地區。 </p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>