<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/rest/db/schema/stone.xsd">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>N.N.</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
    
    <seriesStmt>
        <!-- Titel und Kürzel des Bandes in @n -->
        <title n="sichuan_volume1" xml:lang="en">Sichuan Volume 1</title>
        <title n="sichuan_volume1" xml:lang="zh">四川省第一卷</title>
        <!-- Ordnungsnummer für Kapitelreihenfolge in @n -->
        <biblScope unit="chapter" n="3"/>
    </seriesStmt> <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date/>
                <respStmt>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:id="Site_WFY_Section_G">
        <body>
            <div xml:lang="zh">
                <head>G區概覽</head>
                <p>該區位於北岩大臥佛的東西兩側，包括四座洞窟和一座浮雕墓塔。 <ptr target="Recl_Buddha_1_2_Map.jpg"/>, 為<foreign xml:lang="en">G</foreign>區西段的平面及立面圖，包含<hi rend="bold">1</hi>、<hi rend="bold">2</hi>號窟。由立面圖可見，臥佛位於石窟的東邊。西部的<hi rend="bold">1</hi>、<hi rend="bold">2</hi>號窟為一組雙窟，左右毗鄰，自西向東編號。
                    此二窟與涅槃像被崖面上的一塊凸起岩塊分隔開來。<hi rend="bold">2</hi>號窟東壁距佛足約9米。四座洞窟之中只有<hi rend="bold">1</hi>、<hi rend="bold">2</hi>號窟刻有經文。</p>
                <p>只開鑿了一半的<hi rend="bold">123</hi>號窟和無任何內容的<hi rend="bold">125</hi>號窟（自東向西編號），分別位於臥佛以東228米和150米處的崖面上。
                <hi rend="bold">123</hi>號窟西側10米遠的地方，是編號為<hi rend="bold">124</hi>號的浮雕墓塔。 2008年，作為洞窟保護工程的一部份，
                    有關部門在臥佛上方的崖頂檯面上開出一條排水溝。但有一些批評意見指出，這一舉措產生了負面效果， 實際上加重了<hi rend="bold">1</hi>、<hi rend="bold">2</hi>號窟的滲水現象。</p>
                <ab>
                    <abbr>雷德侯</abbr>
                </ab>
                <figure n="figure" xml:id="Recl_Buddha_1_2_Map.jpg" rend="center">
                    <head xml:lang="zh">
                        <foreign xml:lang="en">G</foreign>區西段的平面及立面圖</head>
                    <head>Ground plan and elevation of the western part of section G</head>
                    <graphic url="Recl_Buddha_1_2_Map.jpg"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="en">
                <head>Section G</head>
                <p>In the northern cliff, to the west and east of the giant statue of the reclining
                    Buddha, section G comprises four caves and one tomb pagoda in relief. Figure <ptr target="Recl_Buddha_1_2_Map.jpg"/> shows the ground plan and the elevation of the western part of section G with caves <hi rend="bold">1</hi> and <hi rend="bold">2</hi>. In the elevation, the figure of the Reclining Buddha is seen to the east of the two caves. The two
                    western caves, <hi rend="bold">1</hi> and <hi rend="bold">2</hi>, are twin caves which are arranged side by side and have
                    been numbered from west to east. They are separated from the reclining figure by
                    a bulging part of the cliff. The eastern wall of cave <hi rend="bold">2</hi> is 9 meters away from
                    the feet of the statue.  Of the four caves, only these two (<hi rend="bold">1</hi> and <hi rend="bold">2</hi>) are carved
                    with sutras.</p>
                <p>The half finished cave <hi rend="bold">123</hi> and the empty cave <hi rend="bold">125</hi> (numbered from east to west),
                    are situated 228 and 150 meters, respectively, to the east of the Bud­dha figure.
                    Ten meters to the west of <hi rend="bold">123</hi> is the tomb pagoda <hi rend="bold">124</hi>. In 2008 a ditch was dug in
                    the horizontal area on top of the cliff, above the reclining Buddha figure, to
                    drain away water. Some critics maintain that this measure has had the opposite
                    effect and has actually increased the amount of water in caves <hi rend="bold">1</hi> and <hi rend="bold">2</hi>.</p>
                <ab>
                    <abbr>LL</abbr>
                </ab>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>