<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/rest/db/schema/stone.xsd">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Introduction to the Site of Mount Tianchi</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>N.N.</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <!-- Titel und Kürzel des Bandes in @n -->
                <title n="shandong_volume1" xml:lang="en">Shandong Volume 1</title>
                <title n="shandong_volume1" xml:lang="zh">山東省第一卷</title>
                <!-- Ordnungsnummer für Kapitelreihenfolge in @n -->
                <biblScope unit="chapter" n="3"/>
            </seriesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>25.03.2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>JMP</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Aktualisierung Gliederung</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>31.03.2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Fußnoten und Abschnitt Carving Techniques überarbeitet</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>03.04.2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Abschnitt Location überarbeitet gemäß Markette</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>17.04.2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Abschnitt Related Monasteries eingefügt (vgl. Mount Dazhai)</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>01.09.2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Eintrag umgearbeitet nach neuer Gliederung "Inscriptions"</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>10.03.2011</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Abschnitt Related Monasteries eingefügt von Mount Dazhai; dort (und bei Mount
                    Shuyuan, Ergu und Yuncui)jetzt Verweis auf Mount Tianchi.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>April 4th 2011</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Änderungen und Kürzungen von LL eingearbeitet</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:id="Site_TC">
        <body>
            <div xml:lang="zh">
                <head>天池山</head>
                <figure rend="full" xml:id="TC_sc_DSCF0140.JPG">
                    <head>Niches hewn in a steep cliff at Mount Tianchi; photograph taken in
                        2006</head>
                    <head xml:lang="zh">天池山摩崖石龕，2006年照片</head>
                    <graphic url="TC_sc_DSCF0140.JPG"/>
                </figure>
                <div>
                    <head>空間</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>地理位置</head>
                        <p>位於平陰縣洪範池鎮書院村北部的天池山（<ptr target="SY_sc_DSCF0124.JPG"/>），是魯中石灰岩質低山丘陵的一部分，其山體在很大程度上未受黃河沖積沉降的影響。天池山位於鲁中呈南北走向、寬闊的大寨谷之内，山谷由黄河支流之一<hi rend="dash">──</hi>浪溪河<hi rend="dash">──</hi>沖刷所形成。
                            因河流沖積作用帶來的肥沃土壤，形成了這一地區發達的農業。天池山矗立在大寨谷東側。附近的書院村聚落被馬蹄形的天池山及其相鄰的書院東山所環繞。</p>
                        <p>天池山位於平陰縣西南24.5公里、聊城市東南偏南47.5公里、東平縣西北22.5公里處（見封二地圖）。山腳海拔高度約為100米。目前，岩石上没有近代人工的痕跡。鄰近書院村的房屋修建在靠近山腳處。</p>
                        <p>天池山的地理位置是東經116.2934度，北緯36.1013度，相當於UTM坐標系統第50S帶，東行436400，北行3995410。銘刻和雕像位於天池山的南麓，面向西南偏西。
                                天池山與其南面的書院東山相連，書院東山西崖也有面向西南的石刻，天池山和書院東山的銘刻（天池山1號；書院東山1號）在彼此遠眺視線所及之處。在天池山以西2.1公里處、與天池山石刻隔大寨谷相望的是二鼓山石刻，石刻位於二鼓山東側，面向西方，因此此二處石刻（天池山1號；二鼓山1-3號）也在彼此遠眺視線所及之處。天池山東南3.5公里是大寨山石刻，但因被幾條更高的大寨山山脊所阻擋，故此處石刻（大寨山1號）與天池山石刻在彼此遠眺視線所及之外（地圖，<ptr target="Map_5_2013_01_29a.jpg"/>）。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>史英</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>地形與空間構成</head>
                        <p>書院村正北方的天池山，在其南麓的陡峭崖壁之上開鑿有幾個佛龕和洞窟（<ptr target="TC_sc_DSCF0140.JPG"/>）。
                                這六個接近方形的洞窟不規則地分佈在崖壁上，窟內空無一物，其原始功能不明。其中，崖壁頂部的一個洞窟，以及蓮花座和似塔頂的裝飾，形制類似寳塔（<ptr target="TC_scu_4220-1.JPG"/>），因此推測其它可能用於保存聖物，比如高僧骨灰。</p>
                        <p>崖壁北端有兩個大型佛龕，佛龕之間以石碑為間隔。碑首裝飾有龍，但碑身並無任何刊刻文字（<ptr target="TC_4241-2.jpg"/>）。其左側的佛龕有一菩薩立像（<ptr target="TC_scu_detail_DSCF0117.JPG"/>）。
                            右邊的佛龕更大， 內有一個佛立像及兩尊脅侍菩薩。在“文化大革命”時期，這些雕像都遭到了嚴重破壞，佛像幾乎全部被毁，菩薩像的臉部也被破壞（<ptr target="TC_scu_detail_DSCF0093.jpg"/>）。雕像之側題刻有佛名和菩薩名。
                                    儘管題刻的佛名也遭極度破壞，但仍可被復原。根據題刻，釋迦牟尼佛兩側是觀世音菩薩和大勢至菩薩。右側有一單尊菩薩造像龕，龕中左側題詞說明該像是觀世音菩薩，由鄆州人供養敬造。<note>見唐仲明在<foreign lang="en">2009</foreign>’中國重慶大足石刻國際學術研討會上發表的文章摘要。見<ref type="biblio" target="DZ_shikeyishu_bwg2009b">33-34</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>根據風格，這兩個造像龕內雕像的雕刻時代可能是唐代，但是摩崖表面的石刻工作則持續了更長時間。唐代的佛龕可能破壞了崖壁上更早的銘文遺存。在天池山陡峭崖壁的北盡頭，雕有
                                釋迦牟尼佛像及觀世音和大勢至菩薩像的大型佛龕右側，還有一個方形洞窟（<ptr target="TC_r__DSCF0103.JPG"/>）。洞窟右側的一縱向題銘為“大空王佛”（天池山1號石刻）。在這個單獨的佛名之外，在天池山並没有發現其他唐代以前的石刻。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>溫狄婭</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>釋名</head>
                        <p>道光版《東阿縣志》載：“峰頂有泉，謂之‘天池’”，因此得名“天池山”。<note>《東阿縣志》<ref type="biblio" target="Donge_Xianzhi">1: 139</ref>。民國版《東阿縣志》<ref type="biblio" target="Donge_Xianzhi_minguo_a">82</ref>，從之。</note>
                        </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>賴非、蔡穗玲</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <figure rend="center" xml:id="Map_5_2013_01_29a.jpg" n="map">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">大寨谷內之摩崖刻經遺址</head>
                            <head>Map of inscription sites in Dazhai valley</head>
                            <graphic url="Map_5_2013_01_29a.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>時間</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>相關寺院</head>
                        <p>
                            <anchor xml:id="TC11zh"/>大寨谷內有五處摩崖石刻，大寨山、二鼓山、天池山、書院東山以及雲翠山，它們都與洪範池鎮的崇梵寺緊密相關。</p>
                        <p>洪範池鎮三面環山，泉水突湧，風光優美。周邊分佈著眾多佛教遺跡。1982年11月，沿該鎮中央台地北緣修公路取土時，
                            在離台地表層約1.6米深處發現了大隋皇帝舍利寳塔石函。平陰縣文化館文物工作者隨即清理了現場。</p>
                        <p>清理簡報說：</p>
                        <quote>石函出土於台地的東北部，周圍是一片夯土。……夯土厚2.5米，夯層厚10—15釐米。石函周圍夯土層純淨，不包含磚石等任何建築材料，
                            亦未發現地宫建築痕跡。……石函分內外兩重：……內函通高97釐米，平面呈正方形，邊長83釐米。函身用整塊石頭鑿成，……函蓋盝頂，……蓋頂分兩行鎸刻“大隋皇帝舍利寳塔”八個字。
                            ……外函通高135釐米，系由六塊石板組成。……在外函底板之上，內函與外函邊板之間，周匝相疊排列三百六十餘枚隋五銖錢。
                                ……在四個角上各放置一枚北周“永通萬國”錢。<note>見邱玉鼎、楊書杰 <ref type="biblio" target="Qiu_Yang1986"/>。</note>
                        </quote>
                        <p>此舍利寳函的出土，再次印證了文獻中隋文帝（581-604年在位）於仁壽間（601-604）頒分舍利於諸州的事實。史籍載，隋文帝詔分舍利先後有三次，並在全國一百一十三個州建起一百一十三座舍利塔供奉。
                                其中，山東地區分得舍利者有十五處，其中包括瀛州釋明馭送舍利到達的濟州崇梵寺。<note>有關隋代仁壽年間分得舍利的寺院名單，見游自勇
                                    <ref type="biblio" target="YouZiyong2002">24-30</ref>；有關隋代仁壽年間舍利的分頒，見陳金華 <ref target="ChenJinhua2002a" type="biblio">51-87</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>《續高僧傳》卷二十六《釋明馭傳》<note>《續高僧傳》T#2060, 50:
                            674b29-c22。</note>載，釋明馭護送舍利至崇梵寺引起了該地區的極大震動：</p>
                        <quote>仁壽中年，敕請送舍利於濟州崇梵寺，寺基帶危峰，多饒異樹，山泉盤屈，修竹蒙天，實佳地也。剋日將下，寺有育王瑞像，乃放三通神光，遍於體上，
                            金石榴色朗晃奪精，經一食頃，乃遂漸歇。又聞磬聲搖曳長遠，寺東岩上唱善哉聲，清暢彻心，追尋莫委。又舍利函上光高三尺，狀如花樹。本送舍利分為二粒，
                            出琉璃瓶相隨而轉，並放光明。有黄白雲從西南來，聲如雨相，流音樂聲，正當塔上，凝住不動。復見二花從雲中出，或時上下，大鳥群飛，迴旋塔上。又於雲中現仙人頭，
                                其數無量……。<note>《續高僧傳》T#2060, 50: 674c5-c16。</note>
                        </quote>
                        <p>傳中描寫的寺院周邊環境正與洪範池一帶相符。洪範池鎮距濟州治所約40公里，北朝及隋代濟州（郡）一帶多為平原，其域內没有其他可與洪範池相媲美的環境。以歷史環境與出土的舍利石函作為雙重印證，完全證實這裡就是當年的崇梵寺。崇梵寺舍利石函的出土，不僅證實隋文帝頒舍利於諸州並建塔供奉，
                            還表明洪範池一帶佛教活動與濟州的關係，搞清了淹没已久的洪範池寺院所在地。</p>
                        <p>由於近年洪範池周邊經常發現佛名、佛像，所以，我們必須特別關注寺址的地層情況及崇梵寺的興衰歷史。目前，田野考古工作還未展開，只能從寺址表面了解一些情況。
                            20世紀80年代修路，上層土移走後，下層的泥土內既有隋唐時期的蓮花瓦當、筒瓦、板瓦、獸飾建築構件，也有北朝繩紋磚瓦等遺物。文化層之上覆蓋著50—100釐米左右的黄土層，淤積痕跡相對較少。</p>
                        <p>文化層中發現的大量北朝磚瓦等建築構件，與洪頂山寺院廢墟出土的磚瓦年代相同，說明這裡至少在北齊時期也有寺院存在。
                            而隋代的崇梵寺極有可能是在北朝同名寺院的基礎上擴建的。如果這種推測不誤的話，那就可以說，至少在北朝時期，崇梵寺已經是濟州的佛教中心了。隋文帝能把舍利頒分给它，說明該寺在隋之前已有很高的聲望和地位。</p>
                        <p>然而不久後，崇梵寺即衰落下來。這裡地勢低窪，周圍三面是山。該寺正好處在盆地的邊緣，低窪的地勢，決定了它的命運，就像屢次遷徙的東阿縣城一樣。寺址斷崖上唐文化層之上直接覆蓋著淤積的黄土層，
                            表明崇梵寺大約是在唐早期遭山洪湮没而倒塌的。</p>
                        <p>後來，寺院東遷至書院東山腳下，並易名為洪福寺，明代又改為東流書院。《東阿縣誌》（民國版）卷七曰：“東流書院：在城南十五里東流泉上，即故洪福寺也。嘉靖中拆毁淫祠改為書院，祀宋儒程張朱五賢。……今院祀久廢。”</p>
                        <p>北朝時期盛極一時的崇梵寺，招來了眾多信奉佛教的善男善女，也招來為弘法宣教而奮鬥的大沙門僧安道壹（活躍於
                            562-579）。周邊山崖上鎸刻的佛名，以及司里、洪頂二山上的佛經可能都是他的作品，刊刻的時間大概在北齊皇建二年（561）至河清三年（564）之間。
                                    佛名題刻中出現的幾位供養人，都是參與僧安活動的出資者與同道人。二鼓山上有比丘僧太、比丘道顒、程伯仁，雲翠山上有比丘僧令、比丘道［顒］、比丘僧太、比丘智［顒］、比丘寳陵等。應該說，這些人都與崇梵寺有著密切的關聯。管理他們的州沙門統叫做道研，《北齊書·蘇瓊傳》曰：“道人道研為濟州沙門統，資產巨富。”<note>《北齊書》<ref type="biblio" target="BeiQishu1972">46: 643</ref>。 </note>
                        </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>賴非、項目研究組</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <figure rend="center" xml:id="TC_scu_4220-1.JPG">
                            <head>Cavity with stupa ornament; photograph taken in 2006</head>
                            <head xml:lang="zh">石窟及其塔式裝飾，2006年照片</head>
                            <graphic url="TC_scu_4220-1.JPG"/>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>相關人物</head>
                        <p>該遺址没有留下刻經相關人物的信息。</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>斷代</head>
                        <p>除了佛名銘刻之外，此處不存在其他有關佛名的石刻題記。因此，對天池山的銘刻紀年很難作出確切推斷。以書法風格分析的角度看，此佛名的書寫形式，類似於山東其他北齊、北周時期的摩崖石刻佛名。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>溫狄婭</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>研究史</head>
                        <p>迄今為止，討論天池山石刻的主要有賴非、<note>賴非<ref type="biblio" target="LaiFei2003c">104</ref>；<ref target="LaiFei2007" type="biblio"/>。</note>楊浩和郝莉，<note>楊浩、郝莉<ref type="biblio" target="Yang_Hao2006b">174</ref>。</note>見《北朝摩崖刻經研究［續］》及《北朝摩崖刻經研究［三］》。唐仲明針對此處造像
                                    作了系統的調查與研究，並繪製了龕像的線圖，但未發表全文，僅在2009年中國重慶大足石刻國際學術研討會上發表論文摘要。<note>見<ref type="biblio" target="DZ_shikeyishu_bwg2009b">33-34</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>溫狄婭、蔡穗玲</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>銘刻</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>銘文總數</head>
                        <p>天池山僅存一處佛名題刻（天池山1號石刻）。晚期的造像龕，或許打破並遮蓋了原來其他與佛名同時期的佛經節文。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>蔡穗玲</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>佛名</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>天池山1號</head>
                            <p>“大空王佛”含義見上文洪頂山佛名的相關說明。關於該佛名在山東省的分佈，見洪頂山8號的“討論”部分。</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>溫狄婭</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>刊刻技法</head>
                            <p>天池山刻經技法主要為“雙鈎”刻法。刻工將筆畫雙邊線單鏨刻出，留出筆畫輪廓（<ptr target="TC_1.jpg"/>）。 </p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>賴非</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>書法藝術</head>
                            <p>“佛”字的最後一筆為雙鈎，並稍許拉長（<ptr target="TC_r_1_detail_DSCF0096.JPG"/>），類似於雲翠山所刻佛名（雲翠山1號）。書院東山（書院東山1號）、二鼓山（二鼓山1號）和洪頂山（洪頂山19、20、21.1和23.1號）所刊刻“佛”字的豎畫比此處更長。這是公元6世紀下半葉所刻佛名的一個顯著特徵。</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>溫狄婭</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="en">
                <head>Mount Tianchi</head>
                <div>
                    <head>Space</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Location</head>
                        <p>Mount Tianchi <foreign xml:lang="zh">天池山</foreign>, north of Shuyuan
                            Village in Hongfanchi Township <foreign xml:lang="zh">洪範池鎮</foreign>,
                            Pingyin County <foreign xml:lang="zh">平陰縣</foreign>, is part of the
                            limestone formations of Shandong’s central ranges that were largely
                            unaffected by the Yellow River’s <foreign xml:lang="zh">黃河</foreign>
                            alluvial deposit. It is sited in the Dazhai Valley <foreign xml:lang="zh">大寨谷</foreign>, orientated north-south, in Shandong’s
                            central range. The Langxi River <foreign xml:lang="zh">浪溪河</foreign>, a
                            tributary of the Yellow River, shaped the valley, and its deposits
                            fertilized the soil and fostered agriculture. Mount Tianchi rises
                            steeply to the east of Dazhai Valley. The nearby village at Shuyuan
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">書院村</foreign> is encircled by the
                            horseshoe-shaped range of Mount Tianchi and the adjacent East Mount
                            Shuyuan <foreign xml:lang="zh">書院東山</foreign>. </p>
                        <p>Mount Tianchi lies 24.5 km to the southwest of the county seat of Pingyin
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">平陰</foreign>, 47.5 km to the south-southeast
                            of Liaocheng City <foreign xml:lang="zh">聊城市</foreign>, and 22.5 km
                            northwest of the county seat of Dongping <foreign xml:lang="zh">東平</foreign> (map in front endpaper). Its foot is at an altitude of
                            ca. 100 m above sea level. To date, there has been no modern activity at
                            Mount Tianchi. Houses of Shuyuan Village <foreign xml:lang="zh">書院村</foreign> have been built close to the mountain’s foot.</p>
                        <p>Geographically, Mount Tianchi is situated 116.2934° east and 36.1013°
                            north WGS84. This equals 436400 E (easting) and 3995410 N (northing) on
                            the meridian 50S UTM. The inscription and sculptures are found on the
                            south side of Mount Tianchi, facing west-southwest. To the south, Mount
                            Tianchi merges into East Mount Shuyuan, which carries inscriptions on
                            its west side, facing southwest. The inscriptions of Mounts Tianchi and
                            East Mount Shuyuan are within each other’s line of sight. At the
                            opposite side of Dazhai Valley, at a distance of 2.1 km to the west, are
                            situated the inscriptions of Mount Ergu <foreign xml:lang="zh">二鼓山</foreign>. These have been carved on the east side of the
                            mountain, facing west. Again, the inscriptions of both mountains are
                            within each other’s line of sight. The inscription on Mount Dazhai
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">大寨山</foreign> is 3.5 km to the southeast of
                            Mount Tianchi. Ridges on Mount Dazhai block the view of its inscription
                            (map, fig. <ptr target="Map_5_2013_01_29a.jpg"/>).</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>TS</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Topography and Spatial Grouping</head>
                        <p>At the south side of Mount Tianchi, right above Shuyuan Village, a few
                            niches and cavities were hewn out of the face of a steep cliff (fig.
                                <ptr target="TC_sc_DSCF0140.JPG"/>). About half a dozen almost
                            square openings are distributed irregularly over the cliff. They are
                            empty and their original function is not clear. One of these cavities
                            high on the cliff was decorated in relief with a lotus base below and a
                            pagoda-like roof above its upper edge, characterizing it as a stupa
                            (fig. <ptr target="TC_scu_4220-1.JPG"/>), and thereby giving rise to the
                            suggestion that it was meant to contain something sacred, such as the
                            ashes of a deceased monk.</p>
                        <p>At the northern end of the cliff, two large niches separated by a stele
                            were cut out of the rock. The stele’s head is decorated with dragons,
                            but not a single character was carved on its body (fig. <ptr target="TC_4241-2.jpg"/>). The niche to its right contains a
                            standing bodhisattva (fig. <ptr target="TC_scu_detail_DSCF0117.JPG"/>),
                            while the one to the left is larger and offers enough space for a
                            standing Buddha and two accompanying bodhisattva figures. All the
                            sculptures suffered severe damage during the Cultural Revolution. The
                            Buddha is almost completely destroyed, and the bodhisattvas have lost
                            parts of their faces (fig. <ptr target="TC_scu_detail_DSCF0093.jpg"/>).
                            The Buddha’s and bodhisattvas’ names have been carved next to the
                            sculptures. Although considerable effort was made to blank out the
                            characters of these names as well, they can be reconstructed. According
                            to these inscriptions, Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign>
                            was flanked by the Bodhisattvas Guanshiyin <foreign xml:lang="zh">觀世音</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="sa">Avalokiteśvara</foreign>) and
                            Dashizhi <foreign xml:lang="zh">大勢至</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="sa">Mahā­sthāma­prāpta</foreign>). The inscription next to the single
                            bodhisattva in the niche to the right names the sculpture as a donation
                            of a Bodhisattva Guanshiyin by an individual from Yun Prefecture
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">鄆州</foreign>.<note>See the abstract by Tang
                                Zhongming <foreign xml:lang="zh">唐仲明</foreign> in <ref type="biblio" target="DZ_shikeyishu_bwg2009b">33-34</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>The image niches can be dated to the Tang dynasty on stylistic grounds,
                            but work on the cliff face continued over a longer period of time. The
                            Tang niches probably destroyed earlier traces of inscriptions on the
                            rock face.</p>
                        <p>Another square cavity is located at the northernmost end of the steep
                            cliff, to the left of the large image niche with <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign> and the two bodhisattvas (fig. <ptr target="TC_r__DSCF0103.JPG"/>). Left of the cavity runs one single
                            vertical line reading “Buddha King of Great Emptiness” (TC 1). No other
                            inscriptions pre-dating the Tang dynasty are found at Mount Tianchi.</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>CW</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <figure rend="center" xml:id="TC_scu_detail_DSCF0104.JPG">
                            <head>Image niche and cavity at the northernmost end of Mount Tianchi’s
                                cliff; photograph taken in 2006</head>
                            <head xml:lang="zh">天池山摩崖北端的造像龕和石窟，2006年照片</head>
                            <graphic url="TC_scu_detail_DSCF0104.JPG"/>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Place Name </head>
                        <p>Near the mountain’s top is a spring. It is thus called Tianchi, Heaven’s
                            Pond (according to the <hi rend="italic">Gazetteer of Dong’e County,
                                Daoguang edition </hi> [<hi rend="italic">Daoguang Dong’e xianzhi
                                </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">(道光)東阿縣志</foreign>]), and the mountain
                            is named Mount Heaven’s Pond, Tianchi Shan <foreign xml:lang="zh">天池山</foreign>.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Donge_Xianzhi">1:
                                    139</ref>. The Republican edition of the <hi rend="italic">Gazetteer of Dong’e County </hi>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Donge_Xianzhi_minguo_a">82</ref>, concurs.</note>
                        </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>LF, TSL</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <figure rend="center" xml:id="TC_4241-2.jpg">
                            <head>Stele without characters; photograph taken in 2006</head>
                            <head xml:lang="zh">無字碑，2007年照片</head>
                            <graphic url="TC_4241-2.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Time</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Related Monasteries</head>
                        <p>
                            <anchor xml:id="tc1"/>The five inscription sites situated in the Dazhai
                            valley, Mount Dazhai, Mount Ergu, Mount Tianchi, East Mount Shuyuan, and
                            Mount Yuncui <foreign xml:lang="zh">雲翠山</foreign> have to be seen as in
                            relation to the Chong­fan Monastery <foreign xml:lang="zh">崇梵寺</foreign>
                            in Hongfanchizhen <foreign xml:lang="zh">洪範池鎮</foreign>. </p>
                        <p>The township of Hongfanchi is surrounded by mountains on three sides,
                            with gushing springs, fine scenery, and many Buddhist remains. In
                            November 1982, when earth was removed during road construction along the
                            northern edge of the platform at the center of the municipal area, a
                            stone casket from an imperial reliquiary pagoda of the Great Sui dynasty
                            was discovered 1.6 m below the platform’s surface. This casket is
                            thought to have been deposited in the Chongfan Monastery. Archaeologists
                            from the Cultural Bureau of Pingyin County immediately examined the
                            site.</p>
                        <p>The excavation report reads:</p>
                        <quote> The stone casket was excavated in the northeastern part of the
                            plateau, in a plot of rammed earth. The earth is 2.5 m thick, with
                            layers each measuring 10-15 cm. The layers next to the stone casket are
                            uncontaminated, and do not contain any architectural remains, such as
                            bricks or stones. No traces of the construction of a subterranean crypt
                            were found. The stone reliquary has an inner and outer casket: The inner
                            casket is 97 cm high; its cross-section is square; each side is 83 cm
                            long. The casket is made of a solid block of stone, … it is covered with
                            a lid … on the lid eight characters in two columns are chiseled, reading
                            ‘precious relic stupa of the Emperor of the Great Sui (<hi rend="italic">Da Sui huangdi sheli bao ta</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">大隨皇帝舍利寶塔</foreign>).’ … The outer casket is 135 cm high and
                            composed of six stone slabs. … On the bottom slab of the outer casket,
                            in between the side slabs of the inner and outer caskets, ... 360 <hi rend="italic">wuzhu </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">五銖</foreign> coins
                            dating from the Sui dynasty were arranged. … At each of the four corners
                            was placed a coin from the Northern Zhou dynasty, with the legend
                            ‘forever valid in the ten thousand lands <foreign xml:lang="zh">永通萬國</foreign>’.<note>Excavation report by <ref type="biblio" target="Qiu_Yang1986"/>.</note>
                        </quote>
                        <p>The excavation of this reliquary confirms once more the record that, in
                            the <hi rend="italic">renshou</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">仁壽</foreign>
                            era (601-604), the Sui Emperor Wen <foreign xml:lang="zh">隋文帝</foreign>
                            (r. 581-604) began to distribute relics to all prefectures. On three
                            occasions, the Emperor decreed the distribution of relics, and had 113
                            relic stupas built for veneration in 113 prefectures throughout the
                            country. In the region of Shandong, 15 localities received relics,
                            including those that monk Mingyu <foreign xml:lang="zh">明馭</foreign>
                            from Yingzhou <foreign xml:lang="zh">瀛州</foreign> brought to the
                            Chongfan Monastery in Jizhou <foreign xml:lang="zh">濟州</foreign>.<note>For a list of all monasteries that received
                                relics in the <hi rend="italic">renshou</hi> era see <ref type="biblio" target="YouZiyong2002">24-30</ref>; for the <hi rend="italic">renshou</hi> relics cf. also <ref target="ChenJinhua2002a" type="biblio">51-87</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>According to Mingyu’s biography in scroll 26 of the <hi rend="italic">Sequel to the Biographies of Eminent Monks </hi> (<hi rend="italic">Xu gaoseng zhuan </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">續高僧傳</foreign>),<note>T#2060, 50: 674b29-c22.</note> the region was
                            in a fever of excitement when Mingyu escorted the relics to the Chongfan
                            Monastery.</p>
                        <quote>In the middle years of the <hi rend="italic">renshou</hi> era
                            (601-604), an Imperial order requested the sending of the <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">śarīra</foreign>
                            </hi> to
                            Chongfan Monastery in Jizhou. The monastery was located amidst high
                            peaks among plentiful rare trees, with mountain streams twisting and
                            turning, and tall bamboos reaching up to the sky, a beautiful place
                            indeed. On the day when [the relics] were about to be delivered, the
                            monastery’s auspicious <foreign xml:lang="sa">Aśoka</foreign> icon
                            emitted three beams of supernatural light all over its body. The light
                            had the color of a golden pomegranate, bright and dazzling, forceful and
                            pure. It lingered for a moment, and then vanished gradually. Also, a
                            distant resonating sound of a chime stone was heard, as was a voice
                            singing ‘excellent’ coming from the monastery’s eastern cliff. Clear and
                            unimpeded, it penetrated the heart, but after an investigation, it could
                            not be assigned to anyone. Further, the glow above the reliquary casket
                            was three feet high, in the shape of a blossoming tree. The <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">śarīra</foreign>
                            </hi> that had
                            been sent was composed of two grains. When taken out of the beryl
                            bottle, they turned around each other, shining together. Yellow-white
                            clouds approached from the southwest, with the sound of music like
                            streaming rain. When they reached the top of the stupa, they solidified
                            and did not move. Then two flowers rose from amidst the clouds,
                            sometimes above, sometimes below, and a crowd of big birds flew circling
                            around the stupa. Also the heads of immortals appeared among the clouds
                            in countless numbers… <note>T#2060, 50: 674c5-c16.</note>
                        </quote>
                        <figure rend="center" xml:id="TC_scu_detail_DSCF0117.JPG">
                            <head>Niche with single standing bodhisattva; photograph taken in
                                2006</head>
                            <head xml:lang="zh">有單體菩薩立像的石龕，2007年照片</head>
                            <graphic url="TC_scu_detail_DSCF0117.JPG"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>The environment of the monastery, as described in the texts, fits the
                            region of Hongfanchi, which is 40 kilometers away from the local
                            government seat of Jizhou. In the Northern dynasties and the Sui, the
                            Jizhou area was a wide plain, and the surroundings of the city were not
                            as beautiful as those of Hongfanchi. The excavation of the reliquary and
                            the nature of the landscape have enabled the identification of the site
                            of the Chongfan Monastery. Apart from confirming the Sui Emperor Wen’s
                            proclamation to distribute relics to all prefectures and build stupas,
                            the excavation of the reliquary illustrates the Buddhist activities in
                            the region of Hongfanchi and its relation to Ji­zhou. The excavation has
                            also clarified the naming of Hongfanchi’s monastery, which vanished long
                            ago.</p>
                        <p>As in recent years Buddhist statues and inscriptions have frequently been
                            discovered in the Hongfanchi area, due attention must be given to the
                            stratigraphy of the site and the vicissitudes of Chongfan Monastery in
                            history. At the moment, archaeological fieldwork has not been
                            undertaken, and we can only draw some conclusions from the site’s
                            surface. When soil was removed in the 1980s, the earth beneath contained
                            eave tiles with lotus ornaments, barrel tiles, concave tiles, and
                            architectural components with animal decor from the Sui and Tang
                            dynasties, and bricks and tiles with rope motifs from the Northern
                            dynasties. The occupation level was covered with a layer of yellow earth
                            of about 50-100 cm in depth, which contained relatively few traces of
                            deposits. The large quantities of architectural remains from the
                            Northern dynasties found in the occupation layer, such as bricks and
                            tiles, are from the same period as those excavated at the site of the
                            monastery at Mount Hongding <foreign xml:lang="zh">洪頂山</foreign>. This
                            find indicates that, at least during the Northern Qi dynasty, a
                            monastery was sited here. It is very likely that the Sui dynasty
                            Chongfan Monastery was built on the foundation of a monastery from the
                            Northern dynasties of the same name. If these conjectures are correct,
                            it can be said that, at least during the Northern dynasties, Chongfan
                            Monastery was already the Buddhist center of Jizhou. Emperor Wen of
                            Sui’s gift of relics suggests that this monastery enjoyed a high
                            reputation and status even before the Sui dynasty.</p>
                        <p>Yet, before long, Chongfan Monastery began to decline. The terrain is low
                            and surrounded by mountains on three sides. The monastery was situated
                            right at the edge of the basin. The low lying position determined its
                            fate, which resembles that of the Dong’e County Town, which had to be
                            moved repeatedly. The occupation layer of Tang times at the monastery
                            site is covered with a layer of loess deposit, which shows that,
                            probably during the early Tang period, Chongfan Monastery was devastated
                            by a landslide and collapsed. </p>
                        <p>Later, the monastery was moved eastward to the foot of East Mount
                            Shuyuan, and its name changed to Hongfu Monastery (Hongfu Si <foreign xml:lang="zh">洪福寺</foreign>). In the Ming dynasty, it was again
                            changed to Dong­liu Academy (Dongliu shuyuan <foreign xml:lang="zh">東流書院</foreign>). The <hi rend="italic">Gazetteer of Dong’e County,
                                Republican edition </hi> (<hi rend="italic">Minguo Dong’e xianzhi
                                </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">[民國]東阿縣誌</foreign>), scroll 7, reads:
                            “Dongliu Academy: Located above the fountain Dongliu, 15 <hi rend="italic">li </hi> south of the city; it is the ancient Hongfu
                            Monastery. During the Jiajing <foreign xml:lang="zh">嘉靖</foreign> era
                            (1522-1566), the illegal shrine was demolished and turned into an
                            academy, where sacrifices were offered to the Five Virtuous Confucians,
                            Cheng [Hao and Cheng Yi], Zhang [Zai], and Zhu [Xi] of the Song
                            dynasty...Today, the sacrifices at the academy have long been
                            abandoned.”</p>
                        <p>Chongfan Monastery, which flourished for a time during the Northern
                            dynasties, attracted numerous male and female Buddhist believers, as
                            well as the Great Renunciant Seng’an Daoyi <foreign xml:lang="zh">僧安道壹</foreign> (fl. 562-579). For the Buddha names chiseled on the
                            surrounding mountains and the Buddhist sutras at Mounts Sili <foreign xml:lang="zh">司里山</foreign> and Hongding are probably his works,
                            dating roughly between the second year of the <hi rend="italic">huangjian </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">皇建</foreign> era of the
                            Northern Qi dynasty (561) and the third year of the <hi rend="italic">heqing </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">河清</foreign> era (564). In the
                            colophons to the Buddha names a few donors appear who were peers and
                            sponsors of Seng’an’s activities. At Mount Ergu are the names of monk
                            Sengtai <foreign xml:lang="zh">僧太</foreign>, monk Daoyong <foreign xml:lang="zh">道顒</foreign>, and Cheng Boren <foreign xml:lang="zh">程伯仁</foreign>; at Mount Yuncui are the names of monk Sengling
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">僧令</foreign>, monk Sengtai <foreign xml:lang="zh">僧太</foreign>, monk Dao[yong] <foreign xml:lang="zh">道[顒]</foreign>, monk Zhi[yong] <foreign xml:lang="zh">智[顒]</foreign>, and monk Baoling <foreign xml:lang="zh">寳陵</foreign>. It can be assumed that these men had close relations
                            with the prestigious Chongfan Monastery. The monks’ superintendent of
                            the prefecture was Daoyan <foreign xml:lang="zh">道研</foreign>. The
                            biography of Su Qiong <foreign xml:lang="zh">蘇瓊</foreign> in the <hi rend="italic">History of the Northern Qi Dynasty</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Beiqishu </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">北齊書</foreign>)
                            states: “The practitioner of the Way, Daoyan, is Superintendent of the
                            Monks of Jizhou, and is immensely wealthy.”<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="BeiQishu1972">46: 643</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>LF, RG</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <figure rend="center" xml:id="TC_scu_detail_DSCF0093.jpg">
                            <head>Damaged Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign> and
                                Bodhisattva <foreign xml:lang="sa">Avalokiteśvara</foreign>;
                                photograph taken in 2006</head>
                            <head xml:lang="zh">殘損的釋迦牟尼造像和觀世音造像，2006年照片</head>
                            <graphic url="TC_scu_detail_DSCF0093.jpg" height="140mm"/>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Related Persons </head>
                        <p>No information available. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Dating</head>
                        <p>Since no other inscriptions apart from the Buddha name have been
                            preserved, no exact dating is available for the site of Mount Tianchi.
                            Stylistically, the calligraphy matches that of other carved Buddha names
                            in Shandong that can be dated to the Northern Qi and Northern Zhou
                            dynasties. </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>CW</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Research History</head>
                        <p>The inscription has primarily been discussed by Lai Fei <foreign xml:lang="zh">賴非</foreign>
                            <note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="LaiFei2003c">104</ref>;<ref target="LaiFei2007" type="biblio"/>.</note> and Yang Hao <foreign xml:lang="zh">楊浩</foreign>and Hao Li <foreign xml:lang="zh">郝莉</foreign>.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Yang_Hao2006b">174</ref>.</note> Tang Zhongming <foreign xml:lang="zh">唐仲明</foreign> examined the sculptures at the site. In 2009 he
                            published an abstract of his paper. <note>See <ref type="biblio" target="DZ_shikeyishu_bwg2009b">33-34</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>CW, TSL</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <figure rend="center" xml:id="TC_r__DSCF0103.JPG">
                            <head>Location of Mount Tianchi’s “Buddha King of Great Emptiness”
                                inscription; photograph taken in 2006</head>
                            <head xml:lang="zh">天池山刊刻“大空王佛”的位置，2006年照片</head>
                            <graphic url="TC_r__DSCF0103.JPG"/>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Inscription</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Inventory</head>
                        <p>At Mount Tianchi, one Buddha name (TC 1) was carved. The later niches
                            with sculptures may possibly have obliterated other passages that had
                            earlier been engraved there.</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>TSL</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <figure rend="center" xml:id="TC_r_1_detail_DSCF0096.JPG">
                            <head>Detail of “Buddha King of Great Emptiness” inscription; photograph
                                taken in 2006</head>
                            <head xml:lang="zh">“大空王佛”石刻局部，2006年照片</head>
                            <graphic url="TC_r_1_detail_DSCF0096.JPG"/>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Buddha Name</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>TC 1</head>
                            <p>For the meaning of the name, “Buddha King of Great Emptiness”, see
                                the relevant introduction to Mount Hongding <foreign xml:lang="zh">洪頂山</foreign>, Buddha names. For all occurrences of this name
                                in Shandong Province, see HDS 8, discussion. </p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Carving Techniques</head>
                        <p> The carving technique is in double outlines. The carver chisels only the
                            outline on either sides of a stroke, so that the interior of the stroke
                            remains untouched (fig. <ptr target="TC_1.jpg"/>).</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>LF</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Style of Calligraphy</head>
                        <p>The last stroke of the character for “Buddha” <foreign xml:lang="zh">佛</foreign> was cut in double outlines on the rock face, and its
                            last vertical stroke is relatively long (fig. <ptr target="TC_r_1_detail_DSCF0096.JPG"/>), comparable with the Buddha
                            name carved at Mount Yuncui <foreign xml:lang="zh">雲翠山</foreign> (YC 1).
                            Yet the characters at East Mount Shuyuan <foreign xml:lang="zh">書院東山</foreign> (SY 1), Mount Ergu <foreign xml:lang="zh">二鼓山</foreign> (EG 1), and Mount Hongding <foreign xml:lang="zh">洪頂山</foreign> (HDS 21.1) boast even longer vertical strokes. This
                            is a distinctive feature of carved Buddha names from the second half of
                            the sixth century.</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>CW</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>