<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/rest/db/schema/stone.xsd">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Introduction to the Site of Mount Yin</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>N.N.</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
    
    <seriesStmt>
        <!-- Titel und Kürzel des Bandes in @n -->
        <title n="shandong_volume1" xml:lang="en">Shandong Volume 1</title>
        <title n="shandong_volume1" xml:lang="zh">山東省第一卷</title>
        <!-- Ordnungsnummer für Kapitelreihenfolge in @n -->
        <biblScope unit="chapter" n="9"/>
    </seriesStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>25.03.2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>JMP</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Aktualisierung Gliederung</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>31.03.2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item> Abschnitt Carving Techniques überarbeitet gemäß Markette</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>03.04.2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Abschnitt Location überarbeitet gemäß Markette</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>April 5th 2011</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Änderungen und Kürzungen von LL eingearbeitet</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:id="Site_Yin">
        <body>
            <div xml:lang="zh">
                <head>銀山</head>
                <figure rend="full" xml:id="Yin_sc_2924.JPG">
                    <head>View of Mount Yin from the east; photograph taken in 2006</head>
                    <head xml:lang="zh">銀山東側，2006年照片</head>
                    <graphic url="Yin_sc_2924.JPG"/>
                </figure>
                <div>
                    <head>空間</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>地理位置</head>
                        <p>銀山位於東平湖西岸，東平縣西北33公里、梁山縣以北29公里、聊城市東南偏南45公里處（見封二地圖）。
                            山體南北跨度約0.7公里，東西長約1.3公里，山頂海拔為120米。銀山遭受了嚴重的人為破壞（<ptr target="Yin_sc_DSC3459.JPG"/>）。其石刻位於一個石灰石採石場的邊緣，有被夷為平地的危險。目前保存有一段通向山上一座現代建築的石階、
                            建築本身以及附近的摩崖石刻（<ptr target="Yin_sc_2888-1.jpg"/> 、<ptr target="Yin_sc_68.jpg"/>）。銀山的地理位置是東經116.1186度，北緯36.0655度，相當於UTM坐標系統第50S帶，東行420630，北行3991570。</p>
                        <p>銀山石刻，面向南方。附近的司里山石刻，在其西南偏南方6公里處。在銀山上，可以看到司里山，但因其石刻面朝東方，所以並不在視線之內。與銀山隔東平湖相對的是正東方10.9公里外的洪頂山（地圖，<ptr target="Map_2_Dongping_2013_01_29.jpg"/>)。
                            從銀山可以看到洪頂山，不過在銀山刻經處卻無法看到該山。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>史英</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>地形與空間構成</head>
                        <p>銀山摩崖石刻，可以經由通往一個小型現代建築的陡峭石階到達（<ptr target="Yin_sc_2888-1.jpg"/>；<ptr target="Yin_sc_68.jpg"/>）。該建築是為保護唐代的大像龕而建，龕内雕有兩尊坐佛像。摩崖石刻即刊刻在現代建築東側的岩面上（<ptr target="Yin_r_detail_IMG_2911-2.jpg"/>）。</p>
                        <p>再向東120米，在銀山南麓靠近山腳處有兩個造像龕（<ptr target="Yin_scu_IMG_2930-1.JPG"/>）。左邊較大的壁龕高93釐米，內供一佛坐像。其下底座岩石被磨平，上有一嚴重風化的題記（銀山2號石刻）。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>溫狄婭</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>釋名</head>
                        <p>山名來歷不詳。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>賴非</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <figure rend="page" xml:id="Yin_sc_68.jpg">
                            <head>View of Mount Yin from the south with
                                two stelae erected in 2000, and stairs leading up to the modern building; photograph taken in
                                2004</head>
                            <head xml:lang="zh">銀山及其通向現代建築石階的正視圖，2004年照片</head>
                            <graphic url="Yin_sc_68.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>時間</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>相關寺院</head>
                        <p>沒有相關寺院的資料。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>賴非</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>相關人物</head>
                        <p>銀山背面嚴重風化的題記（銀山2號），提及“高唐縣令”。高唐縣在現今銀山以北90公里處。除了這個人名外，再没有其他與該地點相關的人物信息。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>溫狄婭</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>斷代</head>
                        <p>銀山背面一佛造像龕底座題記中存有唯一一個紀年（銀山2號）。這處題記最初至少有十一行，每行十三字。第一行中可辨認出紀年“大齊天統四年（568）二月”。雖然造像窟與銀山正面的刻經文相隔甚遠，不過，銀山的主要銘刻出自北齊末年的觀點仍得到公認，
                                因其書法及刊刻風格與山東同時期其他石刻相似。<note>見賴非<ref type="biblio" target="LaiFei2003a">104</ref> 和桐谷征一<ref type="biblio" target="Kiriya2003a">74-76</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>溫狄婭</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>研究史</head>
                        <p>2003年出版的《北朝摩崖刻經研究［續］》簡短地描述了這個地點，<note>張總
                            <ref target="ZhangZong2003a" type="biblio">4</ref>。</note>並數次提到了所刻經名。2006年出版的第三輯再次討論了銀山。賴非2007年的專著《山東北朝佛教摩崖刻經調查與研究》，提供銀山1號完整的信息。<note>賴非
                                <ref target="LaiFei2007" type="biblio"/>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>溫狄婭</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>銘刻</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>銘文總數</head>
                        <p>銀山現存一處刻經（銀山1號）和一個造像龕供養題刻（銀山2號）。</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>經名</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>銀山1號</head>
                            <p>“佛說摩訶般若波羅蜜”，總共四行九個大字，刊刻在陡峭的摩崖之上。由於前兩個字“佛說”，這處題銘聽起來類似佛經之名，只是末尾没有“經”字。由此看來，它被當作另一段佛經節文的標題，節文可能刊刻於其下，不過已經湮滅。 <note>張總
                                    <ref target="ZhangZong2003a" type="biblio">4</ref>。</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>然而，最後幾個字“般若波羅蜜”也見於徂徠山映佛岩及陶山石刻，這說明般若波羅蜜也作為習語被刊刻。<note>見桐谷征一<ref type="biblio" target="Kiriya2003a">76</ref>，及《中國佛教石經·山東省》第三卷。</note> 因此“佛說摩訶般若波羅蜜”也並不一定是另一篇或許失傳的佛經節文的標題，而可以理解為頌揚佛所說的般若波羅蜜，類似於洪頂山（洪頂山6號）和司里山（司里山3號）的刻文所具有的避邪功能。寥寥數字刊刻上石，銀山摩崖由此成為獲得般若波羅蜜的聖地。</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>溫狄婭</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>歷史題刻</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>銀山2號</head>
                            <p>2號銘刻與1號刻經無直接關聯。銘刻於造像龕的佛像座，紀年為568年。</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>刊刻技法</head>
                        <p>銀山刻經技法主要為“V”形刻法，即從筆畫兩邊線斜入鏨，簡便快捷。 </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>賴非</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <figure rend="center" xml:id="Yin_sc_DSC3459.JPG">
                            <head xml:lang="en">Mount Yin being used as a quarry; photograph taken
                                in 2012</head>
                            <head xml:lang="zh">銀山當代採石場，照片拍攝於2012年</head>
                            <graphic url="Yin_sc_DSC3459.JPG"/>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="en">
                <head>Mount Yin</head>
                <div>
                    <head>Space</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Location</head>
                        <p>Mount Yin <foreign xml:lang="zh">銀山</foreign> is
                            sited to the west of Lake Dongping <foreign xml:lang="zh">東平湖</foreign>,
                            33 km northwest of the county seat of Dong­ping <foreign xml:lang="zh">東平</foreign>, 29 km
                            north of the county seat of Liangshan <foreign xml:lang="zh">梁山</foreign>, and 45 km
                            south-southeast of Liaocheng City <foreign xml:lang="zh">聊城市</foreign> (map in front endpaper).
                            It has a north-south extension
                            of about 0.7 km, and an east-west extension of about 1.3 km. The peak is
                            at an altitude of 120 m above sea level. Mount Yin has been severely
                            damaged by human activity. Its inscriptions are situated on the brink of
                            a limestone quarry, and are endangered by demolition work (fig. <ptr target="Yin_sc_DSC3459.JPG"/>). A steep flight of stairs leads
                            uphill to a small modern building. The building and the neighboring
                            inscription-bearing rock have been spared. Geographically, Mount Yin is
                            situated 116.1186° east and 36.0655° north WGS84. This equals 420630 E
                            (easting) and 3991570 N (northing) on the meridian 50S UTM.</p>
                        <p>Mount Yin’s inscription faces south. The neighboring inscription site of
                            Mount Sili <foreign xml:lang="zh">司里山</foreign> lies 6 km to the
                            south-southwest. While Mount Sili is visible from Mount Yin, its
                            inscriptions are not within the line of sight, as they face east.
                            Separated by Lake Dongping from Mount Yin, Mount Hongding <foreign xml:lang="zh">洪頂山</foreign> is located exactly to the east at a
                            distance of 10.9 km (map, fig. <ptr target="Map_2_Dongping_2013_01_29.jpg"/>). It can be seen from Mount
                            Yin, but not when standing at the actual inscription site. </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>TS</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Topography and Spatial Grouping</head>
                        <p>Mount Yin’s main polished cliff inscription can be
                            reached by climbing the stairs leading to the modern
                            building  (fig. <ptr target="Yin_sc_2888-1.jpg"/> and fig. <ptr target="Yin_sc_68.jpg"/>), which protects a large niche with two seated Buddhas of the Tang dynasty. The cliff inscription
                            was hewn into the bluff rock face to the east of
                            this building (fig. <ptr target="Yin_r_detail_IMG_2911-2.jpg"/>).</p>
                        <p>About 120 m further to the east, on the southern
                            slope and near to its foot, are two more
                            niches with sculpted images (fig. <ptr target="Yin_scu_IMG_2930-1.JPG"/>).  The larger niche to the left,
                            which is 93 cm high, contains a seated Buddha sculpture. The rock of the
                            pedestal beneath has been smoothed and contains a heavily weathered and
                            damaged votive inscription (Yin 2).</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>CW</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Place Name </head>
                        <p>The origin of the mountain’s name is not clear.</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>LF</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <figure rend="center" xml:id="Yin_sc_2888-1.jpg">
                            <head>Modern building next to carved cliff; photograph taken in
                                2006</head>
                            <head xml:lang="zh">現代建築在石刻摩崖之側，2006年照片</head>
                            <graphic url="Yin_sc_2888-1.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Time</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Related Monasteries</head>
                        <p>There is no information on a related monastery.</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>LF</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Related Persons </head>
                        <p>The votive inscription on Mount Yin’s southern slope mentions the title
                            of a local official and probable donor, a “County Magistrate of Gaotang”
                            (Gaotang xianling <foreign xml:lang="zh">高唐縣令</foreign>). The modern
                            city of Gaotang lies 90 kilometers to the north. Apart from this name, there is
                            no information on the persons related to this site.</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>CW</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Dating</head>
                        <p>The only date found at the site is part of the votive inscription on the
                            pedestal of the larger niche with the Buddha figure (Yin 2). It
                            originally comprised at least eleven columns with 13 characters each. In
                            the first column, a date of “the second month of the fourth year of the
                            <hi rend="italic">tiantong</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">天統</foreign> era of the Great Qi
                            dynasty” is given that corresponds to 568. Although the niches and
                            the sutra text are quite far apart, it is nevertheless generally agreed
                            that the main inscription at Mount Yin is from the late Northern
                            dynasties because of its stylistic similarity with other Shandong
                                inscriptions.<note>See <ref target="LaiFei2003a" type="biblio">104</ref>, and <ref type="biblio" target="Kiriya2003a">74-76</ref>. </note>
                        </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>CW</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Research History</head>
                        <p>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Research on the Sutras Engraved on Polished Cliffs of the Northern Dynasties, vol. 2</hi>
                            (<hi rend="italic">Beichao moya kejing yanjiu (xu) </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">北朝摩崖刻經研究（續）</foreign>)</title> of 2003 has a
                            short description of the site,<note>
                                <ref target="ZhangZong2003a" type="biblio">4</ref>.</note> and the
                            carved sutra title is mentioned several times. Mount Yin is discussed
                            once more in the third volume of 2006.  Lai Fei’s monograph
                            of 2007 gives full information on the inscription Yin 1.<note>
                                <ref target="LaiFei2007" type="biblio"/>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>CW</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Inscriptions</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Inventory</head>
                        <p>At Mount Yin, one sutra title (Yin 1) and one votive inscription (Yin 2)
                            were carved.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Sutra Title</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>Yin 1</head>
                            <p>Nine large characters, arranged in four vertical columns,
                                were carved on the rough cliff face, reading “The Great Perfection
                                of Wisdom Spoken by the Buddha”. The first two characters
                                “Spoken by the Buddha” sound like the title of a sutra,
                                only missing the mandatory “sutra” at the end. Therefore, it has
                                been interpreted as a title for a sutra passage, which was probably
                                carved underneath but has vanished.<note>
                                    <ref target="ZhangZong2003a" type="biblio">4</ref>. </note>
                            </p>
                            <p>Yet, the last characters reading “Perfection of Wisdom” are also seen at Yingfoyan
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">映佛岩</foreign> on Mount Culai <foreign xml:lang="zh">徂徠山</foreign>, and on Mount Tao <foreign xml:lang="zh">陶山</foreign>,<note>
                                    <ref target="Kiriya2003a" type="biblio">76</ref>.</note>
                                indicating that the Perfection of Wisdom was also carved as a phrase
                                of its own (see vol. 3 for Mount Tao and for Mount Culai).
                                Thus, the formulation “The Great Perfection of Wisdom Spoken by the
                                Buddha” does not necessarily have to be the title of another lost
                                inscription, but it can be understood as the eulogized Great
                                Perfection of Wisdom as spoken by the Enlightened One himself, with
                                a similar talismanic function, as seen on Mount Hongding <foreign xml:lang="zh">洪頂山</foreign> (HDS 6) and Mount Sili <foreign xml:lang="zh">司里山</foreign> (Sili 3).
                                In this case, the act of
                                simply carving the characters would transform the rocky grounds of
                                Mount Yin into the very place where perfect enlightenment is
                                attained. </p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>CW</abbr>
                            </ab>
                            <figure rend="center" xml:id="Yin_scu_IMG_2930-1.JPG">
                                <head>Two niches on the southern slope of Mount Yin; photograph taken in
                                    2006</head>
                                <head xml:lang="zh">銀山南麓的兩個佛龕，2006年照片</head>
                                <graphic url="Yin_scu_IMG_2930-1.JPG"/>
                            </figure>
                            <figure rend="center" xml:id="Yin_r_detail_IMG_2911-2.jpg">
                                <head>Cliff carved with “The Great Perfection of Wisdom Spoken by the
                                    Buddha”; Photograph taken in 2006</head>
                                <head xml:lang="zh">“佛說摩訶般若波羅蜜”摩崖石刻，2006年照片</head>
                                <graphic url="Yin_r_detail_IMG_2911-2.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Historical inscription</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>Yin 2</head>
                            <p>The inscription Yin 2 is not directly related to the inscription Yin 1. It is carved on the base of a seated Buddha  figure in a niche, dated to the year 568.</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>TSL</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Carving Techniques</head>
                        <p>The technique is mainly V-shaped carving. The carver chisels slanting
                            lines from both sides of a stroke, a convenient and fast technique.</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>LF</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>