<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/rest/db/schema/stone.xsd">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Site Mount Hongding</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>N.N.</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <!-- Titel und Kürzel des Bandes in @n -->
                <title n="shandong_volume1" xml:lang="en">Shandong Volume 1</title>
                <title n="shandong_volume1" xml:lang="zh">山東省第一卷</title>
                <!-- Ordnungsnummer für Kapitelreihenfolge in @n -->
                <biblScope unit="chapter" n="2"/>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>29.07.2008</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>correct spelling of *Mandra[sena] and *Saṃghabhara included, more corrections
                    proposed by Funayama Toru included</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>24.03.2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Korrekturen der "Markette" eingearbeitet</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>27.03.2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Fußnoten überarbeitet</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>08.05.09</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>JMP</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Korrektur SZ, einzelne Wörter </item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>13.08.2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Ergänzung Location, einzelne Korrekturen</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>19.08.09</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Research History by Zhang Zong added</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>20.08.09</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Dating by Zhang Zong added</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>21.08.2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Related Persons by Zhang Zong added</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>21.09.2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>RRO</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>This is a placeholder entry, which I will use to make a list of Sanskrit sutra
                    names to be applied consistently throughout. *Candragarbha-vaipulya-sūtra;
                    Śaptaśatikā-prajñāpāramitā; Mahāratnakūṭa-sūtra;
                    *Mahāvaipulya-mahāsaṃnipāta-sūtra; Pañcaviṃśatisāhasrikā-prajñāpāramitā;
                    Mahā-prajñāpāramitā-śāstra, *Mahā-prajñāpāramitā-hṛdaya-sūtra </item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>23.02.2010</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW and RRO</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Ledderose’s corrections included into the text</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>25.11.2010</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>SZ and CC</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Buddha Names by Tsai Sueyling added</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>27.11.2010</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>SZ</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>New version of chinese translation included into the text</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>19 May 2011</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>English text written by LL added; HDS 4, Layout, and Style of
                    Calligraphy.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>22.11.2012</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Sanskrit terms marked as foreign xml:lang="sa"</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>13.9.2013</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>corrections by Jessica Rawson from 19 August inserted</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:id="Site_HDS">
        <body>
            <div xml:lang="zh">
                <head xml:lang="zh">洪頂山</head>
                <figure xml:id="HDS_sc_8_154" rend="full" n="figure">
                    <head>Inscription HDS 8 on the northern slope seen from afar, the huge “Buddha
                        King of Great Emptiness;” photograph taken in 2002</head>
                    <head xml:lang="zh">洪頂山北麓8號石刻“大空王佛”，2002年照片</head>
                    <graphic url="HongdingShan_Frontispiz_hoch_300.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <div>
                    <head>空間</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>地理位置</head>
                        <p>本節的主角<hi rend="dash">──</hi>洪頂山坐落於東平湖的東岸，由圍繞一道平坦山谷的V形山脊構成。東平湖位於魯中山區的西緣，毗鄰黃河沖積平原。從地質學角度來看，山體屬於山東省境內山脈常見的石灰岩質，基本未受沖積沉降的影響。</p>
                        <p>洪頂山的地理坐標為東經116.238度，北緯36.064度，相當於UTM坐標系統第50S帶，東行431470，北行3991300。洪頂山所圍繞的山谷的海拔有100多米，摩崖石刻即分佈於谷內的南北麓上。</p>
                        <p>洪頂山現隸屬於東平縣，距離東平縣城西北24公里、平陰縣城西南30公里處（見封二地圖）。</p>
                        <p>鄰近的銀山摩崖，位於洪頂山以西10.9公里處，二山隔東平湖相望。站在洪頂山上，可眺望到銀山，但銀山南面的石刻不在視線之內。司里山也位於東平湖西岸，距洪頂山西南11.9公里。在洪頂山上，亦可望見司里山，但看不到主要集中在司里山東面的刻經。洪頂山以東4.9公里處是雲翠山，其刻經位於峰頂正下方，面西。然而礙於山東中西部山區另一座高聳山峰，從洪頂山上不能直接看到雲翠山（地圖，<ptr target="Map_2_Dongping_2013_01_29.jpg"/>）。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>史英</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>地形與空間構成</head>
                        <p>東平湖呈水滴狀，其東北岸為洪頂山兩條山脊向湖延伸所形成的山谷。山谷東側崖壁圍合，曾是茂林脩竹，西側崖壁敞開，連接廣闊湖面，山脊內側南北相對的山崖成為刊刻佛教經典的最佳場所。
                            洪頂山的兩條山脊閉合成橫寫的“V”形，另一條出自“大洪頂山”的山脊平行於該“V”形的北山脊，在其上部形成一個半圓，圍繞著內部的“V”形山脊。
                                從地圖上，可以清楚地看到這一特別的形狀。摩崖刻經由群山庇護，類似陵墓和洞窟的布局（地圖，<ptr target="Map_3_Hongdingshan002_2013_01_29a.jpg"/>）。</p>
                        <p>洪頂山北麓共有十七處刻銘，南麓六處（地圖，<ptr target="Map_4_Hongdingshan_Level3.jpg"/>）。其中，南麓銘文的總長度僅為27.83米，可以視為一組；北麓銘刻（<ptr target="HDS_sc_northern_slope_total_IMG_0363.JPG"/>）的總長度則達45.44米，在空間上可分為四組。前三組在摩崖岩面上的水平位置基本相同，西邊的一組（洪頂山1－4號）與中間的一組（洪頂山5和6號）相距9.82米，中間的一組與東邊的一組（洪頂山7－12號）相距11.63米（<ptr target="HD_northen_slope_Beschr.jpg"/>）。三組刻經之間由緊貼陡峭崖壁的狹窄小徑相聯 （<ptr target="HDS_sc_northern_slope_HD0274.jpg"/>）。當到達東邊一組佛名摩崖（洪頂山9.1-9.16號）處時，參觀者會突然發現自己置身於一個由天然岩石組成的巨大塔狀岩堆之前，其上半部還有一些佛名（洪頂山10－12號）。一條小徑環繞該岩塔向上延伸，通往隱藏在岩塔“東廊”中的第四組石刻（洪頂山13－17號，
                            <ptr target="HDS_gallery.tif"/>）。倚靠在岩塔的背面，參觀者可以近距離地觀看刻經，甚至坐在經文（洪頂山16號）前禪修（<ptr target="meditationseat.jpg"/>），刻經對面的石座正為此用。<note>關於這一刻經以及類似的摩崖刻經被用於禪修的論點在導論中已有討論，見本卷第<ptr type="infra" target="LLmeditationzh"/>頁。
                            </note>向左望去，整個洪頂山谷及西向延伸至天際的東平湖可盡收眼底（<ptr target="HDS_sc_gallery_3296_1.jpg"/>）。<note>公元6世紀時東平湖的確切位置和面積尚不清楚。賴非（<ref target="LaiFei2003c" type="biblio">103-104</ref>）推測現在東平湖北岸的沼澤地帶曾經是乾涸的，因此從洪頂山谷寺院到其西南11.9公里的司里山寺院，可能有陸路連通。</note>
                        </p><?page-break?>
                        <p>洪頂山南麓岩面中部有明顯凹陷的一區，銘文主要刊刻在凹陷崖壁的兩端，其間僅有一條四字題刻（洪頂山20號；見<ptr target="HD_southern_slope_Beschr.jpg"/>）。洪頂南北麓刻經之間的最短距離是151.13米，即北麓巨大的“大空王佛”
                            題刻（洪頂山8號）和南麓較小型的“大空王佛”題刻（洪頂山19號）之間。兩崖刻經之間的最長距離是172.9米，在北麓16號和南麓22號兩處內容相同的刻經之間。這顯示出，刻經的內容增強了此處刻經彼此在空間上的關聯。洪頂山的橫式V形山谷，更進一步證實了山東各處刻經在空間分佈中隱含的基本規律：即使跨越了很大的空間距離，銘刻仍被安排在相對應的位置上。由此，刻經營造者創造出一個在群山景觀中相互呼應的神聖刻經網絡。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>雷德侯，溫狄婭</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <figure rend="center" n="map" xml:id="Map_2_Dongping_2013_01_29.jpg">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">東平湖東西兩岸石刻分佈圖</head>
                            <head>Map of inscription sites east and west of Lake Dongping</head>
                            <graphic url="Map_2_Dongping_2013_01_29.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>釋名</head>
                        <p>東平縣洪頂山有大洪頂、二洪頂之分。山谷東側的主峰名二洪頂，二洪頂以東的山峰叫大洪頂。此處佛教摩崖刻經被發現後，依據清代對當地山名的稱謂，並參照其他諸山刻經的命名（例如，尖山大佛嶺刻經被簡稱為尖山刻經，北葛山刻經叫作葛山刻經），於1995年將二洪頂的刻經命名為“洪頂山刻經”。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>賴非</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>時間</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>相關寺院</head>
                        <p>洪頂山南、北、東山脊之間的山谷內發現有建築遺址，東西長約120米，南北寬約40至50米，面積約5400平方米。該遺址在1964年冬修水庫時被破壞殆盡。據當地村民回憶，當時從水庫區挖出很多磚瓦陶片以及四方柱礎。</p>
                        <p>現存暴露的部分可見一層30至50釐米厚的文化層和幾座晚期墓葬。新石器、戰國、漢代陶片和北朝磚瓦隨處可見，證明這裡不僅曾有人類長期居住生活，而且北朝時還曾修建過大型建築。這組建築應該就是與僧安道壹（活躍於
                            562-579）刻經活動關係密切的寺院。</p>
                        <p>該寺院在唐代以後就不復存在（遺址中未曾發現唐以後的建築遺物）。既没有留下寺名，也没有留下碑刻或其他文字記載。洪頂山刻經經主法洪（鴻），很可能就是該寺的住持。 </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>賴非</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <figure rend="center" n="map" xml:id="Map_3_Hongdingshan002_2013_01_29a.jpg">
                            <head>Map of Mount Greater Hongding</head>
                            <head xml:lang="zh">大洪頂山地形圖</head>
                            <graphic url="Map_3_Hongdingshan002_2013_01_29a.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                        <figure rend="center" n="map" xml:id="Map_4_Hongdingshan_Level3.jpg">
                            <head>Map of the inscription site Mount Hongding</head>
                            <head xml:lang="zh">洪頂山刻經址地圖</head>
                            <graphic url="Map_4_Hongdingshan_Level3.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>相關人物</head>
                        <p>洪頂山摩崖刻經鑿刻偉壯、內涵豐富，有數方刻經、數方佛名、數方銘讚，這顯然與主持參與者的非凡能力有關。幸運的是，兩位僧侶的題名見諸摩崖石刻，極具價值。其一是僧安道壹，他的名字出現在洪頂山3、4、7、15和16.1號題刻中；其二是釋法洪（鴻），他的名字出現在洪頂山9.16、18、21.2和23.2號題刻中。此外，在洪頂山2號《大集經》節文前有“經主道門”的題名，該題名於1995至1999年間遭到了破壞。這一題名表示負責此處刻經的並不限於上述二人，而是一個活躍的僧人團體。</p>
                        <p>作為洪頂摩崖刻經的關鍵人物，僧安道壹和釋法洪（鴻）的銘讚也刻在岩石之上。這正是此處摩崖的獨特價值之所在。北麓的僧安道壹銘讚（洪頂山3號）與南麓的法洪（鴻）銘讚（洪頂山18號）隔山谷遙遙相對。其文辭格式基本一致：均先列出頌主簡況，再讚美其突出業績，最後以四言頌詞結束。</p>
                        <p>可惜僧安道壹銘讚（洪頂山3號）有些殘泐，部分字跡無法識别。但給人突出印象的是讚文以
                            “積石”、“崆峒”般的千峰萬嶺來比喻其道德器度，以“石石鐫銘，山山□□”來歸納他的事業。這昭示了他在摩崖書刻方面的作為<hi rend="dash">──</hi>書丹。洪頂山的摩崖刻經等等，都鐫鑿著僧安道壹的書寫之跡。更確切地說，即僧安道壹是在岩石上寫出佛經片段、佛名數種，用以刻銘存世的書僧。這一點很容易找到旁證，就在此銘右側，一個圭形框格中便是僧安道壹的大字題名（洪頂山4號）。這很有可能是該銘讚（洪頂山3號）的“標題”。另一處《文殊般若經》節文（洪頂山16.2號）前，也題寫著“僧安道壹”之名（洪頂山16.1號）。僧安道壹由此被普遍視為該刻經的經主和書丹人。最後，洪頂山7號明言“大沙門僧安道壹書刊大空王佛七……”，這指明僧安道壹是數處題銘的書者。</p>
                        <p>在洪頂山，僧安道壹的題名出現的次數最為頻繁，而且這些題名也見於其他地方。山東省鄒城四山中，尖山與鐵山摩崖均有僧安道壹題名及題刻。這些摩崖已為晚清的學者和金石學家們重視、著錄及踏查。因此，僧安道壹這位能書擅賦的僧人早已為人所知。洪頂銘讚與刻跡為此提供了進一步的證據。所有這些摩崖題記顯示了他刻經及其他活動的範圍。</p>
                        <p>儘管僧安道壹的名字多次出現在摩崖石刻中，但是在僧傳和地方誌裡都找不到有關其生平的記載。洪頂山題刻的發現，引起了許多學術討論。其中最重要的觀點是將他的刻經活動分成若干階段，<note>見桐谷征一<ref target="Kiriya2003a" type="biblio">74-86</ref>。</note>或是把他的作品分成從稍短的佛經片段（主要出自般若經典）過渡到鐵山長篇節文（《大集經》）的兩大組。<note>見賴非<ref target="LaiFei2003c" type="biblio">119-131</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>僧安道壹的品格在洪頂山15號得到充分稱頌。這一題刻名之為“碑”，緣於其首題是“安公之碑”。碑文內容在“安”與“一”之間做文章，頗有文字遊戲之味。同時又蘊含禪修之意，借此表彰僧安道壹在佛學方面的成就。</p>
                        <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="HDS_sc_northern_slope_total_IMG_0363.JPG">
                            <head>The northern slope of Mount Hongding; photograph taken in
                                2004</head>
                            <head xml:lang="zh">洪頂山北麓，2004年照片</head>
                            <graphic url="HDS_sc_northern slope_total_IMG_0363.JPG"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>洪頂山的第二位關鍵人物釋法洪（鴻）的情况卻頗有不同。銘讚表明，法洪（鴻）是一位經師，即解釋佛學義理的大師。南麓“法洪銘讚”（洪頂山18號，有“非空不談，非如不說。談空說如，是非兩氓。無說無談，有無雙亡”。其銘詞也歸結為：“確尒法界，冥心大空”。這些都明顯集中於表彰其佛教義學，體現出了濃厚的般若空觀內涵。若以洪頂摩崖所刻的佛經內容比照，可以說與之全然契合。如《文殊般若》（洪頂山1，16.2和22號）和《仁王般若》選段（洪頂山6號）、再有大品《摩訶般若經》（《摩訶衍經》）節文（洪頂山5號）及“大空王佛”之佛名，均體現了空觀與般若類經典的對應。當然，就刻經節文之選段與法洪（鴻）思想來說，也不限於全然演述般若空觀。法洪銘讚中
                            “如”與“空”的並列，體現了般若空觀與華嚴思想的平行關係，<note>見羅炤<ref target="LuoZhao2014" type="biblio">待刊</ref>。
                            </note>顯出法洪（鴻）思想較般若空觀更廣闊的一面。</p>
                        <p>和僧安道壹一樣，法洪（鴻）也是摩崖刻經的經主之一。他是南麓《文殊師利所說般若波羅蜜經》節文（洪頂山22號）的“經主”（洪頂山21.2號），也是其中一個“大空王佛”
                            （洪頂山23.1號）的供養人。此外，他很可能與北麓的一大組佛名有關（洪頂山9.1–9.15號）<hi rend="dash">──</hi>即使此處他的名字寫作“法鴻”（洪頂山9.16號）。 </p>
                        <p>僧安道壹與釋法洪（鴻）的兩方銘讚體現的讚頌主題不一，卻能相互配合。由洪頂山南北麓的關係來看，僧安道壹書跡的刻經，反映了法洪（鴻）的思想。兩位高僧之間的配合相契應該存在。</p>
                        <p>與此同時，兩方銘讚開頭對頌主籍貫的陳述卻存在著鮮明的區別。僧安道壹是“廣大鄉空寬里”人，而釋法洪（鴻）卻是來自印度的中天竺人。關於僧安道壹的來歷雖有鄉里，卻是空泛而抽象的，即使結合鐵山刻經處所留的“東嶺僧”題記，也無法澄清他的來歷，反而更顯撲朔迷離，仍需進一步探討。</p>
                        <p>相比之下，釋法洪（鴻）的中天竺<hi rend="dash">──</hi>中印度僧人的身份，卻是明確而肯定的。讚文（洪頂山18號）起句所述的“娑婆國土、閻浮聚落、天竺人也”與頌詞“中天沙門、姓釋名洪”，已指出他來自印度五天竺之一的中天竺。中國古代稱印度為“天竺”，且有東、南、西、北、中五個部分，合稱“五天竺”。<note>如唐代開元年間（713-741），新羅僧人慧超（700-780？）經華赴印求法，歸來後寫成《往五天竺國傳》。原書雖佚，但在敦煌遺書中發現一寫本。日本學者藤田豐八作《慧超傳箋釋》，見<ref target="FujitaT1910" type="biblio"/>。德國學者福克司（<foreign xml:lang="en">Walter Fuchs</foreign>）重新編輯中文原本，並譯成德語，見<ref target="Fuchs1938" type="biblio"/>。
                                </note>“中天竺”即古印度中部。至於“閻浮聚落”與“娑婆國土”則是佛教裡的大洲與世界之觀念，佛經中多有敘說。<note>佛教的世界觀稱須彌山為世界中心，其四方有四大洲，即：東弗于逮，南閻浮提，西瞿耶尼，北鬱單越。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>因此，雖然法洪（鴻）未見於僧傳記載，但他應該是來自中印度的高僧。《高僧傳》所記來華的印度高僧，也常常說明其是中天竺人或是某天竺人。<note>如北齊時著名譯經家那連提離耶舍，為北天竺人，遊方經止茹茹國，天保七年（556）來鄴都，譯經多部，弘揚“末法”說的《大集經月藏分》T#397, 13: 352a18-353a17，即其譯出。
                                較他更早到鄴都的印度僧人，也有一些中天竺人。如中天竺優禪尼國王子月婆首那（538－565），中天竺波羅奈國居士瞿曇般若流支，還有北天竺僧著名譯經元匠菩提流支（？－527）、佛陀扇多（活躍於511）等
                                。</note>那些來華的譯經僧，見載史册的多為身處都會、交接皇親僧統者。而僻居山野者，如法洪（鴻），則只有洪頂刻經的發現才為人所知。</p>
                        <p>總之，參與北齊早期洪頂山刻經活動的人物至少有深通般若學說的印度僧人法洪（鴻）與極擅書法的中土和尚僧安道壹。兩人的大名均刊刻上石，銘讚成篇。因此，洪頂山的摩崖石刻，時代在北齊初年，主要人物來自中印兩國。這兩人之中，法洪（鴻）僅見於洪頂山，而僧安道壹，其刻經書跡遍及魯西地區、甚至可能至於冀境；加之具其題名與頌讚之詞在附近鄒城市的鐵山、尖山摩崖刻經也有出現，所以，對僧安道壹原就頗多關注和探討。洪頂書跡和銘讚的發現，引起了更多對他的積極探討與溯源研究；相對而言，對法洪（鴻）則鮮有關注與研究。</p>
                        <p>法洪（鴻）與僧安道壹兩者之間的關係，就一位精佛學，一位擅書法而言，似乎法洪（鴻）為導師；
                            但從洪頂南北麓兩題刻的關係來說，與僧安道壹相關聯的北麓“大空王佛” （洪頂山8號）遠較南麓法洪供養的“大空王佛”
                            （洪頂山19，20，21.1和23.1號）為大。此外，佛名中那些頌讚山嶽的佛名（洪頂山10和12號）以及“安王佛”
                            （洪頂山11號）可能與僧安道壹相關，在包括過去七佛的那組佛名旁署的卻是法鴻之名（洪頂山9.16號）。可見，二人應有密切的關係，只是如今不得而知。 </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>張總</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>斷代</head>
                        <p>洪頂山幽谷中的刻經，其斷代情況，因存有四條題記，得以基本比定。南麓的法洪（鴻）銘讚（洪頂山18號）銘刻年代為北齊河清三年（564），年份確切，迨無疑問。在北朝諸多刻經缺乏紀年的情況下，益顯珍貴。</p>
                        <p>頗有意趣的是，與此刻遙相對望的北麓，一則僧安道壹題記（洪頂山7號）也帶有紀年。與紀銘天竺僧人使用了中國朝代紀年不同，銘讚中土僧人卻用了佛曆<hi rend="dash">──</hi>佛滅紀年，即以釋迦牟尼佛涅槃日之後的年代數為紀。此紀云刻銘時在釋迦牟尼雙林寂滅後1623年。</p>
                        <p>除僧安道壹題記之外，他的銘讚（洪頂山3號）及“安公之碑”
                            （洪頂山15號）也都使用了佛曆紀年。只是僧安銘讚中紀年的部分殘損，“安公之碑”的年代則是釋迦牟尼雙林寂滅後1620年。</p>
                        <p>中國佛教史上漢藏兩系使用流傳的佛滅紀年多達六十種，其中漢傳佛教最主要使用的有“眾聖點記”、<note>點記是僧徒在佛涅槃後，每年於安居期後在《善見毘婆娑律》手稿上以香火添加的記號，此手稿由譯者僧伽跋陀羅携來中國。據此香火點記計算，佛滅約為公元前485年。見《歷代三寶紀》T#2034, 49: 95b18-c17。
                        </note>佛當周世說、<note>《周書異記》載佛生周昭王廿四年〈公元前958年〉、佛滅當周穆王五十二或五十三年〈公元前878或877年〉，天象均現多瑞異端，太史蘇由、扈多答帝問，釋為西方聖人<hi rend="dash">──</hi>釋迦生滅之徵兆。
                            由此佛的生卒年為公元前958-878/7年。6世紀的佛教護教文獻據此紀年之一例，見《續高僧傳》T#2060, 50: 624c26-625a4。</note>法顯（約337－442）說<note>在法顯求法遊記中，我們可以發現一個彌勒像建造於佛滅300年，此雕像紀年對應周平王統治時期（公元前770-720年），由此佛滅紀年為公元前1070至公元前1020年。
                            見《高僧法顯傳》T#2085, 51: 858a11-14。</note>及“末法”說。</p>
                        <p>一種佛滅紀年的推算與北齊時慧思大師（515－577）的《南嶽思大禪師立誓願文》<note>《南嶽思大禪師立誓願文》T#1933, 46: 786b-792b。</note>相關。在誓願文中，慧思說自己誕生時（北魏延昌四年，515年）已進入“末法”八十二年。<note>《南嶽思大禪師立誓願文》T#1933, 46: 787a4-6。
                            誓願本身立於北齊天寳九年（558），慧思四十三歲之時。見《南嶽思大禪師立誓願文》T#1933, 46: 787b26-c11。</note>
                            據此推算，“末法”時期開始於公元433年。加上末法前的一千五百年（正法一千年、像法五百年），佛滅當在公元前1067年，因此公元515年即為佛滅1582年。如果說洪頂山銘刻全與慧思誓願文吻合，即可推定“安公之碑”（洪頂山15號，佛滅1620年）刻於北齊天保五年（553），而僧安道壹題記（洪頂山7號，佛滅1623年）刻於北齊天保七年（556）。即洪頂山北麓僧安題記（洪頂山7號）比刻於公元564年的法洪銘讚（洪頂山18號）早八年完成。考慮到中古佛滅紀年常有誤差，洪頂山北麓刻銘未必較南麓早八年之久，所以對佛滅1623年相當於天保七年（556）的比定宜稍作保留。</p>
                        <p>
                            <anchor xml:id="zz1zh"/>另如上文已提及，如果洪頂山的佛滅紀年題記，確是嚴格依同於北齊慧思大師的誓願文之說，佛滅至天保七年（556）時已有一千六百二十三年，僧安道壹題記（洪頂山7號）較慧思立誓願文還要早兩年。當然，這並不能排除洪頂山石刻佛滅紀年可比定於慧思的說法。這其中包含著數種可能性，如慧思之說與石刻都參照了一個共同的已知來源；抑或北齊天保八年（558）慧思立誓願文之前，他應該曾提過自己生於“末法”八十二年（北魏延昌四年，515年）之事，
                            而且可能已有流傳。立誓時他已四十三歲，如果此前他没有說過類似的話，時至中年才說未免顯得奇怪。</p>
                        <p>但是現存類似的石刻佛滅紀年，增加了情况的複雜性。例如由上官香等在東魏興和四年（542）於河南汲縣所造的佛像題記記載“如來隱變雙林以有一千六百兩十五年”，<note>見魯迅<ref target="Luxun1987" type="biblio">2, 2: 325</ref>。
                            </note>根據這個題記計算，佛陀於公元前1083年入滅，“末法”時期則始於公元417年。
                        還有一些造像碑的紀年說法相當模糊，如北齊武平五年（574）智度等造像碑后題記，“大聖滅應歸真……自尔以來，餘迳千記”，<note>《智度等造像記》（574），見<ref target="BJTSG1989_91" type="biblio">8: 59</ref>。
                            </note>僅為模糊的佛滅後千紀之說。</p>
                        <p>考慮到這些複雜的情况，洪頂山的刻經年代，可推定為北齊天保初年（550）到河清三年（564）前後。<anchor xml:id="zz2zh"/>
                        </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>張總</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>研究史</head>
                        <p>晚清以來，金石學家、官吏和文人眼光轉向重視北碑<hi rend="dash">──</hi>即北朝以石刻形態表現出的書法遺品，認為其充滿血肉，生動強峻，張力極強，與久為主流的法書墨跡適成比對。</p>
                        <p>因此，從封疆大吏至文人乃至於拓工巧匠，皆遍尋幽谷僻山，踏查碑石，探覓勝蹟。所謂“北碑”，包含墓誌、造像記、碑記、佛經等等。其中佛教石經尤顯出眾。其數雖未有碑版、題記、墓誌為多，但大字巨擘，雄渾偉壯，書寫鑿工皆極難以為之。</p>
                        <p>因此之故，包世臣、康有為等對其交口讚之，如“雲鶴海鷗”、<note>包世臣《藝舟雙楫》<ref type="biblio" target="BaoShichen_Yizhoushuangji">79</ref>。</note>“榜書之宗”<note>康有為《廣藝舟雙楫》：“《經石峪》為榜書之宗。”見《廣藝舟雙楫》<ref target="Kangyouwei1987" type="biblio">474</ref>。</note>云云。泰山經石峪刻經，聲名大振；鄒城四山，流芳一時。但惟東平湖畔洪頂山谷中的刻經，人未識之。</p>
                        <p>及至近現代考古學興起，蔚為世界潮流，田野調查等方法在亞洲也得以應用。20世紀20年代，日本學者常盤大定與関野貞曾廣泛調查中國各地佛教遺蹟，山東地區亦多有涉足。<note>関野貞、常盤大定<ref target="Sekino_Tokiwa1925_31" type="biblio">第七冊和第十一冊</ref>。</note>不過，他們也未發現此處。</p>
                        <p>20世紀80年代，一牧羊人發現洪頂山摩崖刻石；1988年7月這些摩崖遺蹟引起有關當局的注意。喬修罡、青柏於1994、1995 年先後在《濟南日報》<note>喬修罡、青柏<ref type="biblio" target="Qiao_Qing1994"/>。 </note> 與《中國文物報》<note>喬修罡、青柏
                                <ref target="Qiao_Qing1995" type="biblio"/>。
                        </note>刊佈此發現。當時，洪頂山在行政區劃上屬於平陰縣。1996年1月1日，洪頂山劃歸至東平縣。此後，學術界的探查與科學研究以至考古田野工作上的國際合作漸漸展開。<note>吳緒剛<ref type="biblio" target="WuXugang2003">352</ref> 就此作了詳述。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>1997 年，在平陰縣物資局任職的柳文金獲得了一套不完整的拓片，並將其帶至北京。他邀請幾位在京的專家學者於北京體育大學體育館視察這些拓片，而且分發了摩崖題刻的照片及相關信息。</p>
                        <p>之後，李靜杰發表《解讀一本刻在懸崖上的巨幅古經書：觀東平、平陰摩崖刻經拓本瑣談》<note>李靜杰<ref target="LiJingjie1997a" type="biblio"/>。</note>一文，是大陸學者關於洪頂山摩崖的首篇論文。但當時正式的田野考察還未展開。</p>
                        <p>1997 年，柳文金也編輯出版了《山東平陰三山北朝摩崖》一書。其中的拓片非由專業拓工製作，因此不能真實反映石上的刻文。這些拓片都經過了增添及修飾。如洪頂山5號的大部分刻文風化不存，但這裡發表的拓片根據張總鑑定出的“十八空”經文，將其幾乎完整復原描出。因此，這些拓片並未收錄在本卷內容總錄中的“拓片”一項，而僅在“圖示”中出現。本卷僅刊發柳文金洪頂山2號的拓片（<ptr target="HDS_02_B.tif"/>）。雖然可信度不高，但此拓片給出這條幾乎破壞殆盡的銘刻一個整體的展現。該書的最大貢獻是其中張總的文章<note>張總 <ref target="ZhangZong1997" type="biblio"/>。</note>及他提供的刻經目錄。這是對洪頂山刻經第一次作出的學術分類。許多佛經節文首次得到了確認，同時，張總也在山東摩崖遺蹟這一大背景中分析洪頂山刻經。</p>
                        <p>1998年10月，山東省石刻藝術博物館在洪頂山開展第一次田野調查，“大空王佛” （洪頂山8號）旁重要的“佛滅紀年題記”（洪頂山7號）得以精工拓成。此後，張總根據佛曆紀年進行了考釋，並於2000年發表了研究成果。<note>張總
                                <ref target="ZhangZong2000a" type="biblio"/>。 </note>
                        </p>
                        <p>1999年上海復旦大學教授張偉然發表了論僧安道壹稱謂的文章，提出在洪頂山、鐵山和尖山留下若干題刻及題名的僧人，其名字的正確讀法是“僧安道壹”。<note>張偉然
                            <ref target="ZhangWeiran1999" type="biblio"/>。 </note>他認為佛教徒以“釋”為姓，故此前研究中以“安”為姓、以“道一”為名的提法不準確。本卷贊同此讀法。然而，俗名前冠僧字也出現在供養題記中。<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="YangHao2002">50-52</ref>, 及洪頂山3號和7號的“討論”部分。</note>
                        </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>張總</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <p/>
                        <p>《中國書法全集》第十二卷，即賴非主編的《北朝摩崖刻經》，出版於2000年。<note>賴非
                                <ref target="LaiFei2000a" type="biblio"/>。 </note>
                            該書集中體現了刻經研究的最新進展，其內容不但包括了洪頂山刻經當時最完備的錄文，而且還逐字記錄了其保存狀況。</p>
                        <p>2002年，在實地考察了平陰縣內新近發現的刻經之後，山東省石刻藝術博物館主持召開了一個成功的學術研討會，並出版了此會議的論文集《北朝摩崖刻經研究[續]》。<note>《北朝摩崖刻經研究[續]》
                            <ref target="SDSKYS_bwg2003" type="biblio"/>。 </note>與此書同名的第一卷出版於1991年，<note>《北朝摩崖刻經研究》
                                <ref type="biblio" target="SDSKYS_bwg1991a"/>。 </note>那時洪頂山刻經尚未為人所知。在2003年出版的續集中，三分之一的篇幅是關於洪頂山和僧安道壹的討論。賴非《僧安刻經考述》、<note>賴非
                                    <ref target="LaiFei2003c" type="biblio"/>。 </note>許洪國《“僧安道壹”卮言》、<note>許洪國
                                        <ref type="biblio" target="XuHongguo2003"/>。 </note>桐谷征一《北齊大沙門安道壹刻經事跡》、<note>桐谷征一
                                                <ref target="Kiriya2003a" type="biblio"/>。 </note>田熊信之《北朝摩崖刻經與安道壹》，<note>田熊信之
                                                    <ref type="biblio" target="Takuma2003"/>。 </note>
                            都探查了僧安道壹及其刻經。其餘論文分析了鐵山、泰山以及河北邯鄲等地刻經。</p>
                        <p>2006年，《北朝摩崖刻經研究［三］》出版，其中楊浩和郝莉提供了另一份關於整個東平縣內北朝摩崖刻經的調查報告，<note>楊浩、郝莉
                                <ref target="Yang_Hao2006b" type="biblio"/>。 </note>
                            包括了全部錄文及其保存狀況。</p>
                        <p>同年，山東省石刻藝術博物館與德國海德堡科學院合作的洪頂山摩崖刻經調查簡報發表於《文物》雜誌。<note>《洪頂山摩崖刻經考察》
                            <ref type="biblio" target="SDSKYS_HAW2006"/>。 </note>2007年，賴非發表專著《山東北朝佛教摩崖刻經調查與研究》，提供完整錄文、測量數據及有關洪頂山刻經的較新的討論。<note>賴非
                                <ref target="LaiFei2007" type="biblio"/>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>溫狄婭</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <figure xml:id="HDS_sc_northern_slope_HD0274.jpg" rend="page" n="figure">
                            <head>Path alongside the inscriptions of the northern slope</head>
                            <head xml:lang="zh">北麓石刻旁的小徑</head>
                            <graphic url="HDS_sc_northern slope_HD0274.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>銘刻</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>銘文總數</head>
                        <p>洪頂山摩崖石刻包括25處佛名（洪頂山8、9.1-9.15、10、11、12、13、17、19、20、21.1、23.1號），6段佛經節文（洪頂山1、2、5、6、16.2、22號）以及10條題記（洪頂山3、4、7、9.16、14、15、16.1、18、21.2、23.2號）。
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>佛名</head>
                        <p>在洪頂山上共發現分鎸於二十五處、十八個不同的佛名。它們是位於北麓編號8、9.1–9.15、10、11、12、13、17和位於南麓編號19、20、21.1、23.1的刻文。根據佛名的內容可以將它們分為兩組。</p>
                        <div>
                            <head>第一組：大空王佛</head>
                            <p>
                                <anchor xml:id="tsl1zh"/>構成第一組的六條刻文是佛名“大空王佛”，編號分別為8，17，19，20，21.1，23.1。這一組中面積最大的一條刻文（8號），不但是整個洪頂山題刻最宏偉的一條，同時也是書法和雕刻技術最精美的一例。8號刻文的面積為9.2
                                × 3.4米，它位於北麓題刻中段最顯著的位置（<ptr target="HDS_sc_8_154"/>）。最小的一個“大空王佛”（17號）同時也是洪頂山題刻中最小的一條，它以雙鈎勾勒，僅存的一個刻字大小為6 × 28釐米。它隱藏在北麓東邊一處高聳的岩石背後。<note>楊浩、郝莉
                                    <ref target="Yang_Hao2006b" type="biblio">166</ref>，提到了也許是一菩薩名的另外兩字。</note>該雙鈎刻文的書法和雕刻技法非常簡單，和8號刻文形成鮮明的對比。</p>
                            <p>其他四條“大空王佛”皆位於南麓。刻文均僅以雙鈎刻成，且處於石灰岩山體呈紋狀風蝕的表面上，因此極不易辨識（<ptr target="HDS_r_19_total_DSCF0082-1.JPG"/>；<ptr target="HDS_21.1neu.jpg"/>）。日本僧人學者桐谷征一認為這裡是特意用雙鈎的技法留白，以示“無常”和“空”的義理。<note>見桐谷征一<ref target="Kiriya2003a" type="biblio">71-72</ref>。</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>“大空王佛”這一佛名在傳世的早期佛教經典中無跡可尋。不過，“空王佛”(<foreign xml:lang="sa">Dharma­gaganābhyud­gata­rāja</foreign>)則於藏經佛典中有所記載。
                                空王佛是過去諸佛之一，並和釋迦牟尼佛前生故事有著緊密的連繫。《佛說觀佛三昧海經》描述，釋迦牟尼佛在成佛之前的一個前世中，是空王佛的弟子。<note>《佛說觀佛三昧海經》T#643, 15: 688c24-689a12。</note>那時，他親眼見到四位僧人如何在空王佛前觀想並成為正
                                四方之佛。<note>同上。</note>《妙法蓮華經》則記載，空王佛為釋迦牟尼及其弟子阿難的未來成佛作了授記。<note>《妙法蓮華經》T#262, 9: 30a1-7；《添品妙法蓮華經》T#264, 9: 164b16-24。</note>《佛說佛名經》也列出此佛名兩次。<note>
                                    《佛說佛名經》T#441, 14: 264a20; 308b12。</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>特别值得注意的是，空王佛的名字也出現在洪頂山18號銘刻<hi rend="dash">──</hi>“法洪銘讚”中。這段文字是刻經活動的主導者將“空王佛”作為廬舍那佛之對應佛的有力證據。刻文寫道：
                                <quote>［法洪］挺特三空，空王之初；紛綸萬行，盧舍之後。</quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>此處，空王佛是專門宣講般若經典中“空”這一教義的佛，與華嚴經典中佈道“如”的盧舍那佛相對應。因此，“大空王佛”可釋讀為“大—空王佛”，即“偉大的、崇高的空王佛”。通過給空王佛前冠以“大”字，表明了其信徒對他最高的景仰，將他看作至高和絕對的佛。</p>
                            <p>然而，“大空王佛”這個名字組合還巧妙地容許另一種釋讀，即“大空王—佛”。這種釋讀強調了“大空”（<foreign xml:lang="sa">mahāśūnyatā</foreign>），與洪頂山上所鐫刻經文的教義相符。“大空”是大乘教義中智慧的最高境界，以下幾段佛經引文可以印證這一觀點：《佛說觀佛三昧海經》將“大空”視為“般若”的同義詞，並宣揚“甚深妙法、般若波羅蜜大空之義”；<note>《佛說觀佛三昧海經》T#643, 15: 677a10。
                            </note>《佛說入楞伽經》講說七空中的第六空為“第一義聖智大空”；<note>《佛說入楞伽經》T#671, 16: 529a8-10；《楞伽阿跋多羅寶經》T#670, 16: 488c18-20。</note>《佛說華手經》提倡“大空正見”以抗衡“邪見”；<note>《佛說華手經》：“菩薩應當親近修習大空正見。離邪見故。”《大正藏》T#657, 16: 188b9-10。
                            </note>《佛本行經》則表讚“佛大空慧”。<note>《佛本行經》T#193, 4: 55c20。</note>
                            </p><?cb?>
                            <p>而且，“大空”在大乘佛教中還作為涅槃（<foreign xml:lang="sa">nirvāṇa</foreign>）以及如來（<foreign xml:lang="sa">tathāgata</foreign>）的同義詞。《佛說千佛因緣經》描述了佛陀如何“遊於大空、畢竟涅槃”；<note>《佛說千佛因緣經》T#426, 14: 70a17-19。</note>《大般涅槃經》解釋“慈即大空，大空即慈”<note>《大般涅槃經》T#374, 12: 456b15-24。</note>以及“慈即如來”。<note>《大般涅槃經》T#374, 12: 456b15-c5。</note>
                                它的對立術語“偏空”，是大乘佛教用來批判小乘佛教片面性的“空”<note>《摩訶止觀》：“墮偏空裹，或偏假裹。種種蹊徑，令不入圓。”《大正藏》T#1911, 46: 115c7-c8。《大般涅槃經疏》：“二乘偏空故，不見第一義空。” T#1767, 38: 175c12。</note> 的用詞。</p>
                            <p>意味深長的是，“大空”這一術語在洪頂山刻文中出現了兩次。一次是“十八空”之一（洪頂山5號，《摩訶衍經》碑十八空節文）。在這段專門闡釋“空”的經文中，“大空”表示空間上絕對的“空”，即十方皆空。《大方等大集經》對“大空”作出了如下的解釋：
                               <quote> 何者名為大空。東方，東方空。乃至四維空。非積聚，不可壞，不可取。何以故？
                                諸法性爾。是名大空。<note>《大方等大集經》T#397, 13: 360b28-c1。有關類似的闡釋，見《放光般若經》：“何等為大空？八方上下皆空，是為大空。” T#221, 8: 23a16。 《光讚經》：“彼何謂為大空？所謂東方亦空、南方、西方、北方、東南、西南、西北、東北方、上方、下方，皆亦悉空，不可毀傷、不可壞起。所以者何？本淨故也。” T#222, 8: 189b27-c1。《摩訶般若波羅蜜經》：“何等為大空？東方東方相空，非常非滅故。何以故？性自爾。南西北方四維上下南西北方四維上下空，非常非滅故。何以故？性自爾。是名大空。” T#223, 8: 250b20-23。</note>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>“大空”這個術語第二次出現在“法洪銘讚”（刻文18號）中，此處再次用了對應的表述作結語：“確尒法界，冥心大空。”再次強調了分別在《華嚴經》與《般若經》中闡釋的兩個絕對真實。一方面，法洪相信確實的“真如”；另一方面，他卻將自己全部身心投入另一面<hi rend="dash">──</hi>與“般若”等同的“大空”中。從這可以看出，“大空王佛”可釋讀為“大空王—佛”，或者“般若王—佛”。</p>
                            <p>綜上所述，人們可以對“大空王佛”這個佛名作出蘊含了多重意義的兩種釋讀。第一，“大空王佛”可以理解為“大—
                                空王佛”，通過增加“大”這一前綴對該佛表示敬意：他不但是釋迦牟尼佛的導師，還是專門宣講“空”的佛。這正呼應了鐫刻於洪頂山上的般若經典節文。</p>
                            <p>第二，“大空王佛”也可以視為“大空王—
                                佛”。這一名字強調了關於涅槃的大乘佛教教義，即完全的寂滅，佛典亦稱之為“大空”。“大空王—佛”以他的洞察力和正視，否定空間上一切的存在，宣告萬物皆為“空”。</p>
                            <p>這兩種釋讀相輔相成，它們似乎強調了基督神學中所謂的“否定神學”的世界觀，即藉由否定法來闡明上帝即真理。<note>
                                    <ref type="biblio" target="Gimello1976"/> 提出這個類比。<anchor xml:id="tsl2zh"/>
                                </note>
                            </p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>第二組：其他佛名</head>
                            <p>若說第一組銘刻是關於六個分刻於不同地點的同一佛名，第二組銘刻則是由分佈於十九處、十七個不同的佛名（洪頂山9.1–9.15，10，11，12，13號）組成。其中兩個佛名在不同地方各出現兩次（9.1
                                = 9.3；9.8 =
                                9.13號）。這一組刻文均位於北麓東段，刻文9.1–9.15排列緊密地刻在一塊適合刊刻的岩面上。它們統一的書法風格和空間排列揭示出它們應是同時規劃製作的作品。因此，將它們都歸於9號題刻組。這一組的最後一條題記是供養人名諱（刻文9.16）。 </p>
                            <p>與第一組的“空”與“無”相反，第二組通過佛名在宇宙中時間和空間上的涵括性表現出“如”與“有”的觀點。甚至在這裡，佛陀還同女性供養人、山脈以及僧侶書法家僧安道壹緊密地聯繫在一起。現在將第二組刻文詳述於下：</p>
                            <p>“式佛”是過去七佛中的第二位。這個名字首先單獨出現在這裡(洪頂山9.1號)，緊接其右所有過去七佛又按照順序刊刻了一次（刻文9.2–9.8），式佛是其中的刻文9.3號。這一佛名的兩次刊刻可能有諸多原因。</p>
                            <p>式佛的名字被摘選並精巧地鎸鑿在這裡，或許是因為他的名字僅由兩字組成，從大小上來說恰好適合於此處的岩面。此外，式佛代表了久遠的過去，因此和9號佛名組中的最後一個佛陀<hi rend="dash">──</hi>未來佛“安樂佛”（洪頂山9.15號）構成了呼應。由此，這兩個代表過去與未來的佛陀一首一尾地涵包住了整個9號佛名組。</p>
                            <p>除了作為過去七佛的一員，式佛也在《阿育王息壞目因緣經》<note>《阿育王息壞目因緣經》T#2045, 50: 172a-183a。</note>中單獨出現一次。在這部經中，阿育王的妃子月光夫人在一前世中向式佛發願，祈求達到眼根淨的菩提境地。藉由此願力，她治癒了她兒子被戳瞎的雙眼。
                                這條隱含了月光夫人的佛名暗示此條可能由一位女性供養人出資鐫刻。<note>更詳細的闡述,見蔡穗玲<ref target="TsaiSueyling2009" type="biblio"/> ;<ref target="TsaiSueyling2012" type="biblio"/>。有關此佛名在傳統堪輿學中可能蘊含的意義，見蔡穗玲<ref target="TsaiSueyling2011" type="biblio">132</ref>。
                                </note>
                            </p>
                            <p>洪頂山9.2–9.9號為過去七佛加未來佛彌勒佛。這裡作為第七佛的釋迦牟尼佛代表現在賢劫（洪頂山9.8號）。因此，這一組表現的是一個時間上的延續<hi rend="dash">──</hi>過去、現在和未來。同時，這七佛也體現出宇宙中橫向空間的全括性。在各種版本的經文中，七佛的名字有不同的傳譯。
                                洪頂山的這一組與陀羅尼經所載相符。<note>例如《七佛八菩薩所說大陀羅尼神呪經》T#1332, 21: 536b14-538b9；
                                    《陀羅尼雜集》T#1336, 21: 627a20-22; 627c28-628a1；
                                    《大方等陀羅尼經》T#1339, 21: 650c3-4; 652c17-653b10；《佛說摩尼羅亶經》T#1393, 21: 910b15-18。這裡的“拘樓秦佛”和“釋迦牟尼佛”與刻文稍有區別，即用“拘留秦佛”替換了“拘樓秦佛”，
                                    用“釋迦文佛”替換了“釋迦牟尼佛”。見殷光明<ref target="YinGuangming1999" type="biblio">164-169</ref>。 </note>早在洪頂山摩崖刊刻的一百多年之前，一組包括彌勒佛在內的相同佛名已鎸刻於北涼時期（397-439）的石塔上。 石塔上的每一佛以《易經》中的一卦為標誌，代表了四維八方中的一個方位：第一佛表示東方，第二佛代表東南，第三佛代表南方，依此類推。<note>殷光明
                                    <ref target="YinGuangming1999" type="biblio">171–181</ref>，更多參考文獻見註<ptr type="footnote" target="LL291zh"/>。
                                </note>
                            </p>
                            <p>洪頂山9.10–9.12號的內容涉及西方淨土：阿彌陀佛、觀世音佛和大勢至佛。後兩位通常以掌管西方極樂淨土的阿彌陀佛的脅侍菩薩身份出現。在洪頂山，這兩位菩薩被稱為佛，並不只是給他們的一個尊稱而已，更重要的是顯示出他們的另一個身份，即阿彌陀佛的未來繼承佛。根據曇無讖（385-433或436）所翻譯的《悲華經》，觀世音菩薩在阿彌陀佛涅槃之後將成為他的繼承佛，大勢至菩薩則在觀世音佛涅槃之後接替掌管西方淨土。<note>《悲華經》T#157, 3: 185c4-186c26。</note>
                                此處，在西方淨土對未來的展望之中再次表現出時間上的延續性。</p>
                            <p>有趣的是，組成洪頂山9.13–9.14號的兩個佛陀，他們在歷史世界中曾是一對夫妻：即釋迦牟尼佛和具足千萬光相佛。在《妙法蓮華經》中，釋迦牟尼在歷史世界的妻子耶輸陀羅未來將會成佛，具足千萬光相佛即是她成佛後的佛名。<note>《妙法蓮華經》T#262, 9: 36a24-b2。耶輸陀羅是羅睺羅的母親，據說在釋迦牟尼成等正覺後五年出家。</note>別具意義的是，釋迦牟尼佛的名字在前面已經出現過一次（洪頂山9.8號），這裡再次被刊刻到他“夫人”的旁邊。這給6世紀佛教中性別和家庭的地位提出了新的議題，值得進一步研究。</p>
                            <p>洪頂山9.15號佛名是關於一位未來佛，即安樂佛。雖然安樂是阿彌陀佛淨土的同義詞，安樂佛不是阿彌陀佛，而是一位未來佛。《現在賢劫千佛經》中兩次提到他作為現在賢劫中的未來佛。在現在賢劫的千佛中，釋迦牟尼佛為第四位，第一位安樂佛位列第九十八位，<note>《現在賢劫千佛經》T#447a, 14: 376b26-27。</note>
                                第二位安樂佛則排至九百九十四位。<note>《現在賢劫千佛經》T#447a, 14: 383a17-18。</note>
                                這裡刻他的名字，再次強調了佛教宇宙中時間上直至未來的延續性。</p>
                            <p>同時，選擇“安樂佛”這個名字應該也是為了表讚在洪頂山15號中被尊稱為安公的僧安道壹。</p>
                            <p>洪頂山10號“高山佛”和12號“大山巖佛”刻於北麓東段高聳的岩石上。“高山佛”在《佛說佛名經》中出現了四次。<note>紙本《大正藏》出現三次：《佛說佛名經》T#441, 14: 221a17; 229c16; 283c14-15。修正電子版《大正藏》多此一次：T#441, 14: 279c21。</note>在佛經中未能找到“大山巖佛”。很可能這個名字是專為洪頂山而創造的。前者代表的是遠方一座非特定的山嶽，而後者則常住於當地的山中。對山峰的崇拜也體現在歷史題記（洪頂山3號），該題記用“積石之千峰”、“崆峒之萬嵿”來讚揚僧安道壹宗教修養的造詣。</p>
                            <p>洪頂山11號“安王佛”的鎸刻處是所有佛名中最高的一處。此佛名出現在三部經典中。一是《十方千五百佛名經》，<note>《大正藏》T#442, 14: 316a28-29。</note>
                                若以一代全，這個名字代表了十方：四維、八方、天上和地下。在《佛說華手經》中，安王佛是一位過去佛。<note>《佛說華手經》T#657, 16: 140a28-142b22; 169b26-171b22。</note>而在《未來星宿劫千佛名經》<note>《大正藏》T#448b, 14: 394b28。</note>中，安王佛則是一位未來佛。從當地山谷中高高在上的位置為起點，他可說連接了十方，以及過去、現在和將來的佛陀世界。</p>
                            <p>除了此佛名所蘊含的全括性宇宙意義之外，它還涉及洪頂山的地方性意義。安王佛這一名字暗喻了僧人書法家僧安道壹。它令人聯想起到該刻經點中“安公”的書法，並借此歌頌和紀念他的人格。</p>
                            <p>洪頂山12號“大山巖佛”不見於任何佛教經典，很可能是專門為洪頂山而創造的。與源於佛經但沒有特指具體山脈的10號佛名不同，大山巖佛指的是當地的山脈。這兩條佛名再次體現了空間上的全括性：近和遠。</p>
                            <p>作為上述西方淨土的回應，洪頂山13號的佛名是東方淨琉璃世界的主佛藥師琉璃光佛，有別於西方極樂世界的阿彌陀佛，藥師琉璃光佛為眾生減輕一切苦難，賜予眾生世俗的利益，如美食、
                                財富，甚至解脫他們的刑罰。<note>《灌頂經》T#1331, 21: 532c18-533a13。最早關於藥師琉璃光佛信仰的記載見於《灌頂經》卷十二“佛說灌頂拔除過罪生死得度經”，《大正藏》T#1331, 21: 532-536。該經於公元5世紀中葉傳入中國。見司馬虛 <ref target="Strickmann1990" type="biblio">90–93</ref>。</note>位於北麓東段高處岩石西壁上的這則刻文，書法風格與該山其他佛名不同，字體較小，平穩收斂。也許是後來添加的。
                            </p>
                            <p>
                                <anchor xml:id="tsl3zh"/>綜上所述，第二組佛名肯定了宇宙中的“有”，時間上包含了來自過去、現在和未來的佛，空間上包括了來自東、西、十方以及當地和宇宙的佛。其他方面還包括了性別議題、大山崇拜和對僧安道壹的頌揚。</p>
                            <p>法洪（鴻）的名字作為佛名的供養人出現了三次：第一組中兩次（洪頂山21.2和23.2號）；作為第二組唯一的供養人一次（洪頂山刻文9.16號）。在上述“相關人士”的段落中已經對18號“法洪銘讚”部分地進行了引述。他的銘讚表現出，在教義上，他同時精通兩個看似對立但又相互關聯的存在觀點：“空”和“如有”。銘讚顯露出法洪對“空”教義的傾向性，但並未特別堅持任何一方。洪頂山上刊刻的經文中出自般若經典的經文數量也是這一點的旁證。然而，第二組佛名的刊刻顯示了“如有”教義在洪頂山的同等重要性，正如銘讚結尾的偈言說道：“確尒法界，
                                冥心大空。”</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>蔡穗玲</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>佛經 （洪頂山1，2，5，6，16.2，22號）</head>
                        <p>刊刻在洪頂山的六段佛經節文分別出自四部佛經，其中的三部都屬於般若波羅蜜系統。而這六段節文中的三段均引自《文殊師利所說摩訶般若波羅蜜經》<note>《大正藏》T#232, 8: 726c-732a。</note>。就主題而言，這些佛經節文著重於“觀佛”、“空”的概念和六波羅蜜，尤為強調神秘的般若波羅蜜。 </p>
                        <div>
                            <head>洪頂山1號</head>
                            <p>這段刻經出自曼陀羅仙翻譯的般若波羅蜜經，譯本題為《文殊師利所說摩訶般若波羅蜜經》<note>同上。</note>。曼陀羅仙於公元503年來到中國，主要活動在南梁（502-557）治內。據說他來自扶南，其部分地區隸屬於如今的柬埔寨。僧伽婆羅也翻譯過這部佛經，他的譯本題為《文殊師利所說般若波羅蜜經》。<note>《大正藏》T#233, 8: 732a-739c。</note>
                                據說他也來自扶南，並曾和曼陀羅仙共事。洪頂山這段54字節文，論及佛性和觀佛要義，只出現在曼陀羅仙的譯本，<note>《大正藏》T#232, 8: 728a26-29。</note>卻不見於僧伽婆羅譯本。此段節文也出現在公元8世紀初期《大寳積經》譯本<note>《大正藏》T#310, 11: 652b15-18；
                                    見《開元釋教錄》，《大正藏》T#2154, 55: 586b4-8。</note>所輯錄的曼陀羅仙文本。該選段出自舍利弗與文殊師利有關佛性的對話，在洪頂山刻經節文之前的一段文字是：
                           <quote>舍利弗語文殊師利言：“云何名佛？云何觀佛？”文殊師利言：“云何為我？”舍利弗言：“我者但有名字，名字相空。”文殊師利言：“如是，如是！如我但有名字，佛亦但有名字。名字相空，即是菩提，不以名字爾求菩提。
                                菩提之相，無言無說。何以故？言說菩提，二俱空故。”<note>《大正藏》T#232, 8: 728a19-25。</note>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>柏剛</abbr>
                            </ab>
                            <p/>
                            <p xml:id="cw02">
                                <anchor xml:id="cw1zh"/>《文殊師利所說摩訶般若波羅蜜經》屬於大乘佛教般若波羅蜜經典，這部佛經倡導通過了悟“空”而達到“成等覺”的般若思想。般若是菩薩拯救眾生的一種修行。《文殊師利所說摩訶般若波羅蜜經》是一部相對較晚的般若經典，並受到如來藏的影響，認為眾生與佛性無二。這部佛經強調實踐，推崇一種名為“一行三昧”的修持，特別主張重複地一心繫念佛名。
                                洪頂山崖壁上所刻諸多佛名，也許和這一修行有關。<anchor xml:id="cw3zh"/>此外《文殊師利所說摩訶般若波羅蜜經》也是早期禪宗大師們極為推崇的經典之一。<note>現存最早的中國禪宗經典，禪宗四祖道信（580-651）所著《入道安心要方便法門》即參照了這部佛經。見<ref type="biblio" target="Chappell1983">97-100</ref>。此外，《文殊師利所說摩訶般若波羅蜜經》也是伯4646號敦煌寫經中的一部分，張總認為該寫經所包含的十五個文本與禪宗打坐有關。見張總<ref target="ZhangZong2000a" type="biblio"> 64-65</ref>。</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>洪頂山刻經大多出自此經（洪頂山1，16.2和22號），連同大量的佛名及銘讚（洪頂山3，15和18號）有關禪修的隱喻，都清楚地反映了此時期佛教修行中繫念佛名與禪修之間並無矛盾。<note>有關早期淨土宗和禪宗的禪修及念佛修行，見釋恆清
                                        <ref type="biblio" target="HengchingShih1992">
                                    26-61</ref>。</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>至於《文殊師利所說摩訶般若波羅蜜經》五十四字節文的文本，洪頂山所刻與其他流傳至今的版本基本一致。<note>只有一則例外：敦煌寫本（北
                                3492號）在“云何觀佛”後多加了一個“佛”字，因而讀作“云何觀佛？佛者，不生不滅……” 見《敦煌寳藏》<ref type="biblio" target="Dunhuangbaozang1981_1986">78: 270b</ref>。
                                </note>
                                完全相同的選段還出現在水牛山摩崖石刻、房山雲居寺石經<note>存於石經山第四窟的石經板刻於隋唐時期，拓片見《房山石經》<ref type="biblio" target="FS_SJ2000">1: 121</ref>；以及同窟內刻於1081年的第378號石經板，拓片見《房山石經》<ref target="FS_SJ2000" type="biblio">7: 371</ref>。</note>以及現代版《大正藏》所收錄的佛教經典。<anchor xml:id="cw1azh"/>
                            </p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>溫狄婭</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>洪頂山2號</head>
                            <p>這段刻經出自曇無讖（385-433或436）所譯的《大方等大集經》，<note>有關該經譯者曇無讖的研究，見鎌田茂雄<ref target="Kamata1978" type="biblio">80-82</ref>。</note>節文選自《海慧菩薩品》。<note>刻文為第五品第八卷中的一段；第五品包括第八至第十一卷。見《大正藏》T#397, 13: 50b15-18。</note>據傳，曇無讖出生於中印度，公元412年來到北涼都城姑臧，並在那裡停留至公元422年。<note>陳金華
                                <ref type="biblio" target="ChenJinhua2004a"/>多次提及，特別在257-258頁，他贊同湯用彤的看法，認為曇無讖於420年到達中國。但這與《高僧傳》T#2059, 50: 335c16-337b4所記相矛盾。</note>
                                在于闐行後，曇無讖據說返回了姑臧。此後再次西行，於公元433年在途中遇難。通常認為該譯本在公元420年完成，不過陳金華對此提出質疑， 認為譯本的完成時間應該在公元422年至431年之間。<note>陳金華
                                    <ref type="biblio" target="ChenJinhua2004a">257-258</ref>。</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>洪頂山2號論及六波羅蜜，即布施、持戒、忍辱、精進、禪定、般若，作為佛教修行的根本之一。不過，此刻經在20世紀90年代末遭到嚴重破壞，確切的原文已不復可知。 現存僅有其被破壞之前拓制的一張不甚清晰的拓片，<note>《洪頂山摩崖刻經考察》<ref type="biblio" target="SDSKYS_HAW2006">84，圖8</ref>。</note>以及桐谷征一於1995年8月20日完成的一手抄本，不過，有關六波羅蜜的相同節文也出現在鄒城鐵山的刻經之中。
                                    鐵山刻經同樣出自《大集經》，但選取的篇幅多於洪頂山2號。鐵山所刻六波羅蜜節文與房山雲居寺石經中的經文版本、<note>唐代2號洞窟的第683號石經板正面刻文僅保留有首行及第二行的一半，見
                                        <ref target="FS_SJ2000" type="biblio">3: 265a</ref>。
                                        同窟內完成於1063年的第332號石經板，幾乎完整保存了同一文本，見 <ref target="FS_SJ2000" type="biblio">9: 203</ref>。</note>宋（1104-1148和1239）、元（1290）及明（1601）刻本相同。<note>《大正藏》T#397, 13: 50b15-18；T#397, 13: 50, 註7。</note>
                            </p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>柏剛，溫狄婭</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>洪頂山5號</head>
                            <p>題為《摩訶衍經》的洪頂山5號似乎未完成，僅完整刻出幾個字，除此之外，只有一些雙鈎的筆畫。刻文呈碑狀，立於一正面昂首的贔屭背上。碑身以雙鈎畫線格，半圓形碑額仍依稀可見。碑額為蟠龍圍繞，中間劃一正方形刻四字經題。洪頂山碑形刻經很可能影響了稍晚的鄒城鐵山的巨型碑形刻經（鐵山1號）。<note>見《中國佛教石經·山東省》第二卷。</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>
                                刻經碑首題銘為“摩訶衍經”。如張總所論，《摩訶衍經》很可能指的是《大智度論》。傳統上認為《大智度論》的作者是龍樹菩薩（約150-250年），推測譯者為鳩摩羅什（344-413）。<note>這位來自龜茲的譯經師鳩摩羅什於公元401年來到中國，由此成為東亞佛教史上無可爭議、最具影響力的譯經大師。他的譯著包括《妙法蓮華經》和《金剛經》等等。周伯戡<ref target="ChouPokan2004" type="biblio">281-327</ref>
                                    認為，鳩摩羅什的弟子僧睿是這篇“論”的真正作者，雖然他並不否認其梵文原著的存在。</note>在敦煌寫經中， 此經首題《大智度論》，尾題《摩訶衍經》。<note>張總
                                    <ref target="ZhangZong2000a" type="biblio"> 66-68</ref>。</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>《大智度論》第四十六卷十八品所引用和加註的一段節文<note>《大正藏》T#1509, 25: 393c1-5。</note>與鳩摩羅什（344-413）所譯《摩訶般若波羅蜜經·問乘品》<note>《大正藏》T#223, 8: 250b3-7。</note>論及十八空的節文相同。</p>
                            <p>《大正藏》收錄的《摩訶般若波羅蜜經》與此處刻經略有不同，讀作：“是為菩薩摩訶薩摩訶衍。復次，須菩提！菩薩摩訶薩復有摩訶衍……”<note>《大正藏》T#223, 8: 250b2-3。</note>
                                洪頂山選段從經文前一段的最後一句開始，似乎將此句作為整個節文的標題。</p>
                            <p>在內容上與此刻經相似的一段節文，刻於徂徠山光化寺附近一巨石上。此處沒有列舉出十八空，而是只有十七種“空”。（見《中國佛教石經·山東省》第三卷。）
                            </p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>柏剛，溫狄婭</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>洪頂山6號</head>
                            <p>這段刻經出自《佛說仁王般若波羅蜜經》。<note>《大正藏》T#245, 8: 825a-834b。</note>
                                通常認為此經由鳩摩羅什所譯，不過很可能於公元470年前後在中國重編。起初，這部佛經被視為偽經，直到公元597年費長房在《歷代三寳紀》<note>《大正藏》T#2034, 49: 22c-127c。</note>中才將其正統化。它頌揚作為護國及祈福途徑之一的般若波羅蜜，因而被唐代宗（762-779在位）所用。 他開設“仁王”法會，並在公元765年詔令高僧不空（705-774）再次翻譯此經。<note>
                                    <ref type="biblio" target="Orzech1998">74-78</ref>。
                                    </note>以第二次譯經為基礎的護國儀軌後來盛行於日本和朝鮮。除其政治關聯以外，洪頂山刻經所選節文祈求般若波羅蜜的神力，表現出強烈的道教色彩。<note>根據
                                        <ref type="biblio" target="Orzech1998">85</ref>，洪頂山刻經只見於公元5世紀譯本，而不在不空的“譯本”中。其實不空並沒有真正進行翻譯的工作，他只是對該經文做了二次編輯。</note>般若波羅蜜被比作一系列強大的避邪之物，這一點很值得關注，不僅因為多篇經文使用了類似的比喻，而且其中許多避邪之物為中國所特有。<note>關於中國稍晚的符咒，見柏剛<ref target="Copp2008" type="biblio"/>。</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>該刻經節文的現代校訂版見於《大正藏》，<note>《大正藏》T#245, 8: 832c23-26。</note>此段經文並没有提及在洪頂山6號出現的波斯匿王，而僅僅由“大王”開始，因為他的名字在之前<note>《大正藏》T#245, 8: 832b20。</note>已有介紹。其餘的刻經文字皆等同《大正藏》以及公元5世紀流傳下來的幾個寫本。<note>
                                    <ref type="biblio" target="Orzech1998">79</ref>，註39，提及敦煌寫經片斷：斯124號; 斯3472; 斯4582; 斯7242號; 北3481-3號。</note>
                            </p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>柏剛，溫狄婭</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>洪頂山16.2和洪頂山22號</head>
                            <p>洪頂山16.2和22號兩段刻經，為同一段九十八字節文，出自《文殊師利所說摩訶般若波羅蜜經》，<note>《大正藏》T#232, 8: 726a-732c。</note>論及般若的本質。該節文出自曼陀羅仙譯本。如前所述（洪頂山1號），曼陀羅仙曾與僧伽婆羅共事，而後者也曾翻譯過《文殊師利所說摩訶般若波羅蜜經》。<note>《大正藏》T#233, 8: 732c-739c。</note>在目前輯錄的《大正藏》中，與此處刻經相同的段落出現在僧伽婆羅的譯本，<note>《大正藏》T#233, 8: 738a19-24。</note>而與曼陀羅仙的譯本有所出入。然而，對經文版本的流傳進行細緻考察後可以發現，這個段落其實是對僧伽婆羅譯本的一個後代的改編，而這一點在《大正藏》中並沒有標明。<note>這個增補首先由羅炤於2004年在海德堡大學訪問期間發現。</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>這兩個譯本均見於北京附近的房山石經。此處該節文的僧伽婆羅翻譯版本與洪頂山所刻極為不同，而曼陀羅仙的譯本與之卻只有一字之差。</p>
                            <p>房山石經中關於這段九十八字節文最早的版本見於石經山4號藏經洞內的經板。這些刊刻於隋唐年間的石經板保存了曼陀羅仙的譯本。<note>《房山石經》
                                    <ref target="FS_SJ2000" type="biblio">1: 125</ref>。</note> 4號藏經洞內的石經板也存有遼金時代刊刻的為“扶南三藏法師曼陀羅仙”和“扶南三藏法師僧伽婆羅”所譯的該段經文。<note>《房山石經》
                                    <ref target="FS_SJ2000" type="biblio">30: 233</ref>。</note> 在374號石經板，倒數的第十三行，僧伽婆羅的原譯本開始出現問題。<note>《房山石經》
                                    <ref target="FS_SJ2000" type="biblio">7: 375</ref>。</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>這裡僧伽婆羅的翻譯與曼陀羅仙對相應段落的翻譯出現了很大差別。因此，我們可以推斷，曼陀羅仙譯本中的相關段落在某個時候替換了僧伽婆羅的原譯本。而僧伽婆羅的原譯本還保存在敦煌寫經（斯576號，北3497號）中。</p>
                            <p>此外，斯2653號敦煌寫經也與山東摩崖刻經版本相同。後來，這段節文被修改，很可能是為了將意思表達得更明確。<note>石經山2號窟第378號石刻經板刊刻於公元1081年，顯示了如下的變更，在“非行非不行處悉入一乘”中增補一個“處”字，由此讀作“非行處非不行處悉入一乘”，或許文辭更為通順，見《房山石經》<ref target="FS_SJ2000" type="biblio">7: 372</ref>。後來，這個變更消失了，包括現代《大正藏》在內的刊印佛教經典中，“處”字保留，而刪去原文的“行”字。這些版本還另外增補二字，變“何故”為“何以故”，變“如”為“猶如”。
                                    </note>與修改後較長的版本不同的是，寫本所保存的版本更傾向刪減文字來減短篇幅。<note>斯1908號和北3492號敦煌寫經將“無邊無際”縮減為“無邊際”，將“無名無相”縮減為“無名相”。</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>儘管洪頂山北麓第16.2號經文的內容與南麓第22號相同，但是兩段節文在“無”字的寫法上卻存有差異。16.2號通篇使用簡化的
                                “无”，而22號除了一處外皆使用了正體“無”字。與此相似的是，此段節文同樣在鄒城附近的嶧山刊刻了兩次：其中，妖精洞刻經使用了“无”字，而五華峰刻經則使用了“無”字（見《中國佛教石經·山東省》第二卷）。</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>柏剛，溫狄婭</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>題記</head>
                        <p>這裡所刻的十條歷史題記可以分為兩組，一組歸屬於既是供養人又是書法家的僧人僧安道壹，一組歸屬於僧人供養人法洪。兩組都各有一個銘讚（洪頂山3號及其標題洪頂山4號是為僧安道壹所作，洪頂山
                            18號則是為了法洪所寫）。
                            除此之外，還有一段獻給僧安道壹的不尋常的碑文（洪頂山15號），僧安道壹所作的一條題記（洪頂山7號），一條可能是其所作文字的後記（洪頂山14號），以及兩個僧人所留下的署名（僧安道壹：洪頂山16.
                            1號；法洪：洪頂山 21.2號、23. 2號， 還有9.16號的法鴻也極有可能為同一供養人）。 </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>雷德侯</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <div>
                            <head>洪頂山3號</head>
                            <p>洪頂山上最引人入勝、最突出的特徵之一是兩篇銘讚。除了這裡之外，摩崖石刻中還未出現過其他銘讚。</p>
                            <p>僧安道壹銘讚（洪頂山3號）稱頌其佛學成就，而他的名字則被放大寫在左側（洪頂山4號）。根據文辭傳統，銘讚首句應為傳記的開始，其遣詞用句也應和僧人墓誌銘類似。可是該銘讚卻與墓誌銘不同，它没有關於僧安道壹生平的信息，卻首先考慮到了佛教救贖世人的目的 (<foreign xml:lang="en">soteriological needs</foreign>)，把他描述成“廣大鄉空寬里人”。此銘讚與南麓法洪銘讚（洪頂山18號）相類似。 </p>
                            <p>這兩篇銘讚都遵循相同的格式，而與其他僧侶傳記以及僧侶墓誌銘大有不同。這兩篇銘讚都可視為與傳統傳記體裁相似的僧侶銘讚中的特例。</p>
                            <p>僧安道壹銘讚是三個使用了佛滅紀年的題銘之一。不過，這裡所載釋迦涅槃後的確切紀年已無法辨識。</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>柏剛</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>洪頂山4號</head>
                            <p>在洪頂山4號，“僧安道壹”這四個字以超大號字體刻在一個圭形碑邊框內，似乎為隔壁銘讚(洪頂山3號)的標題。這兩處題刻之間的關係可以比照方形墓誌銘的兩部分：石蓋上的大字內容標明了墓主的名字， 而其生平則用小字刻在了下方的石板上。這類墓誌興起於西漢時期，不過直到北朝才普遍流行。<note>趙超
                                    <ref type="biblio" target="ZhaoChao1997">40</ref>。</note>
                            </p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>雷德侯</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>洪頂山7號</head>
                            <p>這個題銘宣告僧安道壹為其左側四字佛名“大空王佛”（洪頂山8號）的書寫者。其明確寫道：“大沙門僧安道壹書刊大空王佛七……書經……”這裡述及僧安親自書寫的幾處題刻。“七”字可能與“大空王佛”的七處刊刻有關。包括洪頂山8號在內，洪頂山上共刊刻了六處大小不一的“大空王佛”。其中至少兩處（洪頂山21.1號和23.1號）的供養人不是僧安道壹，而是法洪（鴻）。不過，在附近平陰縣的二鼓山、雲翠山、天池山和書院東山發現了更多的“大空王佛”題銘。
                                這些佛名可能都是僧安道壹的作品。<note>張總<ref type="biblio" target="ZhangZong2003a">14</ref>；賴非<ref type="biblio" target="LaiFei2003c">96</ref>。 </note>
                            然而，没有任何史料記載提及僧安道壹。已知由他署名的作品只有洪頂山、鐵山和尖山的題銘。</p>
                            <p>洪頂山7號這個題銘是洪頂山三個涉及佛曆紀年的題刻之一。刻文開篇寫道：“釋迦雙林後一千六百廿三年”。根據張總的研究，<note>張總
                                    <ref target="ZhangZong2000b" type="biblio">12-13</ref>。</note>以慧思（515-577）末法說的方法來計算的話，這一紀年對應的是公元556年。</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>張總，溫狄婭</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>洪頂山9.16號</head>
                            <p>洪頂山北麓這一大組佛名的供養人（洪頂山9.1-9.15號）署名為“法鴻”。此人極有可能與釋法洪是同一人。<note>賴非
                                    <ref target="LaiFei2000a" type="biblio">268</ref>；楊浩、郝莉<ref type="biblio" target="Yang_Hao2006b"> 176</ref>。 </note>
                                法洪是南麓兩處佛名的供養人（洪頂山21.2和23.2號），此外，洪頂山上還有一篇表彰他的銘讚（洪頂山18號）。</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>溫狄婭</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>洪頂山14號</head>
                            <p>“風門口碑”四字被認為與相鄰的洪頂山15號和16號題刻存在緊密的關聯。它們可能是這些與僧安道壹相關題刻的某種後記，也許由其追隨者所作。<note>安廷山
                                    <ref target="AnTingshan2003a" type="biblio">59</ref>。</note>
                            </p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>溫狄婭</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>洪頂山15號</head>
                            <p>該刻文名為“安公之碑”，碑文頗具文字遊戲之味。它使用“僧安道壹”四字各自的含義，先是在其間建立起微妙聯繫，而後集中於可稱為禪修之本的“安”與“壹”二字做文章。這篇別具一格的題銘，紀年為“雙林後千六百廿秊”，因此比洪頂山7號早三年。根據慧思“末法”說推算，這個紀年對應的是公元553年。</p>
                            <p>僧安道壹親自為自己的讚碑撰稿並揮毫，這似乎不太可能。因此，一些學者認為該碑是其追隨者所作。<note>劉濤
                                <ref target="LiuTao2003a" type="biblio"> 238-239</ref> 和陳昆麟<ref type="biblio" target="ChenKunlin2003"> 326-329</ref>。</note>然而，另有看法認為，僧安道壹也許在其門徒的請求之下，親自寫出了這段複雜而玄妙的文字。<note>北島信一
                                    <ref target="Kitajima2003" type="biblio">279</ref>。 </note>
                            </p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>溫狄婭</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>洪頂山16.1號</head>
                            <p>此“僧安道壹”題名位於《文殊師利所說摩訶般若波羅蜜經》九十八字節文（洪頂山16.2號）之側。它表明僧安道壹不是此段刻經的書丹人，就是該段刻經的經主，抑或兩者皆是。</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>溫狄婭</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>洪頂山18號</head>
                            <p>與洪頂山3號（僧安銘讚）類似，這段法洪銘讚也未見諸載籍。再者，與洪頂山3號相同，僧侶銘讚的唯一可比體裁就是傳統的傳記。而這篇銘讚首句似乎是一篇傳記的開篇，緊接於此的卻是對法洪的才能和佛學造詣的長篇頌揚，而非普通意義上的僧傳。與使用了佛曆紀年的僧安道壹銘讚不同的是，法洪銘讚使用了普通的紀年：北齊河清三年（564）。</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>柏剛</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>洪頂山21.2號</head>
                            <p>法洪可能不僅僅是此題銘正上方的 “大空王佛”
                                （洪頂山21.１號）的供養人，他還是該題銘之右，洪頂山22號刻經的供養人，因而他在此被稱為“經主 ”。</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>溫狄婭</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>洪頂山 23.2號</head>
                            <p>作為洪頂山18號銘讚頌揚的對象及21.2號經主的法洪，還作為“大空王佛”佛名（洪頂山23.1號）的供養人在此出現。</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>溫狄婭</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>布局</head>
                        <p>洪頂山的銘刻可以分為五類布局。</p>
                        <list type="ordered">
                            <item>沒有邊框的長方形布局。除了洪頂山8號以外，所有寫在一個豎行內的佛名皆屬於這一類（洪頂山 9.1-9.15， 10-13， 17，
                                19， 20， 21.1， 23.1號），簡短的單行“風門碑”（洪頂山
                                14號），以及不止一行的刻文，即佛經節文洪頂山1，2，6，和16.2號、
                                銘讚洪頂山3號和題記洪頂山7號。不僅在佛經節文中，事實上，在洪頂山所有多行刻文中，文字橫向排列十分規整（例外：洪頂山3號的最後一行的紀年）。在洪頂山6號中，一個隱藏的布局是這樣安排的：六次出現的“亦名”：兩個字幾乎處在彼此相鄰的同一橫排內。在損壞比較嚴重的洪頂山2號，“名”字幾乎佔滿了整個第五排。</item>
                            <item>雙重邊框。只有一個佛名放入雙重邊框內。即巨大的洪頂山8號。</item>
                            <item>界格。在洪頂山18號法洪銘讚中，多行題銘的界格以細線刻成，清晰可見（洪頂山3號僧安道壹銘讚沒有這樣的格子線）。在洪頂山22號佛經選段中，只有豎行之間用雙重格子線隔開，橫排之間並沒有。</item>
                            <item>碑形。有三處題銘的布局類似碑刻。雖然在洪頂山4號，僧安道壹的名字僅僅由碑形的輪廓線所包圍，但是人們卻在洪頂山5號佛經節文所在的岩石刻出了一個完整的碑形。
                                洪頂山15號上方一個單獨的區域內寫有四字碑題，明確把該文稱作“碑”。洪頂山14號的單行題銘同樣自稱為碑，不過此處並不見任何碑形痕跡。</item>
                            <item>兩個題銘的組合。洪頂山刻文出現了若干兩個題銘被組合放在入一個布局的例證。僧安道壹的名字洪頂山4號與其銘讚洪頂山3號，可比擬墓誌銘的蓋和底之間的關係。洪頂山7號是其左方佛名洪頂山8號的題記。
                                署名洪頂山9.16號涉及其右方的15個佛名洪頂山9.1 –
                                9.15號。洪頂山21.2號是其右方佛名的署名；洪頂山16.1號則是其右方佛經的署名；洪頂山23.2號是其上方佛名洪頂山23.1號的署名；洪頂山13號中的署名同樣也被計劃放在佛名的下方。</item>
                        </list>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>雷德侯</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>刊刻技法</head>
                        <p>從筆道横斷面對刻經技法進行分析，洪頂山刻經技法可分為五類：</p>
                        <list type="ordered">
                            <item>“U”形刻法。即順筆畫中心單鏨刻成。方便快捷，適用於0.2至0.4釐米寬的筆畫。洪頂山《摩訶衍經》（洪頂山5號）碑框線採用此法。</item>
                            <item>“V”形刻法。即從筆畫兩邊線斜入鏨，雙邊線相交，自然成形。方便快捷，適用於0.7至4釐米寬的筆畫鎸刻。洪頂山90%的刻經採用此法。</item>
                            <item>“雙鈎”刻法。即將筆畫雙邊線單鏨刻出，留出筆畫內痕。適用於寬度為4釐米以上的筆畫。洪頂山南麓“大空王佛”佛名（洪頂山19，20，21.1和23.1號）皆採用此法。</item>
                            <item>“凵”形刻法。即從筆畫兩邊線垂直入鏨。該技法適用於寛度為10釐米以上的筆畫鎸刻。洪頂山“大空王佛”（洪頂山8號）和“大山巖佛”（洪頂山12號）採用此法
                                （<ptr target="HDS_r_12_total_IMG_0469.JPG"/>）。</item>
                            <item>“飛白刻”。類似於書法中的“飛白書”，即將筆畫雙鈎後，在筆畫中刻條線以裝飾，創造出醒目的書法效果。適用於寬度為20釐米以上的筆畫。洪頂山北麓的“大空王佛”（洪頂山8號）採用此法。</item>
                        </list>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>賴非</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>書法藝術</head>
                        <p>從類型學上說，考慮到每個字筆畫的數量和位置的話，這些題銘的書體屬於隸書的晚期階段。有別於南方書體的演變，在中國北方，隸書轉化為楷書的過程是自成一格並且是漸進的。北朝的這種混合體有時被稱作楷隸，有時被稱作隸楷。
                            它仍然保持著隸書的類型學特色：例如“糸”字被極端地寫成兩個互相重疊的三角形（洪頂山9.2，
                            9.15號），人們仍然能在“以”字的右半邊看到一個正方形（洪頂山16.2號，10/2；洪頂山22號，7/8）；“洲”字中的點則被彎鈎取而代之（洪頂山16.2號，4/10）；“處”字的結構也與楷書極為不同
                            （洪頂山16.2號，8/6）。</p>
                        <p>在風格上，從明顯舒緩的捺筆，以及從寬胖的整體比例中，仍然可以感覺到隸書的傳統（洪頂山16.
                            2號）。</p>
                        <p>不過，這兩個風格特徵在佛名和佛經中最為明顯，然而在兩個銘讚（洪頂山3和18號），
                            僧安道壹碑（洪頂山15號）以及其題詞（洪頂山7號）中則沒有那麼明顯。書法家對變體和簡化字的自由運用則又增加了類型和風格的模糊性。</p>
                        <p>安公之碑的四字標題（洪頂山15號）用篆體寫成。在北朝時期，這種字體通常被用於碑額和墓誌銘中。<note>有關碑額的篆書，見雷德侯<ref target="Ledderose1970" type="biblio">46-50</ref>。</note>可見，6世紀時，碑文從像公元523年“高貞碑”<note>該碑保存於山東省石刻藝術博物館。</note>刻文那種粗糙、富於裝飾性、有時出現奇特筆畫的風格，
                            發展到了像公元600年“孟顯達碑”<note>該碑保存於西安碑林博物館。拓片圖像見西川寧<ref type="biblio" target="Nishikawa1966">圖版 35</ref>。</note>刻文那樣更平整生硬的風格。洪頂山15號的篆額已經較接近於後者。</p>
                        <p>根據刻字的大小和深度，這些題銘可以分成三組，大體上與文本的內容相協調。佛名用大號字體寫成，有些高達1米以上。洪頂山
                            8號尤其巨大；它的第一個“大”字就有4米寬。這些大號字筆畫刻入很深，結構通常都比較特殊，
                            如只有在佛名裡才能看到重疊筆畫和飛白的三維效果（洪頂山8號，1/1-4；洪頂山9.1號，1/1；洪頂山9.2號，1/1），以及雙重輪廓刻線。僧安道壹的名字同樣用這樣的大號字寫成（洪頂山4號）<hi rend="dash">──</hi>這名僧人顯然自信十足。</p>
                        <p>佛經節文以中號字寫在高與寬約為20釐米的隱藏式正方格內。刻痕比佛名淺。最小的字號往往見於包括了署名在內的歷史題記，通常不高於10釐米。刻痕甚至比經文更淺，因此磨滅的地方也更多，更難辨認。
                            這對文本復原造成了特殊的困難，因為不像佛名和經文，歷史題記未能流傳其他可資比較的版本，如寫本或印本。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>雷德侯</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="en">
                <head>Mount Hongding</head>
                <div>
                    <head>Space</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Location</head>
                        <p>Mount Hongding <foreign xml:lang="zh">洪頂山</foreign>, the key geographical
                            feature in this part of the discussion, consists of a V-shaped range
                            around a level valley on the eastern edge of Lake Dongping <foreign xml:lang="zh">東平湖</foreign>. The lake lies at the west end of the
                            central highland of Shandong Province and abuts the alluvium soil of the
                            Yellow River <foreign xml:lang="zh">黃河</foreign>. Geologically, Mount
                            Hongding belongs to the limestone formations of the Shandong mountains
                            largely unaffected by alluvial deposits.</p>
                        <p>The site is located at 116.238° east, 36.064° north WGS84, equalling
                            431470 E (easting) and 3991300 N (northing) on the meridian 50S UTM. The
                            bed of the valley enclosed by Mount Hongding is at an altitude of slightly more than
                            100 m above sea level.</p>
                        <p>Mount Hongding now belongs to Dongping <foreign xml:lang="zh">東平</foreign> County. It is 24 km northwest of the county seat of
                            Dongping and 30 km southwest of the county seat of Pingyin <foreign xml:lang="zh">平陰</foreign> (map in front endpaper).</p>
                        <p>The inscription site of Mount Yin <foreign xml:lang="zh">銀山</foreign> lies 10.9 km to the west of Mount Hongding, separated
                            by Lake Dongping. Mount Yin is visible from Mount Hongding, but its
                            inscriptions are not within the line of sight. Mount Sili
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">司里山</foreign>, located on the
                            western bank of Lake Dongping, lies 11.9 km to the southwest. Mount Sili
                            is visible from Mount Hongding, but its east-facing inscriptions
                            are not. Mount Yuncui <foreign xml:lang="zh">雲翠山</foreign> lies 4.9 km to the east of Mount Hongding. Its inscriptions are situated 
                            below the summit, facing west; another high peak of Shandong’s
                            western highland prevents a  view of Mount Yuncui from
                            Mount Hongding (map, fig. <ptr target="Map_2_Dongping_2013_01_29.jpg"/>).</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>TS</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Topography and Spatial Grouping</head>
                        <p>At the northeastern end of Lake Dongping, the ridges of Mount Hongding
                            close to the lake’s eastern shore branch out toward the lake to
                            delineate a valley. Enclosed by formerly tree-covered mountains to the
                            east, but open to the vast surface of the lake on the west, the two opposite
                            inner slopes of the ridges were chosen for carvings of sacred Buddhist
                            texts. They face north and south, respectively. The two V-shaped ridges
                            of Mount Hongding are enclosed by a further semi-circle of mountains
                            known as Greater Mount Hongding (Da Hongding Shan <foreign xml:lang="zh">大洪頂山</foreign>). This particular formation is best seen on a map
                            (map, fig. <ptr target="Map_3_Hongdingshan002_2013_01_29a.jpg"/>). The
                            inscriptions are thus sheltered by the mountains,
                            a placement recalling that of tombs and caves.</p>
                        <p>Seventeen inscriptions are revealed on the northern slope and six on the
                            southern slope (map, fig. <ptr target="Map_4_Hongdingshan_Level3.jpg"/>). While the inscriptions on the southern slope cover a length of only
                            27.83 m and might be considered a single group, the inscriptions on the
                            northern slope (fig. <ptr target="HDS_sc_northern_slope_total_IMG_0363.JPG"/>) divide into
                            four distinct groups, stretching over a distance of 45.44 m. The first
                            three groups are set at about the same horizontal level along the
                            slope’s rock face. The western group (HDS 1 - HDS 4) and the central
                            group (HDS 5 and HDS 6) are separated by 9.82 m, and the central and
                            eastern groups (HDS 7 - HDS 12) by 11.63 m (fig. <ptr target="HD_northen_slope_Beschr.jpg"/>). The three groups are
                            connected by a narrow path, which follows closely the contour of the
                            steep rocky slope (fig. <ptr target="HDS_sc_northern_slope_HD0274.jpg"/>). Reaching the Buddha
                            names HDS 9.1 - HDS 9.16 of the eastern group, the visitor suddenly
                            finds himself in front of a huge, tower-like structure of natural rock.
                            Halfway up, more Buddha names are carved (HDS 10 - HDS 12). The path
                            leads around this tower and further up the slope, where the fourth and
                            last group of inscriptions (HDS 13 - HDS 16) is located in the secluded
                            Eastern Gallery (fig. <ptr target="HDS_gallery.tif"/>). Sheltered by
                            the tower, now at their back, visitors may choose to have a closer look
                            at the inscriptions, or even sit down right in front of the sutra
                            passage HDS 16 for meditation. A stone seat opposite the inscription
                            lends itself for this purpose (fig. <ptr target="meditationseat.jpg"/>,
                                <ptr target="HDS_meditation_seat_DSC3295.JPG"/>, and <ptr target="HDS_meditation_DSC3353.JPG"/>).<note>The proposition that
                                this and similar inscriptions were used for meditation is discussed
                                in the Introduction, above p. <ptr type="infra" target="LLmeditation"/>.</note> If they choose to turn their eyes to the left, they will
                            enjoy a breath-taking view across the entire Hongding valley, with Lake
                            Dongping stretching to the horizon in the west (fig. <ptr target="HDS_sc_gallery_3296_1.jpg"/>).<note>The exact location and
                                dimensions of Lake Dongping in the sixth century are unclear. <ref target="LaiFei2003c" type="biblio">103-104</ref> assumes that
                                today’s marshlands at the northern end of the lake were once dry,
                                making it possible to travel by land from the ancient monastery in
                                the valley of Mount Hongding to the monastery at Mount Sili located
                                11.9 km to the southwest.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>The southern slope’s rock face is sharply indented in the middle, so that
                            the inscriptions are grouped into two separate clusters at either end, with a
                            single four-character inscription (HDS 20) in between (fig. <ptr target="HD_southern_slope_Beschr.jpg"/>). </p>
                        <figure xml:id="HD_northen_slope_Beschr.jpg" rend="center" n="figure">
                            <head>Distribution of inscriptions on the northern slope of Mount
                                Hongding</head>
                            <head xml:lang="zh">洪頂山北麓摩崖石刻分佈</head>
                            <graphic url="HD_northen_slope_Beschr.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                        <figure xml:id="HD_southern_slope_Beschr.jpg" rend="center" n="figure">
                            <head>Distribution of inscriptions on the southern slope of Mount
                                Hongding</head>
                            <head xml:lang="zh">洪頂山南麓摩崖石刻分佈</head>
                            <graphic url="HD_southern_slope_Beschr.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                        <figure rend="center" xml:id="flight">
                            <graphic height="320" rend="flash" url="Hongdinshan_Film.swf" width="360"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>The inscriptions on the two slopes are part of a single enterprise. The
                            shortest distance between inscriptions across the valley, amounting to
                            151.13m, is that between the giant “Buddha King of Great Emptiness”
                            (HDS 8) on the northern slope and and the much more modest “Buddha King
                            of Great Emptiness” (HDS 19) on the southern slope. The longest distance
                            between two inscriptions across the valley of 172.9 m is that between
                            inscription HDS 16 on the north and HDS 22 on the south, which both
                            feature an identical passage from the same sutra. Thus the content
                            enhances the spatial coherence of the site. The V-shaped valley of Mount
                            Hongding further conforms to the main principle underlying the spatial
                            arrangement of sacred texts at the Shandong sites: texts are positioned
                            so that they face each other, even over long distances, creating a net
                            of corresponding holy scriptures covering the mountainous landscape.</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>LL, CW</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Place Name</head>
                        <p>Mount Hongding is divided into Greater Mount Hongding <foreign xml:lang="zh">大洪頂山</foreign> and Mount Er Hongding <foreign xml:lang="zh">二洪頂山</foreign>,
                            the main mountain peak at the east end
                            of the valley (map, fig. <ptr target="Map_3_Hongdingshan002_2013_01_29a.jpg"/>). After the
                            discovery of stone inscriptions, the name “stone inscriptions of Mount
                            Hongding” was assigned in 1995 to the inscriptions that are
                            actually on Mount Er Hongding. This choice here followed the practice used in
                            Qing times of naming locally renowned mountains, in line with that for
                            stone inscriptions on other mountains. For instance, the stone
                            inscriptions at the Great Buddha Ridge of Mount Jian <foreign xml:lang="zh">尖山大佛嶺</foreign> were simply called stone inscriptions
                            of Mount Jian <foreign xml:lang="zh">尖山</foreign>, and those at the
                            North Mount Ge <foreign xml:lang="zh">北葛山</foreign> were named stone
                            inscriptions of Mount Ge <foreign xml:lang="zh">葛山</foreign>.</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>LF</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="HDS_sc_gallery_3296_1.jpg">
                            <head>View of the valley and Lake Dongping from the secluded Eastern
                                Gallery; photograph taken in 2006</head>
                            <head xml:lang="zh">從隱蔽的東部臺地俯視山谷和東平湖，2006年照片</head>
                            <graphic url="HDS_sc_gallery_3296_1.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Time</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Related Monasteries</head>
                        <p>In the valley enclosed by the southern, northern, and eastern peaks of
                            Mount Hongding, architectural remains were found (map, fig. <ptr target="Map_4_Hongdingshan_Level3.jpg"/>). These have an approximate
                            length of 120 m from east to west, and an approximate width of 40 to 50
                            m from north to south; the whole area measures about 5,400 m². In the
                            winter of 1964, when a reservoir was constructed, this site was almost
                            completely destroyed. According to local villagers, pottery and bricks, as well as four pillar bases, were excavated from
                            the area of the reservoir.</p>
                        <p>Where a section is still exposed, a 30 to 50 cm high occupation layer and
                            some late tombs can be seen. Pottery sherds
                            from the Neolithic, the <hi rend="nh">Warring</hi> States period and the Han dynasty, as
                            well as bricks and tiles from the Northern dynasties, demonstrate not
                            only that people settled here for a long time, but also that,
                            in the Northern dynasties, large buildings had stood there.
                            These must have belonged to a monastery that had close ties
                            with the sutra carving project of Seng’an Daoyi <foreign xml:lang="zh">僧安道壹</foreign> (fl. 562-579, see below).</p>
                        <p>The monastery ceased to exist after the Tang dynasty. Its
                            name has not been transmitted. Nor have stelae or other historical records
                            come down to us. Fahong, who is called sutra donor in Mount Hongding’s 
                            stone inscriptions (see below), may have been the abbot of this monastery.</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>LF</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="HDS_gallery.tif">
                            <head>Entrance to the secluded Eastern Gallery, topmost inscription
                                group at Mount Hongding; photograph taken in 2004</head>
                            <head xml:lang="zh">洪頂山最高一組石刻，風門口的入口，2004年照片</head>
                            <graphic url="HDS_gallery.tif"/>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Related Persons</head>
                        <p>The impressive stone sutra carving project at Mount Hongding, with its
                            diverse contents of Buddha names, sutra passages, and historical texts,
                            including encomiums, is testimony to the exceptional capabilities of the
                            people who managed and participated in this project. Fortunately, the names of two
                            monks of great significance have been preserved in the rock cut
                            inscriptions. The first person is the Great Renunciant (<hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">śramaṇa</foreign>
                            </hi>) Seng’an Daoyi <foreign xml:lang="zh">僧安道壹</foreign>, whose name
                            appears in inscriptions HDS 3, 4, 7, 15, and 16.1; the second is the
                            Renunciant Venerable Fahong <foreign xml:lang="zh">釋法洪</foreign>, who is
                            mentioned and praised in inscriptions HDS 9.16, 18, 21.2 and 23.2.
                            Furthermore, a colophon damaged sometime between 1995 and 1999 mentions
                            “Sutra Donor Dao [. . .] ” in front of inscription HDS 2. These names suggest
                            that several persons were in charge at this inscription site, and,
                            indeed, that an association of monks was active.</p>
                        <p>Encomiums were carved on the rocks for the key figures of this
                            inscription site, the renunciants Seng’an Daoyi and Fahong. These are
                            among the special features of Mount Hongding. The encomiums on the
                            northern (HDS 3) and the southern slopes (HDS 18) face each other across
                            the width of the valley. The texts follow the same patterns: First some
                            general information about the eulogized person is given; then his
                            outstanding accomplishments are praised, and finally the content is
                            summed up in verses with lines of four characters each. </p>
                        <p/>
                        <p>Unfortunately, the encomium for Seng’an Daoyi (HDS 3) is partly damaged,
                            and some characters are totally illegible. However, his moral personality
                            is most impressively symbolized by the words “thousand peaks of Amassed
                            Stones” and the “myriad summits of Empty Undividedness”, and his career
                            may be inferred from the words “on stone after stone he chisels and
                            engraves, on mountain after mountain he [...] [...]”. </p>
                        <p>These
                            comments on Seng’an Daoyi’s achievements in cliff inscription and
                            chiseling demonstrate that he was the calligrapher, who wrote the
                            passages of Buddhist sutras and the various Buddha names to endure on
                            the rocks through the ages. Collateral evidence for this hypothesis can
                           easily be found. To the right of the encomium is his signature, written
                            in large characters within a pointed frame, HDS 4. It may well be the
                            ‘title’ of the encomium, HDS 3.</p>
                        <p>Elsewhere, in front of HDS 16.2, the passage from
                            the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Great Perfection of Wisdom Spoken by
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mañjuśrī</foreign>
                                </hi>
                            </title> (<hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sapta­śatikā­prajñā­pāramitā-sūtra</foreign>
                            </hi>, <hi rend="italic">Wen­shu­shili suo shuo mohe bore boluomi
                                jing </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">文殊師利所說摩訶般若波羅蜜經</foreign>), the name “Seng’an Daoyi” appears again (HDS 16.1).
                            It is commonly understood that he, himself, donated and wrote the sutra
                            passage.</p>
                        <p>Finally, the colophon of HDS 7 states that “the
                            Great Renunciant Seng’an Daoyi wrote and carved: Buddha King of Great
                            Emptiness, seven …, wrote sutras…”, referring to several inscriptions
                            that Seng’an personally inscribed on the rocks. The signatures of Seng’an Daoyi occur most frequently on Mount Hongding,
                            but they are also found in other places. Among the Four Mountains at
                            Zoucheng <foreign xml:lang="zh">鄒城四山</foreign> in Shandong,<note> Mount Gang (Gangshan <foreign xml:lang="zh">崗山</foreign>), Mount Ge (Geshan <foreign xml:lang="zh">葛山</foreign>), 
                                Mount Jian (Jianshan <foreign xml:lang="zh">尖山</foreign>),
                                and Mount Tie (Tieshan <foreign xml:lang="zh">鐵山</foreign>), see Shandong, vol. 2.</note> Mount Jian
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">尖山</foreign> and Mount Tie <foreign xml:lang="zh">鐵山</foreign> both carry inscriptions and colophons by
                            him. These mountains have long been held in high esteem and were
                            explored and documented by epigraphers and scholars of the late Qing
                            dynasty. For Seng’an Daoyi, the well-versed calligrapher monk, was
                            already known in the late eighteenth century. The inscriptions and
                            encomiums at Mount Hongding provide further evidence of the scope of his
                            inscriptions and of his other activities.</p>
                        <p>Although Seng’an Daoyi’s name appears quite often in the stone
                            inscriptions, no traces of his life survive in texts, such as the
                            biographies of monks or the local gazetteers. The discovery of the
                            colophons on Mount Hongding has generated many proposals. The
                            most important of these divide his life into several periods<note>
                                <ref target="Kiriya2003a" type="biblio">74-86</ref>.</note> or
                            identify two major groups in Seng’an’s work,<note>
                                <ref target="LaiFei2003c" type="biblio">119-131</ref>.
                            </note> with a switch from shorter sutra excerpts
                            (mainly from the <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">prajñā</foreign>
                            </hi> sutras) to the longer section of the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Vast and Universal Great Collection Sutra</hi>
                                    (<hi rend="italic">Dafangdeng daji jing</hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">大方等大集經</foreign>
                            </title>) at Mount Tie. </p>
                        <p>The personality of Seng’an Daoyi is eulogized in inscription HDS 15,
                            which names itself a stele with a title that reads “Stele of Sire
                            Serenity” (<hi rend="italic">An gong zhi bei </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">安公之碑</foreign>). The stele text is a literary composition playing with the
                            words <hi rend="italic">an </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">安</foreign> [peace] and <hi rend="italic">yi </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">一</foreign> [oneness] and alludes to the practice
                            of meditation, thereby glorifying Seng’an Daoyi for his spiritual
                            achievements as well.</p>
                        <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="meditationseat.jpg">
                            <head xml:lang="en">Detail of 3D model showing the stone seat opposite
                                the inscription HDS 16</head>
                            <head xml:lang="zh">三維模型細部圖展示正對著刻文洪頂山16號的石座</head>
                            <graphic url="meditationseat.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p/>
                        <p>The background of the second key figure at Mount Hongding, Renunciant
                            Fahong, is quite different. The surviving evidence suggests that he was
                            in fact a lecturing monk, a master who explained the teachings. In his
                            encomium (HDS 18) we read: “If it is not emptiness, he does not discuss
                            it. If it is not thusness, he does not speak on it. When he discusses
                            emptiness and speaks on thusness, affirmation and negation are both
                            extinguished. When he neither discusses nor speaks, being and non-being
                            both vanish.” And the verse of his encomium states that “he affirms the
                            Realm of Law; darkens his mind in the Great Emptiness.” This evidently
                            pays tribute to the monk’s Buddhist erudition, and carries strong
                            reference to the <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">prajñā</foreign>
                            </hi> view of emptiness. The Buddhist sutras carved on
                            the rocks of Mount Hongding confirm this interpretation as well. For
                            example, the selected passages from the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Great Perfection of Wisdom Spoken by
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mañjuśrī</foreign>
                                </hi>
                            </title> (HDS 1, 16.2, 22), the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Sutra Spoken by the Buddha on the Perfection of Wisdom for Humane Kings</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Fo shuo renwang bore boluomi jing </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">佛說仁王般若波羅蜜經</foreign>,
                            </title> HDS 6) or the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Great Perfection of Wisdom Sutra </hi>
                            </title> (HDS 5), and the seven “Buddha King of Great Emptiness”
                            inscriptions all match the contents of the encomium for Fahong and
                            demonstrate his affinity with the genre of <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">prajñā</foreign>
                            </hi> scriptures. How­ever, Fahong’s thought and the selected sutra
                            passages are not restricted to the <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">prajñā</foreign>
                            </hi> view of emptiness. The encomium’s juxtaposition of emptiness and
                            thusness implies a juxtaposition of <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">prajñā</foreign>
                            </hi> and of <hi rend="italic">Huayan </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">華嚴</foreign> thought.<note>
                                <ref target="LuoZhao2014" type="biblio"/>.
                            </note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Like Seng’an, Fahong was also a donor of rock inscriptions. He signs as
                            “Sutra Donor” (HDS 21.2) for the passage taken from the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Great Perfection of Wisdom Spoken by
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mañjuśrī</foreign>
                                </hi>
                            </title> on the southern slope (HDS 22), and he offered one of the
                            “Buddha King of Great Emptiness” inscriptions (HDS 23.1). He was also
                            probably responsible for the large group of Buddha names on the northern
                            slope (HDS 9.1-9.15), even though his name is written with a different
                            character here (HDS 9.16).</p>
                        <p/>
                        <p>The two eminent monks were in all likelihood connected. Although the
                            themes of both encomiums are not the same, they are related. The
                            inscriptions written by Seng’an on the northern slope reflect Fahong’s
                            thoughts on the southern slope.</p>
                        <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="HDS_meditation_seat_DSC3295.JPG">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">洪頂山16號經文下方天然石座</head>
                            <head xml:lang="en">Natural stone seat beneath HDS 16</head>
                            <graphic url="HDS_meditation_seat_DSC3295.JPG"/>
                        </figure>
                        <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="HDS_meditation_DSC3353.JPG">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">洪頂山16號前禪修示意</head>
                            <head xml:lang="en">Meditation pose in front of HDS 16</head>
                            <graphic url="HDS_meditation_DSC3353.JPG"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>Nevertheless, a sharp contrast exists with regard to the native districts
                            of the eulogized renunciants as mentioned at the beginnings of their
                            encomiums. Seng’an Daoyi is a man from the “neighborhood of Empty
                            Immensity” within the “village of Vast Enormity”. These are vague and
                            abstract notions. Not even the colophon by “Seng’an Daoyi of the Eastern
                            Range” to the inscription site of Mount Tie is of any use in clarifying
                            his origin; on the contrary, it only adds to the confusion.</p>
                        <p>By contrast, the beginning of Fahong’s encomium (HDS 18) reports that he
                            is “a man from India (Tianzhu <foreign xml:lang="zh">天竺</foreign>),
                            within the <foreign xml:lang="sa">Jambudvīpa</foreign> settlements of
                            the <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sahā</foreign> Lands”, and the verses record that 
                            “this renunciant (<hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">śramaṇa</foreign>
                            </hi>) from India (Zhong Tianzhu <foreign xml:lang="zh">中天竺</foreign>),
                            his surname is Shi and his name Hong”, indicating that he came from central
                            Tianzhu <foreign xml:lang="zh">天竺</foreign>, one of the five states in
                            India. In ancient Chinese, India was called “Tianzhu”, and the eastern,
                            southern, western, northern and middle parts were called the “five
                            Tianzhu states” (<hi rend="italic">wu Tianzhu guo </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">五天竺國</foreign>).<note>For example, during the
                                <hi rend="italic">kaiyuan</hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">開元
                                </foreign> era (713-741) of the Tang dynasty, the monk Huichao <foreign xml:lang="zh">慧超</foreign> (Hye Ch’o, ca. 700-780?), who came
                                from Silla to China on his way to India in search of the Law, wrote
                                his <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Account of Travels to the Five States of
                                        Tianzhu</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Wang wu Tianzhu guo zhuan </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh"> 往五天竺國傳</foreign>)</title> after his
                                return. The original book was lost, but a version was rediscovered
                                among the Dunhuang manuscripts. Fujita Toyohachi <foreign xml:lang="zh">藤田豐八</foreign> wrote the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Annotations on Huichao’s Account</hi> (<hi rend="italic">
                                        <foreign xml:lang="ja">Echō den senshaku</foreign>
                                    </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">慧超傳箋釋</foreign>)</title>. See <ref target="FujitaT1910" type="biblio"/>. Walter Fuchs re-edited the Chinese text and translated it into
                                German. See <ref target="Fuchs1938" type="biblio"/>.
                            </note> Central Tianzhu is the middle part of ancient India
                            and refers to a geographic region, but the “<foreign xml:lang="sa">Jambudvīpa</foreign> settlements” and
                            the “<foreign xml:lang="sa">Sahā</foreign> Lands” are Buddhist names for
                            imaginary continents and worlds often mentioned in Buddhist
                                sutras.<note>According to Buddhist cosmology, Mount Sumeru is the
                                center of the world, around which four continents are situated,
                                namely, the eastern <foreign xml:lang="sa">Pūrvavideha</foreign>,
                                the southern <foreign xml:lang="sa">Jambudvīpa</foreign>, the
                                western <foreign xml:lang="sa">Godānīya</foreign>, and the northern
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Uttarakuru</foreign>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Central India may thus have been Fahong’s home land. Although he
                            does not appear in the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Biographies of Eminent Monks</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Gaoseng zhuan </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">高僧傳</foreign>)</title>, many other monks
                            recorded there are said to have been of Indian origin from Central
                            Tianzhu or elsewhere.<note>An influential monk of the Northern Qi
                                dynasty, <foreign xml:lang="sa">Narendrayaśas</foreign>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">那連提耶舍</foreign>, came from Northern Tianzhu,
                                arriving in the dynasty’s capital, Ye <foreign xml:lang="zh">鄴</foreign>, in 556, and translated the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">*Candragarbhavaipulyasūtra</foreign>
                                    </hi>
                                </title> (<title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Daji jing yuezangfen </hi>
                                </title>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">大集經月藏分</foreign>, T#397, 13: 352a18-353a17),
                                which propagates the teaching of the End of the Law. Other monks had
                                moved with the Northern Wei dynasty to the new capital of Ye,
                                including <foreign xml:lang="sa">*Upaśūnya</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="sa">*Ūrdhvaśūnya</foreign>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">月婆首那</foreign> (538-565) from Central
                                Tianzhu, <foreign xml:lang="sa">Gautamaprajñāruci</foreign>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">瞿曇般若流支</foreign> (fl. 516-543) from <foreign xml:lang="sa">Vārāṇasī</foreign> in Central Tianzhu, and the
                                celebrated <foreign xml:lang="sa">Bodhiruci</foreign>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">菩提流支</foreign> (?-527) and <foreign xml:lang="sa">Buddhaśānta</foreign>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">佛陀扇多</foreign> (active in 511) from Northern Tianzhu.
                            </note> These scholar monks mainly consorted with the imperial court and
                            monastic superintendents in the capital. Someone like Fahong, who had
                            chosen to live in the quiet mountains, has only become known through the
                            discovery of the rock inscriptions at Mount Hongding.</p>
                        <p/>
                        <p>The activity at Mount Hongding in the early Northern Qi dynasty seems
                            thus to have involved people from both India and China: the Indian monk
                            Fahong, well versed in <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">prajñā</foreign>
                            </hi> studies, and the Chinese monk Seng’an Daoyi, the eminent
                            calligrapher. Fahong’s name is only recorded at Mount Hongding, while
                            Seng’an Daoyi, judging from his calligraphic traces, was also active in
                            western Shandong and may have reached out into the region of present-day
                            Hebei. Because the rock cut inscriptions at Mount Jian and Mount Tie in
                            neighboring Zoucheng also have colophons and a eulogy about him, much
                            attention has been paid to Seng’an Daoyi. The discovery of the encomium
                            and the calligraphy at Mount Hongding has led to even more enthusiastic
                            research and investigation. By contrast, the attention paid to Fahong
                            has been relatively sparse.</p>
                        <p>Given that Fahong was proficient in Buddhist teachings, and Seng’an was
                            skilled in calligraphy, it might be suggested that Fahong was the leading
                            personality. However, we should also consider the relationships of the
                            inscriptions on the northern and southern slopes of Mount Hongding. The
                            “Buddha King of Great Emptiness” on the northern slope, (HDS 8), which
                            is associated with Seng’an Daoyi, is far larger than the “Buddha King of
                            Great Emptiness” inscriptions on the southern slope HDS 19, 20, 21.1,
                            23.1).</p>
                        <p>Elsewhere, among the Buddha names, those eulogizing the mountain
                            (HDS 10 and 12), and a “Buddha King of Serenity” (HDS 11) may have had connections with Seng’an Daoyi,
                            while Fahong’s name shows up (HDS 9.16) next to the group of Buddha
                            names containing the seven Buddhas of the past. There must have been an intensive relationship between the two monks. However, we do not, today, know what
                            it was.</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>ZZ</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Dating</head>
                        <p>Among the carvings in the secluded valley of Mount Hongding, four
                            inscriptions carry a date. On the southern slope, the “Encomium to
                            Fahong” (HDS 18), carries the date: Third year of the <hi rend="italic">heqing </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">河清</foreign> era of the Northern Qi dynasty
                            (564). This clear dating is exact and beyond doubt. Among the many
                            undated inscriptions of the Northern dynasties, it is all the more
                            precious.</p>
                        <p>Another dated inscription is the colophon by Seng’an Daoyi (HDS 7) on the
                            opposite side, the northern slope. Unlike the encomium for the Indian
                            monk, which uses the dates of the Chinese dynasty, the inscription
                            praising the Chinese monk uses the Buddhist calendar, which begins with
                            the date of the Buddha’s demise, and reckons the years after the Buddha
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign> entered nirvana. This
                            inscription gives as the time of its creation “1,623 years after
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign> [entered into nirvana]
                            under the twin trees”.</p>
                        <p>In addition to the colophon by Seng’an Daoyi, the encomium for him (HDS
                            3), and the “Stele of Sire Serenity”, dedicated to him (HDS 15), also
                            make use of the Buddhist calendar. While the dating of the encomium is
                            partly damaged, the stele is dated to the year 1620 after <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign> entered into nirvana under the
                            twin trees.</p>
                        <p/>
                        <p> Chinese and Tibetan Buddhist writings offer more than 60 ways of
                            calculating the year of the Buddha’s demise. For China, the most
                            significant were the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Record of All Sages</hi>
                            </title> (<title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Zhongsheng dianji </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">眾聖點記</foreign>
                            </title> ),<note>This is the legendary “dotted record”, transmitted to
                                China by the translator <foreign xml:lang="sa">*Saṃghabhadra</foreign> with the text <hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Samantapāsādikā</foreign>
                                </hi>. This text was allegedly marked with
                                a dot at the end of every rain retreat following the Buddha’s
                                entrance into nirvana. By counting the number of dots on the
                                manuscript, scholars could calculate the Buddha’s entrance into
                                nirvana to approximately 485 BCE; see T#2034, 49: 95b18-c17.</note>
                            the theory that the Buddha lived at the time of the Zhou
                                dynasty,<note>The <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Zhoushu yiji </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">周書異記</foreign>
                                </title> claimed that the Buddha was born in the twenty-fourth year of the
                                    reign of King Zhao of the Zhou dynasty <foreign xml:lang="zh">周昭王</foreign>, and entered nirvana in the 52nd or 53rd year of
                                the reign of King Mu of Zhou <foreign xml:lang="zh">周穆王</foreign>.
                                This would date the Buddha’s life to 958-878/7 BCE. For an example
                                of this text being used in the context of sixth century Buddhist
                                apologetics, see T#2060, 50: 624c26-625a4.</note> the teachings of
                            Faxian <foreign xml:lang="zh">法顯</foreign> (ca. 337-442),<note>In the
                                travel account of the pilgrim Faxian, we find the claim that a
                                statue of Maitreya was constructed 300 years after the
                                Buddha’s extinction, and that the date of the statue corresponds to
                                the reign of King Ping of Zhou <foreign xml:lang="zh">周平王</foreign>
                                (r. 770-720 BCE). This would place the date of the <hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">parinirvāṇa</foreign>
                                </hi> in the period 1070-1020 BCE;
                                see T#2085, 51: 858a11-14.</note> and the dates connected with the
                            preachings of the End of the Law (<hi rend="italic">mofa </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">末法</foreign>). </p>
                        <p>
                            <anchor xml:id="zz1"/>Perhaps most relevant to activities in the
                            Northern Qi period was the dating of the demise of the Buddha on the basis of
                            the teachings of the End of the Law, which can be found in the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Vow Taken by the Great Meditation Master [Hui]si
                                    from Nanyue</hi>
                            </title> (<title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Nan­yue Si dachanshi li shiyuan wen </hi>
                            </title>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">南嶽思大禪師立誓願文</foreign>)<note>T#1933,
                                46: 786b-792b.</note> by Great Master Huisi <foreign xml:lang="zh">慧思</foreign> (515-577). In this text, Huisi states that 82
                            years of the period of the End of the Law had already passed from the
                            year in which he was born, namely, the fourth year of the <hi rend="italic">yanchang</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">延昌</foreign> era of the Northern Wei dynasty,
                            515.<note>T#1933, 46: 787a4-6. The vow itself was pledged in the
                                ninth year of the <hi rend="italic">tianbao</hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">天保</foreign> era of
                                the Northern Qi dynasty (558) when he was 43 years old; see
                                T#1933, 46: 787b26-c11.</note> According to this reckoning, the
                            period of the End of the the Law had begun in 433. Calculating the 1,500
                            years before the End of the Law (1,000 years of Correct Law and 500
                            years of Semblance Law), it seems that the Buddha’s demise was thought
                            to have taken place in the year 1,067 BC, and that, by 515, 1,582
                            years had already passed.</p>
                        <p>If we are correct in assuming that Mount
                            Hongding’s inscriptions agree with Huisi’s calculation, the dating of
                            HDS 15 (1,620 years after the Buddha’s demise) would correspond to the
                            year 553, while the dating of HDS 7 (1,623 years after the Buddha’s
                            demise) would be equivalent to the year 556. These calculations
                            indicate that the colophon by Seng’an Daoyi on the northern slope (HDS
                            7) would have been made eight years earlier than the encomium for Fahong
                            on the southern slope (HDS 18), which carries the date of 564.</p>
                        <p>Yet, in the medieval period mistakes often occurred with dates using the
                            Buddha’s demise, and hence the inscription on the northern slope in the
                            Mount Hongding valley does not necessarily have to be eight years
                            earlier than those on the southern slope. The correspondence of
                            1,623 years after the Buddha’s demise to the seventh year of <hi rend="italic">tianbao </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">天保</foreign> era (556) may not be definitive.</p>
                        <p/>
                        <p>Further, it may be problematic to follow Huisi’s calculations in dating
                            the inscriptions on Mount Hongding. First of all, Huisi took his vow in
                            558, (and presumably, therefore, wrote the text, the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Shiyuan wen</hi>
                            </title>) not before, but two years after the year in which the colophon
                            by Seng’an Daoyi (HDS 7) was supposedly completed, namely in 556.</p>
                        <p>On
                            the other hand, we might, nonetheless, accept the possibility of the
                            relevance of Huisi’s calculations, if we suppose that both his teachings
                            and the dating used for the colophon derived from a third shared source.
                            It is also possible that Huisi was widely revered during the Northern Qi
                            dynasty, and that the dating of his birth with respect to the
                            eighty-second year of the <hi rend="italic">mofa</hi> (corresponding to
                            515) was also recognised. </p>
                        <p>Some other carvings mentioning the Buddha’s demise further complicate the
                            situation. For example, the colophon on a Buddha statue that was made by
                            Shangguan Xiang <foreign xml:lang="zh">上官香</foreign> and others in the
                            fourth year of the <hi rend="italic">xinghe </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">興和</foreign> era of the
                            Eastern Wei dynasty (542) in Ji County <foreign xml:lang="zh">汲縣</foreign>,
                            Henan reads: “1,625 years [after] the mysterious transformation of the Tathagata
                             under the twin trees”.<note>“<foreign xml:lang="zh">如來隱變雙林已有一千六百兩十五年</foreign>”. See <ref target="Luxun1987" type="biblio">2, 2: 325</ref>.</note> According to this calculation, the Buddha
                            entered nirvana in 1,083 BCE, and the period of the End of the Law began
                            in 417.</p>
                        <p>There are also some image stelae with quite vague formulations, as in the
                            colophon on an image stele from the fifth year of the <hi rend="italic">wuping </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">武平</foreign> era (574) of the Northern Qi dynasty,
                            reading “the Great Sage in his demise returns to the truth ... since
                            then over a thousand years have passed.”<note>“<foreign xml:lang="zh">大聖滅應歸真…自尔以來，餘迳千記</foreign>”, see Zhidu’s <foreign xml:lang="zh">智度</foreign> votive inscription
                                     of 574, in <ref target="BJTSG1989_91" type="biblio">8: 59</ref>.
                            </note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Taking these conflicting calculations into consideration, the date of the
                            inscriptions at Mount Hongding may best be set in the years from the
                            beginning of the <hi rend="italic">tianbao</hi> era (550) to the third year of the <hi rend="italic">heqing</hi> era
                                (564).<anchor xml:id="zz2"/>
                        </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>ZZ</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Research History</head>
                        <p>From the eighteenth century, epigraphers, officials and literati turned their
                            attention to “northern stelae” (<hi rend="italic">beibei </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">北碑</foreign>), namely the calligraphy of stone
                            inscriptions from the Northern dynasties. They considered them to be
                            full of flesh and blood, lively and stern, with utmost tension, quite
                            the opposite of the calligraphy in ink that had been popular for
                            centuries. </p>
                        <p>Consequently, high provincial officials, literati, and outstanding
                            rubbing artisans searched everywhere, in deep valleys and secluded
                            mountains, personally inspecting stelae and rocks, and exploring famous
                            historical sites. The category “northern stelae” includes not only
                            inscriptions on stelae (<hi rend="italic">beiji </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">碑記</foreign>), but also epitaphs (<hi rend="italic">muzhi </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">墓誌</foreign>), votive inscriptions (<hi rend="italic">zaoxiangji </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">造像記</foreign>), and Buddhist sutras (<hi rend="italic">fojing </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">佛經</foreign>). These all attracted scolarly attention.</p>
                        <p>Among them, the Buddhist stone
                            sutras under the open sky are particularly striking. Although they were
                            never as numerous as the stone tablets (<hi rend="italic">beiban </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">碑版</foreign>), colophons (<hi rend="italic">tiji </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">題記</foreign>), and epitaphs, the giant
                            characters, forceful and magnificent, and the nature of the chiseling
                            have been extremely hard to match. </p>
                        <p>Accordingly, Bao Shichen <foreign xml:lang="zh">包世臣</foreign>
                            (1775-1855) and Kang Youwei <foreign xml:lang="zh">康有為</foreign>
                            (1858-1927) praised the characters as “cloud cranes and sea gulls”<note>“<foreign xml:lang="zh">雲鶴海鷗</foreign>”. See <ref target="BaoShichen_Yizhoushuangji" type="biblio">79</ref>.</note> and “the forefathers of calligraphy on tablets [for
                            buildings]”.<note>“<foreign xml:lang="zh">榜書之宗</foreign>”. See <ref target="Kangyouwei1987" type="biblio">474</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p> The fame of the inscriptions in Sutra Stone Valley
                            (Jingshiyu <foreign xml:lang="zh">經石峪</foreign>) at Mount Tai <foreign xml:lang="zh">泰山</foreign> grew evermore. The Four
                            Mountains in Zoucheng <foreign xml:lang="zh">鄒城四山</foreign> were also
                            renowned at that time. Only the inscriptions in the valley of Mount
                            Hongding on the banks of Lake Dongping were unknown.</p>
                        <p>It was not until the rise of modern archaeology that methods of field
                            investigation became a worldwide practice and were applied in Asia. In the
                            1920s, the Japanese scholars, <foreign xml:lang="ja">Tokiwa
                                Daijō </foreign>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">常盤大定</foreign> (1870-1945) and Sekino Tadashi
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">関野貞</foreign> (1868- 1935), surveyed Buddhist
                            monuments extensively, all over China, and also set foot in Shandong
                            several times.<note>
                                <ref target="Sekino_Tokiwa1925_31" type="biblio">vols. 7 and 11</ref>.
                            </note> However, they did not find and so did not know of the site of Mount
                            Hongding.</p>
                        <p>A shepherd first noticed the inscriptions in the 1980s. They were brought to the
                            attention of the authorities in July 1988. Qiao Xiugang <foreign xml:lang="zh">喬修罡</foreign> and Qing Bai <foreign xml:lang="zh">青柏</foreign>
                            published the discovery in 1994 and 1995 in the 
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Jinan ribao </hi>
                            </title>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">濟南日報</foreign>
                            <note>
                                <ref target="Qiao_Qing1994" type="biblio"/>.
                            </note> and in the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Zhongguo wenwu bao </hi>
                            </title>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">中國文物報</foreign>.<note>
                                <ref target="Qiao_Qing1995" type="biblio"/>.
                            </note> Administratively, Mount Hongding, at that time,
                            still belonged to Pingyin County <foreign xml:lang="zh">平陰縣</foreign>.
                            On January 1, 1996 it became part of Dongping County. Thereafter, academic research lead to
                            international cooperation in archaeological field
                            work and study.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="WuXugang2003">352</ref> gives details of the discovery.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>In 1997, Liu Wenjin <foreign xml:lang="zh">柳文金</foreign>, who held a post in the Goods
                            and Material Office of Pingyin County (Pingyin Xian wuziju <foreign xml:lang="zh">平陰縣物資局</foreign>), acquired an incomplete
                            set of rubbings and took them to Beijing, where he invited a few
                            scholars to examine  them in the gymnasium
                            at the Beijing Sport University. He also distributed photographs
                            and infor­mation on the inscriptions.</p>
                        <p>Thereafter,  Li Jingjie <foreign xml:lang="zh">李靜杰</foreign> published an article, “Reading a Huge Ancient Sutra Engraved on a Cliff: a 
                            Random Discussion of Rubbings of Sutras Engraved on Polished Cliffs in Dongping and Pingyin (<hi rend="italic">Jiedu yi ben ke zai xuanya shang de ju fu gu jingshu: guan Dongping, Pingyin moya
                                kejing taben suotan </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">解讀一本刻在懸崖上的巨幅古經書：觀東平、平陰摩崖刻經拓本瑣談</foreign>)”.<note>
                                <ref target="LiJingjie1997a" type="biblio"/>.
                            </note> This was the first publication by a scholar from mainland China. But
                            at that time official field investigations had not yet taken place.
                        </p>
                        <p>In 1997 also, Liu Wenjin, himself, published rubbings in <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Northern Dynasties Stone Inscriptions on Three Mountains in Pingyin, Shandong</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Shandong Pingyin san shan Beichao moya </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">山東平陰三山北朝摩崖</foreign>)</title>. 
                            His rubbings were not made by specialists and are not faithful to the characters on
                            the rock. They were amended and heavily retouched. For example, although most of the characters in HDS 5 are missing on the rock,
                            a rubbing was almost completely reconstructed based on the sutra text on the Eighteen Aspects of Emptiness,
                            which Zhang Zong had identified. Therefore, these rubbings are not listed in the catalog entries “Rubbings”,
                            but only in the catalog entries “Illustrations”. Only Liu Wenjin’s rubbing of HDS 2 is illustrated (fig. <ptr target="HDS_02_B.tif"/>).
                            Although unreliable, it gives a useful impression of the inscription, which has been almost completely destroyed.
                            Of great value in Liu Wenjin’s publication, however, is Zhang Zong’s <foreign xml:lang="zh">張總</foreign> article and
                            his catalog of the inscriptions.<note>
                                <ref target="ZhangZong1997" type="biblio"/>.</note>
                            This was the very first effort at scholarly classification of the inscriptions at Mount Hongding.
                            Many sutra passages were here identified for the first time, and the inscriptions were placed in the larger context of the Shandong inscription sites.</p>
                        <p>In October 1998, the Shandong Stone Carving Art Museum in Jinan carried
                            out a first site investigation. Rubbings were made by skilled
                            craftsmen, who succeeded in obtaining rubbings even from the most
                            weathered inscriptions, such as the important colophon, HDS 7, next to the
                            giant “Buddha King of Great Emptiness”, HDS 8. Based on this material,
                            Zhang Zong was able to conduct more in-depth studies of the dating of
                            the inscriptions according to the Buddhist calendar, and published his
                            results in 2000.<note>
                                <ref target="ZhangZong2000a" type="biblio"/>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>In an article of 1999,<note>
                                <ref target="ZhangWeiran1999" type="biblio"/>.
                            </note> Zhang Weiran <foreign xml:lang="zh">張偉然</foreign>, from
                            Fudan University <foreign xml:lang="zh">復旦大學</foreign> in Shanghai
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">上海</foreign>, established “Seng’an
                            Daoyi” as the most likely reading of the name of the monk who had left
                            several colophons and signatures at Mount Hongding, as well as at Mount
                            Tie and at Mount Jian. He believes that the readings of “An”, as the
                            man’s family name, and “Daoyi”, as his personal name, are incompatible
                            with Buddhist practice. This reading is accepted in the present volume.
                            However, in some votive inscriptions, individuals, who carry the title
                            <hi rend="italic">seng </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">僧</foreign>, are nevertheless identified by their family name.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="YangHao2002">50-52</ref>, and below, discussions HDS 3 and HDS 7.</note>
                        </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>ZZ</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <p>In 2000, the new interest in the genre of rock carvings culminated in the
                            publication of <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Sutras Engraved on Polished Cliffs of the Northern Dynasties</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Beichao moya kejing </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">北朝摩崖刻經</foreign>)</title> by Lai Fei <foreign xml:lang="zh">賴非</foreign>, which formed volume 12 of the
                            series <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Complete Collection of Chinese Calligraphy</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Zhong­guo shufa quanji </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">中國書法全集</foreign>)</title>.<note>
                                <ref target="LaiFei2000a" type="biblio"/>.
                            </note> The catalog entry on Mount Hongding by Lai Fei provided the
                            best transcription to date and documented every single character’s state
                            of preservation. </p>
                        <p>A site investigation of newly discovered inscriptions on Mount Hongding (formerly part of Pingyin County),
                            was followed by an academic conference in 2002.
                            The papers were collected in a second volume on rock cut inscriptions, entitled <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Research on the Sutras Engraved on Polished Cliffs of the Northern Dynasties, vol. 2</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Beichao moya
                                    kejing yanjiu [xu] </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">北朝摩崖刻經研究</foreign> [<foreign xml:lang="zh">續</foreign>])</title>.<note>
                                <ref target="SDSKYS_bwg2003" type="biblio"/>.
                            </note> A first volume with the same title<note>
                                <ref target="SDSKYS_bwg1991a" type="biblio"/>.
                            </note> had already been published in 1991, before the inscriptions at
                            Mount Hongding were made known to the world. In the second volume of
                            2003, about one third of the articles discuss Mount Hongding and the
                            calligrapher monk Seng’an Daoyi. The papers exploring Seng’an Daoyi and
                            his inscriptions include: Lai Fei, “On the Investigation of Seng’an’s Engraved Sutras (<hi rend="italic">Seng’an kejing kao shu </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">僧安刻經考述</foreign>)”,<note>
                                <ref target="LaiFei2003a" type="biblio"/>.
                            </note> Xu Hongguo <foreign xml:lang="zh">許洪國</foreign>, “Remarks on ‘Seng’an Daoyi’ (<hi rend="italic">‘Seng’an Daoyi’ zhiyan</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">“僧安道壹”卮言</foreign>)”,<note>
                                <ref target="XuHongguo2003" type="biblio"/>.
                            </note>
                            Kiriya Seiichi
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">桐谷征一</foreign>, “Traces of Sutras Engraved by the Great Renunciant An Daoyi of the Qi Dynasty (<hi rend="italic">Bei Qi da shamen An Daoyi kejing
                                shiji </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">北齊大沙門安道壹刻經事跡</foreign>)”,<note>
                                <ref target="Kiriya2003a" type="biblio"/>.
                            </note> and <foreign xml:lang="ja">Takuma Nobuyuki</foreign>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">田熊信之</foreign>, “Sutras Engraved on Polished Cliffs of the Northern Dynasties and An Daoyi (<hi rend="italic">Tianma tushu youxian
                                gongsi </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">北朝摩崖刻經與安道壹</foreign>).”<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Takuma2003"/>.
                            </note> There are also
                            papers analyzing the stone inscriptions at Mount Tie and Mount Tai, and
                            at Handan <foreign xml:lang="zh">邯鄲</foreign> in Hebei <foreign xml:lang="zh">河北</foreign> Province.</p>
                        <p>In 2006, a third volume of <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Beichao moya kejing yanjiu</hi>
                            </title> was issued, in which Yang Hao <foreign xml:lang="zh">楊浩</foreign> and Hao Li <foreign xml:lang="zh">郝莉</foreign>
                            <note>
                                <ref target="Yang_Hao2006b" type="biblio"/>.</note> gave yet another
                            report on all carved inscriptions, complete with transcripts and
                            comments on the state of the preservation. </p>
                        <p>In the same year, a report of the results of the Chinese-German survey of
                            Mount Hongding was published by the Shandong Museum of the Art of Stone
                            Carving and the Heidelberger Akademie der Wissenschaften in <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Wenwu</hi>
                            </title>.<note>
                                <ref target="SDSKYS_HAW2006" type="biblio"/>.</note> The latest
                            account on Mount Hongding’s inscriptions is found in Lai Fei’s monograph
                            of 2007.<note>
                                <ref target="LaiFei2007" type="biblio"/>.
                            </note>
                        </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>CW</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head rend="addspace">Inscriptions</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Inventory</head>
                        <p>At Mount Hongding, 25 Buddha names (HDS 8, 9.1-9.15, 10, 11, 12, 13, 17,
                            19, 20, 21.1, 23.1), six sutra passages (HDS 1, 2, 5, 6, 16.2, 22), and ten
                            historical inscriptions ( HDS 3, 4, 7, 9.16, 14, 15, 16.1, 18, 21.2,
                            23.2) were carved.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Buddha Names </head>
                        <p>On Mount Hongding, 25 separate carvings of 18 distinct Buddha names have been
                            found. They are inscription nos. 8, 9.1–9.15, 10, 11,
                            12, 13, 17 on the northern slope and inscription nos. 19, 20, 21, 23 on
                            the southern slope. According to the contents of the names, they can be
                            divided into two groups.</p>
                        <div>
                            <head>First Group: Da kong wang fo </head>
                            <p>The first group consists of six carvings of the name “Great (Da
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">大</foreign>) emptiness (kong <foreign xml:lang="zh">空</foreign>) king (wang <foreign xml:lang="zh">王</foreign>) Buddha (fo <foreign xml:lang="zh">佛</foreign>)”
                                (HDS 8, 17, 19, 20, 21.1, 23.1). The largest example among this
                                group is also the largest carving at the site, and its calligraphy
                                and carving technique are the most elaborate. It measures 9.2 × 3.4
                                m (HDS 8). This Da kong wang fo inscription is placed prominently in
                                the centre of the row of inscriptions on the northern slope (fig.
                                    <ptr target="HDS_sc_8_154"/>). The smallest Da kong wang fo
                                inscription is also the smallest carving (HDS 17) at the site. It
                                was carved by shallow “double-outline (<hi rend="italic">shuanggou </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">雙鈎</foreign>)” technique. Only a single
                                character measuring 6 × 28 cm is preserved.<note>
                                    <ref target="Yang_Hao2006b" type="biblio">166</ref>, mentions
                                    two more characters, possibly of a bodhisattva name.</note> It
                                is hidden in the elevated rock formation, in the eastern part of the
                                northern slope. Its calligraphy and carving technique are quite
                                simple, again by contrast with the inscription HDS 8.</p>
                            <p>The other four Da kong wang fo inscriptions are all found on the
                                southern slope. They are hard to see. The characters were carved
                                by the double-outline technique as well, amidst the patterned
                                eroded surface of the limestone rock (fig. <ptr target="HDS_r_19_total_DSCF0082-1.JPG"/>-fig. <ptr target="HDS_21.1neu.jpg"/>). The Japanese monk scholar, <foreign xml:lang="ja">Kiriya
                                    Seiichi</foreign>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">桐谷征一</foreign>, has suggested that the
                                outlined characters were left empty intentionally in order to
                                signify the principles of “impermanence” (<hi rend="italic">wuchang </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">無常</foreign>) and “emptiness”.<note>
                                    <ref target="Kiriya2003a" type="biblio">71-72.</ref>
                                </note>
                            </p>
                            <p/>
                            <p>
                                <anchor xml:id="tsl1"/>The name “Da kong wang fo <foreign xml:lang="zh">大空王佛”</foreign> is not found in this exact form in
                                any transmitted text. However, a Buddha King of Emptiness (Kong wang
                                fo <foreign xml:lang="zh">空王佛</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="sa">Dharmagaganābhyudgatarāja</foreign>) is mentioned. He is a
                                Buddha of the Past with a close connection to the historical Buddha,
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign>. The <hi rend="italic">Sutra Spoken by the Buddha on the Ocean-Like
                                        Samadhi of the
                                    Visualization of the Buddha</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Fo shuo
                                    guanfo sanmeihai jing </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">佛說觀佛三昧海經</foreign>) narrates how, in one of
                                his earlier existences, Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign> became a disciple of Buddha King of
                                Emptiness.<note>T#643, 15: 688c24-689a12.</note> On this occasion,
                                he witnessed how four monks meditated on the Buddha King of
                                Emptiness and became the Buddhas of the four cardinal
                                    directions.<note>Ibid.</note> According to the <hi rend="italic">Lotus Sutra</hi>, the Buddha King of Emptiness was even the one
                                who predicted that <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign> and
                                his disciple <foreign xml:lang="sa">Ānanda</foreign> would attain
                                    Buddhahood.<note>T#262, 9: 30a1–7; T#264, 9: 164b16–24.
                                </note> In addition, the <hi rend="italic">Sutra Spoken by the
                                    Buddha on Buddha Names</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Fo shuo foming
                                    jing </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">佛說佛名經</foreign>) mentions the name twice.<note>T#441, 14: 264a20; 308b12: “<foreign xml:lang="zh">南無空王佛</foreign>。”</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>Significantly, the Buddha King of Emptiness is mentioned in
                                inscription HDS 18, the “Encomium to Fahong”. This text provides
                                clear evidence that, for the protagonists of the carving project,
                                the Buddha King of Emptiness was the counterpart of the Buddha
                                Vairocana. It reads: <quote>[Fahong] is surpassing [in his understanding
                                of] the three kinds of emptiness, due to his earlier [incarnation]
                                during the time of the [Buddha] King of Emptiness. He is profound
                                and erudite in the myriad practices, due to his later [incarnation]
                                during the time of Vairocana.</quote> The Buddha King of Emptiness is here
                                the Buddha who teaches, in particular, the doctrine of <hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">śūnya</foreign>
                                </hi> (<hi rend="italic">kong</hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh"> 空</foreign>; emptiness), whereas the Buddha
                                Vairocana teaches <hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">tathā</foreign>
                                </hi> (<hi rend="italic">ru</hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">如</foreign>; thusness), as expounded in the
                                <hi rend="italic">Buddha’s Flower Garland Sutra </hi> (<hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Buddhāvatamsaka-sūtra</foreign>
                                </hi>, <hi rend="italic">Fo huayan jing</hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">佛華嚴經</foreign>).<note>See note <ptr type="footnote" target="TSL_1"/>.</note> Da kong wang fo could thus be
                                understood as: “Great Buddha King of Emptiness” (Da Kongwang fo
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">大空王佛</foreign>), that is, “the
                                dignified, magnificent Buddha King of Emptiness”. By adding the
                                prefix “da <foreign xml:lang="zh">大</foreign>” (great; skr.: <hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">mahā</foreign>
                                </hi>) to the Buddha King of Emptiness, his worshippers
                                demonstrated their highest respect for him and identified him as a
                                sovereign and absolute Buddha.</p>
                            <p>Yet, the name allows another reading: “Buddha King of Great
                                Emptiness” (Dakongwang fo <foreign xml:lang="zh">大空王 佛</foreign>).
                                This reading stresses Great Emptiness (<hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">mahā­śūnyatā</foreign>
                                </hi>), which fits with the doctrines in the sutra passages
                                carved at the site. Great Emptiness is the highest principle of
                                insight in Mahayana doctrine, as
                                the following passages may illuminate. The <hi rend="italic">Sutra
                                    Spoken by the Buddha on the Ocean-Like Samadhi of the Visualization of the Buddha</hi>
                                equates Great Emptiness with the Perfection of Wisdom:
                                “the deeply profound and wonderful Law, the meaning of Great
                                Emptiness of the Perfection of Wisdom”.<note>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">“甚深妙法、般若波羅蜜大空之義。”</foreign>T#643,
                                    15: 677a10.</note> The <hi rend="italic">Sutra of Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                                </hi> (<hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā­vatāra-sūtra</foreign>
                                </hi>, <hi rend="italic">Ru Lengqie jing </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">入楞伽經</foreign>) expounds the sixth of Seven
                                Emptinesses as “Great Emptiness of noble wisdom of the ultimate meaning”.<note>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">“第一義聖智大空。”</foreign>T#671, 16: 529a8-10; T#670, 16: 488c18–20. Suzuki Daisetz (<foreign xml:lang="ja" transliteration="romaji">Teitarō</foreign>) translates the
                                    phrase as follows: “the emptiness in its highest sense of ultimate reality
                                    realizable by noble wisdom”. <ref target="Suzuki1932" type="biblio">66ff</ref>.</note> The <hi rend="italic">Lotus
                                    Hand Sutra</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Huashou jing</hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh"> 華手經</foreign>) promotes the “correct view of
                                Great Emptiness (<hi rend="italic">da kong zhengjian </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">大空正見</foreign>” in contrast
                                to “false views (<hi rend="italic">xiejian </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">邪見</foreign>)”.<note>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">“菩薩應當親近修習大空正見，離邪見故。”</foreign>T#657,
                                    16: 188b9–10.</note> The <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Past
                                    Deeds of the Buddha</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Fo benxing jing </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">佛本行經</foreign>) praises “the Buddha’s wisdom
                                of Great Emptiness”.<note>“<foreign xml:lang="zh">佛大空慧。</foreign>” T#193, 4: 55c20.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>Further, Great Emptiness is a synonym for Mahayana nirvana as well as for the Tathagata, the Thus Come One (<hi rend="italic">rulai</hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">如來</foreign>). The <hi rend="italic">Sutra Spoken by the Buddha on the Causes and Conditions of the
                                    Thousand Buddhas</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Fo shuo qianfo yinyuan
                                    jing </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">佛說千佛因緣經</foreign>) describes how the Buddha
                                “roamed in the Great Emptiness, the Utmost Nirvana”.<note>“<foreign xml:lang="zh">遊於大空、畢竟涅槃。</foreign>” T#426, 14: 70a17-19.</note> The <hi rend="italic">
                                    Great <foreign xml:lang="sa">Parinirvāṇa</foreign> Sutra
                                </hi> (<hi rend="italic">Da boniepan jing</hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh"> 大般涅槃經</foreign>) says that “Mercy is Great
                                Emptiness, as Great Emptiness is Mercy”, and that “Mercy is the
                                Thus Come One”.<note>“<foreign xml:lang="zh">慈即大空、大空即慈。</foreign>” T#374, 12: 456b15-24. “<foreign xml:lang="zh">慈即如來</foreign>”. T#374, 12: 456b15–c5.</note> Its opposite
                                is “Imbalanced Emptiness (<hi rend="italic">piankong </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">偏空</foreign>)”, a term that Mahayana Buddhists used to criticize
                                what they regarded as the one-sided view of emptiness in “Hinayana” Buddhism.<note>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">《摩訶止觀》：“墮偏空裹，或偏假裹。種種蹊徑，令不入圓。</foreign>” T#1911, 46: 155c7–8.<foreign xml:lang="zh">《大般涅槃經疏》：“二乘偏空故，不見第一義空。”</foreign> T#1767, 38: 175c12.
                                </note>
                            </p>
                            <p>Notably, the term Great Emptiness also appears twice in the texts
                                carved on Mount Hongding. It is one of the Eighteen Aspects of
                                Emptiness, (HDS 5, “Mahayana Sutra” <foreign xml:lang="zh">《摩訶衍經》</foreign>). In this particular
                                set of aspects of emptiness, Great Emptiness refers to the absolute
                                emptiness of space, that is, the emptiness of the ten directions.
                                The <hi rend="italic">Great Collection Sutra</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Daji jing </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">大集經</foreign>) expounds on the term as
                                follows:<quote> What is called Great Emptiness? As for the east, the east
                                is empty. [Also the south, west, and north], all the four
                                intermediate directions, are empty. There is no gathering [of
                                elements]. They are indestructible and ungraspable. Why is this? The
                                nature of entities is thus. This is called Great
                                Emptiness.<note>“<foreign xml:lang="zh">何者名為大空？東方，東方空。乃至四維空。非積聚，不可壞，不可取。何以故？諸法性爾，是名大空。</foreign>”
                                    T#397, 13: 360b28–c1. For similar explanations see <foreign xml:lang="zh">《放光般若經》：“何等為大空？八方上下皆空，是為大空。</foreign>” T#221, 8: 23a16.
                                        <foreign xml:lang="zh">
                                        《光讚經》：“彼何謂為大空？所謂東方亦空、南方、西方、北方、東南、西南、西北、東北方、上方、下方，皆亦悉空，不可毀傷、不可壞起。所以者何？本淨故也。</foreign>” T#222, 8: 189b27-c1. <foreign xml:lang="zh">《摩訶般若波羅蜜經》：“何等為大空？東方東方相空，非常非滅故。何以故？性自爾。南西北方四維上下南西北方四維上下空，非常非滅故。何以故？性自爾。是名大空。</foreign>” T#223, 8: 250b20-23.</note>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>The term occurs again in the encomium for Fahong (HDS 18), which ends
                                with the parallel: “He affirms the Realm of the Law; darkens his
                                mind in the Great Emptiness.” This highlights the two absolute
                                realities expounded in the sutras of the <hi rend="italic">Buddha’s
                                    Flower Adornment</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Perfection of
                                    Wisdom</hi>, respectively. On the one hand, Fahong believes in
                                the true thusness. On the other hand, he devotes all his mind to the
                                other, the Great Emptiness that is equal to the Perfection of
                                Wisdom. In this view, Da kong wang fo is the Buddha King of Great
                                Emptiness, that is, the Buddha King of the Perfection of Wisdom. </p>
                            <p>In sum, the name Da kong wang fo allows two readings with multiple
                                contents. First, it may be understood as Da Kongwang fo (Great
                                Buddha King of Emptiness). This is an extension of a Buddha name
                                that appears in the canon. By adding the prefix “great”, the name
                                pays homage to the Buddha who was a teacher of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign> and taught emptiness. This
                                interpretation corresponds to the passages from the sutras of the
                                    <hi rend="italic">Perfection of Wisdom</hi> carved on Mount
                                Hongding. Second, it may be read as Dakongwang fo (Buddha King of
                                Great Emptiness). This alternative reading underlines the Mahayana doctrines on nirvana, absolute extinction, which is
                                likewise named Great Emptiness. With his insight and correct view,
                                this Buddha proclaims the fundamental emptiness of space and all
                                entities.</p>
                            <p>Both readings are complementary. They emphasise what has been called
                                the apophathic aspect of the universe which,
                                by analogy with a Christian theological discourse, holds that God
                                can only be defined by what he is not.<note>
                                    <ref type="biblio" target="Gimello1976"/> has proposed this
                                        analogy.<anchor xml:id="tsl2"/>
                                </note>
                            </p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Second Group: all other names</head>
                            <p>While the first group consists of six separate carvings of a single
                                name, the second group contains nineteen carvings of 17
                                different Buddha names (HDS 9.1–9.15, 10, 11, 12, 13), two of which
                                appear twice (HDS 9.1 = 9.3; 9.8 = 9.13). All of these are
                                on the eastern side of the northern slope. Inscriptions HDS 9.1–9.15
                                are close together on an available rock surface. Their
                                similar calligraphic style and spatial arrangement suggest that they
                                were produced at the same time. Therefore, they are here grouped together, all under
                                HDS 9. At the end, follows the name of the donor (HDS
                                9.16).</p>
                            <p/>
                            <p>By contrast with the apophatic first group, the
                                second group might be said to represent the kataphatic, the affirmative aspect of the cosmos, because
                                it includes Buddhas from all directions and times. In addition, it
                                contains Buddhas who are associated with female devotees, with the
                                monk calligrapher Seng’an Daoyi, and with mountains. This second
                                group merits some comments:</p>
                            <p>The first of the inscriptions, “Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śikhin</foreign>” (HDS 9.1) refers to the second of the Seven
                                Buddhas of the Past. The name first appears separately, although the
                                entire set of the Seven Buddhas of the Past immediately follows in
                                its usual sequence (HDS 9.2–9.8), in which the Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śikhin</foreign> is
                                named again in inscription HDS 9.3. There are several possible
                                reasons for the double carving of this name.</p>
                            <p>Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śikhin</foreign> (HDS 9.1) may have been carved
                                simply because his name consists of only two characters and fits
                                well in the available space. Yet Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śikhin</foreign> also represents the remote past and
                               balances the last name of HDS 9, that of Buddha Serenity and
                                Joy (Anle fo <foreign xml:lang="zh"> 安樂佛</foreign>; HDS 9.15), a
                                Buddha of the future. These two Buddha names thus frame the entire
                                HDS 9.</p>
                            <p>Apart from being one of the Seven Buddhas of the Past, the Buddha
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śikhin</foreign> also appears once alone
                                in the canon, in the <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Causes and
                                    Conditions of the Injured Eyes of King <foreign xml:lang="sa">Aśoka</foreign>’s Son</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Ayuwang xi
                                    huaimu yinyuan jing</hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh"> 阿育王息壞目因緣經</foreign>; T#2045, 50). There he is
                                the Buddha to whom Lady Moonlight, a consort of King <foreign xml:lang="sa">Aśoka</foreign> in an earlier life, directed her
                                vow to attain the stage of Pureness of Sight Faculty (<hi rend="italic">yan’gen jing </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh"> 眼根淨</foreign>). With this vow, she could
                                heal the injured eyes of her son. The implied reference to Lady
                                Moonlight may indicate a female patronage of the carving.<note>For
                                    more detail, see <ref target="TsaiSueyling2009" type="biblio"/>; <ref target="TsaiSueyling2012" type="biblio"/>. For the possible meaning of the name in the geomantic discourse, see <ref target="TsaiSueyling2011" type="biblio">132</ref>.
                                </note>
                            </p>
                            <p>The inscriptions HDS 9.2–9.9 name the Seven Buddhas of the Past together with the
                                future Buddha Maitreya. The seventh in this sequence is the
                                historical Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign> of the
                                present world age (HDS 9.8). In this way, temporal continuity —
                                past, present, and future — is established here. At the same time,
                                these Buddhas cover the eight directions of the cosmos. In various
                                texts, the names of the seven Buddhas are transliterated differently.
                                The set on Mount Hongding is identical with the names in the
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Dhāraṇī</foreign> Sutras (sutras with
                                    spells).<note>Such as the <hi rend="italic">Sutra of Great
                                            <foreign xml:lang="sa">Dhāraṇī</foreign> Spirit-spells
                                        Spoken by the Seven Buddhas and the Eight Bodhisattvas</hi>
                                        (<hi rend="italic">Qifo bapusa suoshuo da tuoluoni shenzhou
                                        jing</hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh"> 七佛八菩薩所說大陀羅尼神呪經</foreign>; T#1332,
                                    21: 536b14-538b9), and the <hi rend="italic">Miscellaneous
                                        Collection of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Dhāraṇīs</foreign>
                                    </hi> (<hi rend="italic">Tuoluoni zaji</hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh"> 陀羅尼雜集</foreign>; T#1336, 21: 627a20-22;
                                    627c28-628a01), <hi rend="italic">Greatly extended <foreign xml:lang="sa">Dhāraṇī Sutra</foreign>
                                    </hi> (<hi rend="italic">Da fangdeng tuoluoni jing</hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh"> 大方等陀羅尼經</foreign>; <hi rend="italic">
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">*Pratyutpanna­buddha­sammukhāvasthita­samādhi-sūtra</foreign>
                                    </hi>; T#1339, 21: 650c3-4; 652c17-653b10), and the <hi rend="italic">True Sutra of the <foreign xml:lang="sa">Maṇiratna</foreign>
                                    </hi> (<hi rend="italic">Fo shuo Moniluo dan jing</hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh"> 佛說摩尼羅亶經</foreign>; T#1393,
                                    21: 910b15-18) with two slight differences in the names of Buddha
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">Krakucchanda</foreign> and Buddha
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign> as <foreign xml:lang="zh">拘留秦佛</foreign>, instead of <foreign xml:lang="zh">拘樓秦佛</foreign>, and <foreign xml:lang="zh">釋迦文佛</foreign> instead of <foreign xml:lang="zh">釋迦牟尼佛</foreign>. <ref target="YinGuangming1999" type="biblio">164–169</ref>.</note> More than a century
                                earlier, these specific names of the Seven Buddhas, with that of the
                                Buddha Maitreya, were carved on small stone pagodas in the territory
                                of the Northern Liang dynasty (Beiliang <foreign xml:lang="zh">北涼</foreign>; 397–439). On some pagodas, each
                                Buddha is allotted a trigram from the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Yijing</hi>
                                </title>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh"> 易經</foreign> (<title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Book of Changes</hi>
                                </title>) that represents one of the eight directions: The first
                                Buddha is allotted the east, the second the southeast, the third the
                                south, and so forth.<note>
                                    <ref target="YinGuangming1999" type="biblio">171–181</ref>, see also note <ptr type="footnote" target="LL291"/>.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>Inscriptions HDS 9.10–9.12 concern the Western Pure Land: Buddhas
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="sa">Avalokiteśvara</foreign>, and <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mahāsthāmaprāpta</foreign>. The latter two are
                                usually known as bodhisattvas attending the Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign>, the lord of the Western Pure
                                Land. Yet here the two bodhisattvas are called <hi rend="italic">fo </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">佛</foreign>, Buddha. They are thus not merely
                                the attendants, but the successors of the Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign>. According to the <hi rend="italic">Compassionate Flower Sutra</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Beihua jing </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">悲華經</foreign>), translated by <foreign xml:lang="sa">Dharmakṣema</foreign> (Tan Wuchen <foreign xml:lang="zh">曇無讖</foreign>; 385–433 or 436), Bodhisattva
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">Ava­lokiteśvara</foreign> will succeed
                                Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> after he enters
                                    nirvana, while Bodhisattva
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mahā­sthāma­prāpta</foreign> will replace
                                Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Avalokiteśvara</foreign> after he
                                enters nirvana.<note>T#157,
                                    3: 185c4-186c26.</note> Again, a temporal continuity is presented
                                here with a view into the future of the Western Paradise.</p>
                            <p>Inscriptions HDS 9.13–9.14, remarkably, name two Buddhas who were a
                                married couple in historical time: Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign> and the Buddha with the Complete Attributes of a
                                Thousand Ten Thousand Rays of Light (Juzu qianwanguangxiang fo
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">具足千萬光相佛</foreign>). In the <hi rend="italic">Lotus Sutra</hi>, the latter name was given to
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Yaśodharā</foreign>, the wife of the
                                Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign>, when it was
                                predicted that she would become a Buddha.<note>T#262, 9: 36a24-b2.
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Yaśodharā</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="sa">Rāhula</foreign>’s mother, is said to have
                                    become a nun five years after her husband’s
                                    enlightenment.</note> It is highly unusual to see Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign>, whose name has appeared once
                                before (HDS 9.8), carved again at the side of his wife.
                                This choice raises questions of gender and family status in the sixth
                                century.</p>
                            <p>Inscription HDS 9.15 names a Buddha of the Future, the Buddha of
                                Serenity and Joy (Anle fo <foreign xml:lang="zh"> 安樂佛</foreign>).
                                Serenity and Joy is a synonym for the Pure Land of the Buddha
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign>. Yet here the Buddha
                                of Serenity and Joy is not the Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign>, but a Buddha of the future. The <hi rend="italic">Sutra of the Thousand Buddhas of the Present
                                    Worthy Eon</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Xianzai xianjie qianfo jing </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">現在賢劫千佛經</foreign>) lists him twice as a
                                future Buddha of the present eon. While Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign> is the fourth of the Thousand
                                Buddhas of this eon, the first Buddha of Serenity and Joy is the
                                    ninety-eighth,<note>T#447a, 14: 376b26–27.</note> and the second
                                Buddha of Serenity and Joy is the nine hundred and
                                    ninety-fourth.<note>T#447a, 14: 383a17–18.</note> The carving of
                                his name thus stresses once more the temporal continuity of the
                                Buddhist cosmos into the future.</p>
                            <p>At the same time, the name Serenity and Joy (Anle <foreign xml:lang="zh">安樂</foreign>) must also have been chosen in homage
                                to the monk Seng’an Daoyi <foreign xml:lang="zh">僧安道壹</foreign>, who
                                is honourably called “Sire Serenity” (An gong <foreign xml:lang="zh">安公</foreign>) in inscription HDS 15.</p>
                            <p>Inscriptions HDS 10, Buddha Lofty Mountain (Gaoshan fo <foreign xml:lang="zh">高山佛</foreign>), and HDS 12, Buddha Great Mountain
                                Cliff (Dashanyan fo <foreign xml:lang="zh">大山巖佛</foreign>), are
                                fittingly carved on a towering cliff at the eastern part of the
                                northern slope. The first name occurs four times in the <hi rend="italic">Sutra Spoken by the Buddha on Buddha Names</hi>.<note>The printed <hi rend="italic">Taishō</hi> canon
                                   records three occurrences: T#441, 14: 221a17; 229c16; 283c14–15. The revised CBETA has one more: T#441, 14: 279c21.</note> The second
                                name is not found in the canon. Most likely, this name was
                                specifically created for Mount Hongding. While the former Buddha
                                refers to an unspecified mountain in a faraway space, the latter
                                Buddha resides in the local mountain. A mountain cult is also
                                evident in the historical inscription (HDS 3) on the spiritual
                                achievements of Seng’an Daoyi, which talks about “thousand peaks of
                                Amassed Stones <foreign xml:lang="zh">積石之千峰</foreign>” and “myriad
                                summits of Empty Undividedness <foreign xml:lang="zh">崆峒之萬嵿</foreign>”.</p>
                            <p>Inscription HDS 11, Buddha King of Serenity (Anwang fo <foreign xml:lang="zh">安王佛</foreign>), is placed higher up than other
                                Buddha names. Three sutras contain this name. It is recorded in the
                                    <hi rend="italic">Sutra of One Thousand Five Hundred Buddha
                                    Names of the Ten Directions</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Shifang
                                    qianwubai foming jing </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">十方千五百佛名經</foreign>) and thus could, <hi rend="italic">pars pro toto</hi>, stand for the ten directions
                                (the cardinal and intermediate directions, together with the zenith and nadir).
                                In the <hi rend="italic">Lotus Hand Sutra Spoken by the Buddha</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Fo shuo huashou jing </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">佛說華手經</foreign>), Buddha King of
                                Serenity is a Buddha of the past.<note>T#657, 16: 140a28-142b22;
                                    169b26-171b22.</note> In the <hi rend="italic">Sutra of the Names of
                                    One Thousand Buddhas of the Future Star Constellation Eon</hi>
                                    (<hi rend="italic">Weilai xingsujie qianfoming jing </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">未來星宿劫千佛名經</foreign>),<note>T#448b,
                                    14: 394b28.</note> Buddha King of Serenity is a Buddha of the
                                future. From his elevated position on Mount Hongding, the Buddha
                                connects to the ten directions, the past, the present, and the
                                future of the Buddhist cosmos. In addition to all these cosmological
                                references, the name King of Serenity again suggests a parallel to the monk-calligrapher Seng’an Daoyi. Thus it points to the
                                calligraphy of “Sire of Serenity” at the site and celebrates his
                                personality and character.</p>
                            <p>Complementing the Western Pure Land mentioned above, inscription HDS
                                13 names Buddha Medicine Master of Berylline Radiance (Yaoshi
                                liu­liguang fo <foreign xml:lang="zh"> 藥師琉璃光佛</foreign>), the lord of
                                the Eastern Pure Beryl World (Dongfang jing liuli shijie <foreign xml:lang="zh">東方淨琉璃世界</foreign>). Unlike Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> in his blissful Western
                                Paradise, Buddha Medicine Master of Berylline Radiance relieves
                                sentient beings from all kinds of suffering and bestows on them
                                worldly benefits, such as good food, wealth, and even liberation
                                from punishment.<note>T#1331, 21: 532c18–533a13. The earliest evidence
                                    for the belief in the healing Buddha, Buddha Medicine Master of
                                    Berylline Radiance, is the twelfth chapter of the <hi rend="italic">Consecration Sutra</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Guanding
                                        jing</hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh"> 灌頂經</foreign>), on “Eliminating Faults
                                    and Transcending Life and Death” (<hi rend="italic">Bachu guozui
                                        shengsi dedu jing</hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh"> 拔除過罪生死得度經</foreign>; T#1331,
                                    21: 532–536), which first appeared in China in the mid-fifth
                                    century. <ref target="Strickmann1990" type="biblio">90–93</ref>.</note> His name on the west wall of the Eastern
                                Gallery of the northern slope is written in small characters in a
                                restrained manner, very different from all other Buddha names on the
                                mountain. It may be a later addition. </p>
                            <p>
                                <anchor xml:id="tsl3"/>In sum, the kataphatic
                                group of Buddha names temporally encompasses Buddhas from the past,
                                present, and future, and spatially brings together Buddhas from east
                                and west, the ten directions, the local, and the universal. This
                                group also hints at issues of gender, the cult of the mountains, and
                                local admiration for Seng’an Daoyi.</p>
                            <p>Fahong’s name appears three times as donor for inscriptions
                                of Buddha names: twice (HDS 21.2 and 23.2) in the apophatic group, and once as the only donor (HDS 9.16) in
                                the kataphatic group. The “Encomium to
                                Fahong” (HDS 18) shows that, doctrinally, he was well-versed in both
                                seemingly opposing, but mutually interconnected, concepts of being:
                                the apophatic “emptiness” and the kataphatic “thusness”. The encomium suggests
                                that Monk Fahong preferred the former doctrine, but clung to
                                neither. This preference is confirmed by the number of sutra
                                passages from the <hi rend="italic">Perfection of Wisdom</hi>
                                literature on Mount Hongding. Nevertheless, the carvings of the kataphatic group of Buddha names show that
                                the doctrine of thusness was also important on Mount Hongding, as
                                the poem at the end of the encomium sums up: “He affirms the Realm
                                of the Law; darkens his mind in the Great Emptiness. <foreign xml:lang="zh">確尒法界, 冥心大空.</foreign>”</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>TSL</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Sutra Passages (HDS 1, 2, 5, 6, 16.2, 22)</head>
                        <p>
                            The six sutra passages carved at Mount Hongding
                            are taken from four different sutras, of which three belong to the group
                            of scriptures dealing with the Perfection of Wisdom (<hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">prajñāpāramitā</foreign>
                            </hi>, <hi rend="italic">bore boluomi</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">般若波羅蜜</foreign>). Three of the carved passages
                            are, furthermore, quotations from the same sutra, namely the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Great Perfection of Wisdom Spoken by
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mañjuśrī</foreign>
                                </hi>
                            </title> (<title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Wenshushili suoshuo mohe bore boluomi jing</hi>
                            </title>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">文殊師利所說摩訶般若波羅蜜經</foreign>; T#232, 8: 726a-732c).
                            Thematically, the sutra excerpts focus on Buddha contemplation (<hi rend="italic">guanfo</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">觀佛</foreign>), the concept of emptiness (<hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">śūnyatā</foreign>
                            </hi>, <hi rend="italic">kong</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">空</foreign>), and the Six Perfections of a
                            bodhisattva (<hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">ṣaṭ­pāramitā</foreign>
                            </hi>, <hi rend="italic">liu boluomi</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">六波羅蜜</foreign>), with a strong emphasis on the
                            numinous Perfection of Wisdom (<hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">prajñāpāramitā</foreign>
                            </hi>). </p>
                        <div>
                            <head>HDS 1</head>
                            <p>The text is drawn from *Mandra[sena]’s (Mantuoluoxian <foreign xml:lang="zh">曼陀羅仙</foreign>) translation of the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śaptaśatikā­prajñā­pāramitā</foreign>
                                    </hi>
                                </title> (the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Perfection of Wisdom in 700 Lines</hi>
                                </title>), entitled <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Great Perfection of Wisdom Spoken
                                        by <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mañjuśrī</foreign>
                                    </hi>
                                </title> (<title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Wenshushili suoshuo mohe bore boluomi jing</hi>
                                </title>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">文殊師利所說摩訶般若波羅蜜經</foreign>; T#232). *Mandra[sena]
                                arrived in China in 503 and was active in the Liang dynasty
                                (502-557) in the south. He is said to have come from Funan <foreign xml:lang="zh">扶南</foreign>, a country identified with part of
                                the region now occupied by modern Cambodia. This scripture was also
                                translated by <foreign xml:lang="sa">*Saṃghabhara</foreign>
                                (Sengqiepolo <foreign xml:lang="zh">僧伽婆羅</foreign>) as the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Perfection of Wisdom Spoken by
                                            <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mañjuśrī</foreign>
                                    </hi>
                                </title> (<title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Wenshushili suoshuo bore boluomi jing</hi>
                                </title>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">文殊師利所說般若波羅蜜經</foreign>; T#233,
                                8: 732c-739c). <foreign xml:lang="sa">*Saṃghabhara</foreign> is also
                                said to have come from Funan and to have worked sometimes with
                                    *Mandra[sena]. The carved
                                passage consists of a 54 characters text on the nature of the Buddha
                                and on how to contemplate on him, which is only contained in
                                    *Mandra[sena]’s translation (T#232, 8: 728a26-29), but not in that by *<foreign xml:lang="sa">Saṃghabhara</foreign>. It also occurs within a section of
                                    *Mandra[sena]’s text collected
                                in the early eighth century translation of the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Great Gem Collection Sutra</hi>
                                </title> (<title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mahā­ratnakūṭa­sūtra</foreign>
                                    </hi>, <hi rend="italic">Da baoji jing </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">大寶積經</foreign>
                                </title>; T#310, 11: 652b15-18).<note>See <title>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Kaiyuan Era Catalog of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni’s</foreign> 
                                        Teachings</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Kaiyuan shijiao lu </hi>
                                        <foreign xml:lang="zh">開元釋教錄</foreign>
                                    </title>), T#2154, 55: 586b4-8.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>The passage comes from a conversation between <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śāriputra</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mañjuśrī</foreign> about the nature of the Buddha. The lines
                                that precede our passage are as follows:
                                <quote>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śāriputra</foreign> inquired of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mañjuśrī</foreign>:  ‘What is named the Buddha? What is
                                    Contemplating the Buddha?’ <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mañjuśrī</foreign>
                                    said:  ‘What is it that constitutes  “I”’?’ <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śāriputra</foreign> said: ‘“I” is just a name and names are
                                    characterized by emptiness.” <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mañjuśrī</foreign> said: ‘Just so! Just so! Just as “I” is a
                                    name, so as well “Buddha” is simply a name. Names are characterized
                                by emptiness, which is none other than <hi rend="italic">bodhi</hi>.
                                Do not seek <hi rend="italic">bodhi</hi> by means of names. The
                                attributes of <hi rend="italic">bodhi</hi> cannot be put in words,
                                cannot be explained. Why is this? Because words, explanations, and
                                    <hi rend="italic">bodhi</hi> are all empty.’<note>T#232, 8: 728a19-25:
                                        <foreign xml:lang="zh">舍利弗語文殊師利言：‘云何名佛？云何觀佛？’文殊師利言：‘云何為我？’舍利弗言：‘我者但有名字，名字相空。’文殊師利言：‘如是，如是！如我但有名字，佛亦但有名字。名字相空，即是菩提，不以名字爾求菩提。
                                            菩提之相，無言無說。何以故？言說菩提，二俱空故。’</foreign>
                                    </note>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>PC</abbr>
                            </ab>
                            <p/>
                            <p>
                                <anchor xml:id="cw1"/>The <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Great Perfection of Wisdom Spoken
                                    by <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mañjuśrī</foreign>
                                </hi> belongs to the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">Prajñāpāramitā</foreign>
                                    </hi>
                                </title> group of Mahayana
                                sutras, which promotes the Perfection of Wisdom by means of
                                realizing emptiness (<hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">śūnyatā</foreign>
                                </hi>, <hi rend="italic">kong</hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">空</foreign>) to attain ultimate
                                enlightenment. Perfection of Wisdom is the code of practice for a
                                bodhisattva in his quest to save all sentient beings. The <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Great Perfection of Wisdom Spoken
                                        by <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mañjuśrī</foreign>
                                    </hi>
                                </title> is a relatively late <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">Prajñāpāramitā</foreign>
                                    </hi>
                                </title> text, which was also influenced by <hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">tathāgatagarbha</foreign>
                                </hi> doctrine, postulating the non-duality
                                of sentient beings and the Buddha-nature. This sutra lays particular
                                stress on practice, promoting a meditation called “single-practice
                                    absorption” (<hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">eka­vyūha­samādhi</foreign>
                                </hi>, <hi rend="italic">yixing sanmei</hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">一行三昧</foreign>), which strongly recommends
                                repeated and single-minded invocation of the name of a Buddha. The
                                carving of various Buddha names on the slopes of Mount Hongding may
                                also be related to this practice.<anchor xml:id="cw3"/> The sutra on
                                the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Great Perfection of Wisdom Spoken by <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mañjuśrī</foreign>
                                    </hi>
                                </title> is, in addition, one of the scriptures held in high esteem
                                by early Chan Masters.<note>The earliest preserved text of the
                                    Chinese Chan tradition, The <title>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Fundamental Expedient Teachings for
                                            Calming the Mind Which Attains Enlightenment</hi>
                                    </title> (<title>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Rudao anxinyao fangbianfamen </hi>
                                        <foreign xml:lang="zh">入道安心要方便法門</foreign>
                                    </title>) by Daoxin (<foreign xml:lang="zh">道信</foreign>,
                                    580-651), fourth patriarch of the lineage, makes use of this sutra:
                                    see <ref type="biblio" target="Chappell1983">97-100</ref>. The
                                        <hi rend="italic">Great Perfection of Wisdom Spoken by
                                            <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mañjuśrī</foreign>
                                    </hi> is furthermore part of the Dunhuang manuscript, Pelliot chinois 4646, a
                                    collection of five texts that was identified by <ref target="ZhangZong2000a" type="biblio">64-65</ref>, as being
                                    related to Chan meditations.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>The dominance of excerpts from this sutra on Mount Hongding (HDS 1,
                                16.2 and 22), combined with the large number of Buddha names on
                                the one hand and allusions in the encomiums (HDS 3, 15, and 18) to
                                contemplative achievements on the other, clearly reflects Buddhist
                                practice of the time, which saw no incompatibility between the
                                invocation of Buddha names and meditation.<note>For a description of
                                    meditational and <hi rend="italic">nianfo</hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">念佛</foreign> practices by early Pure Land
                                    and Chan patriarchs and their common ground see <ref target="HengchingShih1992" type="biblio">26-61</ref>.
                                </note>
                            </p>
                            <p>The carved text of the 54 character passage of the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Great Perfection of Wisdom Spoken
                                        by <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mañjuśrī</foreign>
                                    </hi>
                                </title> is identical to virtually all versions
                                that have come down to us.<note>There is only one exception: The
                                    Dunhuang manuscript <hi rend="italic">Bei</hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">北</foreign> 3492 adds
                                    the character <foreign xml:lang="zh">佛</foreign> to the phrase
                                        “<foreign xml:lang="zh">云何觀佛者? 不生不滅</foreign>…” to read
                                    “<foreign xml:lang="zh">云何觀佛? 佛者不生不滅</foreign>…”. See <ref type="biblio" target="Dunhuangbaozang1981_1986">78: 270b</ref>.
                                </note>
                                Exactly the same passage appears on the rock of Mount Shuiniu, on
                                stone slabs in Cloud Dwelling Monastery (Yunju Si <foreign xml:lang="zh">雲居寺</foreign>) in Fangshan <foreign xml:lang="zh">房山</foreign>,<note>See the fragments of a stone slab from cave
                                    4, carved in the Sui or Tang dynasties, <ref target="FS_SJ2000" type="biblio">1: 121</ref>, and stone slab no. 378 from
                                    the same cave, carved in the year 1081, <ref target="FS_SJ2000" type="biblio">7: 371</ref>.</note> and in the modern
                                printed <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">
                                        <foreign xml:lang="ja">Taishō</foreign>
                                    </hi>
                                </title> edition of the Buddhist canon.<anchor xml:id="cw1a"/>
                            </p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>CW</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>HDS 2</head>
                            <p>The passage carved here is drawn from
                                the translation of the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">*Mahāvaipulya­mahāsaṃnipāta-sūtra</foreign>
                                    </hi>
                                </title> by <foreign xml:lang="sa">Dharmakṣema</foreign>,<note>For the translator <foreign xml:lang="sa">Dharmakṣema</foreign> see the study by <ref type="biblio" target="Kamata1978">80-82</ref>.</note> entitled <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Vast and Universal Great Collection Sutra</hi>
                                </title> (<title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Da fangdeng daji jing</hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">大方等大集經</foreign>
                                </title>). It was taken from the “Chapter on Bodhisattva Ocean-like
                                Wisdom” (from a portion of chapter 5 in scroll 8, with chapter 5 running
                                from scroll 8 to 11) and corresponds to T#397, 13: 50b15-18.
                                According to tradition, <foreign xml:lang="sa">Dharmakṣema</foreign>
                                was born in Central India, and traveled to the Northern Liang
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">北涼</foreign> capital, Guzang <foreign xml:lang="zh">姑臧</foreign>, in 412, where he remained until 422.<note>
                                    <ref type="biblio" target="ChenJinhua2004a">passim, and
                                    especially 257-258</ref>, following Tang Yongtong, believes that
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">Dharma­kṣema</foreign> arrived in 420. But
                                this contradicts the evidence given in the <hi rend="italic">Biographies of Eminent Monks</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Gaoseng
                                    zhuan</hi>, T#2059, 50: 335c16-337b4].</note> After a trip to Khotan,
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Dharmakṣema</foreign> is said to have
                                returned to Guzang and then set off once again on a
                                journey to the western regions during which he was killed in 433.
                                The translation is traditionally dated to 420, though Chen Jinhua argues
                                instead that the text dates to
                                a period stretching from 422 to 431.<note>
                                    <ref type="biblio" target="ChenJinhua2004a">257-258</ref>.
                                </note>
                            </p>
                            <p> The text of HDS 2 concerns the nature of the Six Perfections (<hi rend="italic">liu boluomi </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">六波羅蜜</foreign>)—Generosity, Precepts,
                                Patience, Vigor, Absorption, and Wisdom—one of the basic tenets of
                                Buddhist practice. But since the inscription was badly damaged in
                                the late 1990s, the exact wording can no longer be established.
                                Before that, it was transcribed only once by
                                    Kiriya Seiichi on August 20,
                                1995. An earlier rubbing of poor quality also exists;<note>
                                    <ref type="biblio" target="SDSKYS_HAW2006">84, fig.
                                    8</ref>.</note> it is not very reliable.</p>
                            <p>The same text passage about the nature of the Six Perfections also
                                appears on Mount Tie in Zoucheng within the much larger passage from
                                the <hi rend="italic">Great Collection Sutra</hi> carved there. The
                                text about the Six Perfections at Mount Tie is identical with the
                                versions preserved in the stone-cut canon of Cloud Dwelling
                                Monastery in Fangshan,<note>Only the first one and a half lines of
                                    the text are preserved on the front side of stone slab no. 683
                                    from cave 2, which was carved in the Tang dynasty, see <ref target="FS_SJ2000" type="biblio">3: 265a</ref>. On the
                                    front side of stone slab no. 332, carved in the year 1063, from
                                    the same cave, the text is almost completely preserved, see <ref target="FS_SJ2000" type="biblio">9: 203</ref>.</note>
                                and in the printed canon editions of the Song (1104-1148 and 1239),
                                Yuan (1290) and Ming (1601) dynasties.<note>T#397, 13: 50b15-18, and T#397, 13: 50, note 7.</note>
                            </p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>PC, CW</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>HDS 5</head>
                            <p>The text of inscription HDS 5, entitled “Mahayana Sutra”, was seemingly never finished. Only a
                                few characters were fully carved, with some additional strokes in
                                double outlines. The inscription in the shape of a stele rests on
                                the shell of a frontally depicted, single tortoise with uplifted
                                head. The body of the stele was provided with a grid in double
                                lines, and, on top, a round stele head with an inner square field
                                for the four character title, surrounded by pairs of intertwined
                                dragons, is still visible. Mount Hongding’s stele inscription might
                                well have influenced the slightly later monumental stele at Mount
                                Tie <foreign xml:lang="zh">鐵山</foreign> (Tie 1) in the city of
                                Zoucheng <foreign xml:lang="zh">鄒城</foreign> (see Shandong, vol. 2).</p>
                            <p>The stele head carries a title reading “Mahayana Sutra” (<title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Moheyan jing </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">摩訶衍經</foreign>
                                </title>). Zhang Zong argues that “Mahayana
                                     Sutra” probably refers to the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Treatise on the Great Perfection of Wisdom
                                    </hi>
                                </title> (<title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">*Mahāprajñā­pāramitā­śāstra</foreign>
                                    </hi>, <hi rend="italic">Da zhidu lun</hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">大智度論</foreign>
                                </title>)<note>The <title>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Treatise on the Great Perfection of Wisdom</hi>
                                    </title> is traditionally
                                    attributed to <foreign xml:lang="sa">Nāgārjuna</foreign> (ca. 150–250), and was supposedly
                                    translated by <foreign xml:lang="sa">Kumārajīva</foreign>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">鳩摩羅什</foreign> (344-413). The Kuchean
                                    monk, <foreign xml:lang="sa">Kumārajīva</foreign>, arrived
                                    in China in the year 401, where he arguably became the single
                                    most influential translator in the history of East Asian
                                    Buddhism. His translations include versions of the <hi rend="italic">Lotus Sutra</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Diamond Sutra</hi>. Chou Po-kan suggested that <foreign xml:lang="sa">Kumārajīva</foreign>’s disciple, Sengrui, was
                                    the actual author of the <hi rend="italic">Treatise</hi>, though
                                    he does not deny the existence of a Sanskrit original, <ref target="ChouPokan2004" type="biblio">281-327</ref>.</note>
                                because this sutra’s head title is <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Da zhidu lun</hi>
                                </title> in the Dunhuang manuscripts, and its end title is <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Mahayana Sutra</hi>
                                </title>.<note>
                                    <ref target="ZhangZong2000a" type="biblio">66-68</ref>.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p> A passage quoted and commented upon in chapter 18 of scroll 46 of
                                the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Treatise on the Great Perfection of Wisdom</hi>
                                </title>
                                    (T#1509, 25: 393c1-5) is identical to a passage
                                introducing eighteen kinds of emptiness from the chapter “Inquiring
                                About the Vehicle” (<hi rend="italic">wensheng pin </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">問乘品 </foreign>) of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Kumārajīva</foreign>’s translation of the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Great Perfection of Wisdom Sutra</hi>
                                </title> (<hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Pañcaviṃśati­sāhasrikā­prajñā­pāramitā</foreign>
                                </hi>, <hi rend="italic">Mohe bore boluomi jing </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">摩訶般若波羅蜜經</foreign>, T#223, 8: 250b3-7).</p>
                            <p> The received version of the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Great Perfection of Wisdom Sutra</hi>
                                </title> in the <hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="ja">Taishō</foreign>
                                </hi> edition differs slightly, reading “This constitutes the
                                    Mahayana of the bodhisattva.
                                And then, Subhuti, the <foreign xml:lang="sa">bodhisattva-mahāsattva</foreign> also has a Mahayana...”<note>
                                    “<foreign xml:lang="zh">是為菩薩摩訶薩摩訶衍。復次，須菩提！菩薩摩訶薩復有摩訶衍</foreign>...”
                                    T#223, 8: 250b2-3.</note> The Mount Hongding text begins
                                with the last sentence of the previous section within the source
                                text, which it seems to present as a subject line of the text.</p>
                            <p>A thematically similar passage enumerating not eighteen, but
                                seventeen kinds of emptiness was carved on a single rock at Mount
                                Culai (Culai Shan <foreign xml:lang="zh">徂徠山</foreign>), close to
                                Guanghua Monastery (Guanghua Si <foreign xml:lang="zh">光化寺</foreign>,
                                see vol. 3).</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>PC, CW</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>HDS 6</head>
                            <p>The passage is drawn from the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Sutra Spoken by the Buddha on the Perfection of Wisdom for Humane Kings</hi>
                                </title> (<hi rend="italic">Fo shuo renwang bore boluomi jing </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">佛說仁王般若波羅蜜經</foreign>; T#245, 8: 825a-834a), a
                                scripture traditionally attributed to <foreign xml:lang="sa">Kumārajīva</foreign>, but probably compiled in China
                                in the 470s. This sutra was first considered spurious, and was only
                                given canonical status in 597 by Fei Changfang <foreign xml:lang="zh">費長房</foreign> in his <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Record of the Three Jewels throughout
                                        Successive Generations </hi>
                                </title> (<title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Lidai sanbao ji </hi>
                                </title>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">歷代三寶紀</foreign>, T#2034, 49: 22c-127c). The
                                sutra praises the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">prajñā­pāramitā</foreign>
                                    </hi>
                                </title> as a means of state protection and welfare, and was so used
                                by Emperor Daizong <foreign xml:lang="zh">代宗</foreign> (r. 762-779)
                                of the Tang dynasty, who
                                initiated a “Humane Kings” assembly and ordered a second translation
                                of the sutra in 765 by the famous monk <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amoghavajra</foreign> (Bukong <foreign xml:lang="zh">不空</foreign>, 705-774).<note>
                                    <ref target="Orzech1998" type="biblio">74-78</ref>.</note> On
                                the basis of the second translation, state-protecting rituals later
                                became popular in Korea and Japan. Apart from its political
                                relevance, the passage, at Mount Hongding, chosen from this sutra
                                has a Daoist flavor,<note>According to <ref target="Orzech1998" type="biblio">85</ref>, that was the
                                    reason why the passage as carved at Mount Hongding is only found
                                    in the fifth century translation, but was omitted by <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amoghavajra</foreign> in his “translation”,
                                    which was actually just a second edition of the text.</note>
                                invoking the magical qualities ascribed to the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">prajñāpāramitā</foreign>
                                    </hi>
                                </title>. The Perfection of Wisdom is likened to a series of
                                powerful talismanic objects, which is notable, not simply because it
                                does so—many texts employ similar vivid metaphors—but because some of
                                these objects are distinctively Chinese.<note>On later Chinese
                                    talsimanic objects see <ref target="Copp2008" type="biblio"/>.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>A modern collated edition of the received version of this passage is
                                located at T#245, 8: 832c23-26. The passage does not include King <foreign xml:lang="sa">Prasenajit</foreign> (<hi rend="italic">Posini wang</hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">波斯匿王</foreign>) seen in HDS 6, but simply
                                begins “Great King” (<hi rend="italic">dawang</hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">大王</foreign>), since the king’s name has been
                                introduced before at T#245, 8: 832b20. The wording of the carved
                                passage otherwise follows the passage in the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">
                                        <foreign xml:lang="ja">Taishō</foreign>
                                    </hi>
                                </title> edition, and those of a few manuscripts from the fifth
                                century that have come down to us.<note>
                                    <ref type="biblio" target="Orzech1998">79, note 39</ref>,
                                    mentions fragmentary Dunhuang manuscripts of the scripture: S.
                                    124, S. 3472, S. 4528, S. 7242, <hi rend="italic">Bei</hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">北</foreign> 3481-3.</note>
                            </p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>PC, CW</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>HDS 16.2 and HDS 22</head>
                            <p>HDS 16.2 and HDS 22 both present the same 98 character passage from
                                the <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Great Perfection of Wisdom Spoken
                                    by <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mañjuśrī</foreign>
                                </hi> (T#232, 8: 726a-732c) on the nature of the Perfection of Wisdom. This
                                passage is drawn from the <foreign xml:lang="sa">*Mandra­[sena]</foreign> (Mantuoluoxian <foreign xml:lang="zh">曼陀羅仙</foreign>, fl. 503)
                                translation of the <hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śaptaśatikā­prajñā­pāramitā-sūtra</foreign>
                                </hi> (the <hi rend="italic">Perfection of Wisdom in 700
                                    Lines</hi>). As mentioned above (HDS 1), <foreign xml:lang="sa">*Mandra­[sena]</foreign> worked with <foreign xml:lang="sa">*Saṃgha­bhara</foreign> (Sengqiepolo <foreign xml:lang="zh">僧伽婆羅</foreign>; b. 460), who also translated the <hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śapta­śatikā­prajñā­pāramitā­sūtra</foreign>
                                </hi> (T#233, 8: 732c-739c). In the current collated <hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="ja">Taishō</foreign>
                                </hi> edition, a passage that is identical with the carved text is
                                found in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Saṃgabhara</foreign>’s translation
                                (T#233, 8: 738a19-24), but it differs somewhat from the same
                                section in <foreign xml:lang="sa">*Mandra[sena]’s</foreign>
                                translation. However, a careful examination of the transmission of
                                the text shows that this passage, found in the carved text as well
                                as in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Saṃgabhara</foreign>’s translation, is
                                indeed a later interpolation unknown to the <hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="ja">Taishō</foreign>
                                </hi> edition.<note>The interpolation was first noticed by Luo Zhao
                                    during his stay at Heidelberg University in 2004.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>Versions of both translations, those by *Mandra[sena] and by <foreign xml:lang="sa">Saṃgabhara</foreign>, survive in the carved canon of Cloud
                                Dwelling Monastery at Fangshan near Beijing. As the Fangshan canon
                                shows, formulations of <foreign xml:lang="sa">*Saṃgabhara</foreign>’s original translation of this passage
                                display strong differences from the carved passage on Mount
                                Hongding. On the other hand, *Mandra[sena]’s translation differs from the carved passage by only
                                one character.</p>
                            <p>The earliest Fangshan version of the 98 characters passage is found
                                on stone slabs in cave 4 of Stone Sutra Mountain <foreign xml:lang="zh">石經山</foreign>. Carved during the Sui or Tang
                                dynasties, these slabs preserve <foreign xml:lang="sa">*Mandra[sena]’s </foreign>translation.<note>
                                    <ref target="FS_SJ2000" type="biblio">1: 125</ref>.</note>
                                Stone slabs in cave 4 carved during the Liao <foreign xml:lang="zh">遼</foreign> and Jin <foreign xml:lang="zh">金</foreign>
                                dynasties also carry the translation by “the Tripitaka Master from Funan, <foreign xml:lang="sa">*Mandra[sena]</foreign>”, as well as that by “the Tripitaka Master from Funan, <foreign xml:lang="sa">*Saṃgha­bhara</foreign>”.<note>
                                    <ref target="FS_SJ2000" type="biblio">30: 233</ref>.</note>
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa"> *Saṃghabhara</foreign>’s original version of
                                the passage in question appears on stone slab no. 374, starting at
                                column 13, counting from the left.<note>
                                    <ref target="FS_SJ2000" type="biblio">7: 375</ref>.
                                </note> It is quite different from the corresponding passage by
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">*Man­dra­[sena]</foreign>. This leads us to
                                conclude that at some point the relevant passage in *Mandra­[sena]’s translation was
                                substituted for the original passage in <foreign xml:lang="sa">*Saṃghabhara</foreign>’s translation, which is preserved also
                                in Dunhuang manuscripts S. 576 and <hi rend="italic">Bei</hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">北</foreign> 3497. </p>
                            <p>In addition, Dunhuang manuscript S. 2653 is also identical with the
                                rock cut Shandong version. Later on, the text of this passage was
                                amended, probably to make the meaning clearer.<note>The text version
                                    of stone slab no. 378, from cave 2 at Fangshan, was carved in
                                    1081, <ref target="FS_SJ2000" type="biblio">7: 372</ref>.
                                    It exhibits such amendments: to <foreign xml:lang="zh">“非行非不行處悉入一乘”</foreign>, it adds an additional <foreign xml:lang="zh">處</foreign> so that the passage reads <foreign xml:lang="zh">“非行處非不行處悉入一乘”</foreign>, perhaps to smooth the
                                    reading of the phrase. This amendment is lost later on, when
                                    printed editions of the Buddhist canon, including the modern <title>
                                        <hi rend="italic">
                                            <foreign xml:lang="ja">Taishō</foreign>
                                        </hi>
                                    </title> edition, keep the character <foreign xml:lang="zh">處</foreign>, but drop the original <foreign xml:lang="zh">行</foreign>. These editions also add two more characters,
                                    changing <foreign xml:lang="zh">何故</foreign> to <foreign xml:lang="zh">何以故</foreign>, and <foreign xml:lang="zh">如</foreign> to <foreign xml:lang="zh">猶如</foreign>.</note>
                                Unlike the amendments, which slightly lengthen the text, the
                                versions preserved in manuscripts tend to shorten the text by
                                employing contractions.<note>Dunhuang manuscripts S. 1908 and
                                    <hi rend="italic">Bei</hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">北</foreign> 3492 reduce <foreign xml:lang="zh">無邊無際</foreign> to <foreign xml:lang="zh">无邊際</foreign>, and <foreign xml:lang="zh">無名無相</foreign>
                                    to <foreign xml:lang="zh">无名相</foreign>.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>Although the wording of inscription HDS 16.2 on the northern slope of
                                Mount Hongding is the same as that of HDS 22 on the southern slope,
                                both inscriptions differ in their writing of the character <foreign xml:lang="zh">無</foreign>: HDS 16.2 uses the abbreviated
                                character <foreign xml:lang="zh">无</foreign> throughout, while HDS
                                22 prefers <foreign xml:lang="zh">無</foreign> in all but one
                                instance. Similarily, at Mount Yi near Zoucheng this passage was
                                also carved twice: At Bewitching Fairy Cave (Yaojing Dong <foreign xml:lang="zh">妖精洞</foreign>), the character <foreign xml:lang="zh">无</foreign> is used, and at Five Blossoms Peak
                                (Wuhua Feng <foreign xml:lang="zh">五華峯</foreign>) the character
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">無</foreign> (see Shandong, vol. 2).</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>PC, CW</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Historical Inscriptions</head>
                        <div>
                            <p>The ten historical inscriptions can be divided into two groups, those
                                pertaining to the monk donor and calligrapher Seng’an Daoyi, and
                                those relating to the monk donor Fahong. In both groups are
                                encomiums (HDS 3 for Seng’an Daoyi, with its title HDS 4, and HDS 18
                                for Fahong). In addition we find an unusual stele text for Seng’an
                                Daoyi (HDS 15), a colophon by him (HDS 7), and possibly a postscript
                                to his writings (HDS 14). Both monks left signatures (Seng’an Daoyi:
                                HDS 16.1; Fahong: HDS 21.2, HDS 23.2, and, most likely, HDS 9.16). </p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>LL</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>HDS 3</head>
                            <p> One of the fascinating and remarkable features of the inscriptions
                                on Mount Hongding is the presence of the two encomiums. There are no
                                other encomiums on the polished cliffs.</p>
                            <p>The “Encomium to Seng’an Daoyi” (HDS 3) praises the spiritual
                                achievements of this monk. According to the conventions of literary
                                genres, the first sentence of the encomium leads the reader to
                                expect a biography, and the language is similar to that used in
                                epitaphs of eminent monks. Unlike an epitaph, however, this encomium
                                gives no information about Seng’an Daoyi’s life, but reflects first
                                of all soteriological needs, when it describes him as “a man of the
                                neighborhood of Empty Immensity within the village of Vast
                                Enormity”. The encomium is comparable to that to Fahong on the
                                southern slope (HDS 18). </p>
                            <p>The two encomiums follow the same general scheme, but are rather
                                different from the more general biographies and epitaphs of eminent
                                monks. Both might be seen as constituting a separate genre of
                                monastic encomium, one which only generally resembles traditional
                                biographical genres.</p>
                            <p> Seng’an’s encomium is one of three inscriptions making use of the
                                Buddhist calendar’s dating in years after the Buddha’s demise.
                                However, here the exact number of years after the Buddha’s nirvana
                                is illegible.</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>PC</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>HDS 4</head>
                            <p>In HDS 4 Seng’an Daoyi’s name in four oversize characters is inserted
                                into a frame in the shape of a stele with a pointed head. It
                                functions like a title to the adjacent encomium, HDS 3. The
                                relationship between the two calligraphies is comparable to that
                                between the two parts of a square tomb inscription (<hi rend="italic">muzhiming</hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">墓誌銘</foreign>).</p><?cb?>
                            <p>The large characters on
                                the cover stone of a tomb inscription include the name of the deceased, while his
                                biography is carved in small characters on the stone below. This
                                type of tomb inscription had evolved from the Western Han dynasty,
                                but it became widespread only under the Northern dynasties.<note>
                                    <ref type="biblio" target="ZhaoChao1997">40</ref>.</note>
                            </p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>LL</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>HDS 7</head>
                            <p>This colophon identifies the renunciant Seng’an Daoyi as the
                                calligrapher of the giant four-character inscription “Buddha King of
                                Great Emptiness” (HDS 8) to the right. It explicitly states that
                                “the Great Renunciant Seng’an Daoyi wrote and carved: Buddha King of
                                Great Emptiness, seven…, wrote sutras…”, and thereby refers to
                                several inscriptions that Seng’an personally inscribed on the rock.
                                The meaning of the word “seven” probably refers to seven places
                                where the name “Buddha King of Great Emptiness” was carved.</p>
                            <p>There
                                are altogether six places on Mount Hongding with larger or smaller
                                “Buddha King of Great Emptiness” inscriptions, including HDS 8. At
                                least two of them (HDS 21.1 and 23.1) were donated not by Seng’an,
                                but by Fahong. But in neighboring Pingyin County <foreign xml:lang="zh">平陰縣</foreign>, more “Buddha King of Great
                                Emptiness” inscriptions were discovered on Mount Ergu <foreign xml:lang="zh">二鼓山</foreign>, Mount Yuncui <foreign xml:lang="zh">雲翠山</foreign>, Mount Tianchi <foreign xml:lang="zh">天池山</foreign> and East Mount Shuyuan <foreign xml:lang="zh">書院東山</foreign>. All these Buddha names have been discussed as
                                possible works by Seng’an.<note>
                                    <ref type="biblio" target="ZhangZong2003a">14</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="LaiFei2003c">96</ref>.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>The colophon is one of the three historical inscriptions at Mount
                                Hongding that refer to the Buddhist calendar. It gives “1,623 years
                                after <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākya­muni</foreign> [entered into
                                nirvana] under the twin trees”. According to Zhang Zong,<note>
                                    <ref target="ZhangZong2000b" type="biblio">12-13</ref>.
                                </note> this date corresponds to the year 556, based on the years
                                after the beginning of the End of the Law as calculated by Huisi
                                (515-577).</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>CW, ZZ</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>HDS 9.16</head>
                            <p>A monk Fahong <foreign xml:lang="zh">法鴻</foreign> has signed here as
                                donor for the large group of Buddha names on the northern slope (HDS
                                9.1-9.15). In all likelihood, this person is identical with monk
                                Fahong <foreign xml:lang="zh">法洪</foreign>
                                <note>
                                    <ref target="LaiFei2000a" type="biblio">268</ref> and <ref target="Yang_Hao2006b" type="biblio">176</ref>.
                                </note> who donated two Buddha names on the southern slope (HDS
                                21.2 and 23.2), and who is venerated in an encomium (HDS 18). </p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>CW</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>HDS 14</head>
                            <p>The four characters reading “Stele of Wind Entrance” have to be seen
                                in close relation to neighboring inscriptions HDS 15 and HDS 16.
                                These might be a form of postscript to these Seng’an Daoyi related
                                inscriptions, perhaps carved by some of his followers.<note>
                                    <ref target="AnTingshan2003a" type="biblio">59</ref>.
                                </note>
                            </p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>CW</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>HDS 15</head>
                            <p>This inscription entitled “Stele of Sire Serenity” presents a
                                word play on Seng’an Daoyi’s four character name. It makes use of
                                each character’s meaning, first establishing subtle relations
                                between them, and finally reducing them to what may be called the
                                very essence of Buddhist practice: Serenity and Unity. This
                                extraordinary inscription is dated “1,620 years after [<foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign> entered into nirvana under]
                                the twin trees”, and is thus three years earlier than HDS 7.
                                According to Huisi’s calculation of the End of the Law, this date
                                should correspond to the year 553.</p>
                            <p>It is unlikely that Seng’an himself composed and wrote the
                                inscription for his honorary stele, and some authors therefore
                                believe it to be a work by his followers.<note>
                                    <ref target="LiuTao2003a" type="biblio">238-239</ref> and <ref target="ChenKunlin2003" type="biblio">326-329</ref>.
                                </note> Yet it has also been suggested that the monk might have been
                                asked by his disciples to write the sophisticated and cryptic text
                                with his own hand.<note>
                                    <ref target="Kitajima2003" type="biblio">279</ref>.
                                </note>
                            </p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>CW</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>HDS 16.1</head>
                            <p>This signature reading “Seng’an Daoyi” is carved next to the sutra
                                passage of 98 characters taken from the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Great Perfection of Wisdom Spoken
                                        by <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mañjuśrī</foreign>
                                    </hi>
                                </title> (HDS 16.2). It designates Seng’an either as calligrapher of
                                the sutra passage, or as donor, or even both.</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>CW</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>HDS 18</head>
                            <p>Like HDS 3, the “Encomium to Seng’an Daoyi”, the text of the encomium
                                for Fahong, is not included in any traditional collection. Again,
                                the only parallels for this monastic encomium are the traditional
                                biographical genres, as in HDS 3. The first sentence leads one to
                                expect a biography, yet what follows is more a panegyric to Fahong’s
                                talents and his mastery of doctrines than a biography in the usual
                                sense. By contrast with the encomium for Seng’an Daoyi, the one for
                                Fahong uses the regular calendar for dating the inscription to the
                                third year of the <hi rend="italic">he­qing</hi> era of the Northern Qi dynasty (564). </p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>PC</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>HDS 21.2</head>
                            <p>Fahong seems to have donated not only the name Buddha King of Great
                                Emptiness (HDS 21.1) right above this inscription, but also the
                                sutra passage of HDS 22 to the right, for he is addressed as “Donor
                                of Sutras”.</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>CW</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>HDS 23.2</head>
                            <p>The same monk Fahong, who is praised in the encomium HDS 18 and named
                                as donor in HDS 21.2, appears here as donor of the name “Buddha King
                                of Great Emptiness” (HDS 23.1). </p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>CW</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Layout</head>
                        <p>Five types of layout can be identified.</p>
                        <list type="ordered">
                            <item>Rectangular layout without frame. Except for HDS 8, all Buddha
                                names written in one vertical column belong in this group (HDS
                                9.1-9.15, 10-13, 17, 19, 20, 21.1, 23.1), as does the short single column
                                “Stele of Wind Entrance” (HDS 14). Texts with more than one
                                column, namely the sutra passages HDS 1, 2, 6, and 16.2, the
                                encomium HDS 3, and the colophon HDS 7 also take this form. In the sutra passages and,
                                indeed, in all texts with several columns carved at Mount Hongding,
                                the characters have been arranged in horizontal rows (exception:
                                last column of HDS 3). In HDS 6, this invisible grid has been
                                calculated in such a way that the two characters, <hi rend="italic">yi ming </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">亦名</foreign>,
                                mostly stand next to each other horizontally. In the largely
                                destroyed HDS 2, the entire fifth row was probably filled by the
                                character <hi rend="italic">ming</hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">名</foreign>. </item>
                            <item>Double frame. Only one Buddha name is encased in a double frame,
                                namely the giant HDS 8.</item>
                            <item>Grid. In the “Encomium to Fahong”, HDS 18, the grid of the
                                multi-column inscriptions has been made visible explicitly by
                                carving thin lines (the “Encomium to Seng’an Daoyi”, HDS 3, has no
                                such grid lines). In the sutra passage HDS 22, only the vertical
                                columns are separated by double grid lines, but not the horizontal
                                rows.</item>
                            <item>Stele shape. Three inscriptions are laid out like a stele. While
                                Seng’an Daoyi’s name in HDS 4 is simply encased by outlines in the
                                shape of a stele, the contours of a full-fledged stele have been
                                carved onto the rock for the sutra passage HDS 5. HDS 15 is
                                surmounted by a separate field for the stele title in four
                                characters that explicitly calls the text a “stele” (<hi rend="italic">bei</hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">碑</foreign>). The one column inscription HDS
                                14 equally calls itself a stele, yet no trace of a stele shape is
                                visible here. </item>
                            <item>Combination of two inscriptions. In several instances two
                                inscriptions are combined in a single layout. Seng’an Daoyi’s name,
                                HDS 4, relates to his encomium, HDS 3, in the manner of the cover stone
                                of a tomb inscription to the inscription below it. HDS 7 is a
                                colophon to the Buddha name, HDS 8, adjacent on its right. Signatures
                                can be placed to the right, to the left, or below the text to which
                                they refer. The signature, HDS 9.16, refers to the 15 Buddha
                                names 9.1- 9.15 on its right. HDS 21.2 is a signature to the Buddha
                                name on its left, and HDS 16.1 a signature to the sutra text on its
                                left. HDS 23.2. is the signature to the Buddha name 23.1 above it,
                                and the signature in HDS 13 is equally placed beneath the Buddha
                                name.</item>
                        </list>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>LL</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Carving Techniques</head>
                        <p>Having examined the carving methods of Mount Hongding’s stone sutras
                            through a transverse section analysis of its strokes, we conclude that
                            the techniques employed fall into five categories:</p>
                        <list type="ordered">
                            <item>U-shaped carving: the carver chisels in one movement along the
                                middle of the stroke. Convenient and fast, this technique is
                                suitable for the carving of strokes 0.2-0.4 cm wide. The lines of
                                the stele frame for the <hi rend="italic">Mahayana Sutra</hi> on Mount Hongding (HDS 5) are carved by this
                                method.</item>
                            <item>V-shaped carving: the carver chisels slanting lines from both
                                sides of a stroke, so that the lines intersect and the stroke
                                naturally takes shape. Convenient and fast, this technique is
                                suitable for the carving of strokes 0.7-4.0 cm wide. 90 % of Mount
                                Hongding’s inscriptions are carved by this method.</item>
                            <item>Double-outline carving: the carver chisels only the outline on
                                either sides of a stroke, so that the interior of the stroke remains
                                untouched. This technique is suitable for the carving of strokes
                                more than 4 centimeters wide. The “Buddha King of Great Emptiness”
                                inscriptions on the southern slope of Mount Hongding (HDS 19, 20,
                                21.1, and 23.1) are carved by this method.</item>
                            <item>Rectangular U-shaped carving: the carver chisels vertical lines on
                                both sides of a stroke. This technique is suitable for strokes more
                                than 10 cm wide. Mount Hongding’s “Buddha King of Great Emptiness”
                                (HDS 8) and “Buddha Great Mountain Cliff” (HDS 12) are carved by
                                this method (fig. <ptr target="HDS_r_12_total_IMG_0469.JPG"/>).</item>
                            <item>“Flying white” carving: the carver first chisels the double
                                outlines of a stroke, and then adds several decorative lines within
                                the stroke to create an effect, similar to “flying white” calligraphy. The giant “Buddha King of Great
                                Emptiness” inscription (HDS 8) on the northern slope of Mount
                                Hongding is carved by this method.</item>
                        </list>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>LF</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Style of Calligraphy</head>
                        <p>Typologically speaking, that is, given the number and position of
                            strokes in a character, the inscriptions belong to the late phase of the
                            clerical script (<hi rend="italic">lishu</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">隸書</foreign>). This type had its own development
                            in the north where, unlike in the south, it turned into the standard
                            script (<hi rend="italic">kaishu</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">楷書</foreign>) only gradually. This amalgam
                            created during the Northern dynasties has sometimes been called <hi rend="italic">kaili</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">楷隸</foreign> and sometimes <hi rend="italic">likai</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">隸楷</foreign>. It retains the typological
                            features of the clerical script: the radical silk, <hi rend="italic">si</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">糸</foreign>, is written with two superimposed
                            triangles (HDS 9.2, 9.15); we find a square on the left side of
                            the <hi rend="italic">yi</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">以</foreign> (HDS 16.2, 10/2; HDS 22, 7/8); hooks
                            in the <hi rend="italic">zhou</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">洲</foreign> instead of dots (HDS 16.2, 4/10), and
                            the composition of the <hi rend="italic">chu</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">處</foreign> remains rather different from the
                            standard form (HDS 16.2, 8/6).</p>
                        <p>Stylistically, the clerical script heritage makes itself felt in
                            conspicuous soft <hi rend="italic">na</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">捺</foreign> strokes (the last strokes in
                            characters drawn out diagonally toward the lower right), and in overall
                            squat proportions (HDS 16.2). However, these two stylistic features are
                            most conspicuous in the Buddha names and sutra passages and less so in
                            the two encomiums (HDS 3 and 18), the stele for Seng’an Daoyi (HDS 15)
                            and in his colophon (HDS 7). The calligraphers freely use deviant forms
                            and abbreviated characters, adding to the picture of typological and
                            stylistic fuzziness.</p>
                        <p>The four title characters of the “Stele of Sire Serenity” (HDS 15) are
                            written in seal script. This script type was commonly used in stele
                            heads (<hi rend="italic">bei’e</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">碑額</foreign>) and on tomb stones during the
                            Northern dynasties.<note>For stele heads in seal script see <ref target="Ledderose1970" type="biblio">46-50</ref>.</note> In the
                            sixth century, a rustic style with decorative, sometimes fancy strokes,
                            as on the <title>Stele for Gao Zhen</title>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">高貞碑</foreign> of 523,<note>Stone kept in the
                                Shandong Stone Carving Art Museum in Jinan.</note> and on the stele,
                            which Lou Rui <foreign xml:lang="zh">婁睿</foreign> had made around 560,<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="LiYuqun2012">plates 9 and 11</ref>.</note>
                            developed into a smoother and more angular style, as on the <title>Stele for Meng Xianda</title>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">孟顯達碑</foreign> of 600.<note>Stone in the Xi’an Beilin Museum. Illustration of rubbing in <ref type="biblio" target="Nishikawa1966">pl. 35</ref>.</note> The seal script
                            title of HDS 15 is already closer to the latter.</p>
                        <p>According to character size and depth of carving, the inscriptions can be
                            divided into three groups that, by and large, coincide with the content
                            of the texts. Buddha names are written in large characters, some more
                            than a meter in height. Exceptionally large is HDS 8; its first
                            character <hi rend="italic">da</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">大</foreign> measures 4 meters in width. The large
                            characters are deeply carved and the strokes are often given a special
                            structure. The three dimensional effect of superimposed strokes and of
                            flying white (HDS 8, 1/1-4; HDS 9.1, 1/1; HDS 9.2, 1/1) is only used
                            for the Buddha names. They can have double contour carving. The name
                            Seng’an Daoyi is also written in these large characters (HDS 4);
                            apparently there was no lack of self confidence on the part of this
                            monk.</p>
                        <p>Sutra texts are written with medium size characters in imaginary squares
                            measuring about 20 centimeters in height and width. The carving is
                            shallower than that of the Buddha names. The smallest characters tend to
                            be those of historical inscriptions, including the signatures. They are
                            often barely higher than 10 centimeters. The carving is shallow, and
                            consequently more effaced and harder to decipher. As a result, these
                            inscriptions are especially difficult to reconstruct because, unlike the
                            Buddha names and the sutra passages, such texts with historical content
                            have not been transmitted in other manuscripts or printed versions with
                            which they might be compared.</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>LL</abbr>
                        </ab><!--figure rend="page" n="figure" xml:id="HDS_r_12_total_IMG_0411.JPG">
                            <head>The carved characters “Buddha Great Mountain Cliff” (HDS 12)
                                imitating the traces of a brush; photograph taken in 2004</head>
                            <head xml:lang="zh">“大山巖佛”（洪頂山12號）模仿書法用筆的佛名石刻，2004年照片</head>
                            <graphic url="HDS_r_12_total_IMG_0411.JPG"/>
                        </figure-->
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>