<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/rest/db/schema/stone.xsd">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Introduction to the site of Wofoyuan</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>N.N.</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>15.02.2012</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>file established</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:id="Site_WFY">
        <body>
            <div xml:lang="zh">
                <head>臥佛院</head>
                <p/>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="en">
                <head>Wofoyuan</head>
                    <figure xml:id="Wfy_001.jpg">
                        <head/>
                        <graphic url="Wfy_001.jpg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>The cave temples at Wofoyuan in Anyue county <foreign xml:lang="zh">安岳</foreign>, the by far largest site of Buddhist cliff carvings in Sichuan province, host sacred Buddhist texts taken from twenty-one sutras, which are 
                        distributed over the interior walls of fifteen caves that were cut out of the rock for that purpose around the Kaiyuan <foreign xml:lang="zh">開元</foreign> era (713-741) of the 
                        Tang dynasty. 
                    </p>
                    <p>The entire site of Wofoyuan encompasses 125 caves and open niches. While some of the caves are seemingly unfinished or left empty, the niches stretching along the cliffs 
                        in between the cave entrances display very fine examples of Sichuanese Tang sculptures. Most impressive is the Giant Reclining Buddha situated at the north cliff, 
                        a twenty-three meter long statue representing <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign> Buddha entering final <foreign xml:lang="sa">nirvāṇa</foreign>, surrounded by his disciples and the eight dragon kings <foreign xml:lang="zh">八龍王</foreign>. 
                        The Buddha’s final nirvāṇa thus provides the <hi rend="italic">leitmotif</hi> for the entire site, and is also reflected in the selection of carved text passages, in the first 
                        place in the chapters taken from the <title xml:lang="en" type="translated">
                            <hi rend="italic">Sutra of the Great Decease</hi>
                        </title> (<title xml:lang="sa">
                            <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mahāparinirvāṇa-sūtra</foreign>
                            </hi>
                        </title>
                        <title xml:lang="zh">
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">佛說大般涅槃經</foreign>
                        </title>), 
                        but also in selected passages from other scriptures.</p>
                </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>