<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/rest/db/schema/stone.xsd">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Introduction to the site of Mount Tao</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>N.N.</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <!-- Titel und Kürzel des Bandes in @n -->
                <title n="shandong_volume3" xml:lang="en">Shandong Volume 3</title>
                <title n="shandong_volume3" xml:lang="zh">山東省第三卷</title>
                <!-- Ordnungsnummer für Kapitelreihenfolge in @n -->
                <biblScope unit="chapter" n="10"/>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>23.01.2012</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>File angelegt</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:id="Site_TS">
        <body>
            <div xml:lang="zh">
                <head>陶<space n="2"/>山</head>
                <p>陶山和龍山是山東佛教摩崖刻經最南端的兩座山。陶山的銘刻僅於1997年引起學術界的關注。除了一個無法辨認的經主名外，只有兩佛名及“般若波羅蜜”之稱名可辨識。然而這三個稱名的組合，讓我們對於僧人對“空觀”的理解及其佛教宇宙的理念，得出影響深遠的結論。</p>
                <ab>
                    <abbr>雷德侯</abbr>
                </ab>
                <figure xml:id="Tao_sc_TaoS-View_total_G7SB7582.jpg" rend="full">
                    <head>Mount Tao seen from the south; photograph taken in 2007</head>
                    <head xml:lang="zh">陶山南面全景。2007年拍攝</head>
                    <graphic url="Tao_sc_TaoS-View_total_G7SB7582.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <div>
                    <head>空間</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>地理位置</head>
                        <p>陶山隸屬滕州市羊莊鎮，位於滕州市東南方23公里，棗莊市東北偏北15公里。該山座落於一排串珠狀山頭的最北端。山體呈山頂平坦的<!--截頂-->橢圓錐體，南北長0.7公里左右。其山峰高於四周平地約100米，海拔高度170米左右。薛河蜿蜒環繞山體成半圓，再繼續流向西南方。陶山地理位置是東經117.3321度，北緯34.9324度，相當於UTM坐標系統第50S帶，東行530330，北行386500。</p>
                        <p>我們調查這個刻經址時，偶然發現了一些具有五千年以上歷史的大汶口文化的陶瓷碎片。罕見近期人跡建築，唯有西邊山脚建了一些屬於西陶山村的房子。</p>
                        <p>附近刻有佛教銘刻的龍山位於西南方5.7公里處。從陶山可看到龍山，但無法見到其刻經址，因它位於山峰的另一邊。鄒城周邊最南方的刻經山嶧山，距離陶山西北偏北方51.7公里。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>史英</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>地形與空間構成</head>
                        <p>陶山平坦的山頂，有一塊約20×40米見方的光滑石坪，該石坪自南至北逐漸往下傾斜。其石灰岩層的山頂風化成梯形狀。銘文刊刻於石坪北面略微偏東處，朝向東北偏北。經主名號刻於右側，即佛名之西。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>温狄婭</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <figure xml:id="TS-Map_2007.jpg" rend="left">
                            <head>Map of the summit of Mount Tao</head>
                            <head xml:lang="zh">陶山山頂等高綫圖</head>
                            <graphic url="TS-Map_2007.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                        <figure xml:id="Tao_r_total_G7SB7492.jpg" rend="center">
                            <head>Mount Tao, northern end of the summit’s plateau with the
                                inscriptions in the foreground; photograph taken in 2007</head>
                            <head xml:lang="zh">陶山山頂石坪的北端及刻銘。2007年拍攝</head>
                            <graphic url="Tao_r_total_G7SB7492.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>地名</head>
                        <p>陶山，又名華彩山。<note>安廷山 <ref type="biblio" target="AnTingshan1997">第134頁</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>賴非</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>時間</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>相關寺院</head>
                        <p>柱孔遍布於梯狀石灰岩山頂，大部分爲圓孔。直徑最長43釐米，最短8釐米，中等尺寸爲16釐米，其中有兩個大約19×44釐米的矩形孔眼（<ptr target="Tao_r_TaoS-PV_detail_G7SB7575.jpg"/>
                            ）。這些都可證明此處曾有建築物。至今没有找到關於其年代的信息。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>賴非</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>相關人物</head>
                        <p>
                            <anchor xml:id="TS_SenganDaoyi_zh"/>安廷山提出，經主名可釋讀爲“安公”，並藉此將陶山的銘刻與山東刻經址的關鍵人物即僧人書法家“僧安道壹”（活動於562－579
                                年）聯繫起來。<note> 安廷山 <ref type="biblio" target="AnTingshan1997">第135頁</ref>。</note>除此，未見他説。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>温狄婭</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>斷代</head>
                        <p>刻銘無紀年，不過其書法風格近似山東省其他刻銘，例如洪頂山（洪頂山9.10號和洪頂山16.2號；550－564年）、<note>《中國佛教石經•山東省》第一卷，<ref type="biblio" target="Shandong_1">第191－194頁和第255－261頁</ref>。</note>徂徠山（徂徠山2號和徂徠山9號；570年）<note>見本卷徂徠山“刻銘”。</note>及鐵山（鐵山1號；579年）。<note>《中國佛教石經•山東省》第二卷，<ref type="biblio" target="Shandong_2">第117－147頁</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>研究史</head>
                        <p>陶山的銘刻不爲清代金石學家所知。安廷山於1997年發表的《山東摩崖書刻藝術》首次深入探討， <note>安廷山<ref type="biblio" target="AnTingshan1997"/>。</note>該書主要關注佛教與道教的摩崖書刻藝術。後來對此刻經址的調查，未增加新資料。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>温狄婭</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>刻銘</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>總目</head>
                        <p>陶山刊刻二佛名及一“般若波羅蜜”稱名（陶山1號），此外還有一則題記（陶山2號）。</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>佛名</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>陶山1號</head>
                            <p>
                                <anchor xml:id="Tao_intro_Bn_zh"/>以三名爲一組直行書寫，自右至左並排刊刻阿弥陁佛、觀世音佛及般若波羅蜜。這兩個亦刊刻於洪頂山和徂徠山的佛名，確立了觀世音佛爲現在西方净土世界阿彌陀佛的直接繼任者的身份。</p>
                            <p>如本卷上文所示，<note>見徂徠山“刻銘”部分，<ptr type="infra" target="Culai_buddhas_zh Culai_buddhas_end_zh"/>。</note>
                                    觀世音佛（和大勢至佛）繼承阿彌陀佛的説法出自三部經典，即《悲華經》的兩個漢譯本<note>《悲華經》T#157，3：167－233c8。《大乘悲分陀利經》T#158，3：233c13－289a。</note>
                                    和《觀世音菩薩授記經》。<note>《觀世音菩薩授記經》T#371，12：353b5－357c17。</note>
                                    此外，至少還有一部未入藏的經典描述觀世音成佛的事迹，<anchor xml:id="TenVows_zh"/>即《觀世音十大願經》，又名《弘猛慧海經》。<note>“《觀世音十大願經》一卷。仁壽録云：一名‘大悲觀世音經’，具題云‘大悲觀世音弘猛慧海十大願品第七百’。”《開元釋教録》T#2154，55：675b12－13。</note>首次提及此經的《歴代三寶紀》稱該經屬於“大乘修多羅，
                                    失譯”，<note>《歴代三寶紀》T#2034，49：113c5。</note>隋代及後來的藏經目録均標示此經爲疑僞經。<note>《衆經目録》T#2146，55：126b22－23，法經（生卒年不詳）撰。《衆經目録》T#2147，55：172c13－14，
                                    彦琮（活動於七世紀中）於602年完成。《大周刊定眾經目録》T#2153，55：472c8－9，明佺（卒於712年之後）撰。《開元釋教録》T#2154，55：675b12－13。</note><!--</p>
                            <p>-->經文描述名爲善光太子者，得空王觀世音佛授記於未來成佛，發願於未來行菩薩道時名觀世音。這十大願中的兩項明顯涉及波若，即“乘波若船”和“得智慧風”。</p>
                            <p>《觀世音十大願經》這部疑僞經的佚文僅存於佛典的抄引節文<note>慧沼（650－714）的《十一面神咒心經義疏》T#1802,
                                    39：1004b－1011c13是玄奘（約602－664）譯《十一面神呪心經》T#1071, 20:
                                    152–55之註解本，該義疏引用了十大願。十大願引文的開頭：“弘猛海慧經曰：昔此閻浮提有王名曰善首，有五百王子，第一太子名善光。値空王觀世音佛乃發十願。”T#1802，39：1006c27－1007a1。吉藏（549－623）所撰的四部關於《法華經》的註疏，其中最早的一部《法華玄論》T#1720，34：361a－450c指出“弘猛海惠經明，觀音過去世値空王觀世音佛發願，願未來名觀世音。”
                                    T#1720，34：449a29－449b1。</note>以及兩處石刻。<note>河北涉縣木井寺一石碑上所刻《遺教經》本包含觀世音十大願。該碑紀年573年，十大願刊刻於碑側，題爲“大悲觀世音願”。河北曲陽縣八會寺南側佛龕東面的弘猛海慧經觀音願之下，也有刊刻於隋朝的十大願（題記紀年593年）。馬忠理<ref type="biblio" target="MaZhongli2006b">第43頁</ref>。倉本尚德<ref type="biblio" target="Kuramoto2011a">第229、232頁</ref>。倉本尚德<ref type="biblio" target="Kuramoto2011b">第11－12頁</ref>。倉本尚德<ref type="biblio" target="Kuramoto2016">第464、467頁</ref>。氣賀澤保規<ref type="biblio" target="Kegasawa2009b"/>。趙洲<ref type="biblio" target="ZhaoZhou2010a">第22頁</ref>。倉本尚德<ref type="biblio" target="Kuramoto2011a">第228、232頁</ref>。倉本尚德<ref type="biblio" target="Kuramoto2016">第460、467－468頁</ref>。</note>徂徠山及陶山摩崖石刻刊刻時，此經已流通。因此它可能是理解觀世音佛和在陶山刊刻於其側的般若波羅蜜二者關係的關鍵。</p>
                            <p>般若波羅蜜是指與成佛有關的智慧，是菩薩道上修行六波羅蜜的第六法，且經常等同於對“空性”的理解。般若波羅蜜亦被擬人化，刊刻於另外兩個佛名之側。它是智慧的召唤，而此智慧又稱佛母，是成就圓覺不可缺少的要件。</p>
                            <!--<?pb?>-->
                            <p>山東另外三個刻經址的佛名緊鄰般若經節文。洪頂山的佛名群組（洪頂山9.1－9.15號；洪頂山10－13號）刊刻於《文殊師利所説般若波羅蜜經》<note>《文殊師利所説摩訶般若波羅蜜經》T#232，8：731a15－21。《文殊師利所説般若波羅蜜經》T#233，8：738a19－24。洪頂山16.2號。</note>九十八字節文之下及側面，該經叙述佛陀爲文殊師利闡明般若波羅蜜。<note>關於這段節文，見《中國佛教石經•山東省》第一卷，<ref type="biblio" target="Shandong_1">第65頁和第255－261頁</ref>。</note>徂徠山光化寺附近有一刊刻節録自《摩訶般若波羅蜜經》<note>《摩訶般若波羅蜜經》T#223，8：250b3－7。</note>十七空節文的巨石，據説現已不存的佛名（徂徠山9號和徂徠山10號）原刊刻於此巨石附近，或直接刻於此巨石之上
                                    。在這些刻經址，大空王佛刻銘始終緊鄰闡述般若波羅蜜及其相同的概念<hi rend="dash">──</hi>空（洪頂山8號和徂徠山10號）的佛經節文。尖山也是如此，其九十八字節文（尖山6號）刻於大空王佛名（尖山10號）之上。<note>見<ptr target="JS_reconstruction_whole_RGB_final_version.jpg"/>。</note>如此排列，更加强化了佛名與“般若波羅蜜”或“空”這個教法的密切聯繫。</p>
                            <p>陶山的佛名排序與原本刊刻於徂徠山巨石的佛名順序相近。徂徠山巨石“大空王佛”（徂徠山10號）在“觀世音佛”（徂徠山9號）之後。而陶山“觀世音佛”佛名之後接續的是“般若波羅蜜”，顯示此名與其他刻經址著名的“大空王佛”地位相等。<anchor xml:id="Tao_intro_Bn_end_zh"/>
                            </p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>温狄婭</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>題記</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>陶山2號</head>
                            <p>這則題記只有開頭的“經主”二字清晰可辨。由此或可推測，除佛名外，此處曾另刻一段佛經節文，或至少曾有刊刻計劃。<note>賴非<ref type="biblio" target="LaiFei2004">第116頁</ref>。</note>洪頂山“大空王佛”（洪頂山21.1號）刻銘的題記可供比較。該題記爲小字“經主釋法洪供□”（洪頂山21.2號）。<note>《中國佛教石經•山東省》第一卷，<ref type="biblio" target="Shandong_1">第284－292頁</ref>。</note>佛名與題記似乎自成一組，但事實上，這則題記涉及刊刻於其右側的佛經節文（洪頂山22號）。<note>《中國佛教石經•山東省》第一卷，<ref type="biblio" target="Shandong_1">第71頁，圖8</ref>。</note>根據這個比較，也許可提出陶山亦曾刻有佛經節文的假設。</p>
                            <p>陶山的經主名風化嚴重，無法確認上文所及安廷山的釋讀。<note> 安廷山 <ref type="biblio" target="AnTingshan1997">第135頁</ref>。</note>
                            </p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>温狄婭</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>刊刻技法</head>
                        <p>陶山刻經技法爲“V”字型刻法，即從筆畫兩邊綫斜入鏨，雙邊綫相交，自然形成。 </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>賴非</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <!-- <div>
                        <head>書法藝術</head>
                        <p/>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>温狄婭</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>-->
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="en">
                <head>Mount Tao</head>
                <p>Mount Tao <foreign xml:lang="zh">陶山</foreign> and Mount Long <foreign xml:lang="zh">龍山</foreign> are the southernmost mountains in Shandong with
                    engraved Buddhist inscriptions. Mount Tao’s inscriptions were brought to the
                    attention of the scholarly world only in 1997. In addition to the unidentifiable
                    name of a donor, only two Buddha names and an invocation of the Perfection of
                        <hi rend="nh">Wisdom</hi><!--an abbreviated sutra title -->have been
                    recognized. Yet the combination of these three invocations allows far-reaching
                    conclusions about the monks’ understanding of the concept of Emptiness and their
                    ideas about the Buddhist cosmos.</p>
                <ab>
                    <abbr>LL</abbr>
                </ab>
                <div>
                    <head>Space</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Location</head>
                        <p>Mount Tao is within the Yangzhuang Township <foreign xml:lang="zh">羊莊鎮</foreign>, under the city of Tengzhou <foreign xml:lang="zh">滕州市</foreign>. It is located 23 km southeast of Tengzhou City and
                            15 km to the north-northeast of Zaozhuang City <foreign xml:lang="zh">棗莊市</foreign>. The mountain is the northernmost peak in a row of
                            outcrops that follow each other like beads on a string. It is shaped
                            like an evenly truncated elliptical cone with a north-south extension of
                            about 0.7 km. Its peak, rising about 100 m above the mostly flat
                            surrounding area, is ca. 170 m above sea level. The River Xue <foreign xml:lang="zh">薛河</foreign> winds its way around the mountain in a
                            semicircle and continues in a southwestern direction. Mount Tao’s
                            geographic location is 117.3321° east and 34.9324° north WGS84. This
                            equals 530330 E (easting) and 386500 N (northing) on the meridian 50S
                            UTM. </p>
                        <p>During our survey of the inscription site, we came across some ceramic
                            sherds of the Dawenkou culture <foreign xml:lang="zh">大汶口文化</foreign>,
                            more than five thousand years in age. There has been little human
                            activity in recent times. Houses in West Mount Tao Village <foreign xml:lang="zh">西陶山村</foreign> have been built at the western foot of
                            the mountain.</p>
                        <p>The neighboring mountain with a Buddhist inscription, Mount Long, is 5.7
                            km to the southwest. It is visible from Mount Tao, but its inscription
                            site is not, as it lies beyond the peak. The southernmost of the
                            inscribed mountains around Zoucheng, Mount Yi <foreign xml:lang="zh">嶧山</foreign>, is at a distance of 51.7 km to the north-northwest of
                            Mount Tao.</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>TS</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Topography and Spatial Grouping</head>
                        <p>On the flat mountain summit, a plateau of smooth rock, ca. 20 x 40
                            meters, slopes gently down from south to north. The layers of the
                            limestone sediment have weathered into steps. The inscriptions are
                            engraved on the plateau at the northeast. They face north-northeast. A
                            reference to a donor is on the right, that is, to the west of the Buddha
                            names.</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>CW</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Place Name </head>
                        <p>Mount Tao is also called Mount Huacai <foreign xml:lang="zh">華彩</foreign>.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="AnTingshan1997">134</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>LF</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <figure xml:id="Tao_sc_TaoS-View_total_G7SB7520.jpg" rend="center">
                            <head>Looking southwest from the summit’s plateau; photograph taken in
                                2007</head>
                            <head xml:lang="zh">由陶山山頂石坪眺望西南方。2007年拍攝</head>
                            <graphic url="Tao_sc_TaoS-View_total_G7SB7520.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Time</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Related monasteries</head>
                        <p>Post holes are distributed over the entire summit on the stepped
                            limestone. Most are circular. The largest diameter is 43 cm, the
                            smallest 8 cm, the mean is 16 cm, and there are two rectangular holes of
                            ca. 19 x 44 cm (fig. <ptr target="Tao_r_TaoS-PV_detail_G7SB7575.jpg"/>).
                            All these are evidence that buildings once stood here. As yet, no
                            information on their age is available. </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>LF</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Related Persons </head>
                        <p>
                            <anchor xml:id="TS_SenganDaoyi"/>An Tingshan <foreign xml:lang="zh">安廷山</foreign> has suggested that the name of the sutra donor could
                            be read as “Sire An” (Angong <foreign xml:lang="zh">安公</foreign>). This
                            identification enabled him to connect the carvings at Mount Tao with the
                            key figure of the Shandong sites, the monk calligrapher Seng’an Daoyi
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">僧安道壹</foreign> (fl. 562–579).<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="AnTingshan1997">135</ref>.</note> Apart
                            from this suggestion, no other proposals have been made.</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>CW</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <figure xml:id="Tao_sc_TaoS-View_total_G7SB7523.jpg" rend="center">
                            <head>Looking southeast from the summit’s plateau; photograph taken in
                                2007</head>
                            <head xml:lang="zh">由陶山山頂石坪眺望東南方。2007年拍攝</head>
                            <graphic url="Tao_sc_TaoS-View_total_G7SB7523.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Dating</head>
                        <p>The inscriptions are undated. However, the calligraphic style is close to
                            that of other Shandong inscriptions, such as those on Mount Hongding
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">洪頂山</foreign> (HDS 9.10, HDS 16.2; dated
                                    550–564),<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Shandong_1">191–194,
                                    255–261</ref>.</note> Mount Culai <foreign xml:lang="zh">徂徠山</foreign> (CLS 2, CLS 9; dated 570),<note>See the present
                                volume, Mount Culai, Inscriptions.</note> and Mount Tie <foreign xml:lang="zh">鐵山</foreign> (Tie 1; dated 579).<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Shandong_2">117–147</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>CW</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Research History</head>
                        <p>The inscriptions at Mount Tao were not known to the epigraphers of the
                            eighteenth and nineteenth centuries. The first thorough study was
                            undertaken by An Tingshan <foreign xml:lang="zh">安廷山</foreign> in his
                            1997 publication on <hi rend="italic">The Art of Calligraphic Engravings
                                on Polished Cliffs in Shandong</hi>,<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="AnTingshan1997"/>.</note> a work that is primarily
                            concerned with the calligraphy of the Buddhist and Daoist polished cliff
                            inscriptions. Later surveys of the site have not added substantially to
                            this information. </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>CW</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Inscriptions</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Inventory</head>
                        <p>At Mount Tao two Buddha names and one invocation of the Perfection of
                            Wisdom (TS 1) were carved, and, in addition, a colophon (TS 2).</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Buddha Names</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>TS 1</head>
                            <p>
                                <anchor xml:id="Tao_intro_Bn"/>Three vertically written, parallel
                                engravings are aligned from right to left, Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha </foreign> (Amituo fo <foreign xml:lang="zh">阿弥陀佛</foreign>), Buddha Perceiver of the World’s
                                Sounds (Guanshiyin fo <foreign xml:lang="zh">觀世音佛</foreign>), and
                                Perfection of Wisdom (<hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">prajñāpāramitā</foreign>
                                </hi>, <hi rend="italic">bore
                                    boluomi </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">般若波羅蜜</foreign>). The two
                                Buddha names, which are also carved at Mount Hongding and Mount
                                Culai, establish the position of the Buddha Perceiver of the World’s
                                Sounds as the immediate successor of Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> in the latter’s Pure Land in the West.</p>
                            <p>As shown earlier in this volume,<note>See the Introduction to Mount
                                    Culai, Inscriptions, pp. <ptr type="infra" target="Culai_buddhas Culai_buddhas_end"/>.</note> the
                                succession of Buddha Perceiver of the World’s Sounds (and the Buddha
                                Great Power Obtained; <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mahā­sthāma­prāpta</foreign>; Dashizhi <foreign xml:lang="zh">大勢至佛</foreign>) to <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> is
                                based on three canonical sutras, namely two Chinese translations of
                                the <hi rend="italic">Sutra of the Compassionate Lotus Flower</hi>
                                (T#157 and T#158), and the <hi rend="italic">Sutra of Bodhisattva
                                    Perceiver of the World’s Sounds Receiving a Prophecy</hi>
                                (T#371). In addition, at least one non-canonical scripture narrates
                                the circumstances of the Bodhisattva Perceiver of the World’s Sounds
                                becoming a Buddha.<anchor xml:id="TenVows"/> This is the <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Ten Great Vows taken by the Perceiver
                                    of the World’s Sounds</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Guanshiyin shi da
                                    yuan jing </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">觀世音十大願經</foreign>), which
                                is also known under the title, <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Vast
                                    and Fierce Ocean-like Wisdom</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Hong­meng
                                    huihai jing </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">弘猛慧海經</foreign>).<note>See the <hi rend="italic">Kaiyuan Era
                                        Catalog of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign>’s
                                        Teachings</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Kaiyuan shijiao lu
                                        </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">開元釋教録</foreign>): “<hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Ten Great Vows taken by the
                                        Perceiver of the World’s Sounds</hi>, in one scroll. The <hi rend="italic">Catalog of the Renshou Era</hi> [T#2147,
                                    completed in 602 by Yancong <foreign xml:lang="zh">彥琮</foreign>
                                    (557–610) and others] says: Another name for this sutra is <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Great Compassionate Perceiver of
                                        the World’s Sounds</hi>. The full title is <hi rend="italic">Sutra on Ten Great Vows of the Vast and Fierce Ocean-like
                                        Wisdom Taken by the Great Compassionate Perceiver of the
                                        World’s Sounds</hi>, in 700 chapters. <foreign xml:lang="zh">《觀世音十大願經》一卷。</foreign>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">仁壽録云：“‘一名大悲觀世音經’，具題云：大悲觀世音弘猛慧海十大願品第七百</foreign>。” (T#2154,
                                    55: 675b12–13).</note> This text is first mentioned as a
                                “Mahayana Sutra; translator’s [name] lost”;<note>See the <hi rend="italic">Record of the Three Jewels in Successive
                                        Dynasties</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Lidai sanbao ji
                                        </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">歷代三寶紀</foreign>), T#2034, 49:
                                    113c5: <foreign xml:lang="zh">“大乘修多羅失譯。”</foreign>
                                </note> Sui
                                dynasty and later catalogs label it as apocryphal (<hi rend="italic">yiwei </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh"> 疑僞</foreign>).<note>See the
                                        <hi rend="italic">Catalog of All Canonical Scriptures</hi>
                                        (<hi rend="italic">Zhongjing mulu </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">眾經目録</foreign>) by Fajing <foreign xml:lang="zh">法經</foreign> (dates unknown) at T#2146, 55:
                                    126b22–23; the <hi rend="italic">Catalog of All Canonical
                                        Scriptures</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Zhongjing mulu
                                        </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">眾經目録</foreign>), completed in
                                    602 by Yancong <foreign xml:lang="zh">彥琮</foreign> (mid-seventh
                                    century) at T#2147, 55: 172c13–14); and the <hi rend="italic">Catalog of All Canonical Scriptures, Authorized by the
                                        Great Zhou</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Da Zhou kanding zhongjing
                                        mulu </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">大周刊定眾經目録</foreign>) by
                                    Mingquan <foreign xml:lang="zh">明佺</foreign> (d. after 712) at
                                    T#2153, 55: 472c8–9, as well as the above mentioned <hi rend="italic">Kaiyuan Era Catalog of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign>’s Teachings</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Kaiyuan shijiao lu </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">開元釋教録</foreign>) at T#2154, 55: 675b12–13.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>The text narrates, how a certain Prince Shan­guang <foreign xml:lang="zh">善光</foreign> received the prophecy about his
                                future Buddhahood from a Buddha called “Buddha King of Emptiness
                                Perceiver of the World’s Sounds <foreign xml:lang="zh">空王觀世音佛</foreign>”, and thereupon vowed to be called “Perceiver
                                of the World’s Sounds” in a future life, when following the
                                bodhisattva path. Two of the ten vows that he took are explicitly
                                concerned with wisdom (<hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">prajñā</foreign>
                                </hi>; <hi rend="italic">bore </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">波若</foreign>), namely to “sail the boat of wisdom”
                                    (<hi rend="italic">cheng bore chuan </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">乘波若船</foreign>) and to “catch the wind of wisdom” (<hi rend="italic">de zhihui feng </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">得智慧風</foreign>). </p>
                            <p> The apocryphal <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Ten Great Vows taken
                                    by the Perceiver of the World’s Sounds</hi> has only survived in
                                quotations in other works of the Buddhist Canon,<note>The ten vows
                                    are quoted in <hi rend="italic">The Meanings of the Heart of the
                                        Incantation of the Eleven-Faced One</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Shiyi mian shenzhou xin jing yishu </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">十一面神咒心經義疏</foreign>), which is a commentary by
                                    Huizhao <foreign xml:lang="zh">慧沼</foreign> (650–714) on
                                    Xuanzang’s <foreign xml:lang="zh">玄奘</foreign> (ca. 602–664)
                                    translation of the <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Heart of the
                                        Incantation of the Eleven-Faced One</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Shiyi mianshenzhou xin jing </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">十一面神咒心經</foreign>; T#1071, 20: 152–55). The beginning of
                                    the quote on the ten vows reads: “The <hi rend="italic">Sutra on
                                        the Vast and Fierce Ocean-like Wisdom</hi> says: ‘Once, a
                                    king, by the name of Shanshou <foreign xml:lang="zh">善首</foreign>, lived in this <foreign xml:lang="sa">Jambudvīpa</foreign>, who had five hundred sons. The
                                    first-born son, by the name of Shanguang <foreign xml:lang="zh">善光</foreign>, met Buddha King of Emptiness Perceiver of the
                                    World’s Sounds, and, thereupon, took ten vows…<foreign xml:lang="zh">弘猛海慧經曰∶昔此閻浮提有王名曰善首，有五百王子，第一太子名善光。值空王觀世音佛乃發十願。</foreign>’”
                                    (T#1802, 39: 1006c27–1007a1). In his first of four commentaries
                                    on the <hi rend="italic">Lotus Sutra</hi>, <hi rend="italic">The
                                        Treatise on the Profundity of the [Sutra on the] Lotus [of
                                        the Wonderful] Law</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Fahua xuanlun
                                        </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">法華玄論</foreign>; T#1720, 34:
                                    361a–450c), Jizang <foreign xml:lang="zh">吉藏</foreign> (549–623)
                                    also points out that “the <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Vast
                                        and Fierce Ocean-like Wisdom</hi> explains that, in the
                                    past, Perceiver of the [World’s] Sounds met Buddha King of
                                    Emptiness Perceiver of the World’s Sounds and made a vow. He
                                    vowed to be called ‘Perceiver of the World’s Sounds’ in a future
                                        life.<foreign xml:lang="zh">弘猛海惠經明，觀音過去世值空王觀世音佛發願，願未來名觀世音。</foreign>” (T#1720, 34:
                                    449a29–449b1).</note> and in two stone-cut versions.<note>
                                    <ref type="biblio" target="MaZhongli2006b">43</ref>, <ref type="biblio" target="Kuramoto2011a">229, 232</ref>, <ref type="biblio" target="Kuramoto2011b">11–12</ref>, and <ref type="biblio" target="Kuramoto2016">464, 467</ref> say that
                                    the version of the <hi rend="italic">Sutra of the Teaching Left
                                        Behind [by the Buddha]</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Yijiao
                                        jing</hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">遺教經</foreign>), carved on a
                                    stele at Mujing Monastery <foreign xml:lang="zh">木井寺</foreign>
                                    in She County <foreign xml:lang="zh">涉縣</foreign>, Hebei,
                                    contains the wording of these ten great vows of Perceiver of the
                                    World’s Sounds. This stele is dated to the year 573, and the
                                    text of the ten vows is found on its narrow right side, under
                                    the title “Vows of the Great Compassionate Perceiver of the
                                    World’s Sounds” (“Da bei Guanshiyin yuan” <foreign xml:lang="zh">大悲觀世音願</foreign>). The ten great vows were also carved
                                    during the Sui dynasty at Bahui Monastery <foreign xml:lang="zh">八會寺</foreign> in Quyang County <foreign xml:lang="zh">曲陽縣</foreign>, Hebei (colophon dated 593). Here, they are
                                    found on the east side of the southern niche, under the heading,
                                        <hi rend="italic">Vows taken by the Perceiver of the
                                        [World’s] Sounds from the Sutra on the Vast and Fierce
                                        Ocean-like Wisdom</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Hongmeng huihai
                                        jing Guanyin yuan </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">弘猛慧海經觀音願</foreign>); see <ref type="biblio" target="Kegasawa2009b"/>; <ref type="biblio" target="ZhaoZhou2010a">22</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="Kuramoto2011a">228, 232</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="Kuramoto2016">460, 467–468</ref>.</note> The sutra
                                was already in circulation when the cliff inscriptions at Mount
                                Culai and Mount Tao were
                                carved.<!--<note>The stele at Mujing Monastery <foreign xml:lang="zh">木井寺</foreign> in Shexian <foreign xml:lang="zh">涉縣</foreign>, which preserves the text of the ten vows, is dated to 573.</note>-->
                                It may thus hold the key for understanding the connection between
                                Buddha Perceiver of the World’s Sounds and the Perfection of Wisdom
                                    (<hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">prajñāpāramitā</foreign>
                                </hi>, <hi rend="italic">bore
                                    boluomi </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">般若波羅蜜</foreign>), carved
                                next to it on Mount Tao.</p>
                            <p>The Perfection of Wisdom is the wisdom associated with the
                                realization of Buddhahood. It is the sixth of the Six Perfections
                                practiced on the bodhisattva path, and often equated with the
                                knowledge of Emptiness. The Perfection of Wisdom was also
                                personified as its characters are carved alongside the other two
                                Buddha names. It is an evocation of the quality of wisdom, which is
                                said to be the mother of all Buddhas, indispensable for their
                                complete awakening.</p>
                            <figure xml:id="Tao_r_TaoS-PV_detail_G7SB7575.jpg" rend="center">
                                <head>Rectangular post-holes on the summit’s plateau; photograph
                                    taken in 2007</head>
                                <head xml:lang="zh">陶山山頂石坪的矩形柱洞。2007年拍攝</head>
                                <graphic url="Tao_r_TaoS-PV_detail_G7SB7575.jpg"/>
                            </figure>
                            <p>At three other Shandong inscription sites, Buddha names are placed
                                close to excerpts from <hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Prajñāpāramitā</foreign>
                                </hi> Sutras. At Mount Hongding,
                                groups of Buddha names (HDS 9.1–9.15; HDS 10–13) are located below
                                and next to the passage of 98 characters taken from the <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Great Perfection of Wisdom Spoken by
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mañjuśrī</foreign>
                                </hi> (<hi rend="italic">Wenshushili suo shuo boreboluomi jing
                                    </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">文殊師利所説般若波羅蜜經</foreign> T#232, 8:
                                731a15–21; T#233, 8: 738a19–24; HDS 16.2), in which the Buddha
                                explains <hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">prajñāpāramitā</foreign>
                                </hi> to <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mañjuśrī</foreign>.<note>For this sutra passage, see <ref type="biblio" target="Shandong_1">90–91 and
                                    255–261</ref>.</note> At Mount Culai, the now lost Buddha names
                                (CLS 9 and CLS 10) are said to have been placed close to or even on
                                the boulder near Guang­hua Monastery that is engraved with a passage
                                on the Seventeen Kinds of Emptiness taken from the <hi rend="italic">Great Perfection of Wisdom Sutra</hi> (<hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Pañca­viṃśatisāhasrikā­prajñā­pāramitā</foreign>
                                </hi>; <hi rend="italic">Mohe bore boluomi jing </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">摩訶般若波羅蜜經</foreign>; T#223, 8:
                                250b3–7).<!--<note>See the present volume, pp.</note>--> At these
                                sites, the name Buddha King of Great Emptiness (Da kong wang fo
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">大空王佛</foreign>) is carved close to sutra
                                passages that expound on the Perfection of Wisdom and its twin
                                concept, Emptiness (HDS 8 and CLS 10). The same is true for Mount
                                Jian, where the passage of 98 characters (JS 6) was once located
                                above the name Buddha King of Great Emptiness (JS 10).<note>See the
                                    present volume, Mount Jian, fig. <ptr target="JS_reconstruction_whole_RGB_final_version.jpg"/>.</note> This juxtaposition further strengthens the intimate
                                ties between Buddha names and the teachings of the Perfection of
                                Wisdom, or Emptiness.</p>
                            <p>The sequence of the names carved here at Mount Tao is closely akin to
                                that originally carved on the boulder at Mount Culai. There, the
                                name, Buddha King of Great Emptiness (CLS 10), follows the name,
                                Buddha Perceiver of the World’s Sounds (CLS 9). At Mount Tao,
                                instead the evocation of the Perfection of Wisdom follows the name,
                                Buddha Perceiver of the World’s Sounds, which indicates that the
                                Buddha King of Great Emptiness celebrated at other sites is
                                equivalent to the Perfection of Wisdom.<anchor xml:id="Tao_intro_Bn_end"/>
                            </p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>CW</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Colophon</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>TS 2</head>
                            <p>Only the first two characters of the colophon, reading “Sutra Donor”
                                are clearly legible. This title has given rise to the assumption
                                that, originally, in addition to the Buddha names, a sutra passage
                                was also carved, or at least envisioned.<note>
                                    <ref type="biblio" target="LaiFei2004">116</ref>.</note> The colophon to the
                                inscription “Buddha King of Great Emptiness” at Mount Hongding (HDS
                                21.1), is comparable. In small characters, it reads “Offered
                                [respectfully] by the Donor of Sutras, Venerable Fahong” (HDS
                                    21.2).<note>See <ref type="biblio" target="Shandong_1">284–292</ref>.</note> Although the Buddha name and the
                                colophon appear to form a single group, in fact, the colophon refers
                                to the sutra passage carved to its right (HDS 22).<note>See <ref type="biblio" target="Shandong_1">71, fig. 8</ref>.</note>
                                On the basis of this comparison, it may be possible to argue that
                                there was also a carved sutra passage at Mount Tao. </p>
                            <p>On Mount Tao, the name of the donor is heavily weathered;
                                consequently the reading by An Tingshan, mentioned above, cannot be
                                        confirmed.<note>
                                    <ref type="biblio" target="AnTingshan1997">135</ref>.</note>
                            </p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Carving Techniques</head>
                        <p>The carving technique is predominantly V-shaped. Slanting lines are
                            chiselled from both sides of a stroke, so that they intersect and the
                            stroke naturally takes shape.</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>LF</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>