<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/rest/db/schema/stone.xsd">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Introduction to the Site of Mount Ergu</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
    
    <seriesStmt>
        <!-- Titel und Kürzel des Bandes in @n -->
        <title n="shandong_volume1" xml:lang="en">Shandong Volume 1</title>
        <title n="shandong_volume1" xml:lang="zh">山東省第一卷</title>
        <!-- Ordnungsnummer für Kapitelreihenfolge in @n -->
        <biblScope unit="chapter" n="5"/>
    </seriesStmt> <publisher>N.N.</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>25.03.2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>JMP</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Aktualisierung Gliederung</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>31.03.2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Carving techniques korrigiert gemäß Markette</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>03.04.2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Abschnitt Location überarbeitet gemäß Markette</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>17.04.2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Abschnitt Related Monasteries eingefügt (vgl. Mount Dazhai)</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>1.09.2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>neue Gliederung des Abschnitts "Inscriptions" und Text eingefüllt</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>10.03.2011</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Abschnitt Related Monasteries geändert auf Verweis auf Mount Tianchi.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>22.11.2012</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Sanskrit terms marked as foreign xml:lang="sa"</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:id="Site_EG">
        <body>
            <div xml:lang="zh">
                <head>二鼓山</head>
                <figure xml:id="EG_r_part_DSCF0043.JPG" rend="full">
                    <head>Rocky ground of Mount Ergu; photograph taken in 2004</head>
                    <head xml:lang="zh">二鼓山岩石地表，2004年照片</head>
                    <graphic url="EG_r_part_DSCF0043.JPG"/>
                </figure>
                <div>
                    <head>空間</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>地理位置</head>
                        <p>二鼓山是魯中山脈中的另一處刻經點。二鼓山的梯形山坡在大寨谷之西緩緩地升起，它位於平陰縣西南25公里、聊城市東南47公里、東平縣北24公里處（見封二地圖）。 二鼓山山腳的海拔高度是100米。</p>
                        <p>二鼓山的地理位置是東經116.2694度，北緯36.1011度，相當於UTM坐標系統的第50S帶，東行434240，北行3995410。
                            二鼓山的摩崖石刻在山的東坡，面向西方（<ptr target="EG_w_3991.JPG"/>）。在大寨山谷的另一面，向東2.1公里，是天池山和書院東山摩崖石刻（地圖，<ptr target="Map_5_2013_01_29a.jpg"/>）。由於這兩座山的石刻分别面向西南偏西和西南，
                            這三處石刻皆相望所及。洪頂山在二鼓山西南僅5公里處，不過其間幾座山脊遮擋了視線。二鼓山東南偏南4.7公里處是雲翠山。其上的石刻在峰頂之下，並且面向西方，
                            因此該石刻原本應該在二鼓山遠眺視線所及之處，可是茂密的叢林阻擋了觀者的視線。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>史英</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>地形與空間構成</head>
                        <p>摩崖石刻位於二鼓山東麓一處稍微向南傾斜的坡岩之上。岩上曾經修築梯田。2011年，計劃在題刻之上修建一座維護性的建築。拆除緊鄰題刻北緣的壘石墻時，發現其下帶有紀年的五字題記（<ptr target="EG_r_part_DSCF0043.JPG"/>）。</p>
                        <p>有供養人姓名的題記位於佛名下方，而新發現的紀年則在佛名的右上方。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>溫狄婭</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>釋名</head>
                        <p>在洪範池鎮張海村西，兩座相鄰的山頭平如鼓，故曰“二鼓山”。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>賴非</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>時間</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>相關寺院</head>
                        <p>見天池山“導論”部分。</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>相關人物</head>
                        <p>四位供養人，即比丘僧太、比丘道顒、僧安一和程伯仁署名於“大空王佛”佛名之下方。其中比丘僧太，很可能還有道顒，也出現在雲翠山銘刻中（雲翠山2號）。</p>
                        <p>很明顯地，有一群可能來自當時濟州崇梵寺的僧人曾活躍於今平陰縣地區， 他們在二鼓山與雲翠山<hi rend="dash">──</hi>也可能還包括其他刻經點<hi rend="dash">──</hi>完成了較小規模的摩崖石刻。<note>賴非<ref type="biblio" target="LaiFei2003c">107</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>題刻中第三個人名“僧安一”的身份，頗有爭議。此名字可以單純讀作“僧·安一”，但大部分學者更傾向於認為他就是參與洪頂山、鐵山和尖山刻經的大沙門僧安道壹。<note>桐谷征一<ref type="biblio" target="Kiriya2003a">51, 74</ref>；賴非<ref type="biblio" target="LaiFei2003c">126</ref>；劉濤<ref target="LiuTao2003a" type="biblio">238</ref>；田熊信之<ref target="Takuma2003" type="biblio">188</ref>；許洪國<ref target="XuHongguo2003" type="biblio">245</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>第四個供養人程伯仁是一個俗家信徒的名字，有關其人，惜無跡可尋。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>雷德侯、蔡穗玲</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>斷代</head>
                        <p>該摩崖石刻的紀年為河清元年，即公元562年。在這條紀年重見天日之前，此處摩崖的刊刻年代一般根據書法風格被推斷為北齊時期（550-574）。那些認為此處石刻與僧安道壹（活躍於 562-579）有關的學者，
                            把二鼓山佛名題刻認作其具有早期風格的作品，因此推測石刻的刊刻年代為稍早於公元564年。<note>桐谷征一<ref type="biblio" target="Kiriya2003a">51, 74</ref>；賴非<ref type="biblio" target="LaiFei2003c">107</ref>。</note>紀年石刻的發現肯定了之前對刊刻年代的推斷。 </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>雷德侯，蔡穗玲</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>研究史</head>
                        <p>有關二鼓山的研究，主要見於山東省石刻藝術博物館編的《北朝摩崖刻經研究［續］》。在2003年出版的這一輯中，多次提及此處石刻，並討論題記中記載的僧人。在2006年出版的 《北朝摩崖刻經研究［三］》，楊浩也對此處石刻做了簡短描述。<note>楊浩、郝莉<ref type="biblio" target="Yang_Hao2006b">174</ref>。</note> 2011年發現了562年紀年題刻。 </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>溫狄婭</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>銘刻</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>銘文總數</head>
                        <p>二鼓山刊刻有一個佛名（二鼓山1號）及兩個題記（二鼓山2號及3號）。</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>佛名</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>二鼓山1號</head>
                            <p>有關佛名“大空王佛”的含義，見洪頂山佛名的相關說明。關於該佛名在山東省的分佈，見洪頂山8號的討論。 </p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>題記</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>二鼓山2號</head>
                            <p> 第一條題記包括三個僧名和一個居士名（<ptr target="EG_r_2_part_4022-2.jpg"/>）。無籍貫等相關信息。</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>二鼓山3號</head>
                            <p> 第二條題記由五個字組成，記錄了二鼓山摩崖石刻的紀年。</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>溫狄婭</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>刊刻技法</head>
                        <p>二鼓山摩崖石刻主要以“凵”形技法刊刻。刻工從筆畫的兩邊傾斜鑿入，在中間相交所自然形成的筆道。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>賴非</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>書法藝術</head>
                        <p>二鼓山所刻佛名，超過3米長，是山東境內三個最大的“大空王佛”石刻之一（洪頂山8號和尖山10號）。
                            這些巨大的佛名有一個共同的風格特徵，即“佛”字的最後兩個豎筆的頂端，形似所謂的“佛手”（見扉頁）。<note>桐谷征一<ref type="biblio" target="Kiriya2003a">71</ref>；北島信一<ref target="Kitajima2003" type="biblio">281</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>“佛”字的最後一個特長的筆畫，見天池山（天池山1號）的相關介紹。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>溫狄婭</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="en">
                <head>Mount Ergu</head>
                <div>
                    <head>Space</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Location</head>
                        <p>Mount Ergu <foreign xml:lang="zh">二鼓山</foreign> is another site in the
                            Shandong central ranges. The terraced slopes of Mount Ergu rise gently
                            to the west of Dazhai Valley <foreign xml:lang="zh">大寨谷</foreign>. It is
                            sited 25 km southwest of the county seat of Pingyin <foreign xml:lang="zh">平陰</foreign>, 47
                            km southeast of Liaocheng City <foreign xml:lang="zh">聊城市</foreign>, and 24 km
                            north of the county seat of Dongping <foreign xml:lang="zh">東平</foreign> (map in front endpaper). The foot of Mount Ergu is at an
                            altitude of 100 m above sea level. Apart from the stone walls terracing
                            the slope, there has been no recent interference with the inscribed
                            rock.</p>
                        <p>Geographically, Mount Ergu is situated 116.2694° east and 36.1011° north
                            WGS 84. This equals 434240 E (easting) and 3995410 N (northing) on the
                            meridian 50S UTM. Mount Ergu’s inscription can be found at the east side
                            of the mountain, facing west (fig. <ptr target="EG_w_3991.JPG"/>). On
                            the opposite side of Dazhai Valley, 2.1 km to the east, are the
                            inscription sites of Mount Tianchi <foreign xml:lang="zh">天池山</foreign>
                            and East Mount Shuyuan <foreign xml:lang="zh">書院東山</foreign> (map, fig.
                                <ptr target="Map_5_2013_01_29a.jpg"/>). Since the inscriptions of
                            both sites are facing west-southwest and southwest respectively, they
                            are within each other’s line of sight. The inscriptions of Mount
                            Hongding <foreign xml:lang="zh">洪頂山</foreign> are located only 5 km to
                            the southwest of Mount Ergu, but some mountain ridges block the view
                            from Mount Ergu to Mount Hongding. Mount Yuncui <foreign xml:lang="zh">雲翠山</foreign> lies 4.7 km to the south-southeast of Mount Ergu. Since its
                            inscriptions are situated underneath the mountain’s peak and face west,
                            they may be considered to be in the line of sight from Mount Ergu.
                            Nevertheless, the dense forest prohibits a clear view. </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>TS</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Topography and Spatial Grouping</head>
                        <p>The inscriptions are situated at the east side of the mountain, on a
                            section of bedrock sloping slightly toward the south. Terraces have been built into the slope. In 2011, a building was going to be erected over the inscription. When for this purpose
                            the wall of piled stones abutting the inscription to the north (fig. <ptr target="EG_r_part_DSCF0043.JPG"/>) was removed, five
                            characters with a date appeared beneath it.</p>
                        <p>The historical inscription is placed below the Buddha name, and the newly discovered date to its left.</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>CW</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Place Name</head>
                        <p>Located to the west of Zhanghai Village <foreign xml:lang="zh">張海村</foreign> of Hongfanchi Township <foreign xml:lang="zh">洪範池鎮</foreign>, the two adjoining mountains look like drums;
                            therefore the mountain is called “Two Drums Mountain”, Ergu Shan <foreign xml:lang="zh">二鼓山</foreign>.</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>LF</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <figure rend="center" xml:id="EG_w_3991.JPG">
                            <head>Documentation of the exact location of Mount Ergu’s inscriptions;
                                photograph taken in 2006</head>
                            <head xml:lang="zh">測繪二鼓山石刻的確切地理位置，2006年照片</head>
                            <graphic url="EG_w_3991.JPG"/>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Time</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Related Monasteries</head>
                        <p>See the introduction to Mount Tianchi <foreign xml:lang="zh">天池山</foreign>.</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>LF</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Related Persons</head>
                        <p>The names of four donors, namely <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">bhikṣu</foreign>
                            </hi> Sengtai <foreign xml:lang="zh">比丘僧太</foreign>, <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">bhikṣu</foreign>
                            </hi> Daoyong <foreign xml:lang="zh">比丘道顒</foreign>, Seng Anyi <foreign xml:lang="zh">僧安一</foreign>, and Cheng Boren <foreign xml:lang="zh">程伯仁</foreign>, are recorded in the colophon located beneath the
                            carved Buddha name, “Buddha King of Great Emptiness”. Sengtai <foreign xml:lang="zh">僧太</foreign>, and possibly Daoyong <foreign xml:lang="zh">道顒</foreign> are also known from
                            the colophon at Mount Yuncui <foreign xml:lang="zh">雲翠山</foreign>
                            (YC 2). </p>
                        <p>Apparently, a group of monks, probably from Chongfan Monastery <foreign xml:lang="zh">崇梵寺</foreign>, was active in the area of today’s
                            Pingyin County and created smaller scale inscriptions at Mount Ergu and
                            Mount Yuncui, and perhaps at other sites as well.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="LaiFei2003c">107</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>The identity of the third name appearing in the colophon, reading “Seng
                            Anyi”, is debated. While it may simply read “Venerable Anyi”, most authors prefer to identify it with the Great Renunciant Seng’an Daoyi
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">僧安道壹</foreign> (fl. 562-579), known from
                            Mount Hongding <foreign xml:lang="zh">洪頂山</foreign>, Mount Tie <foreign xml:lang="zh">鐵山</foreign>, and Mount Jian <foreign xml:lang="zh">尖山</foreign>.<note>
                                <ref target="Kiriya2003a" type="biblio">51, 74</ref>; <ref target="LaiFei2003c" type="biblio">126</ref>; <ref target="LiuTao2003a" type="biblio">238</ref>; <ref target="Takuma2003" type="biblio">188</ref>; <ref target="XuHongguo2003" type="biblio">245</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>The fourth name, Cheng Boren <foreign xml:lang="zh">程伯仁</foreign>,
                            is that of a layperson, about whom nothing else is known.</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>LL, TSL</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Dating</head>
                        <p>The inscription is dated to 562, the first year of the <hi rend="italic">heqing</hi> era
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">河清元年</foreign>. Before the carved date came
                            to light, the inscription was generally dated to the Northern Qi dynasty
                            (550-574) based on the calligraphic style. Those authors who connected
                            the inscription to the monk Seng’an Daoyi, assigned Mount Ergu’s Buddha
                            name to an early period of this monk’s works, which they had dated to somewhat earlier than 564.<note>
                                <ref target="Kiriya2003a" type="biblio">51, 74</ref>; <ref target="LaiFei2003c" type="biblio">107</ref>.</note> The
                            discovery of the inscription has confirmed the early dating.</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>LL, TSL</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Research History</head>
                        <p>Research on Mount Ergu is primarily found in the second volume of <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Research on the Sutras Engraved on Polished Cliffs of the Northern Dynasties </hi> (<hi rend="italic">Beichao moya kejing yanjiu
                                    [xu] </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">北朝摩崖刻經研究(續)</foreign>)</title>. In this
                            volume from 2003, the site is mentioned several times, and the identity
                            of the monks mentioned in the colophon is discussed. In the third volume
                            of <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Research on the Sutras Engraved on Polished Cliffs of the Northern Dynasties</hi>
                            </title> from 2006, Yang Hao <foreign xml:lang="zh">楊浩</foreign> gives
                            another short description of the site.<note>
                                <ref target="Yang_Hao2006b" type="biblio">174</ref>.</note> The date
                            corresponding to 562 was discovered in 2011. </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>CW</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Inscriptions</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Inventory</head>
                        <p>One Buddha name (EG 1) and two historical inscriptions (EG 2, EG 3).</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Buddha Name</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>EG 1</head>
                            <p>For the “Buddha King of Great Emptiness” see the
                                relevant introduction on Mount Hongding’s <foreign xml:lang="zh">洪頂山</foreign> Buddha names. For all occurrences of this name in
                                Shandong Province see HDS 8, discussion. </p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Historical Inscriptions</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>EG 2</head>
                            <p>The first historical inscription consists of the names of three monks and one layperson (fig. <ptr target="EG_r_2_part_4022-2.jpg"/>). No place of origin is given. </p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>CW</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>EG 3</head>
                            <p>The second historical inscription consists of five characters giving
                                the date 562. </p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Carving Techniques</head>
                        <p>The technique is mainly the rectangular U-shaped carving. The carver chisels slanting
                            lines from both sides of a stroke, so that the lines intersect and the
                            stroke naturally takes shape.</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>LF</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <figure rend="center" xml:id="EG_r_2_part_4022-2.jpg">
                            <head>Detail of EG 2; photograph taken in 2006</head>
                            <head xml:lang="zh">二鼓山2號摩崖局部，2006年照片</head>
                            <graphic url="EG_r_2_part_4022-2.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Style of Calligraphy</head>
                        <p>The Buddha name of Mount Ergu, measuring more than three meters in height, is one
                            of three examples of giant sized names of the “Buddha King
                            of Great Emptiness” carved in Shandong (HDS 8 and JS 10). They
                            share the stylistic feature of shaping the top ends of the last two
                            vertical strokes of the character <hi rend="italic">fo</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">佛</foreign> in a certain way, which has been
                            described as “hands of the Buddha” (see frontispiece).<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Kiriya2003a">71</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="Kitajima2003">281</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>For the last stroke of the character for “Buddha” <foreign xml:lang="zh">佛</foreign>, see the relevant introduction to Mount Tianchi
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">天池山</foreign> (TC 1).</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>CW</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>