<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Introduction to the site of the Yangyue Monastery</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>N.N.</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>27.11.2017</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>created</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>21.03.2023</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>photographs by Yang Xiao from 2022 inserted</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>11.03.2025</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>finally starting the write-up</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>25.03.2025</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>somehow finishing the write-up</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>07.05.2026</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>inserting the Chinese translation by Wang Jialu</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:id="Site_Yangyuesi">
        <body>
            <div xml:lang="zh">
                <head>陽岳寺</head>
                <p>陽岳寺<!--石刻-->摩崖造像<!--遺址-->規模較小，僅在一處醒目崖壁底部開鑿了七個龕窟。<!--這處偏遠刻經址的特徵在於成行排列的佛像-->
                    以雕刻成排的多佛造像為特徵，其身份曾通過附屬銘文得以確認。
                    公元756年捐造的五十三佛及附刻的佛經段落，與兩個設有群像<!--佈局-->的大型佛龕之間存在關聯。根據龕側銘文記載，其中一龕為阿彌陀佛净土變相。佛名群組與圖像表現相結合，共同體現了供養人對亡者福祉的深切關懷。</p>
                <div>
                    <head>遺址</head>
                    <p>陽岳寺位於一處醒目的垂直崖壁下部（<ptr target="YYS_DSC_8299.JPG"/>），地處四川北部廣元市蒼溪縣三川鎮境内。當地農民在耕作附近田地時，曾多次發現宋代（960－1279年）與明代（1368－1644年）石制器物。因此，可推測該地曾存在一處宗教建築，
                        <!--二手文獻-->現代調查研究中通常將其稱作“陽岳寺”。</p>
                    <p>沿着自東北至西南延展的崖壁上，開鑿有一組七個龕窟。這些龕窟位置偏僻，難以接近。在第1至第5龕前方，一處規模不大的平整區域近期已被圍欄圍護起來（<ptr target="YYS_DJI_0535.jpg"/>）。此前，佛龕前方狹窄的地面未經鋪砌，加之其所在位置植被茂密（<ptr target="YYS_DSC_8283.JPG"/>），使得整體造訪難度進一步增加。</p>
                    <p>2001年10月至11月，由廣元皇澤寺博物館與成都市文物考古研究所組成的工作隊對該遺址進行了全面考察。此次調查對全部像龕進行了拍攝、測繪和描述，并對現場銘文進行抄録。該調查報告曾兩次發表，首次為2001年，<note>《廣元蒼溪陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001"/>。</note>後於2004年<note>《蒼溪縣陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b"/>。</note>再次出版。下文對龕窟的編號，均采用此官方調查報告中的編號方式。</p>
                   
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>造像龕</head>
                    <p>佛龕編號按自東向西（從右至左）的順序編排（<ptr target="Gesamtansicht_YYS_DJI_0551_mit-Beschriftung.jpg"/>）。前六龕呈橫向排列，總寬度約6米；第7龕則位於崖壁西端的高處（<ptr target="YYS_DSC06162.JPG"/>）。第7龕遺存的造像風格較下方龕更爲粗獷。因此，第7龕被認爲是後期增鑿，而編號爲第1至6的佛龕則應爲同期開鑿。<note>《廣元蒼溪陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">第516頁</ref>；《蒼溪縣陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">第49頁</ref>。</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>最東側的第1龕外框高45厘米、寬25厘米。龕内為單尊立姿菩薩造像，旁側銘文載其為“……菩薩一身”。<note>《廣元蒼溪陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">第509－510頁</ref>；《蒼溪縣陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">第44頁</ref>。</note>由於其右側崖體已崩毀，無從考證原始崖面是否曾存在更多佛龕。如今，第1龕位於規模宏大得多的雙框構造第2龕的右下角前方（<ptr target="YYS_DJI_0498.JPG"/>）。</p>
                    <div>
                        <head>第2龕</head>
                        <p>第2龕外框呈長方形，高115厘米、寬134厘米。内龕亦為長方形，上角略呈弧形。其尺寸為高89厘米、寬112厘米、深14厘米。由於内外龕寬度存在差異，在内龕佛像周圍形成了一圈邊框。邊框兩側分層排列着多尊小像。頂部可見兩尊護法神像，各高31厘米。其下各刻有兩尊供養人像。右側可辯認出兩層女性供養人像。中層兩位女性呈側面像，雙手合十，作合掌印（<hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">añjali-mudrā</foreign>
                            </hi>）；底層兩位則呈正面像。在邊框左側中層，可見兩名呈側面像的男性供養人，一位跪姿，一位立姿。底層三位立像經辨識為女性，皆朝向内龕聖像方向。<note>《廣元蒼溪陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">第510頁</ref>；《蒼溪縣陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">第45－46頁</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>内龕所描繪的是阿彌陀佛净土的殊勝景象。中央主佛端坐於蓮華寶座之上；雙手或作轉法輪印（<hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">dharmacakra-mudrā</foreign>
                            </hi>），即説法之印。兩側的菩薩“舒相”坐於各自的蓮座之上，一腿盤曲於座上，另一腿伸展，垂於旁側較小的蓮華上。</p>
                        <p>中央一舖三尊造像近期經過了大規模修復。原始造像的石質核心外新覆了一層泥塑，但此新泥塑層手法較爲粗糙，不如唐代原作精細。新塑雕像再施以鮮麗彩繪。阿彌陀佛净土中其餘諸尊造像則未經修復處理。其中多尊已損毀，僅存石質胎體或外形輪廓。此類局部修復之擧表明該刻經址仍有宗教活動延續。屬地諸多刻經址皆可見現代修繕痕跡。營山縣太蓬山第13龕即爲顯例，此類粗率修復往往使原造像群之圖像志特徵趨於模糊（見本卷<ptr type="infra" target="blur_start_zh blur_end_zh"/>）。</p>
                    <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="YYS_DJI_0535.jpg">
                        <head xml:lang="zh">陽岳寺石刻。2022年拍攝</head>
                        <head>Cliff Carvings of Yangyue Monastery; photograph taken in 2022</head>
                        <graphic url="YYS_DJI_0535.jpg"/>
                    </figure>
                        <p>第2龕中央三尊像下方設蓮池，池中湧現衆多小型蓮臺。其圖像表現與綿陽碧水寺第19龕、梓潼縣臥龍山第1龕等較早的阿彌陀佛净土場景描繪相類。蓮臺之上，安置有立姿與坐姿的化生人物。部分人物身著僧衣，另有著透明“天衣”者，當爲菩薩服飾。不過此處蓮臺化生人物的總數并非如碧水寺與臥龍山造像中所見的五十身，而是約爲二十六身。因保存狀況限制，難以精確計數。</p>
                        <p>中央三尊像兩側各塑有高樓一幢。每幢均爲雙層構造。深處的屋簷庇蔭着欄后更多天人像之居所。阿彌陀佛頭頂懸有寳蓋，兩側各刻有菩提樹一株。畫面左右兩側，瑞云承托着聖衆自他方世界飛降而來。主尊與脅侍菩薩之間，刻有飛天及兩身蓮臺化生人物。</p>
                        <p>其中出現的建築元素，標志着這幅阿彌陀佛净土圖所呈之像，應被歸入該圖像母題發展的後期階段，大致可追溯到八世紀中期。<note>參見雷玉華<ref type="biblio" target="LeiYuhua2005b">第77頁</ref>中所述阿彌陀佛净土之“C型”圖像表現。</note>這一年代判定可通過相鄰的第3龕下方題記（詳見下文）得以確認，該題記紀年為天寶十五年（公元756）。</p>
                        <p>在第2龕的左側刻有18列題記（編號YY1）。該題記區域高59厘米、寬43厘米。題記文字自左向右排列，然而前五列因一處矩形孔洞而受損；該孔洞可能原是為後期某種遮蔽性設施所設置的木樑槽（<ptr target="YYS_DSC06250_cut.jpg"/>）。因此，原題記的相當一部分内容已佚失。此外，由於現場條件困難，題記上部文字在拍攝的照片中也都模糊不清，因此難以辨識。基於上述原因，本文對該題記的録寫僅能作暫定版本，未達到本刊一貫的出版標準。<note>該題記此前亦轉録於《廣元蒼溪陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">第511頁</ref>及《蒼溪縣陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">第46頁</ref>，其中多處使用問號標示文字辨識存疑。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>題記的標題得以保存，讀作“阿彌陀佛龕贊序”。標題之後刻有一位佛弟子（即供養人）的姓名，但因矩形鑿孔而被抹去。題記文本仍可清晰劃分爲三部分：序、記述供養人和供養事跡的主體部分，以及以詩體形式作結的贊。</p>
                        <p>銘文開篇總述佛陀普渡衆生之恩澤：“佛以無爲，而為紛然，利於法界”。文中既提及佛陀以遍在之法“普導群生”，亦褒揚其他聖賢，即其所稱周帝與老子所開闢的“殊涂”。然而，<!--文末言：-->“誘何多乎，必歸一乘”。</p>
                        
                    <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="YYS_DJI_0498.JPG">
                        <head xml:lang="zh">第1號和第2號龕右邊的《阿彌陀佛龕贊并序》銘文</head>
                        <head>Niches 1 and 2 with the inscription <hi rend="italic">Praise of the
                                Buddha Amitābha Niche with Preface</hi> (YY 1) at their right-hand
                            side; photograph taken in 2022</head>
                        <graphic url="YYS_DJI_0498.JPG"/>
                    </figure>
                        <figure rend="left" n="figure" xml:id="YYS_CIMG4711_CUT.jpg">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">第3龕及其下方《佛説觀藥王藥上二菩薩經》銘文。2022年拍攝</head>
                            <head>Niche 3 with inscription YY 2 below; photograph taken in 2022</head>
                            <graphic url="YYS_CIMG4711_CUT.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>其後，銘文言及“阿彌陀佛者應乎”，謂其應化旨在契合眾生之需求。銘文借《法華經》中著名典故，告誡須“接蒼生於火宅”。銘文第八行起，敘述今日陽岳寺何以成為阿彌陀佛救度眾生之地。</p>
                    </div>
                    <p>文中提及一位僧人，其法名已佚，俗姓蒲氏，來自大石寺。於尋峰之旅，“至此巖泉，瞻眺煙霞，忻然斯住”。由於下文數句釋讀存疑，故該僧於此地的佛教行持難以確考，但文中提及與此處相關之“寒林”與“石室”。</p>
                    <p>下文介紹“崇法弟子王戒度者”。其名複見於銘文末行：“……十五日弟子王戒度表慶訖歷代供養”。由此可見，王戒度即為造像龕及題刻《阿彌陀佛龕贊序》的實際供養人。其捐造此功德之用意，説明如下：</p>
                    <quote>遠世間之非固，知幻境之浮，適愛俗之華因，仰真乘之大益，忻正法之幽妙。念報佛恩，建净土於鴻巖，以酬師德。</quote>
                    <p>王戒度之師承關係，今已難以確考，或即前文所述最初尋至此地定居岩間的大石寺僧。</p>
                    <p>下文述及賢善王戒度所施功德龕之形制：</p>
                    <quote>尔乃霊龕赫然，真相悕怡。浄眾仙僮，具如經之所載。</quote>
                    <p>其後是對第2龕淨土景象的描述：</p>
                    <quote>寶樓寶殿，暎珠網而昤曨；玉樹金柯，韻香風而念佛。</quote>
                    <p>淨土聖眾，如迦陵頻伽等諸禽獸，宣演“七覺之妙音”，流布“八真之道響”。末了，供養人發願云：“普為蒼生尅石銘心焉。乾坤而永固”。</p>
                    <p>依循當時通行之體例，題記內容復以韻文偈頌概述一遍。題記末行載有供養人姓名及紀年。然如前文所述，今僅日序數字得以留存，至於標示造像年份與月份之字跡，則已漫漶磨滅。</p>
                    
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>第3龕</head>
                    <p>第2龕長篇造像題記之側為第3龕，描繪了不同的圖像主題（<ptr target="YYS_CIMG4711_CUT.jpg"/>及<ptr target="YYS_DSC06135.JPG"/>）。第3龕具單一矩形外緣，略呈方框，尺寸為高90厘米、寬92厘米。該龕僅深3厘米。然已足矣。龕內無高浮雕大像，而是刻有七排禪定小佛，每尊高約11厘米。七排之中，五排各雕八佛，自下而上第二、三排則僅雕六佛。龕中心有一小圓拱龕，基座高聳，尺寸為高20厘米、寬14厘米（<ptr target="YYS_CIMG4717_CUT.jpg"/>）。龕內供奉三尊像：一佛結轉法輪印，二菩薩脅侍而立。此三尊像之主尊，為第3龕整體佈局中第五十三佛。圓拱龕左下隅，刻有供養人像二身。其一呈跪姿，著僧袍，後有侍者恭立。<note>該龕細部形制與尺寸，見《廣元蒼溪陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">第512頁</ref>，及《蒼溪縣陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">第46－47頁</ref>。</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>與鄰側《阿彌陀佛龕贊序》銘文相同，第3龕亦遭一矩形柱孔破壞，致使右緣第四、五兩排中二小佛幾近全毀。但其原先存在無庸置疑，蓋因七排禪定小佛佈局井然有序。加之中心圓拱基座刻有銘文，記佛像總數為五十三尊。</p>
                    <p>此銘文自左至右共七列，部分漫漶難辨。前兩列尚可識讀為“普光佛一舖/五十三身囗”，第六、七列則為“奉為一切蒼/生咸沾此福”。<note>完整録文見《廣元蒼溪陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">第512頁</ref>，《蒼溪縣陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">第47頁</ref>，及雷玉華和樊拓宇<ref type="biblio" target="Lei_Fan2016">第399頁</ref>。</note> “普光佛”乃五十三佛名號序列中之第一佛。值得注意的是，第3龕所刻其餘五十二尊禪定佛，其佛名曾一一鐫於像側。但因風雨剝蝕，現已漫漶莫辨。唯餘一佛名尚可辨識：在圓拱龕正下方二小佛之間，刻有“普明佛”三字（<ptr target="YYS_DSC06205_CUT_mit-Markierung.tiff"/>）。</p>
                    <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="YYS_DSC06138.JPG">
                        <head xml:lang="zh">第4龕。2022年拍攝</head>
                        <head>Niche 4; photograph taken in 2022</head>
                        <graphic url="YYS_DSC06138.JPG"/>
                    </figure>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>第4龕</head>
                    <p>第4龕是此刻經址最大的一龕，位於第3龕左側（<ptr target="YYS_DSC06138.JPG"/>）。其形制與雙重邊緣的第2龕相似，尺寸則更大一些。外龕高137厘米、寬219厘米，素面無飾。內龕上隅呈弧形，高100厘米、寬185厘米。龕深43厘米，內供奉七尊造像。<note>第4龕的尺寸與描述，見《廣元蒼溪陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">第513－514頁</ref>，及《蒼溪縣陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">第48頁</ref>。</note>所有造像近年皆經重修。頭部以泥塑修補，面部、衣紋及主佛蓮座複施新彩。</p>
                    <p>2001年調查所拍照片及線圖顯示，<note>線圖發表於Y《廣元蒼溪陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">第513頁，圖3；第514頁，圖4</ref>。照片見同文圖版35.1。</note>彼時造像尚未經此改動。這些圖像資料亦揭示，重塑後的佛像手印已非原貌。據2001年時的殘存原貌推斷，主尊應原結觸地印（<hi rend="italic">
                            <foreign xml:lang="sa">bhūmi-sparśa-mudrā</foreign>
                        </hi>），亦作降魔印。其左手撫左膝，五指下垂；右手已佚，原或施無畏印（<hi rend="italic">
                            <foreign xml:lang="sa">abhaya-mudrā</foreign>
                        </hi>）。由此，主尊或可認定為釋迦摩尼佛。主尊左側之佛，結跏趺坐於蓮台，雙手於胸前結説法印。此尊或為阿彌陀佛。主尊右側之佛，以西域裝束倚坐，雙足各踏一小蓮華。手印原貌雖已難辨，然憑倚坐之姿，當認其為彌勒佛。三像立，是為“三佛”主題。<note>調查簡報亦將此組造像讀為“三佛”題材，見《廣元蒼溪陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">第516頁</ref>，及《蒼溪縣陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">第49頁</ref>。</note>兩側則各立一弟子。內龕側壁前蓮座上，複有二菩薩脅侍。</p>
                    <p>第4龕外緣兩側壁，各開一小圓拱龕。右側龕內雕立僧形象一軀，調查報告定其為地藏菩薩。對側左龕內的立佛則被認定為藥師佛。<note>《廣元蒼溪陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">第514頁</ref>，及《蒼溪縣陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">第48頁</ref>。</note>兩軀造像近年修繕時均經改刻。</p>
                   
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>第5龕</head>
                    <p>第4龕旁之岩面在考古調查中被編為“第5龕”，然此五排禪定小佛周邊無龕框界隔（<ptr target="YYS_DSC06162.JPG"/>）。雕鑿區域高90厘米、寬100厘米。壁面共分佈有26個小型園拱龕，分作五層排列。每龕內均有一尊禪定佛像，龕旁刻有佛名，多數仍清晰可辨。<note>佛名抄録於《廣元蒼溪陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">第515頁</ref>，《蒼溪縣陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">第48－49頁</ref>，及雷玉華和樊拓宇 <ref type="biblio" target="Lei_Fan2016">第401頁</ref>。</note>調查團隊對這些佛像進行了系統編號：層位自下而上標記為I至V層，每層內佛像及銘文從左至右依次編數。根據此編號體系，自下而上第II層的中央龕位具有特殊地位。此龕寬度略大於其餘25龕，因其主尊佛像兩側各有一尊脅侍菩薩立像。此外，在左側脅侍菩薩下方可見一跪姿供養人像。<note>關於第5龕的詳細描述，見《廣元蒼溪陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">第514－515頁</ref>，《蒼溪縣陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">第48頁</ref>。</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>所有五層佛像規律排列，圓拱形佛龕與承載銘文的矩形榜題交替分佈。為形成和諧的視覺韻律，佛龕與銘文在縱向上亦呈交錯分佈（<ptr target="YY_Nische-5-Stein-A_2025-12-18.tif"/>）。總共有26個造像龕和25個矩形榜題。<note>需注意，調查報告（《廣元蒼溪陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">第515頁</ref>；《蒼溪縣陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">第48－49頁</ref>）對佛龕與銘文榜題未作區分，其編號存在錯誤。在最頂層，報告列出了5個小佛龕（編號22－26），但實際明顯存在6個小佛龕（見<ptr target="YYS_DSC06162.JPG"/>）。報告稱第二層首龕，即第6小龕左側存在一處風化銘文，但該銘文實際不存在。相反，第6小龕旁所刻的文字仍可辨讀。這些文字對應於報告中列為位於第7龕左側的題記內容：“盧舎那/鏡像仏/□□供養”。</note>因此，實際難以將佛像與榜題准確一一對應起來（<ptr target="DSC06181_DxO_CUT_gerichtet_bearb.jpg"/>）。</p>
                    <p>不過三尊像所在主龕之銘文則易於辨識。該銘文正位於像龕下方。銘文從右至左，共鐫六列，已有部分風化。據調查報告録文，可辨識字跡如下：</p>
                    <quote>南无寶集/佛/□□□□眾信/徒□<!--（慶？）-->敬造廿/五佛一鋪□供養/天寶十三<!--（？）-->
                        <note>石翠<ref type="biblio" target="Roesch2008">第126頁，注釋34，</ref>傾向於識讀為“十五載“，即公元756年。</note>載九月/十五日表慶之。<note>録文見《廣元蒼溪陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">第515頁</ref>，及《蒼溪縣陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">第48－49頁</ref>。</note>
                    </quote>
                    <p>故主龕正下方該段銘文，實為第5龕全舖之造像題記，點名圖像主題為“二十五佛”。然壁面所刻佛像，總計二十有六。或為維持整體佈局對稱，故多增一佛；抑或二十五佛之首寶集佛在此重複出現，一尊置於造像題記上方，另一尊則別刻於某小龕之中。因銘文泐損過甚，諸佛之名號次第已無從復原。殘存銘文中，至少可部分辯讀者僅十二則。每則皆鐫一佛名號，其下多附供養人姓名。</p>
                    <p>另外值得注意的是，第5龕與第3龕的圖像佈局頗為相似。二者皆以別龕突出第一尊佛，附造像題記。其餘佛像則橫向成排，各尊錯位相間，不取垂直對齊，以求視覺疏朗。且每尊佛像原皆有榜題以標識其名。</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>第6龕</head>
                    <p>第6龕位於第5龕下緣左側（<ptr target="YYS_DJI_0535.jpg"/>）。龕高僅13厘米、寬110厘米。內雕七佛，橫向趺坐一排（<ptr target="DJI_0532_CUT_bearb.jpg"/>）。每尊小佛通座高約12厘米。<note>《廣元蒼溪陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">第516頁</ref>，記此龕有“十尊佛像”。《蒼溪縣陽岳寺摩崖石刻造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">第49頁</ref>，訂正為七尊。</note>七佛橫排，或可認定為“過去七佛 ”題材，此乃漢傳佛教藝術中常見母題。然第6龕上方崖壁，尚有餘富空間可供雕鐫。因第6龕上方另有一單尊小龕，故不能排除今第6龕為未完工之殘跡的可能性，原計畫或刻更多排佛像（見下文 <ptr type="infra" target="more_planned_zh"/>）。</p>
                    <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="YYS_DSC06162.JPG">
                        <head xml:lang="zh">名為“第5龕”的岩石區段上的小型佛龕，其上方為第7龕。2022年拍攝</head>
                        <head>Small Buddha niches of the rock section named “niche 5” with niche 7
                            above; photograph taken in 2022 </head>
                        <graphic url="YYS_DSC06162.JPG"/>
                    </figure>
                </div>
            
                <div>
                    <head>銘文</head>

                    <p>除上述《阿彌陀佛龕贊序》外，陽岳寺摩崖刻經所見銘文皆與成體系的佛名序列有關。如前文所述，第3龕所表現的是五十三佛，佛名原皆鐫於像側。同樣，第5龕供養二十五佛，其中部分佛名尚可借龕側題記辨識。在我們探討這兩組佛像及佛名之前，有必要先審視第3龕下方所刻銘文。因其內容可揭示該刻經址所選佛名的由來。</p>
                    <div>
                        <head>《觀二菩薩經》</head>
                        <p>第3龕下方銘文的核心內容録自《佛説觀藥王藥上二菩薩經》（下文簡稱《觀二菩薩經》）。此經舊傳為畺良耶舍（活躍於424－432/442年）所譯。<note>在《大正藏》排印本中，此段文字位於T#1161，20：664a4－29（664a12－16頁除外）。</note>這段經文講述了眾生聞持五十三佛名號所能獲得的福祉。因此，銘文起首處增“此五十三佛名者”一語，以“是故應當皈依、敬礼”作結，以申勸誡。</p>
                        <p>該經節文首段明確指出，聽聞、稱念、禮敬五十三佛名號者，得以消除最為深重的罪業，避免墮入惡道，并且能夠親見十方諸佛。經節文第二部分記載，釋迦牟尼佛自述其於往昔生中曾聽聞此諸佛名號，并以此法教導三千人。藉由稱念五十三佛名號之力，此三千人先後證得佛果。其中一千人遂成過去莊嚴劫千佛；又一千人即為現在賢劫千佛；後一千人則將成未來星宿劫千佛。經中對上述三劫，皆詳列其起始佛與終末佛之名號。此外，經文還指出，現今十方諸佛之所以能夠圓滿成就佛道，亦根源於五十三佛。</p>
                        <p>在緊接《觀二菩薩經》經文的上述兩段之後，石刻文本附加了關於歸命、禮敬五十三佛的教誡，從而使這段話讀來仿佛出自釋迦摩尼之口。同樣值得注意的是，石刻文本所選取的兩段經文，以一種真正普遍性的方式揭示了五十三佛名號的救度力用：其一，因其能除一切衆生一切罪業；其二，其為一切時空一切諸佛悟道之本因緣。</p>
                        <p>因此，第3龕下方的石刻銘文倡導誦念五十三佛名號，視其爲一種有效的滅罪修行，而五十三佛名號確實長久以來與懺悔儀式密切相關。<note>葛利尹<ref type="biblio" target="Greene2021">第162－204頁</ref>，主張將“懺悔”英譯為<foreign xml:lang="en">“repentance”</foreign>為宜。此前，郭麗英<ref type="biblio" target="Kuoliying1994">第7頁</ref>，則傾向於將其譯爲法語<foreign xml:lang="en">“la confession et le regret”</foreign>（認罪與悔恨），以體現儀式中先懺（陳述罪過）後悔（内心悔改）的過程。關於《觀二菩薩經》（T#1161）的簡要概述及其在懺悔儀式中的作用，見郭麗英<ref type="biblio" target="Kuoliying1994">第134－135頁</ref>。</note>懺悔與隨之而來的罪惡消除，不僅能使人避免墮入惡道，其最終目標是往生天界或净土。</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>五十三佛名號</head>
                        <p>除鎸刻於第3龕下方的《觀二菩薩經》段落外，五十三佛名號亦被題刻于造像之側。五十三佛在中國主要以三種形式呈現：僅以圖像；圖像與題刻佛名結合；或僅以佛名列表的形式題刻。</p>
                        <p>迄今所知最早的五十三佛純圖像表現形式，見於洛陽龍門古陽洞西壁。在一個高57厘米、寬55厘米、近似方形的龕内，五十三座小佛龕環繞居於中央的主龕分佈。其中小龕内為禪定佛像，主龕内則供奉交脚彌勒菩薩。附近一則題記顯示該組造像完成於永平四年二月十日，即511年3月24日。供養内容為“敬造彌勒像一區并五十三佛爲亡母，願亡母托生西方妙樂國土。”<note>古陽洞西壁第31龕（編號2235）旁的造像題記録文，見劉景龍<ref type="biblio" target="LiuJinglong2001">第3册：第74頁</ref>。該龕的示意圖與描述，見劉景龍<ref type="biblio" target="LiuJinglong2001">第1册：第22頁及第3册：第14頁</ref>。</note>這一五十三佛造像表現的早期實例并未逐一標注佛名，其附屬題記亦未明確説明諸佛如何助益往生净土。</p>
                        <p>彌勒菩薩與五十三佛的組合造像排列亦見於多件北魏（386－534年）晚期碑刻。<note>王友奎<ref type="biblio" target="Wangyoukui2020">第109－110頁</ref>，提及一件弗利爾美術館藏碑刻、兩件西安碑林博物館藏碑刻，以及一件西安地區出土石碑。</note>迄今發現最早銘刻五十三佛具體名號的造像碑，藏於河南登封崇陽書院的崇陽寺。据碑陽造像題記記載，此碑設立於天平二年四月八日，即535年5月25日。碑陰部分刻有十一排禪定佛像。每排各列八尊，像旁刻有題名，表明這些造像為三十五佛與五十三佛名號組合之呈現。最底層分布有六個稍大的佛龕，分別表現了六方佛：即西、北、下、上、南、東。<note>王景荃<ref type="biblio" target="WangJingquan2009">第144－152頁</ref>，對崇陽寺碑有所著録；張總<ref type="biblio" target="ZhangZong2013">第503－507頁</ref>，及倉本尚德<ref type="biblio" target="Kuramoto2016">第247－248頁</ref>，亦曾對其加以研究。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>隋代（581－618年）可見更多將五十三佛圖像與其題名相結合的例子。在房山雲居寺雷音洞内，四根内柱的最後一根上刻有五十三佛。在此柱的第七面和第八面上刻有五十三尊佛像，每尊佛旁均有銘文標示其名號。<note>八柱面全貌的照片、綫圖及所刻佛名一覽表，見《雷音洞：2012年度考古調查報告》<ref type="biblio" target="LeiyinDong2020">第209－211頁</ref>。</note>在雷音洞柱面上，千佛之像與名號居前，占據前三根石柱的全部以及第四根石柱的大部分空間，其後方為五十三佛。<note>千佛之名號照片、綫圖及録文，見《雷音洞：2012年度考古調查報告》<ref type="biblio" target="LeiyinDong2020">第156－157頁；178－179頁；192－193頁</ref>。</note>如此，五十三佛被納入更爲廣闊的儀軌語境中，在雷音洞的整體造像體系中僅占其中的一個組成部分。</p> <p>雷音洞由僧人靜琬（卒於639年）於616年開鑿，其體系包含十九部佛教經籍，最初鎸刻於經版之上，而後嵌入洞壁。此體系中的一部分為關於佛教修行與净化的經典。在此語境中，可見五十三佛名號第二次被鎸刻，這次位於洞内南壁的一塊經板之上。此經板上，五十三佛名序列之後接有一段節録自《觀二菩薩經》（T#1161，20：664a16－25）的經文，其内容與陽岳寺第3龕下方銘文的後半部分相對應。<note>該房山經板拓片（編號139）發表於《房山石經》<ref type="biblio" target="FS_SJ2000">第1册：第76頁</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>多位學者已注意到雷音洞内所刻佛名號的儀軌語境，五十三佛與千佛組群在這裏存在着密切的關聯。<note>雷德侯<ref type="biblio" target="Ledderose2003">第253－255頁</ref>；石翠<ref type="biblio" target="Roesch2008">第120－123頁</ref>；李琛妍<ref type="biblio" target="LeeSonyaS2010">第58－59頁；第67－68頁</ref>；韋聞笛<ref type="biblio" target="Adamek2021">第59－60頁</ref>；氣賀澤保規<ref type="biblio" target="Kegasawa2023a">第12－18頁</ref>。</note>然而在其他遺址中，五十三佛被置於一個更廣汎的脈絡之中，其中還包含了更多佛名序列。這一情況在河南省寶山靈泉寺大住聖窟外壁所刻經文中尤爲顯著。据兩則造像題記所載，該窟開鑿於大隋開皇九年，即589年。在大住聖窟，五十三佛并非以造像形式呈現，而是以名號序列鎸刻，每尊佛名前均冠以“南无”之號。</p>
                        <p>緊鄰五十三佛名另鎸刻有多組佛名：其上方為二十五佛名；右側為三十五佛名，其後接續刻有十方諸佛名録。這些源自不同佛經的名號序列得以組合呈現於崖壁之上，乃是由一種儀軌語境所促成；該語境於附近另一篇銘文，即《略禮七階佛名懺悔等文》中有所闡明。該文規定了每組佛名序列在特定時段内的儀軌用途。<note>關於此文本的討論、録文與譯文，見韋聞笛<ref type="biblio" target="Adamek2021">第70－78頁；第410－411頁</ref>。石翠<ref type="biblio" target="Roesch2023">第47－53頁；第59－63頁</ref>，則從該文本與信行（540－594）所編纂的一部儀軌文獻可能存在關聯的角度進行討論，該儀軌文獻被鎸刻於陝西淳化縣金川灣窟内的西壁之上。</note>寶山靈泉寺大住聖窟銘文因此清楚表明，至隋代時，五十三佛名號已經被納入擴展形態的懺悔禮儀體系之中。</p>
                        <p>這些發現亦可由稍晚時期，即593至598年鎸刻的文字得到佐證。<note>八會寺的兩則造像題記分別保留了593年與598年的紀年，見趙洲<ref type="biblio" target="ZhaoZhou2010a">第15、19頁</ref>。</note>它們位於河北曲陽八會寺一座四面石幢之上。五十三佛名號被鎸刻於石幢東面，與過去七佛及千佛名號并列。此外，在上述諸佛名録之上，還以禪定坐姿造像表現二十五佛，各標注佛名。儘管八會寺的佛名組合方式可能與寶山有所不同，但其仍然表明，五十三佛名已成爲特定佛名群組中的固定組成部分。而這一類佛名組合，亦可見於其他遺址的懺悔儀式語境之中。<note>石翠<ref type="biblio" target="Roesch2023">第53－55頁</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>自唐代（618－907年）以來，已知有兩則以五十三佛圖像作爲獨立造像題材的實例，皆未見題刻名號。在山西省西部臨汾市隰縣七里脚第2窟内，我們發現一處獨特的造像表現。其佈局為後壁前設有一舖三尊佛像，兩側壁面則滿刻五十三尊禪定坐佛像，每尊高約30厘米，各像旁均以榜題鎸刻佛名。因此，這批造像被判定爲《觀二菩薩經》中的五十三佛。該窟的鑿刻年代約在七世紀中葉至八世紀中葉。<note>關於該窟的描述及照片，見鄭慶春和王進<ref type="biblio" target="Zheng_Wang1998">第78－80頁</ref>，以及石翠<ref type="biblio" target="Roesch2008">第123頁</ref>。</note>另有一處遺址發現于四川邛崍縣華石山華置寺，始建於798年。第3龕中央有一外凸的大龕，内設一舖三尊像，其周圍環繞着五十三尊坐於蓮座上的禪定佛像。此處各尊佛像均未刻題名。<note>石翠<ref type="biblio" target="Roesch2008">第129－130頁</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>二十五佛名號</head>
                        <p>陽岳寺石刻（至少）包含兩組佛名，即第3龕的五十三佛及第5龕的二十五佛。如上所述，現編為第5龕的中央大龕下方存有一則造像題記，此功德被標記爲“廿五佛”。該題記<!--進一步-->列擧了諸佛之首的名號，稱爲“寳集佛”。原本所有佛的名號都題刻在與坐像交替排列的矩形邊框欄位内，但如今僅有少數尚可辨識。
                            這些題刻的名號對應於十二卷本《佛説佛名經》（T#440，14：159c14－161c1）中所記載的一組二十五佛名。<note>關於《佛名經》這一經典系列（特別是以十二卷本位重點）的概況，見陳世崇<ref type="biblio" target="ChenShihChung2014a"/>.</note>同一組佛名也收録於智昇（活躍於約700－740年）所編的《集諸經禮懺儀》（ T#1982，47：456c5－26）中。根據這兩種文獻中佛名的先後順序，陽岳寺崖面上至今仍可辨識的佛名包括：第1佛（寶集佛）、第2佛（寶勝佛）、第4至8佛（廬舍那鏡像佛、廬舍那光明佛、不動佛、大光明佛、无量聲佛）、第10佛（大稱佛）、第12至15佛（得大无畏佛、然燈火佛、實聲佛、无邊无垢佛）和第19佛（无垢光明佛）。</p>
                        <p>根據現存可辨識的題刻，第5龕佛名排列大致可重建如下（<ptr target="YY_Nische-5-Stein-A_2025-12-18.tif"/>）：第1個佛名位於最下層一排的中間位置。序列向左側延續，依次為（現已遺失的）第2和第3佛名。然後繼續延申至第二排，按自左向右的順序展開。第4至第8佛名仍保存完好，但最右側的第9佛名已無法辨識。序列進入第三排改爲自右向左排列。僅有第11佛名無法辨認。從第15佛名開始，序列跳至第四排，再次從左端起始。但第四排中之後的所有佛名均已風化剝蝕，無法辨認。最上一排的右端僅第19佛名尚可辨識，但其位置過於靠後，因此排本應容納第21至25佛名。這或許是由於石刻佛名的順序偏離了大藏經文本的序列，抑或是刻工意識到佛名題記的位置與佛像之間出現了錯位。</p>
                        <p>在八會寺石幢的東面，我們發現了迄今所知最早的一則二十五佛圖像與名號相結合的實例。<note>對此判定，參見趙洲<ref type="biblio" target="ZhaoZhou2010a">第17－18頁</ref>。</note>然而這二十五佛的保存狀況不佳。那些帶有禪定佛像的小龕原本是沿着石幢東面上緣單行排列的。目前仍可辨識出十個小龕，其中的造像尚能辨認為坐佛，但已不存任何細部特徵。佛名題記的保存狀況更差。僅第23佛名“無邊寳佛”的前兩個字尚存，其後為第24佛名“華勝佛”的第一個字。<note>佛名的録文與復原，見趙洲<ref type="biblio" target="ZhaoZhou2010a">第54頁</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>另有一則二十五佛帶有名號的實例，其年代大致與陽岳寺造像相仿。這處隸屬於大旺寺（又作大灣寺）的摩崖造像刻經址，規模相對較小，位於德陽市中江縣蒼山鎮以南兩公里。該<!--刻經-->址共發現二十個造像龕，根據風格判斷，其年代可定為八世紀上半葉及之後。
                            第18龕為一處大龕，其内刻有阿彌陀佛與五十二菩薩像。相鄰崖面上另有數行禪定佛像與鎸刻題記交替分佈的小龕。<note>關於2006年學術調查的成果，見
                                《四川中江縣蒼山鎮大旺寺摩崖造像》<ref type="biblio" target="Sichuan_Zhongjiang_DawangSi_2007"/>。雷玉華和樊拓宇<ref type="biblio" target="Lei_Fan2016">第402－403頁</ref>，雖沿用此次調查的成果，但新增了第18龕相鄰崖面上的造像龕照片，以及銘文拓片的影像。</note>二十五佛的龕像與題名并未全部保存下來。部分佛像與銘文殘塊已掉落，散於地面。此外，各龕的下部仍埋於土中。基於上述原因，對現存銘文的録文<note>見《《四川中江縣蒼山鎮大旺寺摩崖造像》<ref type="biblio" target="Sichuan_Zhongjiang_DawangSi_2007">第32－33頁</ref>。雷玉華和樊拓宇<ref type="biblio" target="Lei_Fan2016">第402－403頁</ref>，則直接采用了這些録文，未作改動。</note>尚屬推測性工作，但二十五佛的前四個佛名仍可識別。該銘文首行標明主題，其文為：“南無寶［集］如來二十五佛等一切諸佛”。對該石刻文本的録文顯示，其中收録了《佛名經》（T#440，14：159c15－18及24－28）的兩段經文。這兩段經文分別位於崖壁上第1佛名“寳集佛”與第2佛名“寶勝佛”之後。或許原始鎸刻内容涵蓋了大藏經中的整段經文（T#440，12：159c14－161c1）。</p>
                        <p>陽岳寺第5龕除二十五佛名號外，未見其他文字題記。就此而言，它與河北八會寺年代較早的隋代刻經更爲相似。不過，第5龕整體采取圖像與名號交錯并置、分五行排列的佈局形式，較之八會寺石幢上的單行龕像，更爲精緻考究。由於第5龕保存狀況較好，我們得以觀察到禪定佛像在造型表現上的若干差異。大多數佛像表現為禪定坐姿，其袈裟或覆蓋整個上身，或於胸前下垂成環而袒露胸部。但最上一排有四尊造像有所不同，因爲它們手中似各持法器。第21佛胸前可見一物，而位於第26號增刻之龕的坐佛或手持某物，或結一尚未辨明之手印（<ptr target="YY_Buddha_21_26DSC06196_CUT.jpg"/>）。在右側，第24佛用雙手護住某物，而第25佛則伴有一隻鳥，這隻鳥緊鄰該佛像現已佚失的右手（<ptr target="YY_Buddha_24_25_DSC06185_CUT.jpg"/>）。特定佛像組合之造像表現所呈現出的圖像學多樣性，迄今尚未受到學界關注。由於缺乏可供比較的實例，或者現存實例保存狀況不佳，<note>八會寺所見二十五佛像已不存細部特徵，而大王岩摩崖石刻的二十五佛僅以低分辨率照片發表。</note>這些造像特徵的具體含義尚不明確。</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>刻經址可能的儀式功能</head>
                    <p>如上所述，在陽岳寺石刻這一相對小型的造像群中，五十三佛名與二十五佛名這兩組内容佔據了顯著地位。我們亦已指出，這些佛名組合無論是以造像形式呈現，抑或僅以結構化的名號題記出現，通常指向一種更為廣氾的儀軌語境。因此，或許有必要重新審視緊鄰第5龕所刻二十五佛名的第6龕。<anchor xml:id="more_planned_zh"/>現存第6龕并排刻有七尊坐佛，通常被理解爲代表過去七佛。然而，這些佛像旁邊并未留下任何銘文來證實這一歸屬。在更廣汎的儀軌語境中，過去七佛作爲五十三佛與二十五佛的補充是合理的。在八會寺，過去七佛的名號鎸刻於五十三佛名號之側；而二十五佛則以造像形式呈現，位於刻有這些佛名列表的龕窟上方。在寶山大住聖窟中，五十三佛與二十五佛以題刻名録形式刻於洞外，而過去七佛則以造像形式位於洞内。<note>韋聞笛<ref type="biblio" target="Adamek2021">第61頁；第74頁；第379－399頁</ref>。</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>不過仍存在一種可能性，即第6龕實際上尚未完工，而原本計劃容納更多造像。在距離最下方一排稍遠處，另有一尊單獨的佛像位於自右第三尊佛像上方。若將此尊造像理解為原本規劃中最上一排佛像的標記，那麽要填滿由此勾勒出的空間，總共需要五排佛像。若假定這五排每一排所配置的佛像數量皆與最下方一排相同，即為七尊，則可推算出應雕刻的佛像總數為三十五尊（<ptr target="DJI_0532_CUT_bearb_rek_35-kleine.tif"/>）。</p>
                    <p>如此一來，三十五佛的圖像表現確實比過去七佛更契合該遺址所見之五十三佛與二十五佛名號系統。三十五佛這一組佛名出自《决定毗尼經》（T#325, 12:38c21－39a6）。在寳山大住聖窟及八會寺的石幢上，這組佛名與同樣出自該經的一段懺悔文節録鎸刻在一起。<note>寳山大住聖窟與八會寺兩處刻經文，均對應於《决定毗尼經》（T#325，12：39a7－27）中緊接三十五佛名號之後的段落。</note>由此可見，三十五佛與懺悔儀式密切相關，與唱<!--持誦奉請-->五十三佛號與二十五佛號的修持形成互補關係。</p>
                    <p>陽岳寺刻經址中五十三佛、二十五佛以及可能存在的三十五佛之施造（及唱號？）意圖，或可從第2龕的圖像主題中推知。該龕描繪了阿彌陀佛净土中的極樂景象，這一景象也在附刻的《阿彌陀佛龕贊并序》中以詩性文字有所描述。正如王戒度將其施造功德普遍回向一切衆生，隨後所刻的五十三佛名號及《觀二菩薩經》節文，同樣宣誓對一切罪業的普遍赦免，承諾得以安然往生，親近諸佛。<note>在安岳縣岳陽鎮菩薩灣遺址的一方造像題記中，也有證據表明懺悔與往生阿彌陀佛净土之間存在類似的關聯。該題記鎸刻於第5龕的側壁，此龕内雕有五十三尊佛像，而相鄰的第4龕内則為一鋪裝飾華麗的净土變相。供養人同時施造了這兩龕，即“西方極樂世界阿彌陀佛并二菩薩一龕”及“五十三佛一龕”。該題記的大部分已風化漫漶，難以辨認，但其中提到有人“作十惡五逆，無門懺悔”。因此，五十三佛必然是懺悔儀軌的一部分，其作用在於净除衆生罪垢，使其得以往生極樂净土。儘管題記中未留存紀年，但間接證據表明，菩薩灣的第4、5龕可能建造于九或十世紀。關於這兩龕内造像的詳細描述以及該造像題記的録文，見《四川安岳岳陽鎮菩薩灣摩崖造像調查簡報》<ref type="biblio" target="Anyue_PusaWan_jianbao2016">第38－41頁</ref>。</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>刻文所選取的經文段落、特定的圖像主題，以及造像題記中明確表達的、相較於常見以個人功德或世俗願求為中心的發願內容形成對比的普世願望，皆表明此刻經址的營建是針對作為一個整體受益對象的亡者。從《阿彌陀佛龕贊并序》可知，那位定居於這處顯要崖壁的佚名僧人，曾見到一座“寒林” 以及一處或幾處“石室” 。這提示了我們一種可能性，即陽岳寺的佛龕可能施造於墓地，以安撫亡靈。</p>
                </div>
            </div>


           


            <div xml:lang="en">
                <head>Yangyue Monastery</head>
                <p>The small site of the cliff carvings at Yangyue Monastery comprises only seven niches hewn in
                    the lower part of a conspicuous cliff. The remote site is characterized by
                    depictions of Buddha images arranged in rows that were once identified in
                    accompanying inscriptions. The donation of Fifty-Three such Buddhas and the
                    carving of an accompanying sutra passage in the year 756 are connected to two
                    large niches with figural configurations. One of them is identified as an
                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> paradise in a nearby inscription.
                    Together, the groups of Buddha names and the pictorial representations imply
                    concerns of the donors for the well-being of the deceased. </p>
                <div>
                    <head>Site</head>
                    <p>The cliff carvings of Yangyue Monastery (Yangyue Si <foreign xml:lang="zh">陽岳寺</foreign>) are located on
                        the lower part of a conspicuous, vertical cliff (fig. <ptr target="YYS_DSC_8299.JPG"/>) in the territory of Sanchuan Township
                        (Sanchuan Zhen <foreign xml:lang="zh">三川鎮</foreign>), which belongs to
                        Cangxi County (Cangxi Xian <foreign xml:lang="zh">蒼溪縣</foreign>) of
                        Guangyuan Municipality (Guangyuan Shi <foreign xml:lang="zh">廣元市</foreign>)
                        in northern Sichuan. When ploughing nearby fields, farmers repeatedly found
                        stone artifacts from the Song (960–1279) and Ming (1368–1644) dynasties.
                        Therefore, it is likely that there was formerly a religious establishment at
                        the site, which is usually referred to in secondary literature as “Yangyue
                        Monastery”. </p>
                    <p>A group of seven niches was hewn on the cliff that stretches from north-east
                        to south-west. These are difficult to access. In front of niches 1–5, a
                        leveled area of modest size has recently been fenced in (fig. <ptr target="YYS_DJI_0535.jpg"/>). Previously, the narrow ground in front of
                        the niches was unpaved, thus adding to the general difficulty of accessing
                        the niches that are situated amidst the dense vegetation (fig. <ptr target="YYS_DSC_8283.JPG"/>).</p>
                    <p>From October to November 2001, a comprehensive survey of the site was
                        conducted by a team from the Museum of Huangze Monastery in Guang­yuan
                        (Guangyuan Huangze Si bowuguan <foreign xml:lang="zh">廣元皇澤寺博物館</foreign>),
                        and the Archaeological Institute for Cultural Relics in Chengdu (Chengdu Shi
                        wenwu kaogu yanjiusuo <foreign xml:lang="zh">成都市文物考古研究所</foreign>). The
                        survey produced photographs, drawings, and descriptions of all image niches,
                        as well as transcriptions of the inscriptions found at the site. The report
                        of this survey was published twice, first in 2001,<note>
                            <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001"/>.</note> and then again in
                                2004.<note>
                            <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b"/>.</note> In the following, we adopt the numbering of the niches from
                        this official survey report.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Image Niches</head>
                    <p>The niches are numbered from east to west, or from the left-hand side to the
                        right-hand side (fig. <ptr target="Gesamtansicht_YYS_DJI_0551_mit-Beschriftung.jpg"/>). The first
                        six niches are arranged in a horizontal row of about 6 m in width, whereas
                        niche 7 is located at the western end of the cliff high up on the rock (fig.
                            <ptr target="YYS_DSC06162.JPG"/>). What has remained of the figures of
                        niche 7 is more coarse in style than the figures in the niches below.
                        Therefore, niche 7 is believed to be a later addition, while the niches
                        numbered 1–6 were probably created around the same time.<note>
                            <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">516</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">49</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <figure rend="left" n="figure" xml:id="YYS_DSC_8299.JPG">
                        <head xml:lang="zh">佛龕群所在崖壁遠景。2009年拍攝</head>
                        <head>Cliff with the Buddhist niches from afar; photograph taken in
                            2009</head>
                        <graphic url="YYS_DSC_8299.JPG"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>The outer frame of the easternmost niche 1 measures 45 cm in height and 25 cm
                        in width. It accommodates a single standing bodhisattva figure, which is
                        identified in a nearby inscription as “. . . one bodhisattva figure” (<hi rend="italic">pusa yi shen </hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="zh">菩薩一身</foreign>).<note>
                            <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">509–510</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">44</ref>.</note>
                        Because the rock to its left-hand side is broken off, it can no longer be
                        known if more niches existed originally. Now, niche 1 sits in front of the
                        lower left-hand corner of the much larger double-framed niche 2 (fig. <ptr target="YYS_DJI_0498.JPG"/>).</p>



                    <div>
                        <head>Niche 2</head>
                        <p>The outer rectangular frame of niche 2 measures 115 cm in height, and 134
                            cm in width. The inner niche is also rectangular in shape, with slightly
                            rounded upper corners. It measures 89 cm in height and 112 cm in width,
                            and is 14 cm deep. Due to the diverging widths of the outer and inner
                            niche, a frame is created around the pictorial depiction that fills the
                            inner niche. Tiers of figures have been placed on both sides of the
                            frame. On top, we see two guardian figures, each measuring 31 cm in
                            height. Below each of them, two donor figures are located. At the
                            left-hand side, two tiers of female donors can be identified. The two
                            women in the middle tier are shown in profile, with hands folded in <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">añjali-mudrā</foreign>
                            </hi>;
                            those in the bottom tier are shown frontally. On the right-hand side of
                            the frame, two male donors are shown in profile in the middle tier, one
                            kneeling, and one standing. In the bottom tier, three standing figures
                            are again identified as females turning towards the holy configuration
                            of the inner niche.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">510</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">45–46</ref>.</note>
                        </p>

                        <p>The inner niche depicts the paradisiacal scenery of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign>’s Pure Land. The central Buddha is
                            seated on his lotus throne; his hands probably display <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">dharmacakra-mudrā</foreign>
                            </hi>, the
                                <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">mudrā</foreign>
                            </hi> of
                            teaching. The two flanking bodhisattvas “sit at ease” (<hi rend="italic">shu­xiang </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">舒相</foreign>) on their lotus
                            seats, with one leg folded on the seat, and the other extended and
                            resting on a nearby smaller lotus blossom. </p>

                        <p>The central triad has recently been heavily restored. A fresh layer of
                            clay was applied over the stone cores of the original figures, but this
                            new layer of clay is molded rather coarsely and does not match the
                            quality of the original Tang figures. The newly molded figures were then
                            painted in bright colors. The other figures that inhabit <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign>’s Pure Land have not been touched.
                            Many of these are damaged, and only their stone cores or silhouettes
                            have remained. Partial restorations such as this one signify that
                            religious activities are still conducted at the site. Many sites in
                            Sichuan show traces of modern restorations. Niche 13 on Mount Taipeng
                            (Taipeng Shan <foreign xml:lang="zh">太蓬山</foreign>) in Yingshan County
                            (Yingshan Xian <foreign xml:lang="zh">營山縣</foreign>) is a prominent
                            example for how such clumsy restorations can blur the iconography of the
                            original sculpture group (see pp. <ptr type="infra" target="blur_start blur_end"/> in the present volume).</p>
                        <p>Below the central triad of niche 2 is a lotus pond in which many smaller
                            lotus blossoms appear. The depiction resembles that of the sceneries in
                            the earlier <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> paradises inside
                            niche 19 at Bi­shui Monastery (Bi­shui Si <foreign xml:lang="zh">碧水寺</foreign>) in Mianyang <foreign xml:lang="zh">綿陽</foreign>, and
                            niche 1 at Mount Wolong (Wolong Shan <foreign xml:lang="zh">卧龍山</foreign>) in Zitong County (Zitong Xian <foreign xml:lang="zh">梓潼縣</foreign>). On top of the lotus blossoms, standing as well as
                            seated figures were placed. Some wear a monk’s garb, and others are clad
                            in transparent “heavenly garments” (<hi rend="italic">tianyi
                                </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">天衣</foreign>) that befit bodhisattvas.
                            However, the total number of these surrounding lotus-based figures is
                            not 50, as was the case at Bishui Monastery and Mount Wolong, but rather
                            around 26, although the state of preservation prohibits a more exact
                            counting. </p>
                        <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="YYS_DSC_8283.JPG">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">遺址考察現場。2009年拍攝</head>
                            <head>Exploration of the site; photograph taken in 2009</head>
                            <graphic url="YYS_DSC_8283.JPG"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>At both sides of the central triad, two high buildings are depicted. Each
                            is composed of two stories. Protruding eaves shelter the residential
                            space of more celestial figures that appear behind the railings. Above
                            the head of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> hovers his
                            jewelled canopy, here flanked by two stems of his <hi rend="italic">bodhi</hi>-tree. From the right and left side, saintly
                            configurations come flying down from other worlds on auspicious clouds.
                            In between the Buddha and his flanking bodhisattvas, <hi rend="italic">apsara</hi>s appear, as well as two more lotus-born figures.</p>

                        <p>The depicted architectural elements assign this representation of
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign>’s Pure Land to a later
                            stage in the development of this iconographical theme, a stage that is
                            roughly dated to the middle of the eighth century.<note>See the “type C”
                                representations of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign>’s Pure
                                Land in <ref type="biblio" target="LeiYuhua2005b">77</ref>.</note>
                            This dating is confirmed by the inscription below the neighboring niche
                            3 (see below), which is dated to the fifteenth year of the <hi rend="italic">tianbao</hi> era (<foreign xml:lang="zh">天寶十五</foreign>), corresponding to the year 756 of the Western
                            calendar.</p>
                        <p>At the right-hand side of niche 2, an inscription in 18 columns (YY 1) is
                            carved. It covers an area measuring 59 cm in height and 43 cm in width.
                            The text runs from left to right, yet the first five columns are damaged
                            by a rectangular hole that may have held a wooden beam for some kind of
                            later sheltering construction (fig. <ptr target="YYS_DSC06250_cut.jpg"/>). Therefore, a substantial part of the original inscription is lost.
                            Moreover, due to the difficult conditions at the site, the characters in
                            the upper rows of the text are always blurred in the photographs that
                            have been taken, and are thus hard to discern. For these reasons, our
                            transcription of the text had to remain tentative and could not meet the
                            usual standards of our publications.<note>The inscription was also
                                transcribed earlier in <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">511</ref>, and <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">46</ref>,
                                where quite a few question marks indicate uncertainties in the
                                identification of
                                characters.<!--, and <ref type="biblio" target="Lei_Fan2016"></ref>-->
                            </note>
                        </p>
                        <p>The title of the inscription is preserved. It reads <hi rend="italic">Praise of the Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign>
                                Niche with Preface</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Emituo Fo kan zan bing xu
                                </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">阿彌陀佛龕贊并序</foreign>). The title was
                            followed by the name of a disciple (<hi rend="italic">dizi </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">弟子</foreign>) of the Buddha, i.e., a donor, whose name
                            was erased by the rectangular hole. The sectioning of the text into a
                            preface (<hi rend="italic">xu </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">序</foreign>),
                            a main part describing the donor and the donation, and a concluding
                            eulogy (<hi rend="italic">zan </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">贊</foreign>)
                            in verse is still comprehensible. </p>
                        <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="Gesamtansicht_YYS_DJI_0551_mit-Beschriftung.jpg">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">陽岳寺刻經全景。2022年拍攝</head>
                            <head>Overview of the Yangyue Monastery cliff carvings; photograph taken in
                                2022</head>
                            <graphic url="Gesamtansicht_YYS_DJI_0551_mit-Beschriftung.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>The text starts with general remarks on the Buddha’s gift of salvation:
                            “By means of the unconditioned, the Buddha acts in manifold [ways],
                            benefitting the Dharma-Realm (<hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">dharmadhātu</foreign>
                            </hi>)” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">佛以無為，而為紛然，利於法界</foreign>). Reference is made to the universality of
                            the Buddha’s means to “universally guide all beings” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">普導群生</foreign>), but the “different paths” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">殊涂</foreign>) offered by other figures—the inscription
                            names the Zhou Emperor <foreign xml:lang="zh">周帝</foreign> and Laozi
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">老子</foreign>—are also praised. However, in
                            the end, “[although] there are so many modes of guidance, they all must
                            return to the One Vehicle” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">誘何多乎，必歸一乘</foreign>).</p>
                        <p>Then the text turns to the “response of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Buddha” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">阿彌陀佛者應乎</foreign>) that is directed to the needs of all beings. By
                            a well-known allusion to the <hi rend="italic">Lotus Sutra</hi>, the
                            text admonishes that it is necessary to “guide all beings [caught in]
                            the burning house” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">接蒼生於火宅</foreign>). At this
                            point, in column 8, a narrative starts about how the particular place of
                            today’s Yangyue Monastery became instrumental in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign>’s salvific work. </p>
                        <p>A monk is introduced, whose clerical name is not preserved, but whose
                            secular name was Pu (<foreign xml:lang="zh">俗姓蒲氏</foreign>), and who was
                            from Big Rock Monastery (Dashi Si <foreign xml:lang="zh">大石寺</foreign>).
                            During his travels of seeking out peaks, “he came here to this cliff and
                            spring. Gazing upon the hazy mountains, he joyfully settled at this
                            [place]” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">至此巖泉，瞻眺煙霞，忻然斯住</foreign>). Due to a lot
                            of uncertainty in the reading of the following characters, it is hard to
                            characterize the Buddhist activities of this monk at the site, but a
                            “cemetery” (<hi rend="italic">hanlin </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">寒林</foreign>) and “stone chamber(s)” (<hi rend="italic">shishi
                                </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">石室</foreign>) are mentioned in
                            connection with it.</p>
                        <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="YYS_DSC06135.JPG">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">第3龕。2022年拍攝</head>
                            <head>Niche 3; photograph taken in 2022</head>
                            <graphic url="YYS_DSC06135.JPG"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>Next, the text introduces “Wang Jiedu, a disciple revering the Dharma”
                                (<foreign xml:lang="zh">崇法弟子王戒度者</foreign>). Wang Jiedu appears
                            again in the final column of the inscription, where we read: “memorial
                            by the disciple Wang Jiedu of the fifteenth day of . . . , [recording]
                            the completion of celebrations by making offerings for successive
                            generations” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">……十五日弟子王戒度表慶訖歷代供養</foreign>). Wang
                            Jiedu is thus the actual donor of the image niche, and of the
                            accompanying <hi rend="italic">Praise of the Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Niche with Preface</hi>
                            inscription. His intention to donate the pious work is explained as
                            follows: </p>
                        <quote>Because he distanced himself from worldly impermanence, knew about
                            the floating emptiness of the illusory realms, and refrained from love
                            of worldly splendors, he aspired after the great benefit of the true
                            vehicle, and he delighted in the profound subtlety of the true Dharma.
                            Mindful of repaying the Buddha’s kindness, he established a Pure Land on
                            the lofty cliff to requite the virtue of his teacher. <foreign xml:lang="zh"><!--今有崇法弟子王戒度者，-->遠世間之非固，知幻境之浮，適愛俗之華因，仰真乘之大益，忻正法之幽妙。念報佛恩，建净土於鴻巖，以酬師德。</foreign>
                        </quote>

                        <p>We do not know who Wang Jiedu’s teacher was, but it may have been the
                            afore-mentioned monk from Big Rock Monastery who initially found the
                            place and settled at the cliff.</p>
                        <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="YYS_CIMG4717_CUT.jpg">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">第3龕中心處小型圓拱龕。2009年拍攝</head>
                            <head>Small round-arched niche in the center of niche 3; photograph
                                taken in 2009</head>
                            <graphic url="YYS_CIMG4717_CUT.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>The next part of the text refers to the appearance of the niche donated
                            by the virtuous Wang Jiedu:</p>

                        <quote>In consequence, the numinous shrine now shines brightly; its true
                            appearance [provides] hope for happiness, [as] the [depicted] pure
                            assembly of celestial beings is just as described in the sutra(s).
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">尔乃霊龕赫然，真相悕怡。浄眾仙僮，具如經之所載。</foreign>
                        </quote>

                        <p>Then follows a description of the Pure Land scene of niche 2:</p>
                        <quote>Precious towers and jeweled palaces are reflected in nets of pearls
                            that cast a shimmering light; jade trees and golden branches resonate
                            with fragrant winds that evoke mindfulness of the Buddha.<foreign xml:lang="zh">寶樓寶殿，暎珠網而昤曨；玉樹金柯，韻香風而念佛。</foreign>
                        </quote>

                        <p>Inhabitants of the Pure Land, such as <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">kalaviṅka</foreign>
                            </hi> birds and other beasts,
                            propagate “the wondrous sounds of the Seven Limbs of Awakening (<hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">saptabodhyaṅgāni</foreign>
                            </hi>)” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">七覺之妙音</foreign>), and “the sounds that lead to the Eightfold Noble
                            Path” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">八真之道響</foreign>). Finally, the donor
                            states that “universally for all beings, we carved the stone and
                            inscribed [it into our] hearts, so that Heaven and Earth may be
                            eternally firm” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">普爲蒼生尅石銘心焉。乾坤而永固</foreign>).</p>

                        <p>Following established customs, the content of the inscription is then
                            again summarized in verse. The final line of the inscription mentions
                            the name of the donor and the date. However, as we have seen above, only
                            the number of the day has remained, while the characters indicating the
                            year and month of the donation have already vanished.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Niche 3</head>
                        <p>Adjacent to this lengthy votive inscription for niche 2, we find niche 3,
                            which depicts a different iconographical theme (fig. <ptr target="YYS_CIMG4711_CUT.jpg"/> and fig. <ptr target="YYS_DSC06135.JPG"/>). Niche 3 has a single rectangular frame
                            and is roughly square in shape, as it measures 90 cm in height, and 92
                            cm in width. It is, however, only 3 cm deep. This depth is sufficient,
                            as the niche does not contain a group of large high-relief figures, but
                            seven rows of small, meditating Buddha figures, each measuring about 11
                            cm in height. Five of the seven rows contain eight Buddha figures each,
                            while the second and third row counted from the bottom contain only six.
                            A small round-arched niche with a high base is placed at the center,
                            measuring 20 cm in height and 14 cm in width (fig. <ptr target="YYS_CIMG4717_CUT.jpg"/>). It accommodates a triad of one
                            Buddha figure displaying <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">dharmacakra-mudrā</foreign>
                            </hi> and two standing bodhisattvas.
                            The central Buddha in this triad is counted as the fifty-third Buddha of
                            the overall arrangement of niche 3. Two donor figures are depicted in
                            the lower right-hand side corner of the round-arched niche. The kneeling
                            figure wears a monk’s robe and is attended by a servant standing behind
                                him.<note>A detailed description of the niche with measurements is
                                provided in <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">512</ref>, and <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">46–47</ref>.</note>
                        </p>

                        <p>Like the neighboring inscription with the <hi rend="italic">Praise of the
                                Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign>
                            </hi>, niche 3 was
                            damaged by a rectangular post hole, which almost completely destroyed
                            two small Buddha figures in rows 4 and 5 at the left-hand rim. However,
                            there is no doubt about their former existence, as the meditating Buddha
                            figures are distributed in a regular pattern across the seven rows. In
                            addition, an inscription carved on the base of the central round-arched
                            niche gives the overall number of Buddha figures as 53.</p>
                        <p>This inscription has 7 columns running from left to right, but is partly
                            illegible. We can still discern “Buddha Universal Illumination, one
                            spread of fifty-three [Buddha?] figures” <foreign xml:lang="zh">普光佛一<!--輔-->舖/五十三身口</foreign> in the first two columns, and “given
                            for all beings; may they all be soaked in this blessing” <foreign xml:lang="zh">奉爲一切蒼/生咸沾此福</foreign> in columns 6 and 7.<note>A
                                complete transcription is published in <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">512</ref>, <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">47</ref>,
                                and <ref type="biblio" target="Lei_Fan2016">399</ref>.</note> The
                            “Buddha Universal Illumination” (Puguang Buddha <foreign xml:lang="zh">普光佛</foreign>) is the first Buddha in the standard list of the
                            Fifty-Three Buddhas. It is noteworthy that the other 52 mediating Buddha
                            figures depicted in niche 3 also had their names inscribed next to the
                            figures. But these inscribed names are heavily weathered and have become
                            illegible. Only one more Buddha name is still discernible: In between
                            the two small figures seated right underneath the round-arched niche, we
                            read “Puming Buddha” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">普明佛</foreign>; fig. <ptr target="YYS_DSC06205_CUT_mit-Markierung.tiff"/>). </p>
                    </div>

                    <div>
                        <head>Niche 4</head>
                        <p>The largest niche at the site is niche 4, located to the right-hand side of niche 3 (fig. <ptr target="YYS_DSC06138.JPG"/>). In shape, it
                            resembles the double-framed niche 2, but it is larger. The outer frame
                            measures 137 cm in height and 219 cm in width. It is plain. The inner
                            frame has rounded upper corners and measures 100 cm in height and 185 cm
                            in width. The niche, which accommodates seven figures in total, is 43 cm
                                deep.<note>For measurements and descriptions of niche 4, see <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">513–514</ref>, <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">48</ref>.</note> All
                            figures have been renovated recently. The heads were molded in clay, and
                            fresh paint was applied to the faces, garments, and the throne of the
                            central Buddha.</p>
                        <p>A photograph taken during the 2001 survey, as well as the drawings that
                            were produced at that time,<note>Drawings are published in <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">513, fig. 3;
                                    514, fig. 4</ref>. The photograph is plate 35.1 in this
                                publication.</note> show the figures without these modifications.
                            Photograph and drawings also reveal that the recent renovation falsified
                            the figure’s hand gestures. According to what had remained of the
                            original figure in 2001, the central Buddha may have displayed the
                            earth-touching gesture (<hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">bhūmi-sparśa-mudrā</foreign>
                            </hi>; <hi rend="italic">chudi
                                yin</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">觸地印</foreign> or <hi rend="italic">xiangmo yin</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">降魔印</foreign>). His left
                            hand rests on his left knee with fingers pointing downwards, and his
                            right hand, now lost, was probably raised in <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">abhaya-mudrā</foreign>
                            </hi> (<hi rend="italic">wuwei yin </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">無畏印</foreign>). Thus, the
                            central Buddha may be identified as <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign>. The Buddha at his right-hand side sits
                            cross-legged on his lotus throne, with hands displaying <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">dharmacakra-mudrā</foreign>
                            </hi> in front of his chest. This might
                            be <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Buddha. The left-hand side
                            Buddha sits in Western style with legs pending from his throne, his feet
                            resting on two small lotuses. The original <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">mudrā</foreign>
                            </hi> is no longer discernible, but
                            the sitting posture speaks in favor of Maitreya Buddha. Together, the
                            three figures represent the theme of the “Three Buddhas” (<hi rend="italic">san Fo </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">三佛</foreign>).<note>The survey report also identifies the group as a representation of the “Three Buddhas,” see <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">516</ref>, and <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">49</ref>.
                            </note> The group is flanked by two standing monk figures and
                            accompanied by two bodhisattvas, seated on lotuses in front of the side
                            walls of the inner niche. </p>
                        <figure rend="float-top" n="figure" xml:id="YYS_DSC06205_CUT_mit-Markierung.tiff">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">第3龕中心小型圓拱龕基座下方題記。2022年拍攝</head>
                            <head>Inscription below the base of the small round-arched niche in the
                                center of niche 3; photograph taken in 2022</head>
                            <graphic url="YYS_DSC06205_CUT_mit-Markierung.tiff"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>Into each of the side walls of the outer frame of niche 4, a small
                            round-arched niche was placed. The left-hand side niche accommodates a
                            standing monk figure, which was identified during the survey as a
                            representation of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Kṣitigarbha</foreign>
                            Bodhisattva. The standing Buddha figure in the opposite niche at the
                            right-hand side was identified as the Medicine Buddha.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">514</ref>,
                                and <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">48</ref>.</note> Both figures were reworked during the latest
                            renovation.</p>
                    </div>


                    <div>
                        <head>Niche 5</head>
                        <p>The rock surface adjacent to niche 4 has been designated “niche 5” by the
                            archaeological survey, despite the fact that there is no demarcating
                            frame around this arrangement of five rows of meditating Buddha figures
                            (fig. <ptr target="YYS_DSC06162.JPG"/>). The carved area measures 90 cm
                            in height, and 100 cm in width. A total of 26 small, round-arched niches
                            are distributed across the surface in five rows. Each contains a
                            meditating Buddha figure. Next to the niches, Buddha names are
                            inscribed. Many of these are still legible.<note>The names are
                                transcribed in <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">515</ref>, <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">48–49</ref>,
                                and <ref type="biblio" target="Lei_Fan2016">401</ref>.</note> The
                            rows were numbered by the survey team from bottom to top (I–V), and the
                            niches and inscriptions of each row were numbered from left to right.
                            According to this numbering, the central niche of the second most bottom
                            row takes a special place. It is slightly wider than the other 25
                            niches, because its central Buddha figure is accompanied by two standing
                            bodhisattvas. Moreover, a kneeling donor figure appears below the
                            right-hand side bodhisattva.<note>A description of niche 5 is found in <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">514–515</ref>, and <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">48</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>In all five rows, round-arched niches with Buddha figures alternate with rectangular-framed fields carrying inscriptions. To create a nice visual
                            pattern, the round-arched image niches and the rectangular inscribed fields also alternate in vertical direction (fig. <ptr target="YY_Nische-5-Stein-A_2025-12-18.tif"/>). In total, we count
                            26 image niches, and 25 rectangular inscriptions.<note>Note that the
                                numbering of Buddha niches and accompanying inscriptions is faulty
                                in the survey report (<ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">515</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">48–49</ref>), which does not distinguish between Buddha niches and
                                fields of script. In the topmost row, the report lists 5 niches,
                                numbered 22–26, but there are clearly six image niches (fig. <ptr target="YYS_DSC06162.JPG"/>). In addition, the report lists a
                                weathered inscription at the right-hand side of niche 6, the first
                                niche in the second row, that does not exist. Instead, the
                                characters carved next to niche 6 are still legible. They correspond
                                to the inscription (<foreign xml:lang="zh">盧舎那/鏡像仏/□□供養</foreign>) listed by the report as being located at
                                the right-hand side of niche 7. </note> Therefore, it is not easy to correlate a particular Buddha image with a particular inscription (fig.
                                <ptr target="DSC06181_DxO_CUT_gerichtet_bearb.jpg"/>).</p>
                        <p>The inscription that accompanies the central niche with the triad, however, is identified easily. It is located right below the image
                            niche. Reading from right to left, six text columns were carved. They are partly weathered. According to a transcription made during the
                            survey, the remaining characters read as follows:</p>
                        <quote>Homage to Buddha Compilation of Treasures. [. . .] [. . .] [. . .][. . .]
                            a multitude of devout followers [. . .] respectfully made one tableau of the Twenty-Five Buddhas
                            for veneration<!--as an offering-->. We $$$memorialized and celebrated its completion on the fifteenth day of the
                            ninth month of the thirteenth<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Roesch2008">126, n. 34</ref>, prefers to read “fifteenth
                                year” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">十五載</foreign>), i.e., 756.</note> year
                            of the <hi rend="italic">tianbao</hi> era [October 5, 754]. <foreign xml:lang="zh">南无寶集/佛/□□□□眾信/徒□<!--（慶？）-->敬造廿/五佛一鋪□供養/天寶十三<!--（？）-->載九月/十五日表慶之。</foreign>
                            <note>Transcription
                                cf: <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">515</ref>, and <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">48–49</ref>.</note>
                        </quote>
                        <p>The inscription below the central niche thus serves as a votive
                            inscription for the entirety of niche 5, and it identifies the
                            iconographical theme as the “Twenty-Five Buddhas.” However, a total of
                            26 Buddha figures are depicted on the rock surface. In order to maintain
                            the composition’s symmetry, one more Buddha figure may have been added,
                            or the first of the Twenty-Five Buddhas, the Buddha Compilation of
                            Treasures (Baoji Fo <foreign xml:lang="zh">寶集佛</foreign>), may have been
                            represented twice, once above the votive inscription, and once
                            separately in one of the small niches. Due to the inscription’s poor
                            state of preservation, the numbering sequence of the Buddha names can no
                            longer be reconstructed. Only twelve of the remaining inscriptions could
                            be deciphered, at least in part. They all give the name of a particular
                            Buddha, often followed by a donor’s name.</p>
                        <p>It is also notable that the visual arrangement of niche 5 is similar to that of niche 3. Both niches accentuate the first Buddha figure by placing it in a separate niche, to which a votive inscription is
                            attached. The other Buddha figures are arranged in horizontal rows that
                            place the individual figures off-center to avoid a strict vertical
                            aligning and to create a more pleasing visual effect. Moreover, each
                            individual Buddha figure was once identified by an inscription. </p>
                        <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="DJI_0532_CUT_bearb.jpg">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">第6龕及龕内一排七尊小佛像。2022年拍攝</head>
                            <head>Niche 6 with a row of seven small Buddhas; photograph taken in
                                2022</head>
                            <graphic url="DJI_0532_CUT_bearb.jpg"/>
                        </figure>

                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Niche 6</head>
                        <p>Niche 6 is located at the right-hand side of the lower rim of niche 5
                            (fig. <ptr target="YYS_DJI_0535.jpg"/>). It measures only 13 cm in
                            height, but 110 cm in width. It contains seven Buddha images seated in a
                            row (fig. <ptr target="DJI_0532_CUT_bearb.jpg"/>). Each of these small
                            figures measures about 12 cm in height, including the seat.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2001">516</ref>,
                                records “ten Buddha images” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">十尊佛像</foreign>) in this niche. <ref type="biblio" target="Guangyuan_huangzesi_bwg2004b">49</ref>, corrects the
                                number to seven Buddha images.</note> Seven Buddhas in a row may
                            easily be identified as a depiction of the “Seven Buddhas of the Past,”
                            a popular motif in Chinese Buddhist art. However, the cliff above niche
                            6 would have offered enough space for more carvings. As another small
                            niche with a single Buddha was carved above niche 6, we cannot exclude
                            the possibility that today’s niche 6 constitutes the remains of an
                            unfinished larger niche, for which more Buddha rows were originally
                            planned (see below, p. <ptr type="infra" target="more_planned"/>).</p>

                        <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="DJI_0532_CUT_bearb_rek_35-kleine.tif">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">未完工之第6龕內三十五佛造像可能配置示意圖</head>
                            <head>Possible distribution of images of the Thirty-Five Buddhas in an
                                unfinished niche 6 </head>
                            <graphic url="DJI_0532_CUT_bearb_rek_35-kleine.tif"/>
                        </figure>

                    </div>
                </div>


                <div>
                    <head>Texts</head>
                    <p>Other than the <hi rend="italic">Praise of the Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Niche with Preface</hi> discussed above, all
                        inscriptions at the Yangyue Monastery cliff site are related to structured lists of Buddha names. As we have seen, niche 3 is a representation of the group of
                        Fifty-Three Buddhas, the names of which were once carved next to the images.
                        In the same way, niche 5 is a donation of the group of Twenty-Five Buddhas,
                        some of which are still identifiable through nearby inscriptions. Before we
                        turn to these two groups of Buddhas or Buddha names, we will first examine
                        the text passage carved below niche 3, as this inscription provides an
                        explanation for the selection of Buddha names at the site.<!--niche 3: <ref type="biblio" target="Adamek2021">409</ref>-->
                        <!--Niche 5<ref type="biblio" target="Adamek2021">406</ref>-->
                    </p>
                    <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="DSC06181_DxO_CUT_gerichtet_bearb.jpg">
                        <head xml:lang="zh">第5龕經修整後的龕面。2022年拍攝</head>
                        <head>Rectified surface of niche 5; photograph taken in 2022</head>
                        <graphic url="DSC06181_DxO_CUT_gerichtet_bearb.jpg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <div>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Visualization of the Two Bodhisattvas</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>The core of the passage carved below niche 3 has been taken from the <hi rend="italic">Sutra Spoken by the Buddha on the Visualization of the Two Bodhisattvas, the King of Medicine and the Superior Physician</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Fo shuo guan Yaowang Yaoshang er
                                pusa jing </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">佛説觀藥王藥上二菩薩經</foreign>;
                            hereafter: <hi rend="italic">Visualization of the Two
                            Bodhisattvas</hi>), a text traditionally ascribed to <foreign xml:lang="sa">Kālayaśas </foreign> <foreign xml:lang="zh">畺良耶舍</foreign> (fl. 424–432/442).<note>In the
                                printed <hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="ja">Taishō</foreign>
                                </hi> edition of the Buddhist canon, this
                                passage is located at T#1161, 20: 664a4–29, excluding
                                664a12–16.</note> This particular passage introduces the benefits
                            for all beings that come with hearing and invoking the names of the
                            Fifty-Three Buddhas. Therefore, the inscribed text adds the words “the
                            names of these Fifty-Three Buddhas” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">此五十三佛名者</foreign>) at the beginning, and ends with the admonishment
                            that, “for this reason, you should take refuge in and venerate [these
                            Fifty-Three Buddhas]” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">是故應當皈依、敬礼</foreign>). </p>
                        <p>The first part of the quoted sutra passage tells us that hearing,
                            invoking, and paying homage to the names of the Fifty-Three Buddhas will
                            eliminate even the greatest of sins, saving the sinners from rebirth in
                            the evil destinies and securing encounter with the Buddhas of the Ten
                            Directions. In the second part, <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign> Buddha relates that, in a former incarnation,
                            he heard these names and taught them to 3,000 persons. Due to the power
                            of the invocation of the Fifty-Three Buddha names, these 3,000 persons
                            achieved Buddhahood one after the other. The first 1,000 have thus
                            become the Thousand Buddhas of the Past Eon; the second 1,000 constitute
                            the Thousand Buddhas of the Present Eon; and the final 1,000 persons
                            will become the Thousand Buddhas of the Future Eon. For each of these
                            three eons, the name of the first and the last Buddha is given.
                            Moreover, the text states that the present Buddhas of the Ten Directions
                            also owe their completion of Buddhahood to the Fifty-Three Buddhas. </p>
                        <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="YY_Nische-5-Stein-A_2025-12-18.tif">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">第5龕內圓拱造像龕與矩形榜題之佈局示意圖。可辨識之佛名及其對應造像龕以紅色標示；漫漶難辨之佛名及未能確定之造像以藍色標示</head>
                            <head>Distribution of round-arched image niches and rectangular
                                inscription fields in niche 5. Legible Buddha names and associated
                                image niches marked in red; illegible names and unidentified images
                                marked in blue</head>
                            <graphic url="YY_Nische-5-Stein-A_2025-12-18.tif"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>After these two paragraphs that follow the canonical text in the <hi rend="italic">Visualization of the Two Bodhisattvas</hi> rather
                            closely, the stone text adds the above-mentioned admonishment about
                            taking refuge in and venerating the Fifty-Three Buddhas, thus making it
                            read as if these were the words of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign>. It is also noteworthy that the stone text selects two passages that characterize the salvific power of the Fifty-Three Buddha names in a truly universal way: First, because these
                            names are able to eliminate all of the sins of all beings; and second,
                            because they constitute the original cause for the awakening of all
                            Buddhas in all of space and time. </p>


                        <p>The stone inscription below niche 3 thus recommends recitation of the
                            Fifty-Three Buddha names as a powerful practice for the elimination of
                            sins, and the Thirty-Five Buddha names have indeed long been connected
                            to repentance (<hi rend="italic">chanhui </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">懺悔</foreign>) rituals.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Greene2021">162–204</ref>, argues in favor of “repentance” as an appropriate translation for the term <hi rend="italic">chanhui
                                    </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">懺悔</foreign>. Earlier, <ref type="biblio" target="Kuoliying1994">7</ref>, preferred to
                                translate it as “la confession et le regret” to reflect an initial
                                act of confessing followed by repenting during the ritual. For a
                                brief summary of the <hi rend="italic">Visualization of the Two
                                    Bodhisattvas</hi> (T#1161) and its role in the context of
                                repentance, see <ref type="biblio" target="Kuoliying1994">134–135</ref>.</note> Repentance and subsequent elimination of
                            sins not only avoid rebirth in the evil paths of destiny; the ultimate
                            aim is rebirth in a heaven or a Pure Land.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Fifty-Three Buddha Names</head>
                        <p>Apart from the passage taken from the <hi rend="italic">Visualization of
                                the Two Bodhisattvas</hi> that was carved below niche 3, the names
                            of the Fifty-Three Buddhas were also inscribed next to the sculpted
                            images. The Fifty-Three Buddhas have been represented in China in three
                            configurations: as images only; as a combination of images and inscribed
                            names; or as inscriptions only, in the form of a list of their
                            names.</p>
                        <p>The earliest known representation of the Fifty-Three Buddhas as images only <!--an iconographical theme -->is found on the west wall of Guyang Cave (Guyang Dong <foreign xml:lang="zh">古陽洞</foreign>) at Longmen <foreign xml:lang="zh">龍門</foreign> near Luoyang <foreign xml:lang="zh">洛陽</foreign>. In an almost square niche, which measures 57 cm in height and 55 cm in width, 53 smaller niches with meditating Buddha figures surround a nestling central niche with a cross-ankled Bodhisattva Maitreya. A nearby inscription dates the composition to the tenth day of the second month of the fourth year of
                            the <hi rend="italic">yongping</hi> era (<foreign xml:lang="zh">永平四年二月十日</foreign>), a date corresponding to March 24, 511. Donated
                            was “one Maitreya figure and Fifty-Three Buddhas for my deceased mother, praying that my deceased mother may be reborn in the western Land of
                            Sublime Bliss.”<note>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">……敬造彌勒像一區并五十三佛爲亡母，願亡母托生西方妙樂國土……</foreign>. A full transcription
                                of the votive inscription next to niche 31 (numbered 2235) on the west wall of Guyang Cave is given in <ref type="biblio" target="LiuJinglong2001">3: 74</ref>. For an illustration and a
                                description of this niche, see <ref type="biblio" target="LiuJinglong2001">1: 22, and 3: 14</ref>.</note> This
                            early example of a representation of the Fifty-Three Buddhas does not identify each Buddha by name, and the accompanying inscription does not
                            explicitly state how these Buddhas help to ensure rebirth in a pure land.</p>
                        <p>Combinations of Bodhisattva Maitreya and arrays of Fifty-Three Buddha
                            images are also known from several late Northern Wei <foreign xml:lang="zh">北魏</foreign> period (386–534) steles.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Wangyoukui2020">109–110</ref>, mentions
                                one stele in the Freer Gallery, two steles in the Forest of Steles
                                Museum in Xi’an (<foreign xml:lang="zh">西安碑林博物館</foreign>), and one
                                stele excavated in Xi’an.</note> The to date earliest stele on which
                            the group of Fifty-Three Buddhas is identified by inscribed names is the
                            stele from Chongyang Monastery (Chongyang Si <foreign xml:lang="zh">崇陽寺</foreign>) kept in Chongyang Academy (Chongyang shuyuan
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">崇陽書院</foreign>) in Dengfeng <foreign xml:lang="zh">登封</foreign>, Henan. According to the votive
                            inscription on the front side, the stele was erected on the eighth day
                            of the fourth month of the second year of the <hi rend="italic">taiping</hi> era (<foreign xml:lang="zh">天平二年四月八日</foreign>), which
                            corresponds to May 25, 535. The rear side of the stele’s body is covered
                            by eleven rows of meditating Buddha figures. Each row contains eight
                            figures, next to which names are inscribed that identify these
                            representations as a combination of the group of Thirty-Five with the
                            group of Fifty-Three Buddha names. The bottom most row contains six
                            slightly larger niches that depict the Buddhas of the six directions:
                            west, north, below, above, south and east.<note>The Chongyang Monastery
                                stele is documented in <ref type="biblio" target="WangJingquan2009">144–152</ref>; it was also studied by <ref type="biblio" target="ZhangZong2013">503–507</ref>, and <ref type="biblio" target="Kuramoto2016">247–248</ref>.</note>
                        </p>



                        <p>More examples of images of the Fifty-Three Buddhas combined with their
                            inscribed names are known from the Sui <foreign xml:lang="zh">隋</foreign> dynasty (581–618). Inside Thunder Sound Cave (Leiyin
                            Dong <foreign xml:lang="zh">雷音洞</foreign>) of Cloud Dwelling Monastery
                            (Yunju Si <foreign xml:lang="zh">雲居寺</foreign>) in Fangshan <foreign xml:lang="zh">房山</foreign>, the Fifty-Three Buddhas appear on
                            the final of four interior pillars. On the seventh and eighth face of
                            this pillar, fifty-three Buddha images are carved, each identified in a
                            nearby inscription.<note>See the photograph and drawing of all eight
                                pillar faces, and the table with the inscribed Buddha names in <ref type="biblio" target="LeiyinDong2020">209–211</ref>.</note> On
                            the pillars of Thunder Sound Cave, the Fifty-Three Buddhas are preceded
                            by images and names of the Thousand Buddhas (<hi rend="italic">qian Fo
                                </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">千佛</foreign>), which occupy all of the
                            first three and most of the fourth pillar.<note>Photographs, drawings,
                                and transcriptions of the names of the Thousand Buddhas are provided
                                in <ref type="biblio" target="LeiyinDong2020">156–157; 178–179;
                                    192–193</ref>.</note> In this way, the Fifty-Three Buddhas are
                            included into a wider liturgical context, in which they constituted just
                            one component of the overall program of Thunder Sound Cave.</p>
                        <p>Thunder Sound Cave, opened in 616 by monk Jingwan <foreign xml:lang="zh">静琬</foreign> (died 639), features a program of 19 Buddhist text
                            that were first carved on dressed stone slabs that were then set into
                            the cave walls. Part of this program are scriptures on Buddhist practice and purification. In this context, we find the Fifty-Three Buddha names
                            carved a second time, now on one of the stone slabs of the cave’s south
                            wall. On this slab, a list of the fifty-three names is followed by a
                            text passage taken from the <hi rend="italic">Visualization of the Two
                                Bodhisattvas</hi> (T#1161, 20: 664a16–25) that corresponds to the
                            second part of the inscription below niche 3 at Yangyue Monastery.<note>See the rubbing of the Fangshan stone slab in question (no. 139) that is
                                published in <ref type="biblio" target="FS_SJ2000">1:
                                76</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Many scholars have noted the liturgical context of the Buddha names
                            carved inside Thunder Sound Cave, where the group of the Fifty-Three Buddhas is intimately related to that of the Thousand Buddhas.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Ledderose2003">253–255</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="Roesch2008">120–123</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="LeeSonyaS2010">58–59; 67–68</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="Adamek2021">59–60</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="Kegasawa2023a">12–18</ref>.</note> At
                            other sites, however, the Fifty-Three Buddhas are embedded in an even
                            wider context that encompasses more lists of Buddha names. This is
                            particularly true for the texts carved on the outside wall of the Cave
                            of the Sages Great Abiding (Dazhusheng Ku <foreign xml:lang="zh">大住聖窟</foreign>) at Lingquan Monastery <foreign xml:lang="zh">靈泉寺</foreign> on Mount Bao (Bao Shan <foreign xml:lang="zh">寶山</foreign>) in Henan Province, which is dated by two votive
                            inscriptions to the ninth year of the <hi rend="italic">kaihuang</hi>
                            era of the Great Sui (<foreign xml:lang="zh">大隋開皇九年</foreign>), that is,
                            589. At the Cave of the Sages Great Abiding, the Fifty-Three Buddhas are
                            not displayed as images, but carved in form of a list, in which each
                            name is preceded by the formula “homage to” (<hi rend="italic">namo</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">南无</foreign>).</p>
                        <p>In the immediate neighborhood of the Fifty-Three Buddhas, more such lists
                            were carved: Above, we find the names of Twenty-Five Buddhas; to the
                            left, those of Thirty-Five Buddhas, followed by a list with the Buddhas
                            of the Ten Directions. The combination of these lists of names, which
                            were all derived from different sutras, and their display on the rock
                            was motivated by a liturgical context that is outlined in another text
                            nearby, the <hi rend="italic">Abridged Text of Reverencing the Buddha
                                Names in Seven Rosters and Repentance, etc</hi>. (<hi rend="italic">Lüe li qi jie Fo ming chanhui deng wen </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">略禮七階佛名懺悔等文</foreign>). This text recommends liturgical uses for
                            each list at a predefined time.<note>For a discussion, transcription,
                                and translation of this text see <ref type="biblio" target="Adamek2021">70–78; 410–411</ref>. <ref type="biblio" target="Roesch2023">47–53; 59–63</ref>, discusses this text in
                                terms of its possible connections to a liturgical text compiled by
                                Xinxing <foreign xml:lang="zh">信行</foreign> (540–594) that was
                                carved on the west wall inside Jinchuanwan Cave in Chunhua County
                                (Chunhua Xian <foreign xml:lang="zh">淳化縣</foreign>), Shaanxi.</note>
                            The inscriptions of the Cave of the Sages Great Abiding on Mount Bao
                            thus clearly evidence that, by the Sui dynasty, the names of the
                            Fifty-Three Buddhas had already become part of an expanded repentance
                            liturgy.</p>
                        <p>These findings are supported by the texts that were carved slightly
                            later, between 593 and 598,<note>Two votive inscriptions at Bahui
                                Monastery preserve dates of 593 and 598, respectively, see <ref type="biblio" target="ZhaoZhou2010a">15, 19</ref>. </note> on a
                            four-sided stone shaft at Bahui Monastery (Bahui Si <foreign xml:lang="zh">八會寺</foreign>) in Quyang <foreign xml:lang="zh">曲陽</foreign>, Hebei. Here, the Fifty-Three Buddha names were carved
                            on the east side of the stone shaft, together with the names of the
                            Seven Buddhas of the Past, and those of the Thousand Buddhas. In
                            addition, the Twenty-Five Buddhas are depicted as meditating figures
                            with accompanying names above these lists. Although the combination at
                            Bahui Monastery may represent a litany different from the one at
                            Bao­shan, it nevertheless signifies that the Fifty-Three Buddha names
                            had already become a regular feature of a particular group of Buddha
                            names that we find in the context of repentance rituals at other
                                    sites.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Roesch2023">53–55</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>From the Tang <foreign xml:lang="zh">唐</foreign> dynasty (618–907), two
                            examples of images of the Fifty-Three Buddhas (without inscribed names)
                            as a stand-alone iconographic theme are known. In Xi County <foreign xml:lang="zh">隰縣</foreign> of Linfen Municipality <foreign xml:lang="zh">臨汾市</foreign> in western Shanxi Province, we find a
                            unique representation inside cave 2 at Qilijiao <foreign xml:lang="zh">七里脚</foreign>. While a triad of three Buddha images sits in front
                            of the rear wall, the side walls are covered by a total of 53 meditating
                            Buddha images, each about 30 cm high, and each has its name inscribed in
                            a nearby cartouche. Thus, they are identified as the Fifty-Three Buddhas
                            of the <hi rend="italic">Visualization of the Two Bodhisattvas</hi>. The
                            cave dates from about the mid-seventh to the mid-eighth
                                century.<note>For a description with photographs of this cave, see
                                    <ref type="biblio" target="Zheng_Wang1998">78–80</ref>, and <ref type="biblio" target="Roesch2008">123</ref>.</note> In Sichuan,
                            another example is known from the site of Huazhi Monastery (Huazhi Si
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">華置寺</foreign>) on Mount Huashi (Huashi Shan
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">華石山</foreign>) in Qionglai County (Qionglai
                            Xian <foreign xml:lang="zh">邛崍縣</foreign>). This site was begun in 798.
                            Niche 3 features 53 meditating Buddha figures seated on lotus flowers
                            around a larger, protruding, central niche with a triad. Here, the
                            individual Buddha images are not identified by inscriptions.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Roesch2008">129–130</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>The Twenty-Five Buddha Names</head>
                        <p>The Yangyue Monastery cliff carvings feature (at least) two groups of Buddha names,
                            the Fifty-Three Buddhas in niche 3, and the Twenty-Five Buddhas in niche
                            5. As mentioned above, the votive inscription below the central niche of
                            what has been designated as niche 5 identifies the donation as
                            the “Twenty-Five Buddhas” (<hi rend="italic">nianwu Fo </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">廿五佛</foreign>). It further names the first among the
                            Buddhas “Buddha Compilation of Treasures” (<hi rend="italic">Baoji Fo
                                </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">寶集佛</foreign>). Originally, the names of
                            all Buddhas were inscribed in the rectangular-framed fields that
                            alternate with the seated images, but only a few are still legible. The
                            inscribed names correspond to those of a list of 25 Buddha names found
                            in the twelve-fascicle version of the <hi rend="italic">Sutra Spoken by
                                the Buddha on the Names of the Buddhas</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Fo
                                shuo Fo ming jing </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">佛説佛名經</foreign>) at
                            T#440, 14: 159c14–161c1.<note>For an overview of the group of the <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Names of the Buddhas</hi> with a focus on the twelve-fascicle version, see <ref type="biblio" target="ChenShihChung2014a"/>.</note> The same list is also
                            contained in the <hi rend="italic">Compilation of Repentance Rituals
                                from the Sutras</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Ji zhu jing chanhui yi
                                </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">集諸經禮懺儀</foreign>) by Zhi­sheng <foreign xml:lang="zh">智昇</foreign> (fl. ca. 700–740) at T#1982, 47:
                            456c5–26. According to the sequence of the names in these two sources,
                            the Buddha names 1 (<foreign xml:lang="zh">寶集佛</foreign>), 2 (<foreign xml:lang="zh">寶勝佛</foreign>), 4–8 (<foreign xml:lang="zh">廬舍那鏡像佛、廬舍那光明佛、不動佛、大光明佛、无量聲佛、</foreign>), 10 (<foreign xml:lang="zh">大稱佛</foreign>), 12–15 (<foreign xml:lang="zh">得大无畏佛、然燈火佛、實聲佛、无邊无垢佛</foreign>), and 19 (<foreign xml:lang="zh">无垢光明佛</foreign>) are still legible on the rock at Yangyue Monastery. </p>


                        <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="YY_Buddha_21_26DSC06196_CUT.jpg">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">第5龕最上排，編號為21（左）和26（右）的小龕内的佛像。2022年拍攝</head>
                            <head>Buddha figures of the small niches numbered 21 (left) and 26
                                (right) in the topmost row of niche 5; photograph taken in
                                2022</head>
                            <graphic url="YY_Buddha_21_26DSC06196_CUT.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>On the basis of the legible inscriptions, the sequence of Buddha names in
                            niche 5 may be reconstructed as follows (fig. <ptr target="YY_Nische-5-Stein-A_2025-12-18.tif"/>): The first name appears in the
                            middle of the bottommost row. The sequence is continued at the left-hand
                            side with the second and the third (now lost) name. It continues in the
                            second row, where it runs from left to right. The names 4–8 are still
                            preserved, but the ninth name at the far right in this row is illegible.
                            The sequence carries on in the third row, this time running from right
                            to left. Only name 11 is illegible. With name 15, the sequence jumps
                            into the fourth row, starting again at the left-hand end. Yet all
                            succeeding names in the fourth row are weathered beyond recognition. At
                            the right-hand end of the topmost row, only name 19 is legible, but it
                            comes too late, as this row should contain names 21–25. Maybe the
                            sequence of the stone carved names deviated from that of the canonical
                            text, or the carver recognized that they mismatched the inscription
                            fields and the Buddha images. </p>
                        <p>On the east side of the stone shaft of Bahui Monastery, we find the
                            earliest known example of a combination of images and names of the
                            Twenty-Five Buddhas.<note>These were identified in <ref type="biblio" target="ZhaoZhou2010a">17–18</ref>.</note> The state of
                            preservation of these Twenty-Five Buddhas is, however, poor. Originally,
                            the small niches with meditating Buddha figures were carved in a single
                            row along the upper border of the shaft’s east side. At present, ten
                            niches are still discernible, with images that can still be identified
                            as seated Buddhas, but do not preserve any details. The condition of the
                            inscribed names is even worse. Only the first two characters of the
                            twenty-third Buddha name, Wubian bao Fo <foreign xml:lang="zh">無邊寶佛</foreign>, have been preserved, followed by the first
                            character of the twenty-fourth Buddha name, Huasheng Fo <foreign xml:lang="zh">華勝佛</foreign>.<note>Transcription and reconstruction
                                of the names in <ref type="biblio" target="ZhaoZhou2010a">54</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="YY_Buddha_24_25_DSC06185_CUT.jpg">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">第5龕最上排，編號爲24（左）和25（右）的小龕内的佛像。2022年拍攝</head>
                            <head>Buddha figures of the small niches numbered 24 (left) and 25
                                (right) in the topmost row of niche 5; photograph taken in
                                2022</head>
                            <graphic url="YY_Buddha_24_25_DSC06185_CUT.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>There is one more example of Twenty-Five Buddhas accompanied by names
                            that appears to be roughly contemporaneous to the cliff
                            carvings at Yangyue Monastery. It belongs to the rather modest site of the cliff carvings of
                            Dawang Monastery (Dawang Si <foreign xml:lang="zh">大旺寺</foreign>; or
                            Dawan Si <foreign xml:lang="zh">大灣寺</foreign>), located two kilometers
                            south of Cangshan Town (Cangshan Zhen <foreign xml:lang="zh">蒼山鎮</foreign>) in Zhongjiang County (Zhongjiang Xian <foreign xml:lang="zh">中江縣</foreign>), Deyang Municipality (Deyang Shi
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">德陽市</foreign>). At this site, 20 image niches
                            have been discovered, which can be dated by style to the first half of
                            the eighth century and later. On the cliff face <!--outside--> next to niche 18, a
                            large niche with a depiction of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> and the 52 bodhisattvas, rows of small niches
                            with meditating Buddha figures alternate with carved texts.<note>For the
                                results of the academic survey conducted in 2006, see <ref type="biblio" target="Sichuan_Zhongjiang_DawangSi_2007"/>. <ref type="biblio" target="Lei_Fan2016">402–403</ref>, rely on this
                                survey, but they add photographs of the cliff face with the Buddha
                                niches next to niche 18, and of the rubbing taken from the
                                inscription.</note> Not all of the Twenty-Five Buddha niches and
                            names have been preserved. Fragments of Buddha images and inscriptions
                            have fallen down and are scattered on the ground. In addition, the
                            bottom part of the niches is still buried under earth. For these
                            reasons, the transcription of the surviving inscriptions<note>See <ref type="biblio" target="Sichuan_Zhongjiang_DawangSi_2007">32–33</ref>. <ref type="biblio" target="Lei_Fan2016">402–403</ref>, adopt these transcriptions without
                                modifications. </note> is rather tentative, but the first four of
                            the Twenty-Five Buddha names are identifiable. The first line of the
                            inscription indicates the topic, reading: “Homage to the Thus-Come One
                            [Compilation of] Treasures of the Twenty-Five Buddhas of all Buddhas”
                                (<foreign xml:lang="zh">南無寶［集］如來二十五佛等一切諸佛</foreign>). The
                            transcription of the carved text records two passages from the <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Names of the Buddhas</hi> (T#440, 14:
                            159c15–18 and 24–28), that appear to have followed the first (Baoji Fo
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">寶集佛</foreign>) and the second (Baosheng Fo
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">寶勝佛</foreign>) Buddha name on the wall,
                            respectively. Maybe the original carving covered the entire passage of
                            the canonical text at T#440, 12: 159c14–161c1. </p>

                        <p>Niche 5 at Yangyue Monastery does not contain other text passages besides the names
                            of the Twenty-Five Buddhas. In this respect, it is closer to the earlier
                            Sui carving at Bahui Monastery in Hebei. Yet the overall layout of niche
                            5 with images and names alternating in five horizontal rows is more
                            refined than the simple row of niches on the Bahui stone shaft. Thanks
                            to the better state of preservation, niche 5 allows us to note certain
                            differences in the depiction of the meditating Buddha figures. Most
                            figures show the Buddha seated in meditation, his robe either veiling
                            his upper body entirely, or baring his breast where it falls in a loop.
                            But four images of the topmost row of niche 5 are different, as these
                            figures seem to hold attributes. An object appears in front of the
                            breast of the Buddha numbered 21, and the Buddha seated inside the
                            surplus niche 26 either holds something in his hands or shows an
                            unidentified <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">mudrā</foreign>
                            </hi> (fig. <ptr target="YY_Buddha_21_26DSC06196_CUT.jpg"/>). At the left-hand side,
                            the Buddha numbered 24 shelters something with both his hands, and the
                            Buddha numbered 25 is in the company of a bird, which appears close to
                            the now lost right hand of this Buddha (fig. <ptr target="YY_Buddha_24_25_DSC06185_CUT.jpg"/>). Iconographical
                            diversification in depictions of particular sets of Buddhas has so far
                            gone unnoticed. Due to a lack of comparative examples, or to the poor
                            state in which existing examples have been preserved,<note>The
                                Twenty-five Buddhas at Bahui Monastery preserve no details, and the
                                Twenty-Five Buddhas of the Dawang cliff carvings are published in a
                                photograph of low resolution only. </note> the meaning of these
                            attributes is not clear.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>A Possible Ritual Function of the Site</head>
                    <p>As outlined above, the two sets of the Fifty-Three Buddha names and the
                        Twenty-Five Buddha names play a prominent role among the rather small group
                        of the Yangyue Monastery cliff carvings. We have also seen that these sets of Buddha
                        names, regardless of whether they are depicted as images or only inscribed
                        as structured lists of Buddha names, usually indicate a wider liturgical
                        context. Therefore, it may be worth taking another look at niche 6, located
                        right next to the Twenty-Five Buddha names of niche 5.<anchor xml:id="more_planned"/> Present niche 6 shows seven Buddha images seated
                        in a row that are usually understood as representing the Seven Buddhas of
                        the Past. However, no inscriptions have been left behind next to the images
                        to corroborate this ascription. In a wider liturgical context, the Seven
                        Buddhas would make a reasonable addition to the Fifty-Three and the
                        Twenty-Five Buddhas. At Bahui Monastery, the names of the Seven Buddhas are
                        inscribed next to those of the Fifty-Three Buddhas, and the Twenty-Five
                        Buddhas are represented as images above the niche that accommodates these
                        inscribed name lists. At the Cave of the Sages Great Abiding at Mount Bao,
                        the Fifty-Three and the Twenty-Five Buddha names are carved as lists outside
                        the cave, while the Seven Buddhas are represented as images inside the
                                cave.<note>
                            <ref type="biblio" target="Adamek2021">61; 74;
                                397–399</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>There remains, however, the possibility that niche 6 is actually unfinished,
                        and was originally planned to contain more images. In this case, we may
                        understand the extant seven Buddha figures as constituting the bottommost
                        row of a larger composition. At some distance from this bottommost row,
                        another single Buddha image was placed right above the third figure from the
                        left. Understanding this figure as a marker for the planned topmost row of
                        Buddha figures, we see that a total of five rows would have been needed to
                        fill the space thus outlined. Assuming that each of these five rows would
                        have had the same number of Buddha images as the bottommost row, i.e.,
                        seven, we arrive at a total number of Thirty-Five Buddha images to be carved
                        (fig. <ptr target="DJI_0532_CUT_bearb_rek_35-kleine.tif"/>).</p>
                    <p>A representation of the Thirty-Five Buddhas would indeed have been an even
                        better match for the Fifty-Three and the Twenty-Five Buddha names at the
                        site. The names of the group of Thirty-Five Buddhas are taken from the <hi rend="italic">Sutra</hi> [<hi rend="italic">of the Inquiry of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Upāli</foreign>
                        </hi>] <hi rend="italic">Regarding
                            Determination of the Vinaya</hi> (<hi rend="italic">
                            <foreign xml:lang="sa">Upāli­pari­pṛcchā-sūtra</foreign>
                        </hi>; <hi rend="italic">Jueding pini jing </hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="zh">决定毗尼經</foreign>; T#325 12:
                        38c21–39a6<!--, hereafter: <hi rend="italic">Jueding pini jing</hi>-->). At
                        the Cave of the Sages Great Abiding at Mount Bao, and on the stone shaft at
                        Bahui Monastery, this group of names was carved together with an excerpt of
                        a repentance text that is also located in this sutra.<note>Both carved texts
                            at the Cave of the Sages Great Abiding at Mount Bao and at Bahui
                            Monastery correspond to the passage immediately following the
                            Thirty-Five names at T#325, 12: 39a7–27.</note> The Thirty-Five Buddhas
                        are thus tied to repentance rituals that complement the invocation of the
                        Fifty-Three and Twenty-Five Buddhas.</p>

                    <p>The intention behind donating (and invoking?) the Fifty-Three, Twenty-Five,
                        and possibly Thirty-Five Buddhas at the Yangyue Monastery site might be inferred from
                        the iconographical theme of niche 2, which depicts the paradisiacal scenery
                        of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign>’s Pure Land, a scenery that is
                        also described in poetic words in the accompanying <hi rend="italic">Praise
                            of the Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Niche with
                            Preface</hi>. In the same way that Wang Jiedu dedicates his donation
                        universally to all beings, the subsequent carving of the Fifty-Three Buddha
                        names and the excerpt from the <hi rend="italic">Visualization of the Two
                            Bodhisattvas</hi> promise universal forgiveness of all sins, and safe
                        rebirth in the presence of Buddhas.<note>A similar connection between
                            repentance and subsequent rebirth in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign>’s Pure Land is attested in a votive inscription
                            at the site of Bodhisattva Bend (Pusa Wan <foreign xml:lang="zh">菩薩灣</foreign>) in Yueyang Community (Yueyang Zhen <foreign xml:lang="zh">岳陽鎮</foreign>) of Anyue <foreign xml:lang="zh">安岳</foreign>. This inscription was carved on the side wall of niche
                            5, which displays 53 Buddha images, while the neighboring niche 4
                            accommodates a richly decorated Pure Land. The donors account for both
                            niches, “the niche with <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Buddha
                            and two bodhisattvas in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sukhāvatī</foreign> in
                            the West” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">西方極樂世界阿彌陀佛并二菩薩一龕</foreign>) and “the
                            niche with Fifty-Three Buddhas” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">五十三佛一龕</foreign>). Many parts of the inscription are weathered and
                            illegible, but it mentions people who “committed the ten evil [acts] and
                            the five heinous crimes, but have no way of repentance” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">作十惡五逆，無門懺悔</foreign>). Therefore, the Fifty-Three
                            Buddhas must be part of a repentance liturgy to clean people from
                            defilements and enable them to be reborn in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sukhāvatī</foreign>. Although no date has remained, circumstantial
                            evidence suggests that niche 4 and 5 at Bodhisattva Bend are from the
                            ninth or tenth century. For detailed descriptions of the sculpted images
                            inside both niches and a transcription of the votive inscription, see
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Anyue_PusaWan_jianbao2016">38–41</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The selection of the carved text passage, the particular iconographical
                        theme, and the outspoken universal aspiration of the votive inscription that
                        contrasts with more commonly found articulations of personal ambitions for
                        making Buddhist donations, all imply that the site was created for the
                        spiritual benefit of the deceased as a general group of dedicatees. The <hi rend="italic">Praise of the Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Niche with Preface</hi> informed us that the
                        anonymous monk who settled down at this conspicuous cliff saw about a
                        “cemetery” and one or several “stone chamber(s).” This suggests the
                        possibility that the Buddhist niches at Yangyue Monastery were donated at the site of
                        a cemetery to set at ease the spirits of the dead.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>