<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Introduction to the site of Mount Wolong</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>N.N.</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>27.11.2017</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>created</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>6.2.2025</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>hoping to finish the write-up by the end of next week</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>24.9.2025</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>inserting the first draft of the Chinese text translated by Jialu</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>13.11.2025</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>inserting the changes to the Chinese translation suggested by Cui Yixiong </item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>31.03.2026</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>inserting the changes to the Chinese translation suggested by Li Fei </item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:id="Site_Wolongshan">
        <body>
            <div xml:lang="zh">
                <head>卧<space n="2"/>龍<space n="2"/>山</head>
                <p>卧龍山現存晚清時期簡樸建築，内部保存有初唐遺址。其早期結構呈“佛塔廟”形制，此類古老建築多見於文獻記載，但其原型可追溯至中亞地區。現今殿内中央矗立一長方體巨石，原初形制或爲四壁圍合、周設廊道的結構。此巨石東側的佛龕歷來爲學界所關注。該龕紀年爲貞觀八年（634年），其圖像主題與碧水寺遺存一致，均爲阿彌陀佛與五十二菩薩坐於蓮臺的净土變相。在臨近岩體上，存有一則碑形刻銘。該刻銘將阿彌陀佛與脅侍菩薩群像稱爲“西域之瑞像”。銘文較爲詳細地記述了此造像如何示顯於世，以及其自古代印度傳入中國的過程。此銘文的另一平行版本見於道宣《集神州三寶感通録》。關於此尊造像傳入中國的記載，不僅旨在印證所呈瑞像爲真，更供述其靈驗事迹。</p>
                
                <div>
                    <head>刻經址</head>
                    <p><!--卧龍山千佛崖是梓潼縣兩處佛教摩崖造像遺址之一。<note>另一處遺址爲梓潼縣城以西0.5公里處的西巖寺；記録於《梓潼西崖寺摩崖造像》<ref type="biblio" target="Zitong_XiyanSi2010">第157－176頁</ref>。</note>-->卧龍山千佛崖位於梓潼縣城以西15公里處。此山得名于三國時期（220－280年）著名政治家與軍事家諸葛亮（181－234年），其號卧龍<!--，山名由此而來-->。諸葛亮北伐魏國期間（228－234年），曾於卧龍山頂設立軍事要塞。該要塞遺址現存四門殘垣，城垣周長約3000米。公元304年，李雄（274－334年）奪取成都政權即位成漢武帝（304－347年）時，爲感念諸葛亮，特於此地修建武侯祠。至公元535年，該祠被納入新建佛教寺院建築群，即通常所稱葛山寺。<note>仇昌仲<ref type="biblio" target="QiuChangzhong1998">第42頁</ref>。</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>這座古老寺院的遺存已所剩無幾。目前，遺址内尚存一組規模不大的晚清（1644－1911年）建築群可供參觀（<ptr target="WLS_DJI_0622.JPG"/>）。<note>此外，仇昌仲<ref type="biblio" target="QiuChangzhong1998">第43頁</ref>，提到現存寺院範圍内有兩座石碑，一座刻於1880年（光緒六年），另一座刻於1927年（民國十六年），内容皆涉及佛教活動。</note>其中一所房屋是爲保護一組開鑿于初唐時期的佛龕而立，該組佛龕雕鑿於一塊長方體巨石之上（<ptr target="WLS_IMG_6149.JPG"/>）。</p>
                    <p>這些佛龕作爲重要文化遺産的價值早在中國建築學先驅梁思成（1901－1972）的著作中就已得到關注。自1937年起，梁思成與妻子林徽因（<foreign xml:lang="en">Phyllis Lin</foreign>）等人共同考察了中國15個省份的重要文化遺址。<note>胡文和<ref type="biblio" target="Huwenhe1991">第81頁</ref>。</note>在建築入口正對面的東側佛龕（第3龕）上方岩壁上刻有題記（<ptr target="WLS_niche3_1917_CIMG4626.JPG"/>），證實了梁思成考察團隊到訪后所采取的保護措施：</p>
                    <quote>中央古物保管委員會示：保護古物，嚴禁重粧。民二八年十一月二日紀念<note>另見胡文和<ref type="biblio" target="Huwenhe1991">第81頁</ref>的録文，但其將上下排列的“二八”兩字誤録爲“六”字。</note>
                    </quote>
                    <p>此項禁令禁止對佛龕造像進行整修，其針對的是通過修繕和重繪佛像以積累功德的佛教習俗。在第3龕上方題記被鎸刻之時，中國知識精英階層已普遍認同：石窟寺院作爲國家遺産，應當以其“原貌”狀態受到保護。由此可見，早在民國時期，中國學術界即開始以科學准則介入文化遺産保護，并在現代民族國家建設的語境中重新審視文化資産的價值。此時，以中央古物保管委員會爲代表的國家機構，開始接管數世紀以來主要由佛教僧侣和民間信衆維護的宗教場所。<note>關於二十世紀四川文化遺産遺址的現代考古學與文物保護歷程，可參閲李琛妍<ref type="biblio" target="LeeSonyaS2021"/>，尤見其第三章“大足遺址管理者、土地與社區”。</note>然而，1939年的初步調查之後，地處偏遠的卧龍山遺址長期未得到重視。</p>
                    <p>於2007年12月到2008年2月期間，四川省文物考古研究院、四川大學藝術學院、綿陽市文物局和梓潼縣文物管理所聯合開展了一次全面的遺址調查，對第1至第3龕進行了詳細測量、繪製及三維掃描記録。<note>此次調查的成果發表於于《梓潼卧龍山千佛崖摩崖造像》<ref type="biblio" target="Zitong_WolongShan2010">第115－156頁</ref>。</note>此次細緻的調查引發了針對該遺址一系列學術成果的集中發表，其中尤以西側第3龕的造像藝術及其所附碑刻題記研究最爲突出。</p>
                    <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="WLS_IMG_6149.JPG">
                        <head xml:lang="zh">卧龍山。現存安置石刻的建築物。2009年拍攝</head>
                        <head>Mount Wolong. Present building hosting the stone carvings; photograph taken in
                            2009</head>
                        <graphic url="WLS_IMG_6149.JPG"/>
                    </figure>
                   
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>巨石與造像佛龕</head>
                    <p>現代保護建築的中心位置矗立着一塊長方體巨石，其測量數據爲：高330厘米，東西長550厘米，南北寬520厘米。<note>測量數據依據仇昌仲<ref type="biblio" target="QiuChangzhong1998">第42頁</ref>。</note>該巨石東、北、西三面開鑿有三座大型造像佛龕。南側未見此類大型佛龕。其壁面代之以布滿約20排千佛圖案淺龕，每排各有50尊坐佛造像。<note>仇昌仲<ref type="biblio" target="QiuChangzhong1998">第42頁</ref>。</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>此巨石原爲原生岩體的一部分，後因在西側開闢繞行禮道而與山體分離。在近期修繕工程中，該巨石頂部已可通達。從其頂部拍攝的照片（<ptr target="WLS_DSC07899.JPG"/>）顯示，該晚清建築的屋頂由木柱支撑，并架設於磚墻之上，磚墻則砌築於開鑿此長方體巨石的自然基岩之上。此外，<!--可見-->巨石頂部西南區域堆積有數排石塊。其中部分石塊可見加工痕迹，包括表面找平、抛光及鑽孔等工藝。</p>
                    <p>梁思成曾將現被保護於建築内部的巨石及其佛龕的形制，與雲岡石窟中心塔柱式龕窟進行類比。<note>楊筱<ref type="biblio" target="Yangxiao2024">第13－14頁</ref>。</note>除中國著名大型石窟<hi rend="dash">──</hi>山西大同雲岡石窟與甘肅敦煌莫高窟石窟<hi rend="dash">──</hi>常見的中心塔柱窟外，另有兩處遺址的結構與卧龍山長方體巨石具有可比性。</p>
                    <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="WLS_DSC07899.JPG">
                        <head xml:lang="zh">卧龍山。長方體巨石頂部修繕施工場景。2022年拍攝</head>
                        <head>Mount Wolong. View of the top of the cuboid boulder during renovation works; photograph taken in
                            2022</head>
                        <graphic url="WLS_DSC07899.JPG"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>第一處是位於河北曲陽的八會寺（約593－598年）。該遺址内一座相似的刻有佛龕的封閉式巨石坐落於低矮臺基之上，現由一座石構小亭保護。<note>關於該遺址及其佛龕内刻經的簡要介紹，可參閲石翠<ref type="biblio" target="Roesch2023">第53－55頁</ref>。目前關於八會寺刻經最全面的研究是趙洲<ref type="biblio" target="ZhaoZhou2010a"/>。</note>在刻有佛龕的巨石頂部，天然石塊堆叠成微微凸起的圓柱形態。該結構的平頂由數塊大型石板構成。如今這塊巨石及其上部結構纏繞着裝飾紋帶，功能可與佛塔相比較（<ptr target="BahuiSi_DSC1314.jpg"/>）。</p>
                    <p>第二處是位於山東濟南歷城區的神通寺（約611年）四門塔（約611年）（<ptr target="ShentongSi_SimenTa_JAC7420_DxO_cut.jpg"/>）。四門塔是中國現存古老的佛教石構建築之一。它的外觀保留了中亞單層佛塔的特徵，但其低矮的塔刹<hi rend="dash">──</hi>由山花蕉葉基座和帶錐形尖頂的叠澀圓盤構成<hi rend="dash">──</hi>冠於金字塔式屋頂之上，而非球形穹頂。塔内爲石砌矩形<!--方形-->中心柱<!--竪井-->結構。在中心柱<!--竪井-->四側的正前方均設有檀臺，其上供奉佛像。信衆可沿中心巨柱與外塔壁中間的狹窄通道繞行禮拜（<ptr target="Simenta_JAC7416_DxO.jpg"/>）。</p>
                    <figure rend="left" n="figure" xml:id="ShentongSi_SimenTa_JAC7420_DxO_cut.jpg">
                        <head xml:lang="zh">山東神通寺四門塔内。2016 年拍攝</head>
                        <head>Four Gates Stupa at Shentong Monastery, Shandong; photograph taken in
                            2016</head>
                        <graphic url="ShentongSi_SimenTa_JAC7420_DxO_cut.jpg"/>
                    </figure>
                    
                    
                    <p>上述例證表明，與現今碧水寺（參見本卷<ptr type="infra" target="BSS_start_zh BSS_end_zh"/>）觀音殿内所保護的自然崖壁不同，卧龍山巨石在初唐鑿建之時，很可能已經是某種整體建築結構的一部分。這一建築形式可與古代龜兹王國（今中亞庫車地區）曾廣汎存在的一種建築類型相類比。文獻資料中，此類建築被稱爲“佛塔廟”。這種獨立式佛塔廟的建築形制，近來已根據敦煌莫高窟第257窟北魏（386－534）末期壁畫的描繪進行了數字化復原。<note>此項數字化重建成果詳見周真如和孫毅華<ref type="biblio" target="Zhou_Sun2024"/>。研究者根據《晋書》卷97中關於庫車的記載判定該建築的類型：“龜茲國西去洛陽八千二百八十里，俗有城郭，其城三重，中有佛塔廟千所。”由於《晋書》成書較晚（646－648年，由房玄齡主持編撰），其中關於庫車的記載追溯到了北魏（386－534）或更早時期，顯得年代不符。不過，《晋書》此處可能是引用了更早的文獻資料，因爲“塔廟”一詞在六世紀已有記載。何書群<ref type="biblio" target="Radich2025">表1，#A0733</ref>，對“塔廟”一詞進行了文獻學分析，并梳理了這一重要術語的闡釋如何影響了佛學研究領域的發展。</note>這幅壁畫是敦煌最早以建築結構框飾佛像的壁畫之一。由於圖像正面視角及其建築框架的呈現，我們似乎看到一座中國傳統殿宇上方矗立着帶塔刹的佛塔穹頂，而佛像正安置于這座殿宇内。通過將這一正面視角轉化三維建築結構，我們得以在理論重建中復原出一座融合式建築：帶山墻屋頂的殿宇位於平頂結構的獨立庭院前方，佛塔的穹頂部分則聳立於庭院屋頂之上。壁畫中央的佛像，据推測應供奉於後院建築的聖域空間内。</p>
                    <p>對卧龍山長方體巨岩的進一步考察顯示，其表面存在更多古代砌築工藝的痕迹。在巨石的北側，一條長形槽痕水平延伸於第2龕上方（<ptr target="WLS_DSC07775.JPG"/>）。槽痕中可見零星鑽孔，似表明此槽曾用於固定某種廊檐或頂棚結構。此外，現存建築的西墻基岩部分向上延伸，其高度約與此岩齊平。從巨岩頂部拍攝的照片背景中可見（<ptr target="WLS_DSC07899.JPG"/>），基岩頂部的北側與西側延伸段被修整爲一條突出的邊緣，似曾用以承托某種平頂構造。此中央巨岩周邊或曾建有帶頂的迴廊結構。</p>
                    <p>循此推之，該中央巨岩外圍或曾建有四面墻體及狹長迴廊，其空間形制可與神通寺四門塔内部結構相比擬。<note>楊筱<ref type="biblio" target="Yangxiao2024">第14頁</ref>，亦提出過類似觀點。</note>四門塔以及敦煌第257窟壁畫所呈現的獨立式“佛塔廟”建築類型最顯著的特徵，莫過於其頂端的塔刹結構（<ptr target="ShentongSi_SimenTa_JAC7420_DxO_cut.jpg"/>）。我們可以推測，卧龍山原始建築結構頂部應同樣冠有某種塔刹，以此彰顯這處布有佛教造像之地的神聖性。</p>
                    <p>在巨岩頂部的西北邊緣，殘存着兩至三列形狀不規則的砌石。這些砌石原有排列方式及功能已難考辨，但其表面皆可見整平、磨光痕迹，部分石塊上還鉆有孔洞。因此，這些砌石可能曾是塔刹等上層結構基座的一部分。</p>
                    
                    <p>當參觀者自東側步入<!--晚晴-->殿宇時，迎面可見一組編號爲第3龕的大型造像群（<ptr target="wolong_niche4.jpg"/>）。該佛龕高210厘米、寬225厘米、深190厘米，向内深鑿於長方體巨岩之中，以至形成兩側壁。側壁上部刻有千佛圖樣（<ptr target="WLS_niche3_DSC0877.JPG"/>）。每側各以淺浮雕形式刻有天王像兩尊。</p>
                    <p>後壁飾有花卉紋圓形拱頂的大型龕室内，密集排列着以中央倚坐佛像爲核心的造像群，坐佛的雙足踏於兩朵大型蓮臺之上。主尊佛像的脅侍共由16尊造像組成。<note>《梓潼卧龍山千佛崖摩崖造像》<ref type="biblio" target="Zitong_WolongShan2010">第144－152頁</ref>，對此佛龕内的造像組合和尺寸數據進行了詳細描述和記録。</note>主尊佛像、脅侍菩薩及龕角處的力士像皆以高浮雕技法刻成。主尊兩側各有一身弟子像，另各有一身帶有頭光的人物<hi rend="dash">──</hi>其身份未能被辨認，但<!--左-->右側爲在家信士形象，<!--右-->左側爲出家僧侣形象<hi rend="dash">──</hi>皆以半身浮雕形式表現。佛龕上部背景空間以淺浮雕技法滿刻天龍八部像（<ptr target="WLS_niche3_DSC0877.JPG"/>）。通過造像立體層次的遞進處理，該構圖形成了前景、中景與背景的三重空間縱深感。此外，諸尊造像呈180度扇形排列，故無法通過單一視點完整觀測（或拍攝）全部形象。由此，造像群的密集感更顯强烈。此種多層造像布局爲四川佛教藝術的典型特徵。</p>
                    <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="Simenta_JAC7416_DxO.jpg">
                        <head xml:lang="zh">四門塔。中央石砌塔心柱及迴廊通道。2016年拍攝</head>
                        <head>Four Gates Stupa. Central stoneblock pillar with passageway for circumambulation; photograph taken in 2016</head>
                        <graphic url="Simenta_JAC7416_DxO.jpg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>儘管第3龕中央主尊佛像的身份判定尚存争議，但其倚坐的姿勢特徵，對其爲彌勒佛的判定傾向提供了依據。<note>肥田路美<ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2009">第114頁</ref>，提出此處三龕的組合分别爲阿彌陀佛（第1龕），釋迦牟尼佛（第2龕），與彌勒佛（第3龕）。仇昌仲<ref type="biblio" target="QiuChangzhong1998">第42－43頁</ref>，判定第3龕主尊爲藥師佛，其脅侍爲日光菩薩與月光菩薩。</note>
                        <anchor xml:id="Changjing_start_zh"/>位於巨石北面第2龕的主尊佛像呈禪定坐姿，其旁題記標明此爲釋迦牟尼佛。此銘文位於狹窄<!--右-->左側壁面上方，其下方爲一尊護法神像。据考證（參照第3龕造像組合），該護法神應爲四大天王之一（<ptr target="WLS_niche3_DSC0826.JPG"/>）。題記文字刻鑿不深，岩面亦未經細緻磨光，仍可見因粗略打磨而留下的平行刮痕。顯然，此銘文爲造像群完工後補刻而成。</p>
                    <p>第2龕旁題記篇幅較短。末署“中和四年八月廾[9]日”（即公元884年9月2日）。紀年之後有一處注釋，寫作“設齊[齋]表”。
                        <!--相同表述亦見於營山縣太蓬山兩處：其一爲第16龕千手千眼觀世音菩薩造像題記，完成于895年（參見本卷<ptr type="infrafootnote" target="biao_1_zh"/>）；另一處爲該龕旁嚴重風化的碑文（參見本卷<ptr type="infra" target="biao_2_start_zh biao_2_end_zh"/>），其紀年爲文德元年十二月十六日（即公元889年1月21日）。-->
                        <!--“表”通常爲臣民上呈君主之奏章。在太蓬山題記中，我們知道此處所設之“齋”是針對地獄十王進行的，這些儀式係爲亡者舉行全套“七七齋”法式之組成部分。<note>見太史文<ref type="biblio" target="Teiser1994">第20－30頁</ref>，及本卷<ptr type="infra" target="sevenseven_zh"/>。</note>因此，第2龕側所刻“設齊[齋]表”的呈遞對象很可能是地獄十王。十王的職責是根據亡者的業力來審判其功過，并決定其轉生去向。-->
                        碑文中，比丘常静記載道，他爲了已故的母親和姨母（亡妣亡姨），重修北面釋迦牟尼佛變。常静祈願亡者往生净土，衆生俱得解脱。<note>題記中部分文字難以辨認。録文可參見肥田路美<ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2009">第107頁</ref>，及《梓潼卧龍山千佛崖摩崖造像》<ref type="biblio" target="Zitong_WolongShan2010">第143頁</ref>。</note>因此，佛像的修復是爲亡者積累功德，但整體的捐獻規模可能更大，并且可能包含某種形式的儀式。這裏的設齋可能僅指常静爲僧伽提供素齋，但也有可能指爲亡者舉行完整的超度儀式。<note>上文提到的太蓬山題記在“設齊[齋]表”后分别標注了“慶訖”和“慶畢”，表明此事已圓滿結束。</note>
                        <anchor xml:id="Changjing_end_zh"/>
                    </p>
                    <p>第2龕高250厘米，寬210厘米，深152厘米。其尺寸及造像布局與第3龕相似。<note>《梓潼卧龍山千佛崖摩崖造像》<ref type="biblio" target="Zitong_WolongShan2010">第134－143頁</ref>，對該龕造像組合及尺寸進行了詳細記録。</note>中央主尊被認定爲釋迦牟尼佛，結跏趺坐於仰蓮座上，蓮座下方爲裝飾華麗的八角須彌座（<ptr target="wolong_niche3.jpg"/>）。其脅侍組合與前面相同：二菩薩、二弟子、二護法神像，背景爲天龍八部衆代表形象。兩側菩薩與護法神之間，各有一身未辨識的半身像。其形制與第3龕同類造像高度相似。<!--右-->左側世俗裝束的帶頭光形象，所戴冠飾與其相同。第2龕男性造像無鬚（<ptr target="WLS_niche3_DSC0826.JPG"/>），而第3龕造像則面型丰圓，蓄有鬍鬚（<ptr target="WLS_niche3_DSC0877.JPG"/>）。</p>
                    <p>儘管第2龕與第3龕造像局部經過大型修繕，但二者仍呈現一致的風格特徵。它們在構圖與風格上的統一性，與位於巨石西面的第1龕形成對比，後者的圖像母題在風格上對於當時的觀者而言應顯得較爲陌生。</p>
                   
                    
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>西龕阿彌陀佛與五十二菩薩像</head>
                    <p>該巨石西壁佛龕的圖像主題與碧水寺第19龕相同，均爲表現阿彌陀佛於極樂净土中爲五十或五十二菩薩所環繞之場景。在卧龍山，有文字證據可資判别此主題：龕室<!--左-->右側刻於巨石西面的銘文題爲《阿彌陀佛并五十二菩薩傳》（下稱《傳像記》 ，詳見下文討論）。然而，佛陀隨從菩薩的確切人數，於銘文開篇首句即存在歧義，其文稱：</p>
                    <quote>阿彌陀佛五十菩薩像者，蓋西域之瑞像也。<note>銘文録文參見本卷<ptr type="infra" target="WLS1_transcription"/>。</note>
                    </quote>
                    <p>圍繞阿彌陀佛的菩薩確切數目，取决於是否將兩位主尊菩薩計入總數之中。若將其計入，總數即爲五十二位菩薩。然而在很多情况下，兩位主尊菩薩没有被算入，這可能是因爲觀音菩薩與勢至菩薩侍立阿彌陀佛左右已成定式，阿彌陀佛之出現幾不脱離二者陪侍。於此類情形中，僅對蓮座上較小菩薩造像進行計數。</p>
                    <p>自2008年調研以來，位於巨石西面的此龕被編爲第1龕。其高196厘米，寬240厘米，深46厘米。此龕的深度較第2龕和第3龕爲淺，因其構圖無需如後兩者般營造前景、中景與背景的多層次空間關係。相較之下，此龕將五十尊小型菩薩像環繞配置於中央三尊周圍：阿彌陀佛居中，觀音菩薩侍右<!--左-->，大勢至菩薩侍左<!--右-->。將五十尊菩薩均匀分布於中央三尊上方（<ptr target="WLS_niche1_DSC0869.jpg"/>）、下方（<ptr target="WLS_niche1_DSC0872.JPG"/>）以及左右兩側，其所營造之視覺效果，旨在使觀者猶如身臨阿彌陀佛净土之蓮池之中。</p>
                    <p>西龕采用雙重龕框結構：圓拱形龕内雕刻阿彌陀佛與五十尊菩薩像，該内龕又置於更大的矩形外龕之中（<ptr target="wolong_niche1.jpg"/>），此種結構爲内龕前方預留了安置兩尊護法神像的空間。儘管保存狀况不佳，因其左手持有金剛杵，<!--右-->左側護法神像仍可被推測爲金剛力士（<ptr target="WLS_DSC07833.JPG"/>）。</p>
                    <p>在敦煌寫本所存類似圖像中，金剛杵通常呈長條形，尺寸近似於劍，然其形制則爲多結棍狀。金剛杵常見持於其棍身中部之收束處，或如本例所見持於一端。<note>可參加例如一幅十世紀所繪雙金剛神素描（19.5 x 42厘米。藏於大英圖書館，IOL Tib J 1363），發表於<ref type="biblio" target="Agnew_Reed_Ball2016">第269頁</ref>（圖録編號41）；亦可參見一幅九世紀下半葉繪有金剛力士的彩繪幡（187.5 x 18.6厘米。藏於大英博物館，1919，0101，0.124（Ch.004）），發表於<ref type="biblio" target="Agnew_Reed_Ball2016">第271頁</ref>（圖録編號43）。</note> 矩形外龕兩側窄壁上端，後續分别增鑿了兩個附龕。其所容納之造像在風格上更接近第2與第3龕，似乎并非第1龕原有設計的一部分。<note>這兩處附加龕編號分别爲1-1和1-2，詳見《梓潼卧龍山千佛崖摩崖造像》<ref type="biblio" target="Zitong_WolongShan2010">第129－133頁</ref>。</note>
                    </p>
                    
                    
                    <p>内龕上方的寬拱飾以婉轉纏繞的<!--藤曼-->蔓草紋，其間隱現數尊禪定小佛像。拱券下方，阿彌陀佛與兩位主尊菩薩立於中央。第1龕造像的風格特徵在這兩尊菩薩像中表現尤爲明顯。它們與第2和第3龕中對應造像顯著不同。第2龕中的菩薩像（<ptr target="wolong_niche3.jpg"/>）是體現中國美學特徵的典型造像範例：他們的面部豐潤，身形近乎敦實。其長裙衣料厚重，裙褶幾乎覆蓋了赤裸的雙足。菩薩身披寬大半透的披帛覆掩上身，長鏈的瓔珞自腹部交叉下垂至膝部，巧妙淡化了下方的軀體輪廓。此外，這些菩薩頭頂高髻，髻上戴有繁複厚重的寶冠，冠后垂懸長絛帶。相比之下，第1龕内脅侍在阿彌陀佛左側 （<ptr target="WLS_DSC07819.JPG"/>）和右側的菩薩立像身形則顯修長。他們身著薄裙，衣縫緊貼腿部，長度僅及脚踝，足弓全然顯露。裸露的胸膛與手臂上佩戴着繁瑣的項鏈和沉重的珠寶手鐲，精心編挽的髮髻僅飾一枚碩大華飾。</p>
                    <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="wolong_niche1.jpg">
                        <head xml:lang="zh">卧龍山第1號龕。2010年拍攝</head>
                        <head>Mount Wolong, niche 1; photograph taken in 2010</head>
                        <graphic url="wolong_niche1.jpg"/>
                    </figure> 
                    
                    <p>佛陀寬大的蓮座下方，蓮網的中央莖乾生出蓓蕾與花萼，其中化生出小型人物：初僅顯露頭部，繼而顯現半身，雙手呈合十狀（<ptr target="WLS_CIMG4658.JPG"/>）。環繞阿彌陀佛的其他小像，皆已全身出於蓮華。他們坐姿各异，有的盤起脚踝環抱一膝呈游戲坐，有的雙足交叉。部分造像以單手托腮，更多則側首傾聽并沉思佛法（<ptr target="WLS_DSC07822.JPG"/>）。<note>《梓潼卧龍山千佛崖摩崖造像》<ref type="biblio" target="Zitong_WolongShan2010">第116－129頁</ref>，對龕内各造像進行了詳細描述，包括尺寸數據和繪圖。</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>既往研究多已指出，綿陽碧水寺第19龕與卧龍山第1龕的造像組合存在高度相似性。<note>岡田健<ref type="biblio" target="Okada2000">第175頁</ref>；肥田路美<ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2009">第109－116頁</ref>；小野英二<ref type="biblio" target="OnoEiji2010">第227－228頁</ref>；于春<ref type="biblio" target="YuChun2019">第277－278頁</ref>；楊筱<ref type="biblio" target="Yangxiao2021">第46－47頁</ref>；楊筱<ref type="biblio" target="Yangxiao2024">第21－22頁</ref>。</note>多數學者認爲卧龍山第1龕阿彌陀佛與五十菩薩造像爲該圖像主題目前已知最早的實例，因其年代確鑿可考。《傳像記》（詳見下文討論）最末欄所記日期爲貞觀八年七月十四日，即公元634年8月13日。而碧水寺第19龕僅能暫定爲貞觀（627－649）前期之作。<note>僅王婷<ref type="biblio" target="WangTing2010">第217頁</ref>，提出碧水寺此龕年代早於卧龍山龕，見<ptr type="infrafootnote_zh" target="datess_zh"/>。</note> 2009年，經對鄰近的第10龕内銘文進行掃描，貞觀元年（627年）紀年得以辨識（<ptr target="BSS_Detail_DSC0371_NEU.tif"/>）。據此，碧水寺第19龕可確立爲該題材最早實例（另見本卷<ptr type="infra" target="Bishui_first_zh"/>）。</p>
                    <p>通過直接比對可見，卧龍山第1龕與碧水寺第19龕在核心三尊像周圍的脅侍造像安排上存在明顯相似性。由於第19龕高度大於寬度（尺寸爲170 x 145.5 x 61厘米），整體構圖顯得較爲擁擠；相較之下，第1龕則寬度大於高度（尺寸爲196 x 240 x 46厘米），因而在空間表現上更爲疏闊。然而細部觀察顯示，兩龕相似性不僅體現在壁面菩薩小像的分布格局上，更見於單尊造像的細節特徵。部分菩薩像的服飾有别於常見的裙裝與披帛，更近似於覆左肩袒右臂的<!--僧袍-->掩腋衣<!--/僧祇支-->（<ptr target="WLS_DSC07821.JPG"/>）。不過這些造像仍佩戴項飾與臂鐲，長髮披垂於肩。碧水寺第19龕可見同類造像表現。手持器物者造像亦不鮮見，如<ptr target="BSS_DSC0253.jpg"/>所示持瓶像，與卧龍山<ptr target="WLS_DSC07821.JPG"/>的菩薩形成對應。</p>
                    <p>碧水寺第19龕的設計，可能與法隆寺金堂現已不存的第6號壁畫存在關聯。<note>王婷<ref type="biblio" target="WangTing2010"/>對二者的圖像表現進行了詳細對比。</note>儘管法隆寺壁畫創作時間約晚70年<hi rend="dash">──</hi>爲女皇帝持統天皇（690－697年在位）<note>柳沢孝<ref type="biblio" target="Yanagisawa1975">第19頁</ref>，提出此年代判定。</note>時期作品<hi rend="dash">──</hi>但二者可能遵循了同一範本。兩處造像的設計可能基於相似的粉本系統（見本卷<ptr type="infra" target="fenben_start_zh fenben_end_zh"/>）。</p>
                    <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="WLS_DSC07822.JPG">
                        <head xml:lang="zh">卧龍山第1號龕。主尊右<!--左-->側三菩薩像（從左至右編號23、22、21）。2022年拍攝</head>
                        <head>Mount Wolong, niche 1. Three bodhisattva figures (numbered from right to left 21, 22, 23) at the left-hand side of the main triad; photograph taken in 2022</head>
                        <graphic url="WLS_DSC07822.JPG"/>
                    </figure>
                    
                    
                    <p>儘管卧龍山第1龕與碧水寺第19龕存在顯著相似性，我們仍需注意，卧龍山遺址西側岩體龕窟的保存狀况實不及綿陽之對應龕完好。卧龍山第1龕多處經過修復，甚或歷經多次修繕。外部矩形框<!--右-->左側邊緣的殘存銘文記載了“又修粧西面阿弥□……”，紀年爲“□和四年四月四□”，即884年5月2日。<note>録文依據肥田路美<ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2009">第107頁</ref>。《梓潼卧龍山千佛崖摩崖造像》<ref type="biblio" target="Zitong_WolongShan2010">第134頁</ref>，給出了略有差异的録文。他們提供的銘文表面尺寸爲高51厘米、寬42厘米，但也承認無法確定銘文是否向下延續。《梓潼卧龍山千佛崖摩崖造像》<ref type="biblio" target="Zitong_WolongShan2010">第132－133頁</ref>，進一步録入了第1龕外框上另外四則歷史銘文的殘片内容。其中兩則爲游人題記：一則紀年爲大明崇禎十二年四月，即1639年5月3－31日；另一則紀年爲大清雍正十三年，即1735年。</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>如前文所述（<ptr type="infra" target="Changjing_start_zh Changjing_end_zh"/>），是年農曆八月，比丘常静爲超度亡母和姨母，對巨石北面第2龕進行了重修。常静有可能也重修了西面的第1龕，但這項早期修繕工程的供養人名諱未在石刻上保存下來。現存銘文内容與第2龕重修題記屬同一類型：第1龕旁銘文末欄起首七字已漶漫難辨，後續存“齊[齋]表畢“三字。<note>録文依據《梓潼卧龍山千佛崖摩崖造像》<ref type="biblio" target="Zitong_WolongShan2010">第134頁</ref>，及肥田路美<ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2009">第107頁</ref>。</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>由於第1龕造像群曾經過較大規模的重修，致使現已無法對其原始圖像學特徵進行深入分析。此佛龕背景今已被刷白，表面平整而模糊，甚至許多蓮花花莖有時也難以辨實。現在無法確認該龕是否存在像在碧水寺第19龕中仍可辨認的山巒背景，這一特徵不僅與法隆寺壁畫相似，也與敦煌莫高窟第332窟東壁壁畫相似（該壁窟根據銘文紀年爲聖曆元年，即698年）。基於上述與碧水寺第19龕的顯著相似性，第1龕仍被歸入這一七世紀阿彌陀佛及脅侍菩薩環繞的造像組合體系中，一些學者還推測阿彌陀佛與菩薩們在蓮池中的聖會原貌應有山巒背景。<note>勝木言一郎<ref type="biblio" target="Katsuki1994">第66－69頁</ref>；肥田路美<ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2009">第112－115頁</ref>；小野英二<ref type="biblio" target="OnoEiji2010">第227－228頁</ref>；肥田路美<ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2011">第378－394頁</ref>[肥田路美<ref type="biblio" target="Hida_Yen2018">第362－371頁</ref>]。</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>關於卧龍山第1龕所呈現的阿彌陀佛與五十菩薩像的圖像學研究，學界已經積累了相當豐碩的成果。本卷中關於碧水寺第19龕的部分提供了該領域研究現狀的概述（<ptr type="infra" target="research_start_zh research_end_zh"/>）。卧龍山的圖像之所以引起如此多的關注正是因爲其附帶的碑文，下文將對此展開具體分析。</p>
                    
                    <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="WLS_DSC07821.JPG">
                        <head xml:lang="zh">卧龍山第1號龕。主尊右側二菩薩像（從左至<!--左-->右編號18、17）。2022年拍攝</head>
                        <head>Mount Wolong, niche 1. Two bodhisattva figures (numbered from right to left 17 and 18) at the left-hand side of the main triad; photograph taken in 2022</head>
                        <graphic url="WLS_DSC07821.JPG"/>
                    </figure>
                    <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="WLS_DSC07819.JPG">
                        <head xml:lang="zh">卧龍山第1號龕。阿彌陀佛<!--左-->右側菩薩立像。2022年拍攝</head>
                        <head>Mount Wolong, niche 1. Bodhisattva to the left of Amitābha Buddha; photograph taken in 2022</head>
                        <graphic url="WLS_DSC07819.JPG"/>
                    </figure>
                    <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="WLS_DSC07833.JPG">
                        <head xml:lang="zh">卧龍山第1號龕。<!--右-->左側護法神像。2022年拍攝</head>
                        <head>Mount Wolong, niche 1. Guardian figure at the right-hand side; photograph taken in 2022</head>
                        <graphic url="WLS_DSC07833.JPG"/>
                    </figure>
                    
                    
                   
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>碑刻題記</head>
                    <p>在第1龕<!--左-->右側，長方體巨石西面刻有一塊碑形的輪廓。銘文區呈長方形，高145.5厘米、寬66－67厘米。碑首高27厘米、寬74厘米，兩角呈弧形。碑身刻有銘文20列，以界格劃分，爲每個字提供了規整的方格（每格約3 x 3厘米）。<note>所有測量數據均依據《梓潼卧龍山千佛崖摩崖造像》<ref type="biblio" target="Zitong_WolongShan2010">第133頁</ref>。</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>碑首刻有七個字。它們不均匀地分布在可用空間中，從右至左排成三列，其中前兩列各含有三個字。銘文并未居中，而是整體略向左偏移。碑首銘文布局失當，令人質疑這些刻字原本不是爲碑首所作；整體觀之，更像是因碑首尚存空白而後續添加的。</p>
                    <p>銘文寫道：</p>
                    <quote>造四面龕僧道密。<note>見本卷<ptr type="infra" target="WLS_transcription"/>録文卧龍山2號。</note>
                    </quote>
                    
                    <p>這則銘文通常被視爲僧人道密起初開鑿長方體巨石四面佛龕的證據，儘管南壁<!--實則-->未鑿成形佛龕，僅布有數排禪定小佛像。這是目前關於卧龍山佛教遺址建造的唯一信息。我們不難注意到那連提黎耶舍（517－589）曾有一位同名弟子，其傳記見於《續高僧傳》（T#2060，50：667b22－668a20）。<note>岡田健<ref type="biblio" target="Okada2000">第199頁，注11</ref>。</note>据那連提黎耶舍傳記所載（T#2060，50：432a24－433b6），道密曾於開皇二年七月[582年8月5日至9月3日]隨師抵達都城，在大興善寺參與經文翻譯工作，擔任筆受一職。<note>T#2060，50：433a4－5：“［開皇］二年七月，弟子道密等侍送入京，住大興善寺。”</note>道密本人的簡短傳記（T#2060，50：667b22－28）<note>道密傳記的主要内容（T#2060，50：667b22－668a20）并非關於此僧生平，而是講述隋文帝（581－604年在位）誕生及少時事迹。文帝生於同州大興國寺（今陜西渭南），并於此寺成長。這正是仁壽年間（601－604）隋文帝分送舍利時，道密被派遣前往的寺院。</note>亦證明他曾參與經文翻譯。儘管護送舍利到大興國寺的僧人道密或可能活至開元年間，但碑首上的七字銘文并未提供進一步證據，無法確認他與“造四面龕”的僧人爲同一人。</p>
                    <p>在刻有道密題記的素面碑首下方，碑文以二十縱列排布，并通過一行空白界格横向分隔爲上下兩部分。上部刻有碑文内容，而下部則列有四十七位供養人的名字。<note>肥田路美<ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2009">第111頁</ref>，提供了這份供養人名單的録文。肥田路美指出，在這些供養人中，以任氏和鄧氏人數最多。她認爲這兩族是當地具有影響力的氏族。</note>這份供養人名録以三欄排列，各欄之間再以兩條空白横列加以區隔。</p>
                    <p>這份名録中的每項供養人條目皆以個人姓名起首，後附“一軀”字樣。若供養人姓名僅有兩字，則附“造一軀”字樣。但有三個名字後附“二軀”字樣。共計47位供養人捐造了50尊造像。這一數字與第1龕阿彌陀佛净土變相中往生菩薩的數量恰好吻合，這并非偶然。由此可推測，這些供養人希望自己或其眷屬能往生阿彌陀佛净土，得蓮華化生。<note>這一造像數量與第1龕往生菩薩數目之間的對應關係，在肥田路美<ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2009">第112頁</ref>，已有論述。</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>供養人名單有時會被與碑首所載僧人道密的記載相關聯。部分學者認爲，僧人道密可能以類似於佛教邑義首領的身份，統領着下方所載的47個供養人。此類社團形式主要見於中國北方。<note>此觀點見於黄夏<ref type="biblio" target="Huangxia2018">第23頁</ref>，及楊筱<ref type="biblio" target="Yangxiao2021">第63－66頁</ref>[楊筱<ref type="biblio" target="Yangxiao2024">第30－31頁</ref>]。</note>然而碑文的設計本身并不必然支持此推論。如前所述，道密的署名在碑首的鎸刻位置頗爲局促。此外，供養人名單顯然是後來增刻，附屬於記載了年代、書法者及刻工姓名的碑文主體部分之後。碑文正文與供養人名單構成一份獨立的文書，無需與巨石四面龕窟的供養人産生關聯。</p>  
                    <div>
                        <head>傳像記</head>
                        <p>碑文首列題名爲《阿彌陀佛并五十二菩薩傳》，后署書法者鄧元覺之名，以及“作龕及鎸字之楊子尚”之名。鄧、楊二姓亦多次出現在下方供養人名單中。由此可合理推斷，此二人與第1龕造像的部分供養者之間存在關聯。值得注意的是，工匠楊子尚的貢獻不僅包括鎸刻碑文，還涉及某種石作工藝。但目前尚無法確定其具體參與程度——究竟是僅協助開鑿石料以辟佛龕，承擔雕琢造像這樣更具藝術性質的工作，還是負責刻繪龕拱上優美的紋飾。</p>
                        <p>因鎸刻有題名、書法者及刻工姓名，碑文首列較後續各列（每列19字）顯著冗長。首列縱貫至下部供養人名列，從而在視覺上將書法者和刻工姓名與其他供養人相連接。</p>
                        <p>從第2欄開始的銘文（本卷<ptr type="infra" target="Wolongtext_start Wolongtext_end"/>已録文并翻譯）記載了阿彌陀佛與五十菩薩像從印度傳至中國的故事。最後一欄明確紀年爲“貞觀八年七月十四日”，即公元634年8月13日。卧龍山碑銘由此成爲此文本最早的版本，該文後來又在《大藏經》中出現了三次。</p>
                        <p>這三次中的首次見於《集神州三寶感通録》（T#2106，下稱《三寶感通録》），此録由道宣（596－667）於664年編撰完成。與道宣本極爲接近的另一版本見於《法苑珠林》（T#2122，53：401a18－b4），該集由道世（卒年不詳）於668年編撰完成。最後，宗曉（1151－1214）所編《樂邦文類》（T#1969A，47：192a13－26）收録了此文本的又一版本，該版本在書中以“引文”形式呈現，但實際上帶有編者修改與詮釋的痕迹。收録于大藏經的諸版本較之早期卧龍山石刻本語義上更爲清晰，這可能得益於編者所進行的修訂潤色。</p>
                        <p>爲便於讀者理解傳像故事的始末脉絡，本文將首先譯出《三寶感通録》所載版本的内容。隨後，本文將通過文本分析，揭示此入藏文本與石刻版本在叙事脉絡上的差异。<note>岡田健<ref type="biblio" target="Okada2000">第166－173頁</ref>，及肥田路美<ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2017a">第1－15頁</ref>，亦采用了相同的研究方法。</note>最後，我們可以得出若干結論，以闡釋早期石刻版本與入藏本之間差异的成因。</p>
                        <p>關於阿彌陀佛與五十菩薩像的記載，乃道宣《三寶感通録》卷二所收録的50則靈應故事之一。<note>T#2106，52：404a7－435a19。篠原亨一<ref type="biblio" target="Shinohara1998"/>對這些靈應故事進行了概括分析，并提供了其他文本中的對應記載，其中主要包括《法苑珠林》（T#2122）、《廣弘明集》（T#2103）和《續高僧傳》（T#2060），偶爾也參考了其他文本。</note>編號爲第37的這則故事（T#2106，52：421a17－b3）所載如下：</p>
                        <quote>三十七：阿彌陀佛五十菩薩像者，西域天竺之瑞像也。相傳云，昔天竺雞頭摩寺<note>關於雞頭摩寺，詳見本卷<ptr type="infrafootnote_zh" target="Jitoumo"/>。</note>五通菩薩，<note>關於此尊菩薩，詳見本卷<ptr type="infrafootnote_zh" target="Wutongpusa"/>。</note>往安樂界請阿彌陀佛：“娑婆衆生願生净土，無佛形像，願力莫由。請垂降許。” 佛言：“汝且前去。尋當現彼。”及菩薩還，其像已至。一佛五十菩薩各坐蓮花，在樹葉上。<note xml:id="tree_zh">菩薩所坐的蓮花座與樹之間的關係，取决於我們將“樹葉”理解爲單數還是複數。在英譯時，我們傾向於采用單數解讀，并認爲下句中菩薩“取葉”之行爲，意在將其舒展至廣遠之境。肥田路美在將該文本譯爲現代日語時，對“樹葉”一詞進行了複數解讀（肥田路美<ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2011">第383－384頁</ref>）。顔娟英在將道宣文本的現代日語譯本轉譯爲現代漢語時，將此句表述爲“一佛五十菩薩各自在樹葉上的蓮花座上”。由於對原文采取複數解讀，肥田路美認爲，道宣所述圖像不同於常見的菩薩坐於池中蓮臺的圖式，而更近似於《覺禪鈔》册頁中所繪：五十二尊小像坐於蓮臺，隱現於巨樹枝葉之間（肥田路美<ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2011">第384頁</ref>；肥田路美<ref type="biblio" target="Hida_Yen2018">第370－371頁</ref>）。關於《覺禪鈔》及其題記之英譯，參見山部能宜<ref type="biblio" target="Yamabe1999">第324－326頁</ref>。北齊（550－577）與隋代（581－618）早期作品中亦可見菩薩坐於菩提樹葉間蓮臺之圖式，參見肥田路美<ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2017a">第9頁</ref>，黄夏所舉諸例：現存華盛頓弗利爾美術館的北齊浮雕，原爲南響堂山第1窟中央柱上部的裝飾；河南博物院藏開皇二年（582年）荀國醜等人所捐獻的造像碑；以及現藏於波士頓美術館的開皇十三年（593年）銅鑄壇具。</note>菩薩取葉<note>黄夏在肥田路美<ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2017a">第10頁</ref>，中對“取葉圖寫”（葉を取つて图写する）的注釋中提出，五通菩薩或許在一片樹葉上圖寫了所受之像，類似於將佛經書寫於羅樹葉的做法；參見真諦（499－569）傳記所載事例（T#2060：50：430b23）。</note>所在圖寫，流布遠近。漢明感夢，使往祈法。便獲迦葉摩騰等至洛陽。<note>關於明帝感夢的後續效應，詳見本卷<ptr type="infrafootnote_zh" target="dream"/>。</note>後騰姊子作沙門，持此瑞像，方達此國所在，圖之未幾，齎像西返。而此圖傳，不甚流廣。魏晋已來，年載久遠，又經滅法，經像湮除，此之瑞迹殆將不見。隋文開教，有沙門明憲，<note>參見本卷<ptr type="infrafootnote_zh" target="note_en_6a"/>。</note>從高齊道長法師<note>關於道長法師，詳見本卷<ptr type="infrafootnote_zh" target="note_en_7"/>。</note>所得此一本，説其本起與傳符焉。是以<note>當讀作“以是”而非“是以”。</note>圖寫流布遍於宇内。時有北齊畫工曹仲達者，本曹國人。<note>曹國（<foreign xml:lang="en">Ushrusana</foreign>）是位於今塔吉克斯坦北部的一個古代王國。</note>善於丹青，妙盡梵迹。傳模西瑞，<note>黄夏在肥田路美<ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2017a">第13－14頁</ref>，中對“傳模”過程的注釋中指出，南齊（479－502）的謝赫（活躍於約500年）在其《古畫品録》序言中定義了品評畫作的“六法”准則。其中第六法爲“傳移模寫”。因此，“傳模”在此可視爲“傳移模寫”的簡稱。《續高僧傳》（T#2060，50：695a28－b1）在住力（544－623）傳記中也提到了通過模寫來傳承<!--瑞祥-->祥瑞图像的做法，載：“大業十年[614] ，自竭身資，以栴檀香木，模寫瑞像并二菩薩。不久尋成同安閣内。”</note>京邑所推。故今寺壁正陽，皆其真範。<note>《樂邦文類》（T#1969A，47：192a25）中載“遺筆”而非“真範”。因此，Hida 2017a，第15頁，論斷“真範”於此當釋作“真筆”。<!--T#2106，52：421a17－b3。--></note>
                        </quote>
                        <p>道宣所記阿彌陀佛與五十菩薩像的叙事脉絡可分爲五個階段：</p>
                        <list type="ordered">
                            <item>安樂界授像與天竺承傳</item>
                            <item>迦葉摩騰親屬於漢世傳像</item>
                            <item>聖像隱没於魏（220－265）晋（265－420）</item>
                            <item>聖像復現於北齊（550－577）與隋（581－618）</item>
                            <item>曹仲達納像入藝</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>前四階段推進叙事的時間綫，而北齊畫師曹仲達之事則似乎僅僅爲聖像傳播譜系的增補條目。在早期階段，聖像的傳承與特定人物緊密相連。傳像始於阿彌陀佛，首先傳于五通菩薩，再由迦葉摩騰的姊子將其傳入人間。傳承一度中斷，后由道長法師與沙門明憲續傳。這些人物皆在特定時期親手持有此聖像。唯一的例外是曹仲達。
                            儘管文中極力稱贊其高招的繪畫技術，卻從未明確記載曹仲達曾親手接收或臨摹過這尊圖像。
                            這種關聯僅僅是基於一種的隱晦推斷：即通過提及曹仲達因承襲其家族原藉“西域”的“傳模”（傳授範本）而聲明遠揚，從而側面暗示了他與該圖像傳承譜係的關係。
                            <!--雖贊揚了他在繪畫上的精湛技藝，卻未曾明言他實際接觸或臨摹過該聖像。
                            這一説法僅間接源自曹氏因“傳模”西域家族傳來的造像範本而顯名的稱引。-->
                        </p>
                        <p>由此可推，道宣補録曹氏畫業的細節，乃是爲了增添叙事的趣味性。卧龍山早期石刻版本則全然未提及曹仲達一事。這是大藏經文本與石刻版本最顯著的分歧之處。其他差异則更爲隱微。不過對這些差异進行細緻分析，仍有助於揭示刻於第1龕旁銘文的一些重要特質。</p>
                        
                        
                        <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="wolong_niche3.jpg">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">卧龍山第2號龕中央釋迦牟尼佛像。2010年拍攝</head>
                            <head>Mount Wolong, niche 2 with central Śākyamuni Buddha; photograph taken in 2010</head>
                            <graphic url="wolong_niche3.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                        
                        <p>在第一部分關於授像的叙述中，石刻文本僅簡略復現阿彌陀佛與五通菩薩之間的對話，而入藏本則以教義論證支持五通所請，指出娑婆衆生需依憑聖像，來成就往生安樂世界之願。於是，聖像應允而現，自然化現於世間。兩種文本版本均對名爲“阿彌陀佛并五十菩薩”的聖像形貌進行了簡要描述，并均記載此像曾受到崇敬，廣爲流傳。石刻版本明確記載，聖像化現於五通菩薩面前時，被繪於一片樹葉之上。五通在此處是被動受像者，後來纔加以敬奉。<note>需要注意的是，關於五通菩薩如何獲得這一瑞像還存在另一個版本的記載。十三世紀的圖像學匯編《覺禪鈔》中收録有一幅册頁，描繪了一株巨樹，其葉片上坐著52尊小像。附文記載道：“菩薩速還本寺，其寺樹木葉上畫佛菩薩像。採集此樹葉數之有五十二體佛菩薩像。”</note>石刻文本進一步將此靈异聖像的授受事件錨定於人間歷史，記載道：“扵是彼國始有此瑞像焉。”此句未見於入藏本中。</p>
                        <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="WLS_niche2_DSC0857.JPG">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">卧龍山第2號龕。龕室<!--左-->右上角細部。2010年拍攝</head>
                            <head>Mount Wolong, niche 2. Detail of the upper left-hand corner of niche 2; photograph taken in 2010</head>
                            <graphic url="WLS_niche2_DSC0857.JPG"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>道宣對該像後來傳入中土的記載，呈現出清醒的歷史編年風格：明帝夜夢异像，遂遣使西行，後使者偕迦葉摩騰歸返帝都。此瑞像的傳入，與歷史上首位登陸中土的印度高僧形成關聯，係其侄隨叔父前來時將聖像一并帶入。雖然这位高僧一开始傳播了瑞像，但很快他就因未知的原因離開了中國，回到了印度。現代學術研究表明，這些記載均無史實依據。<note>關於漢明帝夢見异像的傳説作爲中國佛教起源叙述的重要西方研究成果包括馬伯樂<ref type="biblio" target="Maspero1910"/>，宋柏<ref type="biblio" target="Soper1959">第1－4頁</ref>，以及較爲近期的白安敦<ref type="biblio" target="Palumbo2003">第167－170頁</ref>。另見本卷<ptr type="infrafootnote_zh" target="dream"/>。</note>然而從道宣的觀點來看，這些事件乃是中國佛教正史的一部分。</p>
                        <p>儘管石刻版本在記載這段歷史時，沿用了相同的年代順序和人物，其叙述語調卻有所不同。首先，石刻本明確記載了漢明帝使臣的姓名<hi rend="dash">──</hi>蔡愔。在一段簡短的叙述中，文本勾勒出蔡愔遠赴印度的艱險旅程，期間他遇見迦葉摩騰并向其發出邀請，請他來中國建立佛寺。换言之，石刻本將事件的時間綫與人物關係緊密關聯，通過提及迦葉摩騰與其携像之侄的親屬關係，進一步强化了這一印象。石刻版本再次强調：“扵此漢地始有此像。”</p>
                        <p>在傳像記載的結尾部分，石刻版本補充了一段關於其侄携像突然返回印度的解釋，而這一細節未見於道宣的版本中。石刻本援引一處未具名典據，暗示此次返印爲勢所必然，緣由當時中土民衆尚無法珍視此聖像及其救度之力。不僅如此，文本還明確指出返回天竺的乃是“本像”。需要注意的是，直至此處，複製此像的行爲還從未被提及。</p>
                        <p>据文本所載第三階段，自魏晋以來，佛法屢遭厄難，聖像由是隱没不現。道宣的記載中提到的“瑞迹”<hi rend="dash">──</hi>可能爲本像之摹本<hi rend="dash">──</hi>今已不存。其原因在於歷次滅法中，經像普遍遭到湮除。<note>此處所指，或爲北魏太武帝（423－452年在位）於446至452年間及北周武帝（560－578年在位）於575至577年間所實施的滅佛運動。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>石刻本同樣痛陳佛法所遭“頹毀”，但若援引歷史上毁像事件爲證并無益處，因爲“本像”當時已不在中土。因此，石刻本解釋道：於此法難之際，“夢聞”瑞像重現實無可能。石刻本并未將聖像未現之不詳歸咎於外因，而是再次强調當時世運尚未成熟，使得此像難以重現中土。正如原始佛像在漢代必須返回印度一樣，其原因在於“人情䟽略”，即人們（對於佛教的）情感仍然冷淡而疏遠。</p>
                        <p>情勢直到北齊和隋代纔開始好轉起來。道宣以一貫的簡潔平實筆調，提到隋朝開國時期“開教”的情况，并記載一位名叫“明憲”的僧人從前朝高齊（北齊）的道長法師那裏獲得了該聖像的“一本”。在對照傳像記驗證此摹本的真實性後，更多“圖寫”得以在世界各地流傳。</p>
                        <p>石刻本中的相應段落與此相似。不過“明獻”的寫法有所不同，他從道長法師處獲得的物件被稱爲“一軀”，這一計量單位表明該聖像應爲立體，即雕塑造像。在確認新發現的聖像“與本無別”之後，該像最終得以“圗寫流布”。這是石刻本中首次提及對原始聖像的複製。</p>
                        <p>道宣的傳像記在明憲處結束，石刻本則還有下文。後者在前文記載了該聖像如何從安樂世界降臨至我們所在的娑婆世界，隨後如何傳入中土的經過。這裏又詳述了聖像如何傳入都城長安的具體歷程。据石刻所載，開皇十六年（596年），豫州刾史鄭獲此聖像，并將其與傳像記一并送往都城。聖像最終被供奉于長安真寂寺，廣受信衆禮拜。</p>
                        <p>這是阿彌陀佛與五十菩薩像傳承鏈中的最後一環。該記載遺漏了聖像傳承的最終環節，即從都城傳到四川梓潼縣的過程。然而，若碑首所載“造四面龕僧道密”與那連提黎耶舍的同名弟子爲同一人，則確有可能是他將此像自都城携至四川。</p>
                        
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>傳像記還是聖傳？</head>
                        <p>藝術史學者已充分認可《傳像記》在研究阿彌陀佛與五十菩薩像母題演變過程中的重要意義。他們特别指出，該圖像母題最早分别出現於四川的卧龍山和碧水寺，而《傳像記》爲這些造像作品中所呈現的外來藝術風格特徵提供了可信的解釋。然而多數研究者在追溯這一圖像母題的起源時，僅參考或最初僅參考了入藏本。<note>李巳生<ref type="biblio" target="LiSisheng1991">第49－54頁</ref>；肥田路美<ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2011">第383－384頁</ref> [肥田路美<ref type="biblio" target="Hida_Yen2018">第370－371頁</ref>]；肥田路美<ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2017a">第1－15頁</ref>。</note>石刻版被提及時，主要是用來佐證該圖像母題在隋代便已流傳，以及其傳播路徑是首先傳入都城，繼而繼而傳入四川地區。<note>胡文和<ref type="biblio" target="Huwenhe1991">第90頁</ref>；胡文和<ref type="biblio" target="HuWenhe1994">第245－247頁</ref>；倪雅梅<ref type="biblio" target="McNair2007">第105－106頁</ref>；肥田路美<ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2009">第109－116頁</ref>；蔣曉春<ref type="biblio" target="Jiang_Fu_Luo_Lei2018">第361－362頁</ref>；楊筱<ref type="biblio" target="Yangxiao2021">第212－213頁</ref>。</note>迄今爲止，藝術史學者將石刻版《傳像記》與道宣的<!--入藏經-->版本視爲研究該藝術母題歷史發展的核心文獻。這一母題於七世紀成功傳遍整個東亞地區，并在此後持續興盛。</p>
                        <p>部分學者在搜尋原始文獻時注意到，江都（今江蘇揚州）安樂寺僧人惠海（541－609）的傳記中也提到了由印度菩薩“五通”所繪製的安樂世界變相圖。<note>李巳生<ref type="biblio" target="LiSisheng1991">第49頁</ref>；肥田路美<ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2017a">第5頁</ref>；山部能宜<ref type="biblio" target="Yamabe1999">第325－326頁</ref>。</note>《續高僧傳》的相關記載如下：</p>
                        <quote>忽有齊州僧道詮，齎畫無量壽像來云：“是天竺雞頭摩寺五通菩薩，乘空往彼安樂世界圖寫尊儀。”既冥會素情，深懷禮懺。乃睹神光炤爍，慶所希幸。於是模寫，懇苦願生彼土。<note>T#2060，50：515c14－19。此段亦見於山部能宜<ref type="biblio" target="Yamabe1999">第325頁</ref>。</note>
                        </quote>
                        <p>然而，此段記載并未對《傳像記》所述傳承譜系有所增補，因爲記中道詮所得無量壽佛像，是否呈現爲被五十或五十二菩薩所環繞，仍未可確知。
                            關於印度鷄頭摩寺五通菩薩乘空往净土的記載，很可能僅是借用了<!--和净土主尊 -->無量壽佛/阿彌陀佛住安樂國相關的文學母題。關於惠海從道詮處獲得聖像的記載，首先可被視爲隋代阿彌陀佛瑞像信仰及其崇拜盛行的確證。</p>
                        <p>迄今爲止，衹有岡田健<!--（Okada Ken）-->對早期石刻版《傳像記》與大藏經版本進行過系統比較研究。<note>岡田健<ref type="biblio" target="Okada2000">第163－173頁</ref>。</note>岡田健的這一分析研究，其動機在於對史實性的探尋。例如，他將銘文中提及的“鷄頭摩寺”，辨識爲玄奘（600/602－664）巡禮過的位於摩揭陀國的“雞園僧伽藍”。由於玄奘的記載中并未提及該地存在阿彌陀佛瑞像崇拜，岡田健由此推斷，這一傳説很可能并非起源於印度，而是形成於中國本土。此外，他遺憾地指出，在現存史料中我們無法根據明憲/明獻這一名字考證這位僧人的身份，豫州刾 史鄭的歷史身份也同樣無法確認。因此，岡田衹能得出結論，就史實而言，重要的是要注意到阿彌陀佛與五十菩薩像是從隋代都城傳播開來的。</p>
                        <p>本研究没有將《傳像記》視爲適用於重構圖像母題歷史的文獻資源。如岡田的研究所示，它并不能滿足此研究目的。我們傾向於假設，《傳像記》的意涵實源於其與第1龕造像在空間上的毗鄰關係，并且認爲銘文與圖像間存在緊密關聯<hi rend="dash">──</hi>這纔是石刻本有别於道宣本之處。</p>
                        <p>如上述諸版對比所示，早期石刻文本非但篇幅長於大藏經本，更囊括了未爲道宣所采之内容（若該石刻本確爲其編纂所据之源）。這些内容涉及該聖像從古印度東傳至中國所經歷的時間和空間跨度<hi rend="dash">──</hi>自其首現於世，經漢代初傳中土，復又流布於隋唐兩代之都，迄於今時。顯然，這一時間綫旨在佐證《傳像記》首句所載的可信性，即該聖像乃自西域傳至中土。</p>
                        <p>然而，《傳像記》的初載不僅關乎于聖像起源，更涉及其特殊屬性，即作爲“瑞像”的本質。此類聖像非但能顯現靈异，更以自有靈性而著稱。瑞像可與現實衆生交感，常以夢境示現，藉此傳達其旨意。它們以吉兇之兆，預示王朝興替。它們對其所居之地具有某種掌控之力。衹要聖像仍需由人力携行至他處，它們便輕巧可移；一旦抵達預定之地，便重不可徙，以示其栖止之所。必要時，它們會自行行走，或乘船，或漂浮於水上。<note>這種自主移動的能力，是特定類型瑞像的特徵：即那些被認爲由孔雀王朝阿育王（約公元前268年－232年在位）所造、后傳入中國的聖像。參見篠原亨一<ref type="biblio" target="Shinohara2004">第182－184頁</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>在此語境中，我們得以理解石刻文本叙事中所呈現的種種特殊之處，而這些是道宣版本所未見的。被迦葉摩騰之侄携帶至中國的是原始本像，而非其複刻本。正如五通菩薩作爲聖像的感應示現者，這位僧人則擔當了其承載者的角色。他“持此像來”，并“將此像而歸”。赴中土與返印度皆非僧人之自主選擇，而是由聖像所决定。其返回之因亦有明示，即中土衆生緣念疏遠。</p>
                        <p>聖像返回印度之後，静候機緣，念以夢境示現之可能。托夢乃瑞像傳意之常法，或向夢者昭示愿求，或預警危難，或震懾敵障。<note>參見道宣故事所載二例：第28則（T#2106，52：419b7－c5）記梁武帝（502－549年在位）感夢事（篠原亨一<ref type="biblio" target="Shinohara1998">第153－154頁；173頁；181頁</ref>），及第33則（T#2106，52：420b21－c4）述晋州靈石寺石像托夢求修繕事（篠原亨一<ref type="biblio" target="Shinohara1998">第161頁；172頁；182頁</ref>）。宋柏<ref type="biblio" target="Soper1959">第1－121頁</ref>，在其中國朝代綜論中，輯録了公元1至6世紀文獻所傳的若干托夢事例。托夢母題亦見於山東泰山主峰北麓的玉泉寺（舊稱谷山寺）的建寺傳説中。此傳説載於1201年《谷山寺記碑》，講到一尊羅漢像托夢示現，後爲當地民衆發現并遷至寺院現址，參見温狄婭<ref type="biblio" target="Wenzel2022">第28－31頁</ref>。</note>《傳像記》所述聖像需昭示其真容，即“阿彌陀佛坐千葉蓮華，同根竝出”。雖碑文未載此聖像細節於何時、向何人昭示，但明獻法師確於最早的可能時點<hi rend="dash">──</hi>即隋文帝開皇元年，亦即佛教治世之始<hi rend="dash">──</hi>獲得“此一軀”聖像。</p>
                        <p>自此以後，原雕像的摹製品開始在中土流傳，其形象得以遍布各地。但這些摹製之像均被認證爲“與本無别”。作爲真迹憑證，它們與“本傳”一同流傳。</p>
                        <p>綜合上述證據，《阿彌陀佛并五十二菩薩傳》中真正的能動主體并非那些曾接觸及持像的人物，而是像本身。因此，“傳”字在銘文標題中，似乎不僅可以理解爲關於聖像如何傳入中土及卧龍山的“傳報”，亦可視爲此像的“傳記”甚或“聖傳”。類比《高僧傳》及其續編所集聖僧傳記，此處我們所面對的，實則爲一尊瑞像的生平事迹<hi rend="dash">──</hi>述其如何出現於世、游歷世間，以及藉此所欲達成之目的。</p>
                        <p>將《傳像記》作爲阿彌陀佛與五十菩薩像的聖傳式記載來解讀，我們由此認識到此聖像具有與佛陀舍利相媲美的神聖力量。這種觀感更因阿彌陀佛及五十菩薩像并非由工匠所造，而是由賜予顯現而成，而愈加被强化。無論是石刻文本還是大藏經文本，它們皆强調了此像的這一特質。阿彌陀佛本可允許五通菩薩描繪其“真容”，或協助其完成此造像，<note>此情節見於慧海傳記（T#2060，50：515c14－19）所載版本，詳見前文。</note>但他没有這麽做。相反，他先遣退五通，而後自顯聖像。</p>
                        <p>在道宣文本中，五通以一種祈求恩賜的姿態，請求佛像能“垂降”示現。相比之下，石刻文本并未使用“垂降”佛像的措辭，此説法暗示安樂世界位於人界上方，恰與《無量壽經》（<hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sukhā­vatī­vyūha-sūtra</foreign>
                            </hi>）中所述相違。<note>《無量壽經》（<hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sukhā­vatī­vyūha-sūtra</foreign>
                                </hi>）將安樂界描繪爲一個完全獨立於娑婆世界的體系，位於遥遠西方不可量劫之處。然而六世紀的漢地造像題記顯示，信衆將阿彌陀佛（無量壽佛）之净土想象成一個類似於本世界系中的“天”界，與彌勒所居兜率天相類。關於“垂降佛像”一詞所藴意涵的詳細分析，參見稲葉秀郎<!--（Inaba Hiderō）-->於肥田路美<ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2017a">第4－8頁</ref>，所作的相應注釋。稲葉秀郎總結指出，隋代流傳阿彌陀佛與五十菩薩像之時，尚未出現“天界”與“净土”之分。</note>石刻文本則載佛陀允諾此像將被“尋遣送往[娑婆世界]”。因此，正如道宣所言，該佛像如同承擔了阿彌陀佛的使者角色，具備實現往生净土誓願的神效之力。由是觀之，此瑞像實與佛陀舍利同功，皆以延續佛陀住世應化爲主要宗旨，幾乎可視爲其本生故事的延續。<note>xxx<ref type="biblio" target="Strong2004">第229頁</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>此般考辨遂引出問題<hi rend="dash">──</hi>卧龍山鎸刻文本當屬何種文學體例？就目前所知，卧龍山所刻《傳像記》似乎是此類題材中唯一的代表。縱觀同主題造像遺存，并没有其他與之類似的銘文相伴出現。然而，該圖像中藴含的聖僧傳記特徵與佛陀舍利之間的密切關聯表明，它可能與三十年後纔首次得到證實的一種文本體裁存在淵源。</p>
                        <p>這種文本體裁的典型例證可見於石質碑刻，通常被鎸刻在描繪歷史上的佛陀於摩揭陀國首都巴連弗邑所遺留下的佛足印下方。在《大唐西域記》中，玄奘記載了一則傳説：釋迦牟尼預知阿育王將於涅槃百年后對其聖迹進行朝拜，遂於巨石之上留下雙足印記。<note>T#2087，51：911c10－22；英譯見李榮熙<ref type=" biblio" target="LiRongxi1996">第199－200頁</ref>；<ref type="biblio" target="Beal1884">卷2：第90－91頁</ref>。</note>刻在足迹下方的碑文也提到了這則傳説。</p>
                        <p>現存最早的佛足碑實物，見於陜西省宜君縣玉華寺遺址出土的三塊殘片中。在這些殘片上刻畫有一雙足迹，脚趾朝上，足底飾以吉祥紋案。旁側銘文題爲《佛迹記》。殘片僅保留了銘文的開頭部分，其中提及了巴連弗邑石垣佛足聖迹，乃“奘親觀禮圖”。由於玄奘於659－664年駐玉華寺，學界普遍推定該佛足碑刻於此期間。碑印佛足圖像應是依據玄奘返回中土時所携帶的巴連弗邑原迹的摹本所製。<note>温狄婭<ref type="biblio" target="Wenzel2020">第654－656頁</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>玉華寺佛足碑不僅開創了新的圖像學傳統，也催生出一種新的文學體裁，即這裏所稱的“記”。之後所見的另一通据稱摹自巴連弗邑原迹的佛足碑，爲“太明洪武丁卯”年（即1387年）由長安卧龍禪寺提點寒水僧德明所立。此碑佛足圖像下方的佛足記全文俱存。</p>
                        <p>碑銘首段與《大唐西域記》相應段落高度契合。與玄奘版本不同的是，碑文還提到此佛足聖記在天竺歷經八次毁佛之難而竟得全存。此段叙述似在暗示，佛印於天竺等待玄奘的到來。玄奘以朝聖者之身前往，瞻禮佛足，并摹其形迹帶回中國，獻於皇帝。最終，皇帝下詔推廣，使其得以廣汎流傳。卧龍禪寺碑記后附題記，其中僧人德明自述於1387年<!--奉敕-->令重刻佛足碑之事。<note>圖示見常盤大定和関野貞<ref type="biblio" target="Tokiwa_Sekino1939-1941">9册：第45頁（1）</ref>。録文及銘文英譯見温狄婭<ref type="biblio" target="Wenzel2020">第656－659頁</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>此後，卧龍禪寺佛足碑又多次被摹刻複製。著名的河南登封少林寺於1566年立有一方摹本，<note>圖示及銘文録文見常盤大定和関野貞<ref type="biblio" target="Tokiwa_Sekino1939-1941">9册：第46頁（1）；文第45頁</ref>。</note>浙江寧波的阿育王寺於1899年立有另一方。<note>圖示及銘文録文見常盤大定和関野貞<ref type="biblio" target="Tokiwa_Sekino1939-1941">9册：第46頁（3）；文第45頁</ref>。</note>每當佛足被摹刻於新碑之上，關於其何以流入中國的傳迹記便會被續寫於新的題記中，并述其摹刻源流。如此一來，佛印圖案傳播路綫得以逐次延申銘記。</p>
                        <p>我們知道，玄奘所携巴連弗邑足印摹本及其附帶的傳迹記已傳至朝鮮。亦有證據表明，另一組巴連弗邑佛足摹本曾在中國流通，并最終傳至東瀛（現日本）。此組足印乃由使臣王玄策（622?－682年）由天竺携歸。陜西耀縣所存宋代（960－1279年）佛足印孤本，則屬另一圖像類型。其附文記載，早期的朝聖僧人法顯（320?－420?）於現斯里蘭卡之地摹寫佛足印，并將它們帶回中土。<note>温狄婭<ref type="biblio" target="Wenzel2020">663－665頁</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>“佛足碑”與卧龍山第1龕造像旁的聖記式《傳像記》具有相同的功能<hi rend="dash">──</hi>皆旨在將重要的原像之摹本置於從天竺至中土、朝鮮，乃至東瀛之悠久的傳承譜系之中。因此在中古時期，阿彌陀佛與五十二菩薩等像不僅是聖境化現，也被視作涉及整個佛教世界的地標。</p>
                </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="en">
                <head>Mount Wolong</head>
                <p>On Mount Wolong, a modest building from the late Qing shelters the remains of its early Tang predecessor. This earlier structure took the form of a “Buddha-<hi rend="italic">
                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">stūpa</foreign>
                    </hi>,” an ancient building type attested mostly in literary sources, but with Central Asian prototypes. At the center of the present-day hall stands a massive cuboid boulder that may originally have been surrounded by four outer walls and a narrow corridor. The image niche located on the east face of this boulder has long drawn the attention of scholars. Dated to the eight year of the <hi rend="italic">zhenguan</hi> era (634), it depicts the same iconographic theme as that found at Bishui Monastery, namely, <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Buddha and 52 bodhisattvas seated on lotuses in the Pure Land. On the nearby rock, an inscription was carved on the form of a stele. This inscription names <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Buddha surrounded by his bodhisattvas an “auspicious image from the West.” It reports in some detail how the image came into our world, and how it travelled from ancient India to China. A parallel version of the inscribed text is found in Daoxuan’s <hi rend="italic">Miraculous Responses to the Three Jewels</hi>. The record of the image’s transmission to China not only aims at authenticating the auspicious image at display, but also supplies a hagiographical account for it.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>Site</head>


                    <p><!--Thousand Buddha Cliff (Qianfo Ya <foreign xml:lang="zh">千佛崖</foreign>) at Mount Wolong (Wolong Shan <foreign xml:lang="zh">卧龍山</foreign>) is one of two sites with Buddhist cliff sculptures in Zitong County (Zitong Xian <foreign xml:lang="zh">梓潼縣</foreign>).<note>The second site is that of Xiyan Monastery (Xiyan Si <foreign xml:lang="zh">西巖寺</foreign>), 0.5 km west of the county town of Zitong; it is documented in <ref type="biblio" target="Zitong_XiyanSi2010">157–176</ref>.</note> -->Thousand Buddha Cliff (Qianfo Ya <foreign xml:lang="zh">千佛崖</foreign>) at Mount Wolong (Wolong Shan <foreign xml:lang="zh">卧龍山</foreign>) lies 15 km west of the county town. The mountain derived its name from the famous statesman and general of the early Three Kingdoms period (220–280), Zhuge Liang <foreign xml:lang="zh">諸葛亮</foreign> (181–234), whose sobriquet was “Sleeping Dragon” (Wolong <foreign xml:lang="zh">卧龍</foreign>). During his Northern Expeditions (228–234) against the state of Wei <foreign xml:lang="zh">魏</foreign>, Zhuge Liang erected a garrison on top of the mountain. This stronghold, of which the ruins of four gates have remained, had a circumference of about 3,000 m. In 304, when Li Xiong <foreign xml:lang="zh">李雄</foreign> (274–334) seized the throne in Chengdu to reign as
                        Emperor Wu <foreign xml:lang="zh">武帝</foreign> of the Cheng Han <foreign xml:lang="zh">成漢</foreign> dynasty (304–347), he erected an ancestor shrine for Zhuge Liang at this place out of gratitude for the famous general. In 535, this shrine became part of a newly built Buddhist monastery commonly known as Mount Ge Monastery (Ge Shan Si <foreign xml:lang="zh">葛山寺</foreign>).<note>
                            <ref type="biblio" target="QiuChangzhong1998">42</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                   
                    <p>Not much has remained of this ancient monastery. At present, a modest complex of buildings from the late Qing <foreign xml:lang="zh">清</foreign> dynasty (1644–1911) can be visited at the site (fig. <ptr target="WLS_DJI_0622.JPG"/>).<note>In addition, <ref type="biblio" target="QiuChangzhong1998">43</ref>, mentions two steles on the present temple ground, one dated to 1880 (sixth year of the Guangxu era <foreign xml:lang="zh">光緒六年</foreign>) and the other to 1927 (sixteenth year of the Republican era <foreign xml:lang="zh">民國十六年</foreign>), which report on Buddhist activities.</note> One of these was erected for the protection of a group of Buddhist niches hewn into a single cuboid boulder during the early Tang dynasty (fig. <ptr target="WLS_IMG_6149.JPG"/>).</p>
                    <p>These niches’ importance as artifacts of cultural heritage was already noted by the pioneering scholar of Chinese architecture, Liang Sicheng <foreign xml:lang="zh">梁思成</foreign> (1901–1972). Together with his wife Lin Huiyin <foreign xml:lang="zh">林徽因</foreign> (Phyllis Lin), and others, Liang conducted surveys of important sites of cultural heritage in 15 Chinese provinces from 1937 onwards.<note>
                            <ref type="biblio" target="Huwenhe1991">81</ref>.</note> An inscription carved on the rock above the eastern niche (niche 3) opposite the entrance of the building (fig. <ptr target="WLS_niche3_1917_CIMG4626.JPG"/>) attests to protective measures taken after Liang and his group surveyed the site:</p>
                    <quote>The Central Committee for the Safe-Keeping of Ancient Artifacts makes known: For the protection of ancient artifacts, refurbishing is strictly forbidden. To be kept in mind; second day of the eleventh month of the twenty-eighth year of the Republic [November 2, 1939] <foreign xml:lang="zh">中央古物保管委員會示：保護古物，嚴禁重粧。民二八年十一月二日紀念</foreign>
                        <note>See also the transcription in <ref type="biblio" target="Huwenhe1991">81</ref>, which, however, mistakes the characters “twenty-eight” (<hi rend="italic">er ba </hi> <foreign xml:lang="zh">二八</foreign>) written on top of each other for the character “six” (<hi rend="italic">liu </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">六</foreign>).</note>
                    </quote>
                    <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="WLS_DJI_0622.JPG">
                        <head xml:lang="zh">卧龍山。航拍建築群現貌。2022年拍攝</head>
                        <head> Mount Wolong. Aerial view of present-day buildings; photograph taken in 2022</head>
                        <graphic url="WLS_DJI_0622.JPG"/>
                    </figure> 
                    <p>Prohibition of the re-furbishing of the images niches aimed at the common Buddhist practice of renovating and repainting the sculptures in order to generate karmic merit. At the time this note was carved above niche 3, the Chinese intellectual elite cherished the idea that cave shrines <!--such as those at Mount Wolong -->constituted a <!--precious-->national asset in need of protection in its “original” state. During the Republic of China, we see here the beginning of an academic involvement with cultural properties according to scientific guidelines, and an appreciation of cultural assets in the context of the building of a modern nation. The state, here represented by the Central Committee for the Safe-Keeping of Ancient Artifacts, took control over religious sites that had been maintained for many centuries mainly by Buddhist clerics and private believers.<note>For an introduction to the twentieth-century history of modern archaeology and conservation in the context of Sichuan sites of cultural heritage, see <ref type="biblio" target="LeeSonyaS2021"/>, in particular her chapter 3 on “Dazu Site Managers, Land, Community.”</note> After the initial survey of 1939, however, not much happened at the remote site of Mount Wolong.  </p>
                   
                    <p>Finally, from December 2007 to February 2008, a comprehensive survey of the site was undertaken when the Sichuan Provincial Institute of Cultural Heritage and Archaeology (Sichuan sheng wenwu kaogu yanjiu yuan <foreign xml:lang="zh">四川省文物考古研究院</foreign>), the Academy of the Arts at Sichuan University (Sichuan daxue yishuxue yuan <foreign xml:lang="zh">四川大學藝術學院</foreign>), the Mian­yang Municipal Office for Cultural Heritage (Mian­yang Shi wenwuju <foreign xml:lang="zh">綿陽市文物局</foreign>), and the Administrative Office for the Cultural Heritage of Zitong County (Zitong Xian wenwu guanli suo <foreign xml:lang="zh">梓潼縣文物管理所</foreign>) joined forces to provide detailed descriptions, drawings, and 3D-scans of niches 1–3.<note>The results of this survey are published in <ref type="biblio" target="Zitong_WolongShan2010">115–156</ref>.</note> This careful survey generated on outburst of academic publications on the site, and on the pictorial art of the western niche 3 and its accompanying stele inscription in particular. </p>
                   
                    

                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Boulder and Image Niches</head>
                    <p>At the center of the modern protective building is a single cuboid boulder, which measures 330 cm in height, 550 cm from east to west, and 520 cm from north to south.<note>Measurements after <ref type="biblio" target="QiuChangzhong1998">42</ref>.</note> 
                        Three large niches with images were opened at its east, north, and west sides. The south side has no such large niche. Instead, the wall surface was covered by about 20 rows of shallow niches in the Thousand Buddha pattern, each row containing 50 seated Buddha figures.<note>
                            <ref type="biblio" target="QiuChangzhong1998">42</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The boulder used to be part of the mountain rock from which it was separated by opening a passageway in the west for the purpose of circumambulation. During recent renovation work, the top of the boulder became accessible. A photograph taken from its top (fig. <ptr target="WLS_DSC07899.JPG"/>) shows that the roof of the late Qing building rests on wooden pillars and on walls of bricks laid on top of the natural bedrock from which the cuboid boulder was dressed. In addition, we see that rows of stones are heaped up on the south-western part of the boulder’s top. Some of these show traces of work, such as flattening, polishing, and drilling of holes.</p>
                    <p>Liang Sicheng has already compared the shape of the boulder with its image niches, now protected inside a building, to caves with a central pillar like those at the Yungang cave shrines (Yungang shiku <foreign xml:lang="zh">雲岡石窟</foreign>).<note>
                            <ref type="biblio" target="Yangxiao2024">13–14</ref>.</note> Apart from central pillar caves that are common at China’s large and well-known cave shrines—the Yungang caves near Datong <foreign xml:lang="zh">大同</foreign> in Shanxi Province, and the Mogao caves <foreign xml:lang="zh">摸高石窟</foreign> near Dunhuang <foreign xml:lang="zh">敦煌</foreign> in Gansu Province—two more sites have structures comparable to the Mount Wolong cuboid boulder.</p> 
                       
                    <p>The first is Bahui Monastery (Bahui Si <foreign xml:lang="zh">八會寺</foreign>; dated around 593–598) in Quyang <foreign xml:lang="zh">曲陽</foreign>, Hebei, where a similar walled-in boulder with Buddhist niches stands on top of a low terrace, protected at present by a stone hut.<note>For a brief introduction to this site and the texts carved inside the niches, see <ref type="biblio" target="Roesch2023">53–55</ref>. The most comprehensive study on the texts at Bahui Monastery to date is <ref type="biblio" target="ZhaoZhou2010a"/>.</note> On top of the boulder with the niches, natural stones are heaped up in the shape of a slightly jutting round pillar. This structure has a flat ceiling made up of several large, flat stones. Today, the boulder and its superstructure is wrapped in decorative bands indicating a function comparable to a stupa (fig. <ptr target="BahuiSi_DSC1314.jpg"/>). </p>
                        <figure rend="left" n="figure" xml:id="WLS_niche3_1917_CIMG4626.JPG">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">卧龍山第3號龕。民國二八年［1939年］題記。2009年拍攝</head>
                            <head>Mount Wolong, niche 3. Inscription dated 1939; photograph taken in 2009</head>
                        <graphic url="WLS_niche3_1917_CIMG4626.JPG"/>
                    </figure>  
                        <p>The second site is Four Gates Stupa (Simen Ta <foreign xml:lang="zh">四門塔</foreign>; ca. 611) at Shentong Monastery (Shengtong Si <foreign xml:lang="zh">神通寺</foreign>; ca. 611) in Licheng <foreign xml:lang="zh">歷城</foreign> District, Jinan <foreign xml:lang="zh">濟南</foreign>, Shandong Province (fig. <ptr target="ShentongSi_SimenTa_JAC7420_DxO_cut.jpg"/>). The Four Gates Stupa is one of the earliest surviving Buddhist stone buildings in all of China. Its exterior shape preserves characteristics of single-tier Buddhist stupas of central Asian origin, although the low finial (<hi rend="italic">chattra</hi>; <hi rend="italic">tacha</hi> <foreign xml:lang="zh">塔刹</foreign>)—composed of a base with banana leaf-shaped acroteria and stacked dishes with a cone-shaped tip—crowns a pyramid-shaped roof, and not a spherical dome. Inside is a rectangular central shaft made of stoneblocks. In front of each of the shaft’s four sides, Buddha icons are placed on altar platforms. These could be circumambulated along the narrow passageway in between the massive central shaft and the outside walls of the stupa (fig. <ptr target="Simenta_JAC7416_DxO.jpg"/>). </p>
                    <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="BahuiSi_DSC1314.jpg">
                        <head xml:lang="zh">河北曲陽八會寺。中央巨岩東側，可見由天然石塊構成的上部結構。2023年拍攝</head>
                        <head>Bahui Monastery, Quyang, Hebei. East side of the central boulder with superstructure composed of natural stones; photograph taken in 2023</head>
                        <graphic url="BahuiSi_DSC1314.jpg"/>
                    </figure>
                   
                    <p>The above examples open up the possibility that, unlike the stretch of natural cliff protected today inside Guanyin Hall (Guanyin dian <foreign xml:lang="zh">觀音殿</foreign>) at Bishui Monastery (Bishui Si <foreign xml:lang="zh">碧水寺</foreign>; see pp. <ptr type="infra" target="BSS_start BSS_end"/> in the present volume), the boulder at Mount Wolong was already part of an overarching architectural structure at the time of its creation during the early Tang. It may be compared to an ancient building type that is known to have once been spread widely across the central Asian kingdom of Kucha (Qiuci <foreign xml:lang="zh">龜茲</foreign>). In literary sources, we find the term “Buddha-<hi rend="italic">
                            <foreign xml:lang="sa">stūpa</foreign>
                        </hi>” (<hi rend="italic">Fo tamiao </hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="zh">佛塔廟</foreign>) for this type of building. The appearance of such a freestanding Buddha-<hi rend="italic">
                            <foreign xml:lang="sa">stūpa</foreign>
                        </hi> was recently reconstructed digitally on the basis of a depiction from the late Northern Wei <foreign xml:lang="zh">北魏</foreign> period (386–534) in Mogao Cave 257 at Dunhuang.<note>This digital reconstruction was made in <ref type="biblio" target="Zhou_Sun2024"/>. The authors identify the reconstructed building type on the basis of the following entry on Kucha in fascicle 97 of the <hi rend="italic">History of the Jin Dynasty</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Jinshu </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">晋書</foreign>): “The kingdom of Kucha lies 8,280 <hi rend="italic">li</hi> to the west of Luoyang. It is custom to live in walled cities. These cities are surrounded by three walls; inside, there are a thousand Buddha-<hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">stūpa</foreign>
                            </hi>s.” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">龜茲國西去洛陽八千二百八十里，俗有城郭，其城三重，中有佛塔廟千所。</foreign>) Because the <hi rend="italic">History of the Jin Dynasty</hi> was compiled rather late, in 646–648, by Fang Xuanling <foreign xml:lang="zh">房玄齡</foreign>, the entry on Kucha appears anachronistic for a building type dated to the Northern Wei (386–534) or earlier. There is, however, a possibility that the <hi rend="italic">History of the Jin Dynasty</hi> quotes here from earlier sources, as the term <hi rend="italic">tamiao </hi> <foreign xml:lang="zh">塔廟</foreign> is already attested for the sixth century. <ref type="biblio" target="Radich2025">Table 1, #A0733</ref>, provides a philological analysis of <hi rend="italic">tamiao</hi>, and reviews how the interpretation of this important term shaped the field of Buddhist studies.</note> The painting in question is one of the earliest Dunhuang murals that represents an architectural frame around a Buddha image. Due to the front view of the image and its architectural frame, we seem to perceive the dome of a stupa with finial on top of a traditional Chinese hall, in which the Buddha icon is placed. By translating this front view into three-dimensional architecture, the theoretical reconstruction of a hybrid building emerged, which suggests that the gable roofed hall stood in front of a separate courtyard with a flat roof, on top of which the domed stupa was placed. The Buddha icon, which occupies the center of the mural, was supposedly located in a sanctified space inside the backyard building.</p>
                    <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="WLS_DSC07775.JPG">
                        <head xml:lang="zh">卧龍山長方體巨石（第2龕）北側視角，修繕期間設有脚手架。2022年拍攝</head>
                        <head>Mount Wolong. View of the north side of the cuboid boulder (niche 2) with scaffolding during renovation; photograph taken in 2022</head>
                        <graphic url="WLS_DSC07775.JPG"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>A closer look at the cuboid boulder at Mount Wolong shows more traces of ancient masonry construction. At the north side of the boulder, a long groove runs horizontally above niche 2 (fig. <ptr target="WLS_DSC07775.JPG"/>). Holes have been drilled occasionally, as if the groove helped keeping in place some sort of porch or ceiling. Moreover, the bedrock part of the west wall of the present building reaches up to about the same height as the boulder. In the background of the photograph that was taken from the boulder’s top (fig. <ptr target="WLS_DSC07899.JPG"/>), we see that the northern and western stretch of the top of the bedrock was dressed into a protruding edge that may have hold some sort of flat ceiling. The central boulder conceivably could have been surrounded by a roofed corridor. </p>
                   
                   
                    <!--<figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="WLS_DSC07775.JPG">
                        <head xml:lang="zh">。2022年拍攝</head>
                        <head>North side of the cuboid boulder at Mount Wolong during restoration work; photograph taken in 2022</head>
                        <graphic url="WLS_DSC07775.JPG"/>
                    </figure>--> 
                    <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="wolong_niche4.jpg">
                        <head xml:lang="zh">卧龍山第3龕倚坐佛像。2010年拍攝</head>
                        <head>Mount Wolong, niche 3 with Buddha in  <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">bhadrāsana</foreign>
                            </hi>; photograph taken in 2010</head>
                        <graphic url="wolong_niche4.jpg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Following this line of thought, the central boulder probably was surrounded by four outer walls and a narrow corridor comparable to the interior of the Four Gates Stupa at Shentong Monastery.<note>A similar suggestion has been made by <ref type="biblio" target="Yangxiao2024">14</ref>.</note> The most striking feature of the Four Gates Pagoda, and also of the type of freestanding “pagoda-temple” reconstructed from the Dunhuang mural in cave 257, is the <hi rend="italic">chattra</hi> on top of the building (fig. <ptr target="ShentongSi_SimenTa_JAC7420_DxO_cut.jpg"/>. We may assume that the original building at Mount Wolong was also crowned by some sort of finial to mark the place as a holy space decorated with Buddhist icons.</p>
                   
                    <p>On the north-western edge of the boulder’s top, two or three rows of irregularly shaped stones have remained. It is hard to tell how these were originally arranged, and what their purpose may have been, but they all show traces of flattening, polishing, and some have holes drilled into them. Thus, they may have been part of the base of a superstructure like a <hi rend="italic">chattra</hi>.</p>
                    
                    <p>A visitor entering the hall from the east is received by a large figure group that has been numbered niche 3 (fig. <ptr target="wolong_niche4.jpg"/>). The niche, which measures 210 cm in height, 225 cm in width, and 190 cm in depth, is set so deep into the cuboid boulder that two sidewalls were created. Their upper parts are covered by a Thousand Buddha pattern (fig. <ptr target="WLS_niche3_DSC0877.JPG"/>). Two Heavenly Kings (<hi rend="italic">tianwang </hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="zh">天王</foreign>) are carved in low relief on each side wall.</p>
                    <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="WLS_niche3_DSC0877.JPG">
                        <head xml:lang="zh">卧龍山第3龕。<!--右-->左上角細部，可見背景中諸天形象。2010年拍攝</head>
                        <head>Mount Wolong, niche 3. Detail of the right-hand upper corner with deities in the background; photograph taken in 2010</head>
                        <graphic url="WLS_niche3_DSC0877.JPG"/>
                    </figure> 
                  
                    <p>The large niche with a floral, round arch at the rear contains a crowded figure group around a central Buddha in <hi rend="italic">
                            <foreign xml:lang="sa">bhadrāsana</foreign>
                        </hi>, whose feet rest on two large lotus blossoms. The Buddha’s retinue consists of 16 figures in total.<!--Figures in the foreground are sculpted in the round; those in the middle ground are depicted in relief as half figures, and the Eight Classes of Heavenly Beings (<hi rend="italic">tianlong ba bu  </hi><foreign xml:lang="zh">天龍八部</foreign>) are carved in shallow  relief in the background.-->
                        <note>
                            <ref type="biblio" target="Zitong_WolongShan2010">144–152</ref>, has a detailed description of the figure ensemble in this niche along with measurements.</note> The Buddha, his accompanying bodhisattvas, and the guardian figures (<hi rend="italic">lishi </hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="zh">力士</foreign>) in the corners of the niches are sculpted in the round. The two disciple figures next to the Buddha, as well as two more unidentified, haloed figures—one laymen at the right-hand side, and one monk at the left-hand side—are shown as half figures in relief. The background of the upper part of the niche is filled by the Eight Classes of Heavenly Beings (<hi rend="italic">tianlong ba bu  </hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="zh">天龍八部</foreign>) in shallow reliefs (fig. <ptr target="WLS_niche3_DSC0877.JPG"/>). By grading the dimensionality of the figures, the composition thus creates the impression of a fore-, a middle-, and a background. Moreover, the figures are arrayed in an angle of 180°, so that it is impossible to observe (or photograph) them all from a single viewpoint. In this way, the impression of crowdedness is reinforced. This kind of multi-layered figure arrangements is typical for the art in Sichuan.</p>
                        
                        <!-- <hi rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="sa">vajrapāṇi</foreign></hi>金剛力士-->
                        <!--composition in high and low relief, background characters only heads and chests visible multi-layered arrangement and multi-technique-->
                   
                    <p>Although the identity of the central Buddha in niche 3 is disputed, his <hi rend="italic">
                            <foreign xml:lang="sa">bhadrāsana</foreign>
                        </hi> posture speaks in favor of Maitreya Buddha.<note>
                            <ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2009">114</ref>, suggests a combination of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Buddha (niche 1), <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign> Buddha (niche 2), and Maitreya Buddha (niche 3). <ref type="biblio" target="QiuChangzhong1998">42–43</ref>, identifies the image in niche 3 as the Medicine Buddha <foreign xml:lang="zh">藥師佛</foreign> accompanied by Bodhisattva Sunlight <foreign xml:lang="zh">日光菩薩</foreign> and Bodhisattva Moonlight <foreign xml:lang="zh">月光菩薩</foreign>.</note> <anchor xml:id="Changjing_start"/>The central Buddha in niche 2 on the north face of the boulder, seated in meditation posture, is identified in a nearby inscription as <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign> Buddha. This inscription is located on the upper part of the narrow right-hand side wall, above an armed guardian figure that has been identified (in analogy to the figure ensemble of niche 3) as one of the four Heavenly Kings (fig. <ptr target="WLS_niche3_DSC0826.JPG"/>). The characters were carved not very deeply into the rock surface, which was not properly polished and still shows the parallel striations that resulted from roughly smoothing the rock. Obviously, the inscription was added later to the already finished figure ensemble.</p>
                   
                    <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="WLS_niche3_DSC0826.JPG">
                        <head xml:lang="zh">卧龍山第2龕。<!--右-->左上角細部，可見旁側題記紀年爲884年9月2日（中和四年八月廾[九]日）。2010年拍攝</head>
                        <head>Mount Wolong, niche 2. Detail of the upper right hand corner with nearby inscription dated to September 2, 884 (<foreign xml:lang="zh">中和四年八月廾[九]日</foreign>); photograph taken in 2010</head>
                        <graphic url="WLS_niche3_DSC0826.JPG"/>
                    </figure>
                  
                    <p>The inscription next to niche 2 is not very long. At the end, it is dated to the ninth day of the eighth month of the fourth year of the <hi rend="italic">zhonghe</hi> era (<foreign xml:lang="zh">中和四年八月廾[9]日</foreign>), which corresponds to September 2, 884. The date is followed by a note, reading “memorial of providing a <hi rend="italic">zhai</hi> [ritual]” (<hi rend="italic">shezhai biao </hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="zh">設齊[齋]表</foreign>).
                        
                        
                        
                        <!-- In the final column, six or seven characters are illegible, and then follow two characters reading “memorial of the <hi rend="italic">zhai</hi> [ritual]” (<hi rend="italic">zhai biao </hi><foreign xml:lang="zh">設齊[齋]表</foreign>).<note>The available transcriptions of this poorly preserved inscription differ slightly: <ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2009">107</ref>, reads “memorial of providing a <hi rend="italic">zhai</hi> [ritual]” (<hi rend="italic">shezhai biao </hi><foreign xml:lang="zh">設齊[齋]表</foreign>) in the final column, and <ref type="biblio" target="Zitong_WolongShan2010">134</ref>, transcribe “memorial of the completion of the <hi rend="italic">zhai</hi> [ritual]” (<hi rend="italic">zhai biao bi </hi><foreign xml:lang="zh">齋表畢</foreign>).</note> -->
                        
                        <!--The same formulation is attested twice at Mount Taipeng (Taipeng Shan <foreign xml:lang="zh">太蓬山</foreign>) in Yingshan County (Yingshan Xian <foreign xml:lang="zh">營山縣</foreign>), where we find it in the votive inscription for the Thousand-Eyes-Thousand-Arms Bodhisattva Guanyin of niche 16 that was completed in 895 (see <ptr type="infrafootnote" target="biao_1"/>), and also in the heavily weathered stele text next to this niche (see p. <ptr type="infra" target="biao_2_start biao_2_end"/> in the present volume), which is dated to the sixteenth day of the twelfth month of the first year of the <hi rend="italic">wende</hi> era (<foreign xml:lang="zh">文德元年十二月十六日 </foreign>), that is, January 21, 889.-->
                    </p>
                    
                   <!-- <p>Memorials (<hi rend="italic">biao </hi><foreign xml:lang="zh">表</foreign>) are commonly presented to the throne by petitioners. In the case of the Mount Taipeng inscriptions, we know that the <hi rend="italic">zhai</hi> rituals in question were directed towards the Ten Kings of Hell (<hi rend="italic">shi wang </hi><foreign xml:lang="zh">十王</foreign>) in the context of the performance of a full set of memorial services for the dead known as the Seven Times Seven Feasts (<hi rend="italic">qi qi zhai </hi><foreign xml:lang="zh">七七齋</foreign>).<note>See <ref type="biblio" target="Teiser1994">20–30</ref>, and p. <ptr type="infra" target="sevenseven"/> in the present volume.</note> Therefore, the intended recipients of the “memorial of providing a <hi rend="italic">zhai</hi> [ritual]” carved next to niche 2 were probably also the Ten Kings of Hell, whose duty it is to judge the deceased according to their karmic merits, and to determine their future rebirth.</p>-->
                    
                    
                    <p>In the inscription, <hi rend="italic">
                            <foreign xml:lang="sa">bhikṣu</foreign>
                        </hi> Changjing (<foreign xml:lang="zh">比丘常静</foreign>) reports that he restored the <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign> Buddha image of the northern niche (<foreign xml:lang="zh">北面釋迦牟尼佛變</foreign>) for the sake of his deceased mother and maternal aunt (<foreign xml:lang="zh">亡妣亡姨</foreign>). Changjing prays that the deceased are reborn in a pure Buddha land and that all beings will attain deliverance from suffering.<note>Some characters of the inscription are illegible. A text transcription is provided in <ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2009">107</ref>, and <ref type="biblio" target="Zitong_WolongShan2010">143</ref>.</note> <!--(transcription on p. 107: 敬粧北面釋迦牟尼佛變/ 右囗院比丘常靜奉為亡/  妣亡姨捨囗修粧上件功德願亡者/  乘佛願囗淨國受生法界有情/離苦解囗中和四年八月廾[9]日/  設齊[齋]表   WLS_north_inscription_DSC0824_cut.JPG [2010] and WLS_niche3_DSC0826.JPG [2010]).--> Thus, the restoration of the images was undertaken to generate merit for the dead, yet the entire donation was probably larger and also encompassed some kind of ritual. Providing a <hi rend="italic">zhai</hi> may simply mean that Changjing catered a maigre feast to the  <hi rend="italic">
                            <foreign xml:lang="sa">saṃgha</foreign>
                        </hi>, but it may also refer to the full set of memorial services for the dead.<note>Following the term “memorial of providing a <hi rend="italic">zhai</hi> [ritual],” the above mentioned inscriptions at Mount Taipeng note the “completion of the celebrations” (<hi rend="italic">qingqi </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">慶訖</foreign>, and <hi rend="italic">qingbi </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">慶畢</foreign>, respectively) to indicate that the matter has now been brought to a good end.</note>
                        <anchor xml:id="Changjing_end"/> </p>
                   
                    <p>Niche 2 measures 250 cm in height, 210 cm in width, and 152 cm in depth. These measurements, as well as the figural composition, is similar to niche 3.<note>
                            <ref type="biblio" target="Zitong_WolongShan2010">134–143</ref>, has a detailed description of the figure ensemble in this niche along with measurements.</note> The central Buddha, identified as <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign>, sits cross-legged on a lotus flower with upturned leaves that forms the top of his richly decorated octagonal Sumeru throne (fig. <ptr target="wolong_niche3.jpg"/>). His host consists of the same figures as before: two bodhisattvas, two disciples, two guardian figures, and the representatives of the Eight Classes of Heavenly Beings in the background. We also find the two unidentified half figures at each side between the bodhisattvas and the guardians. They are much like their counterparts in niche 3. The haloed figures in secular garb at the right-hand side wear the same type of headpiece. While the man in niche 2 is clean-shaven (fig. <ptr target="WLS_niche3_DSC0826.JPG"/>), the one in niche 3 has a fuller face and wears a beard (fig. <ptr target="WLS_niche3_DSC0877.JPG"/>). </p>
                    <p>Although the figures in niches 2 and 3 are in parts heavily restored, they exhibit the same stylistic features. Their uniformity in composition and style is contrasted by niche 1 on the west face of the boulder, which exhibits a different motif in a style that must have appeared rather foreign to contemporaneous observers.  </p>
                   
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Western Niche with <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> and 52 Bodhisattvas</head>
                    <p>The iconographic theme of the niche on the west face of the boulder is the same as that of niche 19 at Bishui Monastery, namely, a depiction of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Buddha surrounded by 50 or 52 bodhisattvas in his Pure Land. At Mount Wolong, there is text evidence for the identification of this theme: At the left-hand side of the niche, an inscription was carved on the boulder’s west face, which is titled <hi rend="italic">Transmission Report of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Buddha and the 52 Bodhisattvas</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Emituo Fo bing wushi’er pusa zhuan </hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="zh">阿弥陁佛并五十二菩薩傳</foreign>; hereafter: <hi rend="italic">Transmission Report</hi>, discussed below). The exact number of bodhisattvas in the Buddha’s entourage, however, is compromised in the very first sentence of the inscribed text, which states: </p>
                        <quote>The image of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Buddha accompanied by 50 bodhisattvas is an auspicious image from the Western regions <foreign xml:lang="zh">阿弥陁佛五十菩薩像者，盖西域之瑞像也。</foreign>
                        <note>
                            <foreign xml:lang="en">See the transcription of the carved text on p.</foreign> <ptr type="infra" target="WLS1_transcription"/> <foreign xml:lang="en">in the present volume.</foreign>
                        </note>
                    </quote>
                    <p>The exact number of bodhisattvas surrounding <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Buddha depends on whether the two main bodhisattvas are included into the count or not. If they are included, the total number amounts to 52. Many times, however, the main bodhisattvas are excluded from the overall count, probably because the presence of Bodhisattva Guanyin (<foreign xml:lang="zh">觀音</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="sa">Avalokiteśvara</foreign>) and Bodhisattva Dashizhi (<foreign xml:lang="zh">勢至</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mahā­sthāma­prāpta</foreign>) flanking <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Buddha was taken for granted, and this Buddha could no longer be imagined to appear without his well-known attendants. In this case, only the smaller bodhisattva figures seated on lotus flowers are counted.</p>
                    
                    <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="WLS_niche1_DSC0869.jpg">
                        <head xml:lang="zh">卧龍山第1龕上部。2010年拍攝</head>
                        <head>Mount Wolong, niche 1, upper part; photograph taken in 2010</head>
                        <graphic url="WLS_niche1_DSC0869.jpg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Since the survey of 2008, the niche on the west face of the boulder is numbered niche 1. It measures 196 cm in height, 240 cm in width, and 46 cm in depth. The niche is less deep than niches 2 and 3 because there was no need to create a foreground, middle ground, and background as in the multi-layered compositions of niches 2 and 3. Instead, the 50 smaller figures are arranged all around the central triad of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Buddha with Bodhisattva Guanyin to his left and Bodhisattva Dashizhi to his right. By distributing the 50 bodhisattvas evenly above (fig. <ptr target="WLS_niche1_DSC0869.jpg"/>) and below (fig. <ptr target="WLS_niche1_DSC0872.JPG"/>), and to the left and right of the central triad, the intended visual effect for the observer is that of immersion into the lotus pond of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign>’s Pure Land. </p>
                    <p>The western niche has a double-frame: The depiction of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> surrounded by his 50 bodhisattvas is placed in a round-arched niche, which occupies the rear of a larger, rectangular recess (fig. <ptr target="wolong_niche1.jpg"/>), thereby creating enough space to place two guardian figures in front of the inner niche. Although they are not well preserved, the right-hand side guardian might be identified as a <hi rend="italic">
                            <foreign xml:lang="sa">vajrapāṇi</foreign>
                        </hi> (<hi rend="italic">jingang lishi </hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="zh">金剛力士</foreign>), as he holds a <hi rend="italic">vajra</hi> weapon in his left hand (fig. <ptr target="WLS_DSC07833.JPG"/>).</p>
                    <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="WLS_niche1_DSC0872.JPG">
                        <head xml:lang="zh">卧龍山第1龕下部。2010年拍攝</head>
                        <head>Mount Wolong, niche 1, lower part; photograph taken in 2010</head>
                        <graphic url="WLS_niche1_DSC0872.JPG"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>In comparable depictions preserved in Dunhuang manuscripts, <hi rend="italic">vajra</hi>s are depicted as longish objects the size of a sword, yet in the shape of a multisectional cudgel. <hi rend="italic">Vajra</hi> weapons might be held at the cudgel’s middle constriction, or at one end, as appears to be the case here.<note>See, for example, a tenth-century sketch of two <hi rend="italic">vajra</hi> deities (29.5 x 42 cm. The British Library, IOL Tib J 1363), published in <ref type="biblio" target="Agnew_Reed_Ball2016">269 (cat. 41)</ref>, or the painted banner with a <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">vajrapāṇi</foreign>
                            </hi> from the second half of the ninth century (187.5 x 18.6 cm. The British Museum, 1919,0101,0.124 (Ch.004)), published in <ref type="biblio" target="Agnew_Reed_Ball2016">271 (cat. 43)</ref>.</note> Two additional image niches have been added at a later point in time, one in each of the upper parts of the rectangular recess’s small side walls.                         
                        <!-- Into the upper part of each of the small side walls of the rectangular recess, another image niche has been added at a later point in time. -->They accommodate figures that are closer in style to niches 2 and 3, and do not seem to have been part of the original design of niche 1.<note>These additional niches, numbered 1-1 and 1-2, respectively, are described in detail in <ref type="biblio" target="Zitong_WolongShan2010">129–133</ref>.</note> </p>
                    
                    <p>The broad arch above the inner niche is adorned with elegantly twining vines, among which small meditating Buddha figures emerge. Below the arch, <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Buddha and the two standing main bodhisattvas take center stage. The stylistic particularities of the sculptures in niche 1 become most obvious in these bodhisattva figures. They are markedly different from their counterparts in niches 2 and 3. The bodhisattvas in niche 2 (fig. <ptr target="wolong_niche3.jpg"/>) are an example for a figure type characterised by Chinese aesthetics:   
                     Their faces are full and round, and their bodies almost sturdy. The fabric of their long skirts is rather heavy, and the seams cover most of the bare feet. A broad and half-transparent shawl conceals the nakedness of the upper body, and long chains of jewels, crossing at the height of the belly and hanging down to the height of the knee, distract from the shape of the body underneath. In addition, these bodhisattvas wear heavy and ornate crowns on their topknots, from which long ribbons are suspended. By contrast, the bodhisattvas standing to the right and left (fig. <ptr target="WLS_DSC07819.JPG"/>) of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> in niche 1 are very slender. The seams of their thin skirts, clinging tightly to their legs, hardly cover the ankles and bare the entire bridge of the feet. On their naked chests and arms they wear elaborate necklaces and heavy, jewelled bracelets, and their artfully braided hair is adorned with just one single piece of large jewelry.</p> 
                        
                    <p>Below the broad lotus seat of the Buddha, the central stem of the lotus web sprouts buds and calyxes from which small figures are born, first showing only their heads, then appearing as half-figures with hands joined in <hi rend="italic">
                            <foreign xml:lang="sa">añjali-mudrā</foreign>
                        </hi> (fig. <ptr target="WLS_CIMG4658.JPG"/>). All of the other small figures that surround <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> <!--to listen to his preaching --> have fully emerged from their lotuses. They sit in various postures, with ankles crossed, embracing one knee in <hi rend="italic">
                            <foreign xml:lang="sa">lalitāsana</foreign>
                        </hi>, or with both legs crossed. Some support their chin with one hand, and many incline their heads while listening to and pondering about the Dharma (fig. <ptr target="WLS_DSC07822.JPG"/>).<note>
                            <ref type="biblio" target="Zitong_WolongShan2010">116–129</ref>, has a detailed description of each of the figures of the ensemble in this niche, along with measurements, and several drawings.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The similitude of the figural composition of niche 1 at Mount Wolong and niche 19 at Bishui Monastery in Mianyang has been noted before by many scholars.<note><!--<ref type="biblio" target="LiSisheng1991">54</ref>; -->
                            <ref type="biblio" target="Okada2000">175</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2009">109–116</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="OnoEiji2010">227–228</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="YuChun2019">277–278</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="Yangxiao2021">46–47</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="Yangxiao2024">21–22</ref>.</note> Most of them refer to niche 1 at Mount Wolong as the earliest known example for the iconographical theme of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Buddha surrounded by 50 bodhisattvas, because it is securely dated. The final column of the <hi rend="italic">Transmission Report</hi> (discussed below) provides the fourteenth day of the seventh month of the eight year of the <hi rend="italic">zhenguan</hi> era for a date, which corresponds to August 13, 634. So far, niche 19 at Bishui Monastery could only be dated tentatively to the earlier half of the <hi rend="italic">zhenguan</hi> era (627–649).<note>Only <ref type="biblio" target="WangTing2010">217</ref>, suggested that the Bishui Monastery niche pre-dates the one at Mount Wolong, see <ptr type="infrafootnote" target="datess"/>.</note> When the inscription inside the neighboring niche 10 was scanned in 2009, the date of the first year of the <hi rend="italic">zhenguan</hi> era (627) became visible (fig. <ptr target="BSS_Detail_DSC0371_NEU.tif"/>), and thus Bishui Monastery’s niche 19 could be established as the earliest example (see also p. <ptr type="infra" target="Bishui_first"/> in the present volume).
                        </p>
                    <p>In direct comparison, the similar arrangement of figures around the central triad in niche 1 at Mount Wolong and niche 19 at Bishui Monastery becomes obvious. Because niche 19 is higher than it is wide (measuring 170 x 145.5 x 61 cm), the entire composition appears more crowed than that in niche 1, which is wider than high (measuring 196 x 240 x 46 cm), and appears thus more spacious. Yet when we look at the details, we find similarities not only in the distribution of the smaller bodhisattva figures across the wall surface, but also in details of their individual designs. The garb of some of the bodhisattva figures differs from the usual skirt and shawls, and resembles more a monk’s robe that covers the left shoulder and bares the right (fig. <ptr target="WLS_DSC07821.JPG"/>). Nevertheless, these figures wear necklaces and bracelets, and long strands of hair fall down their shoulders. Similar figures are depicted in niche 19 at Bishui Monastery. It is also not uncommon that they hold objects in hands, such as the flask in fig. <ptr target="BSS_DSC0253.jpg"/>, which finds an analogy in one of the bodhisattvas at Mount Wolong in fig. <ptr target="WLS_DSC07821.JPG"/>.</p>
                    <p>The design of niche 19 at Bishui Monastery could be linked to the now lost mural no. 6 of the Golden Hall (<hi rend="italic">
                            <foreign xml:lang="ja">kondō</foreign>
                        </hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="zh">金堂</foreign>) in <foreign xml:lang="ja">Hōryūji </foreign> <foreign xml:lang="zh">法隆寺</foreign>.<note>
                            <ref type="biblio" target="WangTing2010"/> provides a detailed comparison of both representations.</note> Although the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Hōryūji </foreign> mural was created about 70 year later—during the reign of the female Emperor <foreign xml:lang="ja">Jitō-tennō </foreign> <foreign xml:lang="zh">持統天皇</foreign>, r. 690–697)<note>
                            <ref type="biblio" target="Yanagisawa1975">19</ref>, suggests this dating.</note>—it is possible that both followed the same prototype or model (<hi rend="italic">fanben </hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="zh">範本</foreign>).
                        
                        The creation of both designs may have even been based on a similar repertoire of stencils (<hi rend="italic">fenben </hi> <foreign xml:lang="zh">粉本</foreign>; see pp. <ptr type="infra" target="fenben_start fenben_end"/> in the present volume).</p>
                    <p>Despite the noted obvious similarities between niche 1 at Mount Wolong and niche 19 at Bishui Monastery, we have to take into account that the niche on the west face of the Mount Wolong boulder is not as well preserved as its counterpart in Mian­yang. Many parts of niche 1 have been restored, maybe even more than once. A fragmented inscription on the right-hand edge of its outer rectangular frame attests to a “renovation of the western niche with <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitā[bha]</foreign>” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">……又修粧西面阿弥□……</foreign>) that is dated to the “fourth [day] of the fourth month of the fourth year of the [<hi rend="italic">zhong</hi>]<hi rend="italic">he</hi> era” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">囗和四年四月四囗</foreign>), which corresponds to May 2, 884.<note>Transcription after <ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2009">107</ref>. <ref type="biblio" target="Zitong_WolongShan2010">134</ref>, suggest a slightly different transcription of this text. They give the measurements of the inscribed surface as 51 cm in height, and 42 cm in width, yet they admit to be unsure if the inscription continued further down. <ref type="biblio" target="Zitong_WolongShan2010">132–133</ref>, further transcribe fragments of four more historical inscriptions that are carved on the frame of niche 1. Two of these are visitor inscriptions, one is dated to the fourth month of the twelfth year of the Chongzhen reign of the Great Ming dynasty <foreign xml:lang="zh">大明崇禎十二年四月</foreign>, corresponding to May 3–31, 1639; and one is dated to the thirteenth year of the Yongzheng reign of the Great Qing dynasty (<foreign xml:lang="zh">大清雍正十三年</foreign>), corresponding to the year 1735.
                        
                        <!--(transcription on p. 107: 捨……貳捨伍囗又修粧西面阿/弥……貮菩薩壹龕/第……等發/……此願……康律……脊安?/……過……離苦……眾人/……囗和四年四月四/……齊[齋]表……畢)-->
                        </note>
                    </p>
                    <p>As we have seen above (pp. <ptr type="infra" target="Changjing_start Changjing_end"/>), in the eighth lunar month of the same year, <hi rend="italic">
                            <foreign xml:lang="sa">bhikṣu</foreign>
                        </hi> Changjing renovated niche 2 on the north face of the boulder for the sake of his deceased mother and maternal aunt. It is possible that Changjing also re-embellished niche 1 on the west face, but the name of the donor of this earlier renovation project has not been preserved on the stone. What has been preserved is the same kind of note as that in the renovation inscription of niche 2: The final column of the inscription next to niche 1 starts with seven illegible characters, followed by three characters reading “memorial of the <hi rend="italic">zhai</hi> [ritual] . . . completed” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">齊[齋]表……畢</foreign>). 
                        <note>Transcription after <ref type="biblio" target="Zitong_WolongShan2010">134</ref>, and <ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2009">107</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The rather heavy reworking of the figural ensemble of niche 1 prevented an in-depth analysis of its original iconography. The background of the niche, today white-washed, appears levelled and blurred, and even the stems of the many lotus blossoms are at times hardly observable. It is no longer possible to affirm the presence or absence of the mountainous backdrop still discernible in niche 19 at Bishui Monastery, a feature shared with not only the <foreign xml:lang="ja">Hōryūji</foreign> mural, but also with the mural on the east wall of Mogao cave (Mogao Ku <foreign xml:lang="zh">莫高窟</foreign>) 332 at Dunhuang <foreign xml:lang="zh">敦煌</foreign> (cave dated by inscription to the first year of the <hi rend="italic">shengli</hi> era <foreign xml:lang="zh">聖曆元年</foreign>, 698). Because of the above-mentioned striking resemblances with niche 19 at Bishui Monastery, niche 1 is nevertheless included into this group of seventh-century depictions of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Buddha surrounded by his bodhisattvas, and some authors postulate a mountain backdrop for the original appearance of the holy assembly around <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> in the lotus pond.<note>
                            <ref type="biblio" target="Katsuki1994">66–69</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2009">112–115</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="OnoEiji2010">227–228</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2011">378–394</ref> [<ref type="biblio" target="Hida_Yen2018">362–371</ref>].</note> </p>
                    <p>The research that has been conducted on the iconography of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Buddha with 50 bodhisattvas displayed in niche 1 at Mount Wolong is rather extensive. The section on niche 19 at Bishui Monastery in the present volume provides an overview on the state of research (pp. <ptr type="infra" target="research_start research_end"/>). The reason why the image at Mount Wolong has attracted so much attention is the accompanying stele inscription, to which we turn next.</p>
                    <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="WLS_CIMG4658.JPG">
                        <head xml:lang="zh">卧龍山第1龕。中央三尊造像細部，下方可見蓮花化生人物。2009年拍攝</head>
                        <head>Mount Wolong, niche 1. Detail of central triad with figures born from lotus buds below; photograph taken in 2009</head>
                        <graphic url="WLS_CIMG4658.JPG"/>
                    </figure>   
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Stele Inscription</head>
                    <p>On the left-hand side of niche 1, the outlines of a stele were carved on the west face of the cuboid boulder. The rectangular field of script measures 145.5 cm in height, and 66–78 cm in width. The corners of the stele’s head, which measures 27 cm in height and 74 cm in width, are rounded. The body of the stele carries an inscription in 20 columns, inscribed in a grid that provides regular squares (ca. 3 x 3 cm) for each character.<note>All measurements after <ref type="biblio" target="Zitong_WolongShan2010">133</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Seven characters are inscribed on the stele head. There are unevenly distributed across the available space, in three columns from right to left, the first two of which contain three characters each. The inscription is not centered properly, but shifted slightly to the left. The awkward positioning of the inscription raises doubts if the carved characters were meant to be placed on the stele head in the first place; the overall impression is rather that they may have been added just because the stele head was still blank.</p>
                    <p>The inscription reads: </p>
       <quote>Renunciant Daomi who made the niches on the four faces [of the cuboid boulder] <foreign xml:lang="zh">造四面龕僧道密</foreign>.<note>
                            <foreign xml:lang="en">See the transcription of WLS 2 in the present volume on p. <ptr type="infra" target="WLS_transcription"/>.</foreign>
                        </note>
                    </quote>
                    <p>This inscription is usually taken as evidence that a monk by the name of Daomi initiated the opening of four niches on the four faces of the cuboid boulder, despite the fact that no proper niche was opened on the south face, which is covered by rows of small meditating Buddha figures. It is the only information available on the founding of the Buddhist site at Mount Wolong.</p>
                    <p>It has not gone unnoticed that <foreign xml:lang="sa">Narendrayaśas </foreign> <foreign xml:lang="zh">那連提黎耶舍</foreign> (517–589) had a disciple by the same name, whose biography is found in the <hi rend="italic">Sequel to the Biographies of Eminent Monks</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Xu gaoseng zhuan </hi> <foreign xml:lang="zh">續高僧傳</foreign>) at T#2060, 50: 667b22–668a20.<note>
                            <ref type="biblio" target="Okada2000">199, n11</ref>.</note> From <foreign xml:lang="sa">Narendrayaśas</foreign>’ biography (T#2060, 50: 432a24–433b6) we know that Daomi <!--(died ca. 605) -->came together with his master to the capital in the seventh month of the second year of the <hi rend="italic">kaihuang</hi> era [August 5 to September 3, 582] to act as amanuensis (<foreign xml:lang="zh">筆受</foreign>) in sutra translation carried out at Daxingshan Monastery <foreign xml:lang="zh">大興善寺</foreign>.<note>T#2060, 50: 433a4–5: “<foreign xml:lang="zh">［開皇］二年七月，弟子道密等侍送入京，住大興善寺。</foreign>”</note> Daomi’s own short biography (T#2060, 50: 667b22–28)<note>The major portion of Daomi’s biography at T#2060, 50: 667b22–668a20 is not concerned with the life of this monk, but relates the story of the birth and childhood of the later Emperor Wen of the Sui (Sui Wendi <foreign xml:lang="zh">隋文帝</foreign>; r. 581–604), who was born and raised in Daxingguo Monastery (Daxingguo Si <foreign xml:lang="zh">大興國寺</foreign>) in Tongzhou <foreign xml:lang="zh">同州</foreign> (present Weinan <foreign xml:lang="zh">渭南</foreign> in Shaanxi). This is the monastery to where Daomi was dispatched during the emperor’s <hi rend="italic">renshou</hi> <foreign xml:lang="zh">仁壽</foreign> era (601–604) relic distribution campaigns.</note> also attests to his participation in sutra translation. Although Daomi—the monk who escorted relics to Daxingguo Monastery—may have lived until the <hi rend="italic">kaiyuan</hi> era, the seven-character inscription on the stele head provides no further clue to identify him with the monk “who made the niches on the four faces [of the cuboid boulder].”</p>
                    <p>Below the unadorned stele head with Daomi’s inscription, a text in 20 columns is separated horizontally into an upper and a lower part by a blank grid row. The upper part carries the stele text, while the lower part is a list of 47 donor names.<note>
                            <ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2009">111</ref>, provides a transcription of this list of donor names. Hida notes that among these donors, members of the Ren <foreign xml:lang="zh">任</foreign> and Deng <foreign xml:lang="zh">鄧</foreign> families are most numerous. She takes them to be influential local clans. </note> This list of names is arranged in three registers, which are in turn again separated from each other by two more blank grid rows.</p>
                    <p>Each item in the list consists of the name of the individual donor, followed by the remark “one figure” (<hi rend="italic">yi qu</hi> <foreign xml:lang="zh">一軀</foreign>). In those cases where the individual’s name has only two characters, the name is followed by the expression “made one figure” (<hi rend="italic">zao yi qu</hi> <foreign xml:lang="zh">造一軀</foreign>). The names of three individuals, however, are followed by “two figures” (<hi rend="italic">er qu</hi> <foreign xml:lang="zh">二軀</foreign>). In total, 47 individuals have thus donated 50 figures. It is not by chance that this number coincides with the number of bodhisattvas reborn in the depiction of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitā­bha</foreign>’s Pure Land in niche 1. We may assume that the donors hoped to secure a lotus flower in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitā­bha</foreign>’s paradise for themselves, or for their beloved ones.<note>The coincidence between the number of donated figures and the number of reborn bodhisattvas in niche 1 was already noted by <ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2009">112</ref>.</note>   </p>
                    <p>The list of donor names has occasionally been connected with the person of monk Daomi named on the stele head. Some authors have argued that the monk Daomi lead the 47 donors named further down in a function comparable to the head of a Buddhist association (<hi rend="italic">yiyi </hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="zh">邑義</foreign>), such as those that are known primarily from Northern China.<note>This argument was made by <ref type="biblio" target="Huangxia2018">23</ref>, and <ref type="biblio" target="Yangxiao2021">63–66</ref> [<ref type="biblio" target="Yangxiao2024">30–31</ref>].</note> The design of the stele inscription does necessarily support this suggestion. As noted above, Daomi’s signature is placed rather awkwardly on the stele head. Moreover, the list of donor names appears to be an unambiguous attachment to the main stele text, which gives a date, and the names of the calligrapher and carver. The stele text and the list of donors form a document in its own right that does not need to be connected with the donor of the niches on the four faces of the boulder.</p>
                    
                    
                   <div>
                        <head>The <hi rend="italic">Transmission Report</hi>
                        </head> 
       <p>The first column of the stele text contains the title, <hi rend="italic">Transmission Report of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Buddha and the 52 Bodhisattvas</hi>, followed by the name of the calligrapher, Deng Yuanjue <foreign xml:lang="zh">鄧元覺</foreign>, and the name of the person who “made the niche and carved the characters, Yang Zishang” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">作龕及鎸字之楊子尚</foreign>). The family names of both men, Deng <foreign xml:lang="zh">鄧</foreign> and Yang <foreign xml:lang="zh">楊</foreign>, also appear several times in the list of donors below. We may thus safely assume that they were related to some of the individuals who donated figures for niche 1. It is noteworthy that the contribution made by the artisan Yang Zishang included not only the chiseling of the inscription, but also some kind of masonry, although it is unclear if he simply assisted in breaking the stone to open the niche, or if he executed more artful tasks like giving shape to the figures, or carving the elegant patterns on the arch of the niche.</p>
                       <p>Because it contains the inscription title as well as the names of the calligrapher and the carver, the first column is much longer than the subsequent columns with 19 characters each. It reaches all the way down to the second register of donor names, thus visually connecting the calligrapher’s and the carver’s names with those of the other donors.</p>
                       <p>The text inscribed from column 2 onwards, which is transcribed and translated in the present volume on pp. <ptr type="infra" target="Wolongtext_start Wolongtext_end"/>, relates the story of the transmission of the image of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> and the 50 bodhisattvas from India to China. In the final column, this stone version of the <hi rend="italic">Transmission Report</hi> is securely dated to a day corresponding to August 13, 634, namely, “the fourteenth day of the seventh month of the eight year of the <hi rend="italic">zhenguan</hi> era” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">貞觀八年七月十四日</foreign>). The stele inscription at Mount Wolong thus constitutes the earliest version of a text that is found three more times in the Buddhist canon.</p>
                        
                       <p>The first of these occurrences is in the <hi rend="italic">Collected Records of Miraculous Responses to the Three Jewels in the Sacred Continent</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Ji shenzhou sanbao gantong lu </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">集神州三寶感通録</foreign>, T#2106; hereafter: <hi rend="italic">Miraculous Responses to the Three Jewels </hi>), which was completed in 664 by Daoxuan <foreign xml:lang="zh">道宣</foreign> (596–667). 
                            Very close to Daoxuan’s version is the one contained in the collection of the <hi rend="italic">Jade Forest in the Dharma Garden</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Fayuan zhulin </hi> <foreign xml:lang="zh">法苑珠林</foreign>, T#2122, 53: 401a18–b4), completed in 668 by Daoshi <foreign xml:lang="zh">道世</foreign> (died unknown). Finally, the anthology <hi rend="italic">Collected Passages on Paradise</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Lebang wenlei </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">樂邦文類</foreign>) by Zongxiao <foreign xml:lang="zh">宗曉</foreign> (1151–1214) presents yet another version of this text (T#1969A, 47: 192a13–26), which is presented in-text as a “quote,” but in fact shows traits of editorial modification and interpretation. The text versions that entered the canon are less opaque than the earlier stone text from Mount Wolong, probably because they profited from some editorial polishing. </p> 
                        <p>In order to familiarize readers with the sequence of events of the transmission story, the story in the version from the <hi rend="italic">Miraculous Responses to the Three Jewels</hi> will be translated first. Afterwards, an analysis will show where the plot of this canonized text diverges from the stone version.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Okada2000">166–173</ref>, and <ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2017a">1–15</ref>, chose the same approach.</note> Finally, some conclusions may be drawn to account for the differences between the earlier stone version and the canonical texts.</p>
                       <p>The report on the image of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> and the 50 bodhisattvas is part of a collection of 50 miracle stories contained in the second fascicle of Dao­xuan’s <hi rend="italic">Miraculous Responses to the Three Jewels</hi>.<note>T#2106, 52: 404a7–435a19. <ref type="biblio" target="Shinohara1998"/> provides a general analysis of these miracle stories, for which he also gives parallels in other texts, mostly the <hi rend="italic">Jade Forest in the Dharma Garden</hi> (T#2122), the <hi rend="italic">Extension to the Collection for the Propagation and Clarification of Buddhism</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Guang Hongmingji </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">廣弘明集</foreign>; T#2103), and the <hi rend="italic">Sequel to the Biographies of Eminent Monks</hi> (T#2060), but occasionally also other texts.</note> Numbered story 37, the report reads as follows:</p>
                    <quote>Thirty-seven: The image of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign>
                        Buddha and 50 bodhisattvas is an auspicious image <!--(<hi rend="italic">rui­xiang</hi><foreign xml:lang="zh">瑞像</foreign>)--> from
                        India in the Western regions. According to what has been transmitted, there was once a certain Bodhisattva Wutong <foreign xml:lang="zh">五通菩薩</foreign> (“Bodhisattva Accomplished in the Five Supranormal Powers”)<note>On this bodhisattva, see <ptr type="infrafootnote" target="Wutongpusa"/> in the present volume. </note> from Jitoumo Monastery
                        (<foreign xml:lang="zh">雞頭摩寺</foreign>) in India<note>On Jitoumo Monastery, see <ptr type="infrafootnote" target="Jitoumo"/> in the present volume.</note> who reached <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sukhāvatī</foreign> and asked
                            <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Buddha: “Beings in the
                            <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sahā</foreign> world wish to be born in the pure
                        land. [Yet because they] have no image of [<foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign>] Buddha, the power of their vow has no basis. Please
                        consent to send [such an image] down.” The Buddha said: “You just go ahead.
                        [The image] will soon appear in the other [i.e., the <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sahā</foreign> world].” By the time the bodhisattva returned [to
                            the <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sahā</foreign> world], the image had already
                        arrived. [It showed] one Buddha and 50 bodhisattvas, each seated on lotus flowers, [painted] on a tree leaf.<note xml:id="tree">The relation between the lotus seats on which the bodhisattvas are seated (“<foreign xml:lang="zh">各坐蓮花</foreign>”) and the tree depends on whether we read “<hi rend="italic">shu ye </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">樹葉</foreign>” in the singular or in the plural. Our translation prefers to read the singular here, and assumes that, in the next sentence, the bodhisattva “takes the leaf” (<hi rend="italic">qu ye </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">取葉</foreign>) in order to spread it wide and far. Hida Romi read “<hi rend="italic">shu ye </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">樹葉</foreign>” in plural when she translated the text into modern Japanese (<ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2011">383–384</ref>). When Yen Chuan-ying translated this modern Japanese rendering of Daoxuan’s text into modern Chinese, she framed the phrase as “one Buddha and 50 bodhisattvas, each sitting on his own lotus seat on the leaves of a tree” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">一佛五十菩薩各自在樹葉上的蓮花座上</foreign>). Reading the original sentence in the plural caused Hida to remark that the image described in Daoxuan’s story does not so much resemble the prevalent iconography that shows bodhisattva figures seated on lotuses in a pond, but rather the album leaf of the <hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="ja">Kakuzenshō </foreign>
                                </hi> <foreign xml:lang="zh">覺禪鈔</foreign> that shows a giant tree with 52 small figures seated on lotuses that appear among its leaves (<ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2011">384</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="Hida_Yen2018">370–371</ref>). For the <hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="ja">Kakuzenshō </foreign>
                                </hi> and an English translation of its accompanying inscription, see <ref type="biblio" target="Yamabe1999">324–326</ref>. Bodhisattva figures seated on lotuses among the foliage of the Buddha’s <hi rend="italic">bodhi</hi> tree are also seen in earlier work of the Northern Qi <foreign xml:lang="zh">北齊</foreign> (550–577) and Sui <foreign xml:lang="zh">隋</foreign> (581–618) dynasties, see Huang Xia <foreign xml:lang="zh">黄夏</foreign> in <ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2017a">9</ref>, who names the Northern Qi 
                            relief (now in the Freer Gallery of Art, Washington D.C.) that used to adorn the upper part of the central pillar inside cave 1 at Southern Mount Xiangtang (Nan Xiangtang Shan <foreign xml:lang="zh">南響堂山</foreign>); the image stele donated by Xun Guochou <foreign xml:lang="zh">荀國醜</foreign> and others in the second year of the <hi rend="italic">kaihuang</hi> era (582) in the collection of the Henan Museum (<foreign xml:lang="zh">河南博物院</foreign>); and the bronze altarpiece dated to the thirteenth year of the <hi rend="italic">kaihuang</hi> era (593), now in the collection of the Museum of Fine Arts in Boston.</note> 
                        The bodhisattva took the leaf<note>In her gloss on “picking a leaf and drawing [the image]” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">葉を取つて图写する</foreign>) in <ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2017a">10</ref>, Huang Xia <foreign xml:lang="zh">黄夏</foreign> suggested that Bodhisattva Wutong may have drawn (<hi rend="italic">tuxie </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">圖寫</foreign>) the received image on a leaf, in the same manner as holy texts were sometimes written on palm tree leaves (<hi rend="italic">luoshu ye </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">羅樹葉</foreign>); see, for example, the biography of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Paramārtha </foreign>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">真諦</foreign> (499–569), T#2060: 50: 430b23.</note> on which [the Buddha and the bodhisattvas] were painted and circulated it near and far. 
                       In response to a dream, Emperor Ming (r. 58–76) of the [Eastern] 
                       Han dynasty (25–220) sent [envoys] to [India] to request the Dharma, [and thus] persuaded *<foreign xml:lang="sa">Kāśyapa Mātaṅga</foreign> (?–73) and others to come to Luoyang.<note>On the consequences of Emperor Ming’s dream, see <ptr type="infrafootnote" target="dream"/> in the present volume. </note> 
                        <!--後騰姊子作沙門，持此瑞像，方達此國所在，圖之未幾，齎像西返。-->
                        Later, the son of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mātaṅga</foreign>’s elder sister became a monk. Holding this auspicious image, he had just arrived at where this country [i.e., China] is located, and had copied it a few times, 
                        
                        <!--he also arrived in this country [i.e., China], where he copied it. Before long,--> when he took the image [again] and returned to the West.
                        In consequence, this image and its transmission report did not circulate very widely. <!--魏晉已來，年載久遠，又經滅法，經像湮除，此之瑞迹殆將不見。--> 
                        Since the time of the Wei and Jin dynasties, many years have passed, and [because] the Dharma endured persecution, sutras and images became extinct, [so that] the auspicious traces [of the image] were almost no longer seen at all.
                        When [Emperor] Wen (r. 581–604) of the Sui (581–618) [again made] the [Buddhist] teaching unfold, there was <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">śramaṇa</foreign>
                            </hi> Mingxian,<note>See <ptr type="infrafootnote" target="note_en_6a"/> in the present volume.</note> who obtained a copy [of the image] from Dharma Master Daochang (<foreign xml:lang="zh">道長</foreign>, active around 576) of the Northern Qi dynasty (550–577),<note>On Dharma Master Daochang, see <ptr type="infrafootnote" target="note_en_7"/> in the present volume.</note> who said that its origin coincides with [what] the [transmission] report [relates].
                        Based on this,<note>Reading <hi rend="italic">yi shi </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">以是</foreign> instead of <hi rend="italic">shi yi </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">是以</foreign>.</note> [the image] was [again] copied and disseminated everywhere in this world. At that time, there was Cao Zhongda (died unknown), an artisan-painter of the Northern Qi dynasty, who was originally from the land of Cao.<note>Cao guo <foreign xml:lang="zh">曹國</foreign> (Ushrusana) was an ancient kingdom in the north of modern Tajikistan.</note> 
                        He was well versed in polychrome painting, and an excellent [painter of] Buddhist topics. The models of 
                        Western auspicious [images] that he copied<note>In her gloss on the process of “transmission by copying” (<hi rend="italic">chuanmo </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">傳模</foreign>), Huang Xia <foreign xml:lang="zh">黄夏</foreign> in <ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2017a">13–14</ref>, notes that Xie He <foreign xml:lang="zh">謝赫</foreign> (active around 500) of the Southern Qi dynasty (479–502) defined six principles for judging paintings in the preface of his book <hi rend="italic">Classified Record of Ancient Paintings</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Guhua pinlu </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">古畫品録</foreign>). The sixth item in this list is “transmission through the copying of models” <hi rend="italic">chuanyi moxie </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">傳移模寫</foreign>). Therefore, <hi rend="italic">chuanmo </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">傳模</foreign> is here an abbreviation for <foreign xml:lang="zh">傳移模寫</foreign>. In the biography of Zhuli <foreign xml:lang="zh">住力</foreign> (544–623) in the <hi>Sequel to the Biographies of Eminent Monks</hi> (T#2060, 50: 695a28–b1), the transmission of an auspicious image by copying is also mentioned:
                            “In the tenth year of the <hi rend="italic">daye</hi> era [614], he exhausted his personal possessions and copied an auspicious image together with two bodhisattvas in fragrant sandalwood. Before long, he requested and succeeded to have them placed inside Tongan Hall <foreign xml:lang="zh">大業十年，自竭身資，以栴檀香木，模寫瑞像并二菩薩。不久尋成同安閣内</foreign>.”</note> were recommended at the capital. 
                        Therefore, the south-facing walls of today’s temples are all [decorated with] his true models.<note>The text in the <hi rend="italic">Collected Passages on Paradise</hi> at T#1969A, 47: 192a25 has “traces of the brush” (<hi rend="italic">yibi </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">遺筆</foreign>) instead of “true models” (<hi rend="italic">zhenfan </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">真範</foreign>). Therefore, <ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2017a">15</ref>, concludes that “true models” should mean here “authentic brushwork” (<hi rend="italic">zhenbi </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">真筆</foreign>).
                        </note>
                        <foreign xml:lang="zh">三十七：阿彌陀佛五十菩薩像者，西域天竺之瑞像也。 相傳云，昔天竺雞頭摩寺五通菩薩，往安樂界請阿彌陀佛：“娑婆衆生願生净土，無佛形像，願力莫由。請垂降許。” 佛言：“汝且前去。尋當現彼。”及菩薩還，其像已至。一佛五十菩薩各坐蓮花，在樹葉上。菩薩取葉所在圖寫，流布遠近。
                            漢明感夢，使往祈法。便獲迦葉摩騰等至洛陽。後騰姊子作沙門，持此瑞像，方達此國所在，圖之未幾，齎像西返。而此圖傳，不甚流廣。魏晋已來，年載久遠，又經滅法，經像湮除，此之瑞迹殆將不見。
                            隋文開教， 有沙門明憲，從高齊道長法師所得此一本，説其本起與傳符焉。
                            是以圖寫流布遍於宇内。時有北齊畫工曹仲達者，本曹國人。善於丹青，妙盡梵迹。傳模西瑞，京邑所推。故今寺壁正陽，皆其真範。</foreign>
                            <note>T#2106, 52: 421a17–b3. </note><!--T#1969A, 47: 192a13-26  T47n1969Ap0192a22║教。有沙門明憲。從高齊道[5:長【大】，場【甲】]長法師得本。說-->
                        <!-- <hi>敬佛篇(一三-一四)〉：隋時有</hi>阿彌陀佛五十菩薩像者、西域天竺之瑞像也。相傳云，昔天竺雞頭摩寺五通菩薩，往安樂界請阿彌陀佛：
                        “娑婆眾生願生淨土，無佛形像，願力莫由。請垂降許。”佛言：“汝且前去。尋當現彼。”
                        及菩薩還，其像已至。一佛五十菩薩各坐蓮華，在樹葉上。菩薩取葉所在圖寫，流布遠近。
                        漢明感夢，使往祈法。便獲迦葉摩騰等至雒陽。後騰姊子作沙門，持此瑞像<hi>又</hi>達此國、所在圖之。
                        未幾齎像西返。而此圖傳，不甚流廣。魏晉已來年載<hi>乃</hi>遠，又經滅法，經像湮除。此之瑞迹殆將不見。
                        隋文帝開教。有沙門明憲，從高齊道長法師所得此一本。
                        說其本起與傳符焉。是以圖寫流布遍於宇內。時有北齊畫工曹仲達者。本<hi>是</hi>曹國人、善於丹青。妙盡梵迹傳摸西瑞、京邑所推。
                        故今寺壁正陽，皆其真範<hi>云(右一驗出西域傳記)</hi>。<note>T#2122, 53: 401a18–b4. </note>　-->
                    </quote>
                    <p/>
                   <!-- <p>For a summary of the miracle story accounted in this inscription, see <ref type="biblio" target="Shinohara1998">184</ref>:</p>-->
                  
                   <!-- <p>Summary: The painting of the <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Buddha and 50 bodhisattvas is said to have been originally given by this Buddha to Bodhisattva Wutong <foreign xml:lang="zh">五通菩薩</foreign> in India. After Emperor Ming <foreign xml:lang="zh">明帝</foreign> (r. 58–76) of the Eastern Han dynasty (25–220) had the famous dream and <foreign xml:lang="sa">*Kāśyapa Mātaṅga</foreign> arrived in Luoyang, the son of <foreign xml:lang="sa">*Kāśyapa Mātaṅga</foreign>’s sister brought this painting to China. This long-forgotten painting is said to have been rediscovered under Emperor Wen <foreign xml:lang="zh">文帝</foreign> (r. 581–604) of the Sui <foreign xml:lang="zh">隋</foreign> (581–618). Monk Mingxian <foreign xml:lang="zh">明獻</foreign> obtained a copy from monk Daochang (<foreign xml:lang="zh">道長</foreign>) of the Northern Qi dynasty (550–577), and after its authenticity was confirmed, copies of the painting were sent to everywhere in the empire. At the Sui capital in Daxing <foreign xml:lang="zh">大興</foreign> (under the Tang dynasty named Chang’an <foreign xml:lang="zh">長安</foreign>), it was kept in Zhenji Monastery <foreign xml:lang="zh">真寂寺</foreign>. This monastery was the residence of Xinxing <foreign xml:lang="zh">信行</foreign> (540–594), the founder of the Three Levels Teaching <foreign xml:lang="zh">三階教</foreign>. The monastery was renamed Huadu Monastery <foreign xml:lang="zh">化度寺</foreign> under the Tang, and functioned as headquarter of the Inexhaustible Storehouse (Wujinzang <foreign xml:lang="zh">無盡藏</foreign>) of this movement.</p>-->
                       
                       <p>The plot of Daoxuan’s report on the image of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> and the 50 bodhisattvas evolves in the following five phases:</p>
                       <list type="ordered">
                           <item>Bestowal of the image in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sukhāvatī</foreign> and its reception in ancient India</item>
                           <item>Transmission of the image to China during the Han dynasty by a relative of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Kāśyapa Mātaṅga</foreign>
                            </item>
                           <item>Disappearance of the image since the time of the Wei <foreign xml:lang="zh">魏</foreign> (220–265) and Jin <foreign xml:lang="zh">晋</foreign> (265–420) dynasties </item>
                           <item>Reappearance of the image under the Northern Qi <foreign xml:lang="zh">北齊</foreign> (550–577) and Sui <foreign xml:lang="zh">隋</foreign> (581–618) dynasties</item>
                           <item>Cao Zhongda adds the image to his repertoire</item>
                       </list>
                       <p>While phases one to four advance the timeline of the story, Cao Zhongda, the artisan-painter of the Northern Qi dynasty, seems to merely be an addition to the transmission lineage of the image. In earlier phases, the transmission of the image is tied to individual figures. Starting with <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Buddha, it is first given to Bodhisattva Wutong, then transmitted by the nephew of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Kāśyapa Mātaṅga</foreign>. After a disruption, the lineage is resumed by Master Daochang and monk Mingxian. Each of these figures held the image in hands at a certain point in time. The only exception is Cao Zhongda. While the text praises his mastery in painting, it states nowhere that Cao actually received or copied the image. 
                           This is only implied by reference to Cao winning fame for “passing on models” (<hi rend="italic">chuanmo </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">傳模</foreign>) from the Western regions where his family originated from. </p>
                       <p>Thus, there is reason to assume that Daoxuan appended the details about Cao’s body of work to add some spice to the story. The earlier carved version at Mount Wolong does not mention Cao at all. This is the most obvious divergence between the canonized text and the stone version. Other differences are more subtle. A careful analysis of these will, however, reveal some important particularities of the text inscribed next to niche 1.  </p>
                       <p>In the first section on the bestowal of the image, the stone text reproduces the dialog between <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> and Wutong Bodhisattva very briefly, while the canonized version underpins Wutong’s request with the doctrinal argument that believers in the <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sahā</foreign> world depend on an image to realize their vows for rebirth in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sukhāvatī</foreign>. Thereupon the image is granted and appears spontaneously in our world. Both text versions give a short description of what this image, named “<foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Buddha and 50 bodhi­sattvas,” looked like, and both report that it was revered and spread widely. The stone version explicitly states that the image was drawn on a tree leaf as it manifested in front of Wutong. Wutong is here the passive recipient of the image, which he revers afterwards.<note>Note that there is yet another version of how Wutong received the auspicious image. The thirteenth-century iconographic compendium <hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="ja">Kakuzenshō </foreign>
                                </hi> <foreign xml:lang="zh">覺禪鈔</foreign><!-- from the early Kamakura 鎌倉 period (1185–1333)--> contains an album leaf that shows a giant tree with 52 small figures seated on its leaves. The accompanying text relates that “the bodhisattva quickly returned [from <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sukhāvatī</foreign>] to his own monastery and painted images of Buddhas and bodhisattvas 
                           on the leaves of a tree in the monastery. When people gathered the leaves of the tree and counted them, there were fifty-two 
                           images of Buddhas and bodhisattvas <foreign xml:lang="zh">菩薩速還本寺，其寺樹木葉上畫佛菩薩像。採集此樹葉數之有五十二體佛菩薩像</foreign>. ” Translation after <ref type="biblio" target="Yamabe1999">325</ref>.</note> The stone text further anchors this event, the reception of the miraculous image, in human history by stating that “since that time, our world has this auspicious image.” This sentence is not found in the canonized version.</p>
                       <p>Daoxuan’s report on the subsequent transmission of the image to China reads like a sober chronology of historical events: Emperor Ming has his famous dream and sends an envoy to the West, who then returns to the Chinese capital with <foreign xml:lang="sa">Kāśyapa Mātaṅga</foreign>. The arrival of the auspicious image is linked to this famous figure representing the first Indian monk on Chinese soil by means of a nephew, who brings the image along when following his uncle. Although this monk initially spreads the image, he soon terminates his stay in China for unknown reasons and takes the image back home to India. As modern scholarship has shown, none of these events have any historical basis.<note>Western landmark studies on Emperor Ming’ dream as the founding legend of Chinese Buddhism are <ref type="biblio" target="Maspero1910"/>, <ref type="biblio" target="Soper1959">1–4</ref>,  and, most recently, <ref type="biblio" target="Palumbo2003">167–170</ref>. See also <ptr type="infrafootnote" target="dream"/> in the present volume.</note> From Daoxuan’s viewpoint, however, these incidents are part of the official history of Chinese Buddhism.</p>
                       <p>Although the stone version includes the same chronology and personages in its version of this text section, the tone is different. To begin with, the name of the emperor’s envoy, Cai Yin, is given. In a short narrative passage, the text sketches Cai Yin’s dangerous travel to India, where he meets <foreign xml:lang="sa">Kāśyapa Mātaṅga</foreign> and extends to him his invitation to come to China to establish a Buddhist monastery. In other words, the stone text intimately ties the chronology of events to personal relations, an impression reinforced by mention of the kinship between <foreign xml:lang="sa">Kāśyapa Mātaṅga</foreign> and his nephew, who acts as carrier of the image. Again, the stone version emphasizes that “since then, the image was first known in China.”</p>
                       <p>At the end of the transmission section, the stone text adds an explanation for the sudden return of the nephew—and the image—to India that is not found in Daoxuan’s version. With reference to an unidentified source, the text insinuates that this return to India was inevitable, because the Chinese were still incapable of cherishing the image and its salvific potential. Moreover, the text states that it was the “original image” (<hi rend="italic">benxiang </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">本像</foreign>) that returned to India. Note that, up to this point, the act of copying the image has not even once been mentioned.</p>
                       <p>During the third phase described in our text, from the time of the Wei and Jin dynasties onwards, the Buddhist teaching has suffered many backlashes, and the image has thus disappeared. Daoxuan’s report refers to “auspicious traces” (<hi rend="italic">ruiji </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">瑞迹</foreign>)—probably copies of the original image—that are no longer seen. The reason is that sutras and images in general were obliterated (<hi rend="italic">jing xiang yanchu </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="italic">經像湮除</foreign>) during Buddhist persecutions (<hi rend="italic">miefa </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">滅法</foreign>).<note>This may be a reference to the persecutions carried out under Emperor Taiwu <foreign xml:lang="zh">太武</foreign> of the Northern Wei <foreign xml:lang="zh">北魏</foreign> dynasty (r. 423–452) in 446–452, and Emperor Wu <foreign xml:lang="zh">武</foreign> of the Northern Zhou <foreign xml:lang="zh">北周</foreign> dynasty (r. 560–578) in 575–577.</note>
                        </p>
                       <p>The stone text likewise laments “resistance and slander” (<hi rend="italic">tuihui </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">頺毀</foreign>) encountered by the Dharma, yet referencing historical events of destructions of images would not help its case, as the “original image” was no longer in China at that time. Therefore, the stone text explains that, in such times of distress, it was impossible to “make known in dreams” (<hi rend="italic">mengwen </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">夢聞</foreign>) the reappearance of the auspicious image. 
                           Instead of blaming external factors for the inauspicious absence of the image, the stone text again argues that the times were not ready yet for the image to make its reappearance in China, in the same way as the original image had to return to India under the Han, because “the feelings of people [towards Buddhism] were [still] distant and neglectful” (<hi rend="italic">renqing shulue </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">人情䟽略</foreign>) . </p>
                       <p>Things were changing for the better only under the Northern Qi and Sui dynasties. With his usual brevity and soberness, Daoxuan mentions the “unfolding of the teaching” (<hi rend="italic">kaijiao </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">開教</foreign>) under the first Sui emperor, and states that a monk named Mingxian <foreign xml:lang="zh">明憲</foreign> could obtain “one copy” (<hi rend="italic">yi ben </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">一本</foreign>) of the image from Dharma Master Daochang <foreign xml:lang="zh">道長法師</foreign> of the preceding Gao Qi <foreign xml:lang="zh">高齊</foreign> [Northern Qi ] dynasty. After the authenticity of this copy was affirmed by comparison with the transmission report, more painted copies (<hi rend="italic">tuxie </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">圖寫</foreign>) could be distributed all over the world.</p>
                       <p>The respective passage of the stone text sounds similar. The name of Mingxian <foreign xml:lang="zh">明獻</foreign>, however, is spelled differently here, and the object he received from Daochang is counted as “one <hi rend="italic">qu</hi>” (<hi rend="italic">yi qu </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">一軀</foreign>), a measure that speaks in favor of a three-dimensional, i.e., a sculpted image. After approving that the newly discovered image was “not different from the original” (<hi rend="italic">yu ben wu bie </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">與本無別</foreign>), it was finally “copied and disseminated” (<hi rend="italic">tuxie liubu </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">圗寫流布</foreign>). This is the first time the stone text mentions copying of the original image.</p>
                       <p>While Daoxuan’s transmission report comes to an end with Mingxian <foreign xml:lang="zh">明憲</foreign>, the stone text continues on. Before, it reported how the image came from <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sukhāvatī</foreign> to our <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sahā</foreign> world, and then, how it came to China proper. Now, some details are given how it came to the Chinese capital of Chang’an <foreign xml:lang="zh">長安</foreign>. The stone text reports that Governor Zeng of Yuzhou <foreign xml:lang="zh">豫州刾史鄭</foreign> came into the possession of a sculpted image in the sixteenth year of the <hi rend="italic">kaihuang</hi> era (596), which he sent to the capital along with its transmission record. At the capital’s Zhenji Monastery <foreign xml:lang="zh">真寂寺</foreign>, it was circulated and venerated.</p>
                       <p>This is the last link in the transmission chain of the auspicious image of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> and the 50 bodhisattvas. The record skips the final stage in the transmission of the image, that from the capital to Zitong County in Sichuan. However, if “Daomi who made the niches on the four faces [of the cuboid boulder]” named on the stele head is identical to the eponymous disciple of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Narendrayaśas</foreign>, it may have been him who took the image from the capital to Sichuan.</p>
                    </div>
                   
                    <div>
                        <head>Transmission Report or Hagiography?</head>
                       
                        <p>Scholars of art history have paid ample tribute to the significance of the <hi rend="italic">Transmission Report</hi> in understanding how the iconographic motif of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> and the 50 bodhisattvas evolved. They duly noted that this motif first appears in Sichuan, at Mount Wolong and Bishui Monastery, respectively, and that the <hi rend="italic">Transmission Report</hi> provides a valid explanation for the foreign stylistic features observed in the sculpted images. Most authors, however, refer only, or only initially, to the canonized text version when reconstructing the origin of this iconographic motif.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="LiSisheng1991">49–54</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2011">383–384</ref> [<ref type="biblio" target="Hida_Yen2018">370–371</ref>]; <ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2017a">1–15</ref>.</note> The stone cut version is referenced mainly for stating that the motif was in circulation already under the Sui dynasty, and that it came first to the capital, and then to Sichuan.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Huwenhe1991">90</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="HuWenhe1994">245–247</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="McNair2007">105–106</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2009">109–116</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="Jiang_Fu_Luo_Lei2018">361–362</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="Yangxiao2021">212–213</ref>.</note> Art historians so far treated the stone cut <hi rend="italic">Transmission Report</hi> and the Daoxuan version as primary sources for investigations into the historical development of an art historical motif that successfully spread across all of East Asia during the seventh century and continued to flourish thereafter. </p>
                        <p>In their quest for primary sources, some authors noted that a passage in the biography of Huihai <foreign xml:lang="zh">惠海</foreign> (541–609), a monk from Anle Monastery <foreign xml:lang="zh">安樂寺</foreign> in Jiangdu <foreign xml:lang="zh">江都</foreign> (modern Yangzhou <foreign xml:lang="zh">揚州</foreign> in Jiangsu Province), also refers to an image drawn in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sukhāvatī</foreign> by the Indian Bodhisattva Wutong.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="LiSisheng1991">49</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2017a">5</ref>; <ref type="biblio" target="Yamabe1999">325–326</ref>.</note> The respective passage in the <hi rend="italic">Sequel to the Biographies of Eminent Monks</hi> reads:
                       
                      <!-- A part of the transmission report is also found in the biography <!-\-(T#2060, 50: 515c6–516a6)-\->of Huihai <foreign xml:lang="zh">惠海</foreign> (541–609), a monk from Anle Monastery <foreign xml:lang="zh">安樂寺</foreign> in Jiangdu <foreign xml:lang="zh">江都</foreign> (modern Yangzhou <foreign xml:lang="zh">揚州</foreign> in Jiangsu Province). Huihai is said to have received an image of the true appearance of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitāyus</foreign> Buddha from a monk from Qi­zhou <foreign xml:lang="zh">齊州</foreign>, Daoquan <foreign xml:lang="zh">道詮</foreign>, who informed him that the image was drawn in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sukhāvatī</foreign> by the Indian Bodhisattva Wutong <foreign xml:lang="zh">五通菩薩</foreign>. As the image proofed to be wonder-working, Huihai sincerely revered and copied it. -->
                        </p>
                           
                           
                    <quote><!--忽有齊州僧道詮。齎畫無量壽像來云。是天竺雞頭摩寺五通菩薩。乘空往彼安樂世界圖寫尊儀。-->Then there was Monk Daoquan from Qizhou [present Jinan <foreign xml:lang="zh">濟南</foreign> in Shandong], who brought with him an image of [the Buddha of] Immeasurable Life [i.e., <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitāyus</foreign>], and said: “This  image is the honored appearance [of the Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitāyus</foreign>] that was once drawn by Bodhisattva Wutong from Jitoumo Monastery in India when he rose high into the air and reached that <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sukhāvatī</foreign> world [where <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitāyus</foreign> resides].” [Huihai] silently understood that [this image had come in response to] his original wishes; he cherished it deeply, and made obeisance to it and repented [his sins]. Then he saw an illuminating blaze of divine light, and he rejoiced in his good fortune of [obtaining] what he had hoped for. Thereupon he copied [the image], and, with earnest effort, he took a vow to be reborn in this [pure] land.<!--
                        既冥會silent comprehension素情original feelings,深懷禮懺。乃覩神光炤爍。慶所希幸。於是模寫懇苦earnestly bitterness。願生彼土。Since [this matter] coincided with [Huihai’s] original wish, he cherished deep respect and repentance. Then he saw heavenly and brilliant light and celebrated [the acquisition of] what  was wished for. Thereupon, he copied it.-->
                            <note>The passage is also translated in <ref type="biblio" target="Yamabe1999">325</ref>.</note>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">忽有齊州僧道詮，齎畫無量壽像來云：“是天竺雞頭摩寺五通菩薩，乘空往彼安樂世界圖寫尊儀。”既冥會素情，深懷禮懺。乃睹神光炤爍，慶所希幸。於是模寫，懇苦願生彼土。<!--沒齒為念。--></foreign>
                            <note>T#2060, 50: 515c14–19.</note>
                        </quote>
                        
                        <p>This passage, however, does not add anything to the lineage outlined in the <hi rend="italic">Transmission Report</hi>, as it remains unclear if the image of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitāyus</foreign> (Wuliangshou Fo <foreign xml:lang="zh">無量壽佛</foreign>) received by Daoquan depicted this Buddha surrounded by 50 or 52 bodhisattvas. The story about Bodhisattva Wutong from Jitoumo Monastery in India reaching <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sukhāvatī</foreign> may just have been borrowed as a literary motif in connection with the Buddha residing in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sukhāvatī</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitāyus</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> (Emituo Fo <foreign xml:lang="zh">阿彌陀佛</foreign>), respectively. The passage on Huihai receiving the image from Daoquan can first of all be counted as evidence for the belief in auspicious images of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitāyus</foreign>, and of its thriving cult under the Sui dynasty.</p>
                        <p>A systematic comparison of the earlier stone carved <hi rend="italic">Transmission Report</hi> and its canonized counterpart has so far only been undertaken by Okada Ken <foreign xml:lang="zh">岡田健</foreign>.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Okada2000">163–173</ref>.</note> Okada’s analysis is motivated by his search for historicity. For example, he identifies the Jitou Monastery (Jitoumo Si <foreign xml:lang="zh">鷄頭摩寺</foreign>) mentioned in the inscription as the Jiyuan <hi rend="italic"> <foreign xml:lang="sa">saṃghārāma</foreign>
                            </hi> (Jiyuan sengqielan <foreign xml:lang="zh">鷄園僧伽藍</foreign>) in the kingdom of Magadha that was visited by Xuanzang <foreign xml:lang="zh">玄奘</foreign> (600/602–664).<note>See T#2053, 50: 236b1–3. <!--《大唐大慈恩寺三藏法師傳》卷3：「故城東南有屈吒阿濫摩(唐言鷄園)僧伽藍故基，無憂王所造，是召千僧四事供養處」(CBETA 2023.Q3, T50, no. 2053, p. 236b1-3)--></note> Because Xuanzang nowhere mentions veneration of a miraculous image of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> at this place, Okada concludes that the legend about it may have been created not in India, but in China proper. Moreover, he regrets that it is impossible to identify a monk by the name of Ming­xian (<foreign xml:lang="zh">明憲</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="zh">明獻</foreign>) in historical sources, and that the same is true for Magistrate Zheng in Yu­zhou. As a result, Okada is only able to conclude that, with regard to historical facts, it is important to note that the image of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> and the 50 bodhisattvas was disseminated from the capital of the Sui. </p>
                        <p>Our present approach does not treat the <hi rend="italic">Transmission Report</hi> as an apt source for reconstructing the history of the iconographical motif under review. As Okada has shown, it does not serve this purpose well. We rather assume that the message of the <hi rend="italic">Transmission Report</hi> emerges from its location next to the sculpted images of niche 1, and that there is a close relation between the inscription and the image, which sets the stone text apart from Daoxuan’s version.</p> 
                            
                        <p>As the above comparison of text versions has shown, the earlier stone text is not only longer than the canonized text, it also contains information not adopted by Daoxuan (in case the stone version served as a source for his compilation). This information pertains to the temporal and spatial distance covered by the image on its route from ancient India, since the time when our world first had this image, towards the east to China, when it was first known under the Han dynasty, and further on to the present-time capital of the Sui and the Tang. Obviously, this timeline serves the purpose of authenticating what is claimed in the very first sentence of the <hi rend="italic">Transmission Report</hi>, namely, that the image came to China from the Western regions.</p>
                        <p>However, the initial claim of the <hi rend="italic">Transmission Report</hi> relates not only to the origin of the image, but also to its particular nature, as it is an “auspicious image” (<hi rend="italic">rui­xiang</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">瑞像</foreign>). Such images are not only capable of working wonders, they are also known for developing a life of their own. Auspicious images are able to communicate with the living, usually in dreams, to make known their intentions. They react to the rise and fall of historical dynasties with auspicious and inauspicious signs in a foretelling manner. And they possess power over their place of residence. As long as people are supposed to carry them to places, they are moveable and light; on arrival, they grow heavy and become immovable to indicate their resting place. If necessary, they walk around all by themselves, or ride a boat, or float in water.<note>The power to travel by themselves is characteristic for a particular group of auspicious images: those believed to have been produced by the Mauryan King <foreign xml:lang="sa">Aśoka</foreign> (r. ca. 268–232 BCE) and to have later come to China, see <ref type="biblio" target="Shinohara2004">182–184</ref>.</note>
                            
                           </p>
                        <p>In this context, we can comprehend the particularities in the narrative of the stone text that are not found in Daoxuan’s version. It is the original image that is being carried to China by the sisiter of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Kāśyapa Mātaṅga</foreign>, and not a copy of it. In the same way that Wutong Bodhisattva acted as recipient of the divine image, this nun serves as its carrier. She “came holding this image” (<hi rend="italic">chi ci xiang lai </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">持此像來</foreign>), and she “took this image and returned” (<hi rend="italic">jiang ci xiang er hui </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">将此像而歸</foreign>). Coming to China and returning to India were no decisions made by the nun, but by the image. The reason for its return is given as well, namely, the distant feelings of the Chinese people.</p>
                        <p>After its return to India, the image waited for more favorable times, pondering the possibility to make known in dreams its appearance. Dreams are adequate means of communication for auspicious images, who inform the dreamer about their wishes and needs, warn about pending dangers, or scare off enemies.<note>See, for example, Daoxuan’s story no. 28 (T#2106, 52: 419b7–c5) on the dream of Emperor Wu <foreign xml:lang="zh">武帝</foreign> (r. 502–549) of the Liang <foreign xml:lang="zh">梁</foreign> dynasty (<ref type="biblio" target="Shinohara1998">153–154; 173; 181</ref>), and story no. 33 (T#2106, 52: 420b21–c4) about the stone image of Lingshi Monastery (Lingshi Si <foreign xml:lang="zh">靈石寺</foreign>) in Jinzhou <foreign xml:lang="zh">晋州</foreign> in need of repair (<ref type="biblio" target="Shinohara1998">161; 172; 182</ref>). In his overview of Chinese dynasties, <ref type="biblio" target="Soper1959">1–121</ref>, presents some dream incidents transmitted in literary sources that are ascribed to the first to sixth century. We also find the dream motif in the founding legend of the present Yuqun Monastery (Yuquan Si <foreign xml:lang="zh">玉泉寺</foreign>; formerly known as Gushan Monastery Gushan Si <foreign xml:lang="zh">谷山寺</foreign>), located north of the main summit of Mount Tai (Tai Shan <foreign xml:lang="zh">泰山</foreign>) in Shandong. The legend, transmitted on the <hi rend="italic">Stele with the Record on Gushan Monastery</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Gushan Si ji bei </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">谷山寺記碑</foreign>) of 1201, mentions a Luohan image that communicated in dreams, and was subsequently discovered by locals and moved to the place where the monastery was then established, see <ref type="biblio" target="Wenzel2022">28–31</ref>.</note> The image of the <hi rend="italic">Transmission Report</hi> needs to communicate its true appearance as the “Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> sitting on a lotus with a thousand leaves that all spring from the same root” (<hi rend="italic">Emituo Fo zuo qianye lianhua tonggen bingchu </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">阿弥陁佛坐千葉蓮華，同根竝出</foreign>). Although the inscription does not relate when and to whom these details were communicated, Dharma Master Ming­xian <foreign xml:lang="zh">明獻</foreign> receives “such an image” (<hi rend="italic">ci yi qu </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">此一軀</foreign>) at the earliest possible date, namely, in the first year of the <hi rend="italic">kaihuang</hi> era, which marks the establishment of the Buddhist reign of the first Sui emperor. </p>
                        <p>Henceforth, the sculpted image is disseminated throughout China by crafted copies of the original. But these crafted copies are all certified as being “not different from the original.” As proof of authentication, they are transmitted together with the “original record”  (<hi rend="italic">benzhuan </hi> <foreign xml:lang="zh">本傳</foreign>). </p>
                        <p>Summing up this evidence, the acting agents of the <hi rend="italic">Transmission Report</hi> are not so much the personalities who come into contact with the image and hold it in their hands, but the image itself. Therefore, it seems justified to read the word <hi rend="italic">zhuan </hi> <foreign xml:lang="zh">傳</foreign> in the inscription title not just as a “report” about how the image was transmitted to China and Mount Wolong, but also as the biography or hagiography of the image. In analogy to hagiographies collected in such works as the <hi rend="italic">Biographies of Eminent Monks </hi>(<hi rend="italic">Gaoseng zhuan </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">高僧傳</foreign>) and its sequels, we are confronted here with the life story of an auspicious image, informing us about its coming into the world, its travels through the world, and the goals it pursued by doing so. </p>
                        
                        <p>Reading the <hi rend="italic">Transmission Report</hi> as an hagiographical account of the image of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> and the 50 bodhisattvas, we thus realize that this image possesses powers comparable to those of Buddha relics. This impression is reinforced by the fact that the image of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> and the 50 bodhisattvas was not created by an artist, but came into being by an act of bestowal. Both versions, the stone text, and the canonized story, underline this aspect of the image. <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Buddha may have allowed the bodhisattva Wutong to picture his “true appearance,” or he may have assisted him in the completion of such an image,<note>This is what happened in the version of the story included in the biography of Huihai (T#2060, 50: 515c14–19), see above.</note> but he did not. Instead, he first dismissed Wutong, and then granted the image.</p> 
                        <p>In Daoxuan’s text, Wutong asks for the image to be “sent down” (<hi rend="italic">chuijiang</hi> <foreign xml:lang="zh">垂降</foreign>) in an act of grace. By contrast, the stone text does not use the phrase of “sending down” the image, which implies that <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sukhāvatī</foreign> would be located somewhere above our world of humans, a clear contradiction to the description found in the <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sukhāvatīvyūha-sūtra</foreign>
                            </hi>.<note>The <hi rend="italic">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sukhāvatīvyūha-sūtra</foreign>
                                </hi> describes <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sukhāvatī</foreign> as a world-system totally independent from our <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sahā</foreign> world, located at an immeasurable distance in the west. Yet Chinese votive inscriptions of the sixth century show that the pure land <foreign xml:lang="zh">净土</foreign> of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitāyus</foreign> (Wuliangshou Fo <foreign xml:lang="zh">無量壽佛</foreign>; Buddha Immeasurable Life) was imagined like a heaven <foreign xml:lang="zh">天</foreign> of our world-system, comparable to Maitreya’s <foreign xml:lang="sa">Tuṣita</foreign> Heaven. For a detailed analysis of the implications of the term of “sending down the image,” see the respective gloss by Inaba <foreign xml:lang="ja">Hiderō </foreign>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">稲葉秀郎</foreign> in <ref type="biblio" target="HidaRomi_2017a">4–8</ref>. Inaba concludes that when the image of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> and the 50 bodhisattvas circulated under the Sui, there was yet no difference being made between a “heaven” and a “pure land.” </note> 
                            Instead, the stone text has the Buddha promise that the image will be “soon bestowed and sent off [to the <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sahā</foreign> world]” (<hi rend="italic">xun qiansong wang </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">尋遣送往</foreign>). <!--After the image initially manifested in our world as “a drawing on the leaf of a tree” (<hi rend="italic">yu shuye shang tuxie </hi><foreign xml:lang="zh">扵樹葉上圗寫</foreign>)--> Thus, the image even acts like an official emissary of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Buddha, endowed with the power to render efficient vows of rebirth in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign>’s Pure Land, as Daoxuan pointed out. In this respect, the auspicious image also resembles the relics of the Buddha, whose general purpose is to continue the Buddha’s presence on earth, almost as an extension of his life-story.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Strong2004">229</ref>.</note> </p>
                        
                        <p>These observations entail the question to which literary genre the text carved at Mount Wolong might belong. So far, it seems to be the sole representative of its kind, as none of the many other depictions of this iconographical subject has an accompanying inscription like the <hi rend="italic">Transmission Report</hi> at Mount Wolong. However, the close relationship between the hagiographical aspects of the image and other relics of the Buddha suggests a connection to a text genre that is attested for the first time about three decades later.</p>
                        <p>The genre in question is exemplified by texts carved on stone steles below depictions of the footprints the historical Buddha is said to have left behind in the city of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Pāṭaliputra</foreign> in the kingdom of Magadha. In his <hi rend="italic">Great Tang Record of Travels to the Western Regions</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Da Tang xiyu ji </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">大唐西域記</foreign>), Xuanzang relates the legend on how <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign> left impressions of both his feet on a great stone, knowing that they would be venerated a hundred years after his <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">parinirvāṇa</foreign>
                            </hi> by the future king <foreign xml:lang="sa">Aśoka</foreign>.<note>T#2087, 51: 911c10–22; for translations, see <ref type=" biblio" target="LiRongxi1996">199–200</ref>; 毕爾<ref type="biblio" target="Beal1884">2: 90–91</ref><!--; <ref type="biblio" target="Beal2005"/>-->.<!--《大唐西域記》卷8〈一國．摩揭陀國〉：「窣堵波側不遠，精舍中有大石，如來所履，[A3]雙迹猶存，其長尺有八寸，廣餘六寸[42]矣。兩迹 
                            俱有輪相，十指[A4]皆帶花文，魚形映起，光明時 照。昔者如來將取寂滅，北趣[＊]拘尸那城，南顧摩揭[43]陀國，蹈此石上，告阿難曰：「吾今 最後留此足迹，將入寂滅，顧摩揭陀也。 百歲之後，有無憂王命世[44]君臨，建都此地， 匡護三寶，役使百神。」及無憂王之嗣位也， 遷都築邑，掩[45]周迹石，既近宮城，恒親供養。後諸國王競欲舉歸，石雖不大，眾莫能 轉。近者設賞迦王毀壞佛法，遂即石所，欲 滅聖迹，鑿已還平，文[46]彩如故，於是捐棄殑伽河流，尋復本處」(CBETA 2023.Q3, T51, no. 2087, p. 911c10-22)
                            [A3] 雙【CB】【麗-CB】，變【大】(cf. K32n1065_p0430b15; T50n2053_p0236a23)。　[42] 矣兩【大】，左右【明】。　[A4] 皆【CB】【麗-CB】，念【大】(cf. K32n1065_p0430b16)。　[＊28-2] 拘【大】＊，𤘽【甲】＊，【乙】。　[43] 陀國【大】，國也【乙】。　[44] 君臨建都【大】，建都君臨【明】。　[45] 周【大】，固【宋】。　[46] 彩【大】，采【甲】。-->
                           <!-- Samuel Beal: "Si-yu-ki. Buddhist Records of the Western World - Translated from the Chinese of Hiuen Tsang (AD 629)." (Digital Edition (Version 2.0 of 2005)) https://mbingenheimer.net/tools/beal/xiyuji.html　<ref type="biblio" target="Beal2005"/>
                            By the side of the stūpa, and not far from it, in a vihāra, is a great stone on which Tathāgata walked. There is still the impression of both his feet on it, about eighteen inches long and six inches broad; both the right and left impress have the circle-sign,964 and the ten toes are all fringed with figures of flowers (or flower scrolls) and forms of fishes, which glisten brightly in the light (morning light). In old time Tathāgata, being about to attain Nirvāṇa, was going northward to Kuśinagara, when turning round to the south and looking back at Magadha, he stood upon this stone and said to ānanda, "Now for the very last time I leave this foot-impression, being about to attain Nirvāṇa, and looking at Magadha. A hundred years hence there shall be a King Aśoka;965 he shall build here his capital and establish his court; he shall protect the three religious treasures and command the genii."
                            
                            When Aśoka (Wu-yau) had ascended the throne, he changed his capital and built this town; he enclosed the stone with the impression; and as it was near the royal precinct, he paid it constant personal worship. Afterwards the kings of the neighbourhood wished to carry it off to their own country; but although the stone is not large, they could not move it at all. 
                            Lately Saśāṅka-rāja, when he was overthrowing and destroying the law of Buddha, forthwith came to the place where that stone is, for the purpose of destroying the sacred marks. Having broken it into pieces, it came whole again, and the ornamental figures as before; then he flung it into the river Ganges, but it came back to its old place. -->
                            </note> The texts that are carved on the steles below the footprints also refer to this legend.</p>
                        <p>The earliest known sample of such a “Buddha footprint stele” (<hi rend="italic">Fo zu bei </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">佛足碑</foreign>) has survived in three fragments that were unearthed at Yuhua Monastery (Yuhua Si <foreign xml:lang="zh">玉華寺</foreign>) in Yijun County (Yijun Xian <foreign xml:lang="zh">宜君縣</foreign>), Shaanxi Province. On the fragments, two feet are depicted, with toes turned upwards and soles decorated with auspicious signs. The nearby inscription is titled <hi rend="italic">Report on the Buddha Footprints</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Fo ji ji </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">佛迹記</foreign>). In the case of the Yuhua Monastery fragment, only the beginning of the text is preserved, which references the footprints on the stone in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Pāṭaliputra</foreign> that “Xuanzang saw and venerated in person <foreign xml:lang="zh">奘親觀禮圖</foreign>.” Because Xuanzang stayed at Yuhua Monastery from 659–664, it is generally assumed that the footprint stele was carved during that time, and that the image of the footprints is based on a copy of the original <foreign xml:lang="sa">Pāṭaliputra</foreign> footprints that Xuanzang took with him when he returned to China.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Wenzel2020">654–656</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Yuhua Monastery footprint stele initiated not only a new iconographical tradition, but also a new literary genre, here called simply “report” (<hi rend="italic">ji </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">記</foreign>). The next known footprint stele that claims to be a copy of the original at <foreign xml:lang="sa">Pāṭaliputra</foreign> is the one erected in “the <hi rend="italic">dingmao</hi> year of the Hong­wu reign of the great Ming” (<foreign xml:lang="zh">大明洪武丁卯</foreign>), that is, in 1387, by the supervisor (<hi rend="italic">tidian </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">提點</foreign>) of Wolong <foreign xml:lang="sa">Dhyāna</foreign> Monastery (Wolong chan Si <foreign xml:lang="zh">卧龍禪寺</foreign>) in Chang’an, Monk Deming of Hanshui <foreign xml:lang="zh">寒水僧德明</foreign>. Here, the report below the depiction of the Buddha’s feet has been preserved in its entirety.</p>
                        <p>The first part of the inscription follows the corresponding passage in Xuanzang’s travelog (T#2087, 51: 911c10–22) rather closely. Other than the travelog version, the stone text mentions that, while still in India, the sacred imprints survived a total of eight attempts to destroy them. The implications of this narrative might be that the Buddha’s footprints waited for Xuanzang’s arrival in India. Xuanzang came in his role as a pilgrim, venerated the footprints, and took a copy back to China to present them to the emperor. Finally, the emperor saw to their wide distribution by imperial decree. The transmission report on the Wolong <foreign xml:lang="sa">Dhyāna</foreign> Monastery stele is followed by a byline, in which Monk Deming documents his order to recarve the footprint stele in 1387.<note>For an illustration see <ref type="biblio" target="Tokiwa_Sekino1939-1941">9: 45(1)</ref>. For a transcription and translation of the inscribed text see <ref type="biblio" target="Wenzel2020">656–659</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Afterwards, the Wolong <foreign xml:lang="sa">Dhyāna</foreign> Monastery stele was copied several times. The famous Shaolin Monastery (Shaolin Si <foreign xml:lang="zh">少林寺</foreign>) in Dengfeng <foreign xml:lang="zh">登封</foreign>, Henan, has a copy erected in 1566,<note>For an illustration and transcription of the carved text, see <ref type="biblio" target="Tokiwa_Sekino1939-1941">9: 46(1); text: 45</ref>.</note> and the <foreign xml:lang="sa">Aśoka</foreign> Monastery (Ayu Wang Si <foreign xml:lang="zh">阿育王寺</foreign>) in Ningbo <foreign xml:lang="zh">寧波</foreign>, Zhejiang, has another one that was erected in 1899.<note>For an illustration and transcription of the carved text, see <ref type="biblio" target="Tokiwa_Sekino1939-1941">9: 46(3); text: 45</ref>.</note> Whenever the footprints of the Buddha were recarved on yet another stele, the transmission report on how the image came to China is continued by another byline documenting the copies that have been taken. In this way, one stop after the other is added to the travel route of the image of the Buddha’s footprints. </p>
                        <p>We know that copies of Xuanzang’s <foreign xml:lang="sa">Pāṭaliputra</foreign> footprints with accompanying transmission record even reached Korea. There is also evidence that another set of copies of the <foreign xml:lang="sa">Pāṭaliputra</foreign> footprints circulated in China and eventually reached Japan. These were brought from India by the emissary Wang Xuance <foreign xml:lang="zh">王玄策</foreign> (622?–682). A sole surviving specimen of Buddha footprints in Yao County (Yao Xian <foreign xml:lang="zh">耀縣</foreign>) in Shaanxi from the Song dynasty (960–1279) belongs to another iconographical type. The accompanying text narrates that the early pilgrim-monk Faxian <foreign xml:lang="zh">法顯</foreign> (320?–420?) copied the Buddha’s footprints he saw in what is modern Sri Lanka, and took them to China.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Wenzel2020">663–665</ref>.</note> </p>
                        <p>The “Buddha footprint steles” and the hagiographical <hi rend="italic">Transmission Report</hi> next to the image in niche 1 at Mount Wolong serve the same purpose, namely, to place copies of an distinguished original icon into a long lineage of transmission from ancient India to China, Korea, and Japan. In medieval China, images such as that of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> Buddha and the 52 Bodhisattvas were thus not only considered manifestations of the sacred, but landmarks encompassing the entire Buddhist world. </p>
                </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>