<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/rest/db/schema/stone.xsd">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Site Gangshan</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>N.N.</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <!-- Titel und Kürzel des Bandes in @n -->
                <title n="shandong_volume2" xml:lang="en">Shandong Volume 2</title>
                <title n="shandong_volume2" xml:lang="zh">山東省第二卷</title>
                <!-- Ordnungsnummer für Kapitelreihenfolge in @n -->
                <biblScope unit="chapter" n="6"/>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>29.07.2008</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>correct spelling of *Mandra[sena] and *Saṃghabhara included, more corrections
                    proposed by Funayama Toru included</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>06.03.2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Wenzel</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Passage on "Evening Glow Monastery" added</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>25.03.2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>JMP</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Aktualisierung Gliederung, Aktualisierung Beschriftung groupings</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>01.04.2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>JMP</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Ordering carving techniques</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>03.04.2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Abschnitt Location überarbeitet gemäß Markette</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>13.08.2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Abschnitt Location ergänzt</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>12.10.2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>CW</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>"Related Persons," "Date", and "Research History" by ZZ added.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>23.05.2013</date>
                <respStmt>CW</respStmt>
                <item>text altered by adding text from LL's article on Gangshan</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:id="Site_GS">
        <body>
            <div xml:lang="zh">
                <head>崗山</head>
                <figure n="figure" xml:id="GS_sc_path_DSC2960.JPG" rend="full">
                    <head xml:lang="zh">崗山朝山之路與巨礫刻石；2002年拍攝</head>
                    <head>Boulders along the path taken by devotees on Mount Gang; photograph taken
                        in 2002</head>
                    <graphic url="GS_sc_B28_133-51.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <div>
                    <head>空間</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>地理位置</head>
                        <p>崗山的三段佛經節文刊刻在登山沿途的單石、巨礫和巖壁上，在山東省的摩崖刻經中獨樹一格。崗山位於鄒城北端（地圖，<ptr target="Zoucheng_2013_02_21e.jpg"/>）。山體東西長1.2公里，南北寬0.7公里。峰頂海拔為235米。東面的斜坡向下延伸至一條名為“狼溝”的山谷，溝寬至85米，朝向正東。由於自然風化，山谷中隨處可見巨石和碎礫。山腳處即山谷最低點，海拔為110米。在地理位置上，崗山位於東經116.969度，北緯35.426度，相當於UTM坐標系統第50S帶東行497250，北行3920200。崗山刻經分佈於東面的山谷和靠近山峰的一片高地（地圖，<ptr target="Gangshan_Karte.jpg"/>）。刻經鑿刻在多處岩石和崖壁上，朝向不一。</p>
                        <p>崗山西南不到1.5公里處是面南的鐵山刻經。兩山對望，但刻經不在彼此視線之內。尖山位於崗山東北偏東4.8公里處。從崗山望過去，也看不清尖山刻經（今已被毀）。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>史英</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>地形與空間構成</head>
                        <p>崗山有五組刻經：</p>
                        <list>
                            <item>菩提留支譯《入楞伽經》經首序文小字本（崗山A號）</item>
                            <item>菩提留支譯《入楞伽經》經首序文大字本（崗山B號），較崗山A號稍長</item>
                            <item>《佛說觀無量壽佛經》經首序文（崗山C號）</item>
                            <item>佛名（崗山D號）</item>
                            <item>題記（崗山E號）</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>《入楞伽經》經首序文節文刊刻了兩次，卻不在同一個刻石面上，而是散見於多處岩石。大字本分佈於逾31處崖壁和巨石上（崗山B1號至B31.2號），幾乎遍布整個山體。小字本較為集中，見於五塊單體石面（崗山A1號至A5號；見地圖，<ptr target="Gangshan_Karte.jpg"/>）。</p>
                        <p>朝山者從山的東邊，即狼溝的入口處開始上山，首先映入眼簾的是《入楞伽經》經首序文大字本的第一個經文片段（崗山B1號）。繼而轉向一塊巨大的刻經石。朝山者崎嶇行進，攀岩而過，沿途經過崗山B2號至崗山B19號刻經。至此走出山谷，抵達雞嘴石（<ptr target="GS_sc_jizuishi_G7S92029.jpg"/>）。這是山上形態最奇特的一塊岩石，遠遠就能望見。雞嘴石上有三面銘刻，其中包括《佛說觀無量壽佛經》經首序文（崗山C號）。</p>
                        <p>雞嘴石之上，東區山脊有崗山A1號和崗山A2號刻經，內容為篇幅較短的《入楞伽經》經首序文小字本起首部分。接著地形豁然開朗，彷彿走入一個逐漸升高的圓形劇場，更多的刻經錯落其中（崗山A3號至崗山A5號和崗山B21號至崗山B31.2號）。從東邊的第一處刻經（崗山B1號）到西邊的最後一處（崗山B31.2號），直線距離僅為159.7米。穿梭於海拔169米到234米的山間小徑實則更長。刻有《入楞伽經》經首序文大字本的最後一塊刻石（崗山B31.2號）在一條徑直通往一座道觀的路旁。這座明朝修建的道觀可能建於一座更早廟宇的舊址。一條不規則的山路由此順著山體南坡拾級而下，通向鄒城市。</p>
                        <p>《入楞伽經》經首序文大字本節文依地形分為兩組，一組在雞嘴石東邊（<ptr target="GS_sc_eastern_gorge_comm.jpg"/>），一組在西邊（地圖，<ptr target="Gangshan_Karte.jpg"/>）。刻經內容均分為兩部分，第一部分生動地描述佛陀宣講此經的摩羅耶山勝境；第二部分再現了佛陀說法場景，眾多僧人與來自其他種種佛國的菩薩會集一處。</p>
                        <p>
                            <ptr target="Gangshan_Ost_Cliff_Übersicht.jpg"/>所示為狼溝的南面，沿途為《入楞伽經》經首序文大字本開始之處。照片背景中的樹木令人感受到崖壁的巨大體量。在開始部分的東側，即朝向觀者的那一側，是第一個刻經段落，即崗山B1號，刻有《入楞伽經》首句。它將讀者的注意力引向大海畔楞伽城中的摩羅耶山，佛曾居此說法。大字置細線雙界格中。引人注目的是，經文從左向右寫，與觀者朝山的方向一致。</p>
                        <p>在過去的十五個世紀，地震和山體滑坡擾動了許多巨石和石塊的位置。東邊山谷的若干刻石滾落山谷中央，形成一個凝固的石瀑布。有些巨石傾覆，刻字遮蔽，現已無處尋覓，因而，五段刻經節文已佚失（崗山B4，B6，B17，B20，B22號）。另外，有些幾乎埋沒的刻字面朝上方。崗山B2號和崗山B3號的簡短段落刻於兩塊巨石之上，滾落至崗山B1號下方遠處（<ptr target="GS_sc_eastern_gorge_comm.jpg"/>）。崗山B4號刻經節文的三個字卻已杳然無蹤，這幾個字可能仍存於倒臥的一塊巨石。</p>
                        <p>崗山B5號的兩個字與崗山B1號刻於同一巨岩石面上，但B5號在石面另一段的高部的一個突出聳石，其上方雜草叢生。由於攀爬過於危險，至今未曾打製拓片。然而，即使頑石堅壁也無法抵禦時間，巨大的石塊層層剝落而下。崗山B6號刻經節文的八個字亦下落不明，崗山B7號刻字則見於一塊方整厚重的巨石背面（<ptr target="GS_sc_eastern_gorge_comm.jpg"/>中央）。這塊巨石可能從其後方的石崖落下，石崖上一個凸起如“屋頂”的三角形石塊下方的岩石已付闕如。這段刻經段落也帶有雙界格。也許狼溝崖壁部分的刻石都置於界格中，單體巨石上的刻字則無。由於地貌屢經變化，當初的路徑已不得其詳。而所刻經文見諸印本佛經，刻經節文完整的內容和段落順序因此可得而知。</p>
                        <p>崗山B8號的長篇刻經段落是刻於垂直崖壁的最後一節，面則朝東（<ptr target="GS_r_B8_total_KA23.JPG"/>）。刻字也置於雙界格中，也與迄今所見其他刻經段落一樣，從左向右讀，這與從山谷上山之路的方向是吻合的。</p>
                        <p>崗山B9號位於同一塊岩石朝北的另一側石面上。由此處開始至崗山B19號，為一連串的十塊單石，每石或僅刻一字（崗山B11、B12、B13、B14、B15、B16、B18、B19號），或刻二字（崗山B10號），均無界格，其中崗山17號四個刻字已佚失，可能原本分刻於四塊岩石之上。</p>
                        <p>當朝山者沿著山谷上行，讀到關於摩羅耶山的文字，恍惚置身“諸寶間錯，光明赫炎”，感受“微風吹擊，搖枝動葉”，嗅到“百千妙香”，耳聞“百千妙音，一時俱發”。於是，崗山搖身一變，成了中國的摩羅耶山。這是宗教藝術常見的手法，稱作“場所置換（<foreign xml:lang="en">translatio loci</foreign>）”，即將一處場景轉移重現於另一處。</p>
                        <p>接下來的一長段刻經，崗山B20號，凡二十字，也已不存。它應位於東部山溝的崗山B19號刻石和西邊高地的崗山B21號巨石之間。這二十字最初是散布於山谷中的單塊岩石，還是以較長節文刻於摩崖或巨石，今已無從而知。這段刻經描述重巖“屈曲，處處皆有仙堂、靈室、龕窟，無數眾寶所成”。同樣不清楚的是，此處所渲染的仙堂龕窟仍歸在盤桓登山之路上的刻文，還是已屬於西邊高地分佈在雞嘴石之上的第二部分文字。此處刻經繼續描述佛陀講經的會眾。雖然歷史上的釋迦牟尼佛已離開我們的世界而入般涅槃，但此時此地，信衆彷彿身臨其境，能夠加入“大比丘僧及大菩薩眾，皆從種種他方佛土俱來集會”的行列。身為會眾一員，信衆聆受“具足無量自在三昧，神通之力，奮迅遊化”的菩薩的教誨。在適當的時機，與會者將理解他們的教誨，修成菩薩，並最終成佛。</p>
                        <p>刻經的第二部分散佈於十處岩塊和巨石上。石上的經文的閱讀順序為從右向左，與朝山者上山的走向相應。<note>崗山B21號刻經可從左向右讀，也可以從右向左讀。崗山B22號刻經已不存。崗山B23號刻經從上向下刻。從B24號刻經開始，經文的閱讀方向才得以明確。</note>高地上的刻石移動較少，保存狀況比山溝中的刻石完好，只有一段五字刻文（崗山B22號）下落不明。刻於單塊岩石的字數參差顯著，從一字（崗山B27號）到十八字（崗山B28號）不等。在這個莊嚴的集會之所，銘刻自崗山B23號始，均置雙界格中。此外，從崗山B26號開始，包括僅有一個字的崗山B27號，都飾以蓮瓣和花朵。蓮瓣與花朵是佛土或淨土特屬的裝飾，崗山，或者說我們的世界，在菩薩踐行度化救助眾生之責的那一刻，也化作了淨土。<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Halkias2013">第4頁</ref>。他的評註適用於崗山：“將佛土概念化為淨土，即佛永恆宣說佛法的理想處所，這激發了冥想者、藝術家和思想家去想出新的方法，對其崇高的形式加以表現和置身於其中。”
                            </note>只有崗山B31.1號沒有界格，顯然未刻完就放棄了。</p>
                        <p>通覽大字本刻經節文，刻經顯然是被有意安置於一個廣闊的景觀中。觀者不能如在斗室中安坐於經卷之前，而必須沿著一條預設的小徑巡行山間，逐石拜觀。觀者由此切身領會刻經造就了一個神聖的地理環境，將整座崗山轉化為中土的摩羅耶山。此地佛法猶存且被不斷宣說。</p>
                        <p>較之篇幅稍長的大字本，《入楞伽經》小字本字小，分佈相對集中，僅見於三個小範圍的五塊單體石面（崗山A1號到A5號；見地圖，<ptr target="Gangshan_Karte.jpg"/>）。小字本位於山體中央區域，在大字本的東面部分與西面部分之間。如前文所述，起首兩個段落（崗山A1號和崗山A2號）見於山脊下的崖面，在雞嘴石上方21米處。隨後兩段（崗山A3號和崗山A4號）刻於更上方65米左右處一塊巨石。最後一段（崗山A5號）在另一塊巨石上，位置較前者高20米。該石見<ptr target="GS_sc_path_DSC2960.JPG"/>，橫臥於前景之中。截至“三昧”二字（<ptr target="GS_r_A5_part_G7SB8241.JPG"/>），小字本與大字本刻經的經文相同。大字本此後還有二十三個字，包括棄用的崗山B31.1號上的兩個字（參見本卷第<ptr type="infra" target="endofGSB_zh"/>頁）。</p>
                        <p>朝山者由雞嘴石又看到了另一處“場所置換”。“雞嘴石”似乎由其奇異的外形而得名，尤其是從遠處望去，該岩石的上方形似鳥喙（見扉頁和<ptr target="GS_sc_jizuishi_G7S92029.jpg"/>）。此名何時開始使用，不得而知，也不見於金石文獻。1911年，山東籍金石學家孫葆田談到“雞爪石”。<note>見《山東金石志》<ref type="biblio" target="Shandongjinshizhi">第9253頁</ref>，以及本卷“討論”
                                部分。</note>“雞嘴”在漢語中有吉祥的意味，“雞”和“吉”諧音，意為好運。然而這個名稱與這樣一個佛教聖地似乎不太相稱，聽上去毫無神聖感。其實，這一外形奇異的岩石可能使6世紀的僧侶想到鷲這一種鳥，以及印度著名的鷲峰。此山漢名音譯為耆闍崛山，多稱靈鷲山或簡稱靈山。雞嘴石可能出自其中某個名稱。</p>
                        <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="Gangshan_Karte.jpg">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">崗山地圖</head>
                            <head>Map of Mount Gang</head>
                            <graphic url="Gangshan_Karte.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>印度的鷲峰在古摩揭陀國，靠近王舍城，位於今伽耶市東北約五十公里處，是佛陀心儀的講經說法之處。他曾在此宣講包括著名的《法華經》在內的數部大乘佛經。</p>
                        <p>在印度並不引人注意的鷲峰和鷲之間的相似之處並不明顯，而崗山此石上方的石塊呈水平狀凸出，確實令人聯想到鷲的形狀（<ptr target="Geier_Brehm_bw.jpg"/>），甚至連下方兩塊石頭也類似這種鳥特有的毛茸茸的足爪。</p>
                        <p>更有力的證據是崗山C號、崗山D號、崗山E號三段的銘刻。《佛說觀無量壽佛經》經首序文以較小的字刻成，始於雞嘴石東面（崗山C1號），直至南面（崗山C2號）。此經為佛陀在鷲峰宣講的另一部經，如開篇所言：“如是我聞：一時，佛在王舍城耆闍崛山中，與大比丘眾千二百五十人俱；菩薩三萬二千，文殊師利法王子而為上首。”（<ptr target="GS_r_C1_part_G7S92048.JPG"/>；<ptr target="GS_C1.jpg"/>）。“鷲峰”（耆闍崛山）一名就此刻於雞嘴石之上。</p>
                        <p>該石的北部有三個刻得略大的佛名，“釋迦文佛”、“弥勒尊佛”、“阿弥阤佛”（崗山D1.1號、崗山D1.2號、崗山D1.3號；<ptr target="GS_r_D-E_part_DSC3028.jpg"/>；<ptr target="GS_D1.jpg"/>）。一旁的題記（崗山E號）包含六個署名（<ptr target="GS_r_D-E_part_DSC3092.jpg"/>；<ptr target="GS_E1.jpg"/>），以此借指“大比丘眾千二百五十人”，如經文所說，他們會集於靈鷲峰，聽佛陀說法。彌勒佛和阿彌陀佛也置身其間，如同另外四個佛名，“大空王佛”（崗山D2號）、“阿弥阤佛”（崗山D3號）、“一切佛”（崗山D4號），以及可能是另一個“大空王佛”的殘跡（亦屬崗山D4號），一併刻於附近偃臥的岩石上。他們刻出的名號使諸佛來會。這些佛名與釋迦牟尼佛的名號一起付諸堅石，歷經歲月，確保鷲峰盛會之際初次宣講的教義萬世永存。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>雷德侯<space n="2"/>溫狄婭</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>釋名</head>
                        <p>崗山地名說法不一，一說北崗山，一說大崗山。鐵山曾稱為南崗山，崗山因此也叫後崗山。康熙五十四年（1715）間婁一均纂修的《鄒縣志》載：“北崗有石，卓立如碑。”
                                    <note>《鄒縣志》<ref type="biblio" target="Zouxianzhi1715">第301頁</ref>。</note>
                                民國間張丕矩修《山東鄒縣地理志》稱：“後崗山峰巔有北齊摩崖二十四處。”<note>《鄒縣舊志匯編》 <ref type="biblio" target="Zouxianjiuzhihuibian1986">第25頁</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>賴非</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>時間</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>相關寺院</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>崗山東寺院</head>
                            <p>據說，在崗山山麓“狼溝”曾有一座寺院，姑且稱作崗山東寺院。此處三面環山，地勢開闊。山上樹木蔥鬱，山麓泉水湧流，遠處田疇平展，村落散佈，既幽僻安靜，又可以通達外界。</p>
                            <p>如此佳境符合北朝寺院選址的常規，泰山和嶧山也是如此：地處僻靜，又不遠離人煙；山麓有水可取，並且地勢平坦，土地適於耕作。</p>
                            <p>假如存在這樣一座寺院，或許就在通往狼溝的小徑起點附近。狼溝東邊的那片開闊地適於建造寺院（<ptr target="GS_sc_G7S93333.JPG"/>）。</p>
                            <p>1990年以來，曾多次調查這個地區。但由於長期以來地面挖開取土，以供磚場之需，可供斷代的遺蹟已蕩然無存。</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>晚照寺</head>
                            <p>另一座名為晚照寺的寺院坐落在崗山西北隘口處，有時也被視為刻鑿崗山石經的僧侶們的起居中心。這處遺址東、南、北三面皆山，將午始見日光，寺名由此而來。
                                寺院應當由來已久。遺址面積近七千平方米。西半部於20世紀60年代修水庫時遭到破壞。據村民講，那裡出土了大量磚瓦。遺址東半部是一處高臺，當為殿堂建築地基。出土的粗繩紋長方磚及蓮花紋圓瓦當，證明其建造時代可上推至隋代或唐初。宋元之後棄用，遺址出土有當時的瓷片，而此後的陶瓷幾乎未見。</p>
                            <p>興建晚照寺可能與某一個宗教團體的遷移有關。該團體可能來自推測的崗山東寺院。的確，考慮到崗山的地形和刻石的次第順序，刻經的僧侶應該來自此山東側的一所寺院。
                                雖然晚照寺距崗山刻經也很近，卻遠在崗山B號刻經最後一段之外的西北一側，刻經很可能不是該寺僧人所為。</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>賴非</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>相關人物</head>
                        <p>崗山刻經僅有一則題記。雞嘴石北側刻有題名“二郎，比丘惠暉；比丘尼法會；比丘道成、僧岸、唐章。像主朝思和，韋傳竹妃”（崗山E號；<ptr target="GS_r_D-E_part_DSC3092.jpg"/>），<note>朝思和大概特意選用了這位有德且虔誠的王后韋提希的故事。朝氏極有可能擁有充分資源，因而躋身於眾多為中國佛教遺跡作出貢獻的女性信眾之列。</note>以及紀年“大象二年七月三日”（580年7月29日）、“石經”二字和三個佛名“釋迦文佛”、“弥勒尊佛”、“阿弥阤佛”（崗山D1號；<ptr target="GS_r_D-E_part_DSC3028.jpg"/>）。紀年和題名“比丘道成”刻在並排的兩行，必須連讀。“僧岸”和“唐章”字稍小。此外，一個小型圓龕中有一尊浮雕佛像。</p>
                        <p>《入楞伽經》經首序文大字本和小字本和《佛說觀無量壽佛經》的書風與布局有所不同。因而可以推斷崗山刻經由兩個或兩個以上僧人團體完成。但這些團體與以僧安道壹（活動於562－579年）為首、更為活躍的團體似乎並無關聯。另外，現存僧安道壹團體的諸多題記所見僧人和在家居士的名字與崗山題名也無重合。雞嘴石北側刻有比丘、比丘尼和在家居士的名字，《佛說觀無量壽佛經》的刊刻應與他們有關。他們代表一個佛教團體：比丘、比丘尼和男、女居士（優婆塞和優婆夷）。</p>
                        <p>崗山題記表明，僧人與在家居士聯手參與刻經。題記很短，無法與附近的鐵山“石頌”和稍遠處尖山題記中提到的匡氏和韋氏的譜系相提並論。然而崗山清楚地顯示出北朝時期佛教傳播到了社會的各個階層，上至皇室，下至庶民。與僧安道壹受到匡氏和韋氏家族的資助相比，崗山刻經體現了僧俗信眾的成就和思想。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>張總</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="GS_r_B18_total_G7S93302.jpg">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">崗山B18號刻經《入楞伽經》節文隱現的刻字；2005年拍攝</head>
                            <head>Half-hidden character of the segmented text passage GS B18 from
                                the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Sutra of Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                                    </hi>
                                </title>; photograph
                                taken in 2005</head>
                            <graphic url="GS_r_B18_total_G7S93302.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>斷代</head>
                        <p>崗山上唯一的紀年見於雞嘴石北側：“大象二年七月三日”（580年7月29日）。然而崗山A至E號這五段刻銘內容、格式和書法風格各異，不可能在同一時間總體規劃刻成。儘管相對年代尚無法確定，但可以根據地形和書法作出推斷。</p>
                        <p>《入楞伽經》小字本的五處節文只佔據了狹小的區域。雞嘴石上方的兩面崖壁和西側的兩塊巨石位於《入楞伽經》大字本刻石所標示的更廣大的區域之內（地圖，<ptr target="Gangshan_Karte.jpg"/>）。有理由認為先有較為短小的小字本，繼而為篇幅更長、鑿刻更精緻的版本，而非相反。遵循同樣的推理邏輯，似乎單體的雞嘴石刻文早於《入楞伽經》小字本。這塊岩石兀然挺立，是絕佳的書丹上石之處。較早的山東摩崖刻經，例如嶧山（564）、徂徠山（570）或者毗鄰的鐵山（579）也是如此，刻經石面引人注目，遠處即可望見。</p>
                        <p>雞嘴石及其鄰近刻石上的佛名可能刻成於同時或稍晚。根據這一推定的內容，按時間順序，一個神聖空間漸次由中心循序往外拓展。雞嘴石首當其衝，繼而擴展為一個由《入楞伽經》經首序文小字本所在的神聖區域，隨後為《入楞伽經》經首序文大字本所覆蓋的更大區域。<note>針對相對年代且基於風格分析所作的更進一步的討論，見下文第<ptr type="infra" target="style_zh style_end_zh"/>頁。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>現在的問題是，如何將580年7月29日這一可靠的日期置入當時的事件中。三年前的577年，疆域包括今山東省在內的北齊降服於西邊的鄰居北周。574年6月21日，周武帝（559－578年在位）發起滅佛運動。武帝薨於578年6月21日，他的兒子繼位，宣帝（578－579年在位）隨即糾正最嚴厲的滅佛措施，轉而崇佛。假如以上相對年代推定無誤，崗山刻經則宣告了一個佛教凱旋的嶄新時期的到來。<note>關於滅佛運動，見《中國佛教石經·山東省》第一卷<ref type="biblio" target="Shandong_1">第6－7頁</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>雷德侯</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>研究史</head>
                        <p>18世紀晚期，金石學家開始關注崗山刻經。早期注重踏訪實地的金石學家黃易（1744－1802）在其《岱麓訪碑圖》（作於1797年；<ptr target="Huang_Yi_Gangshan.jpg"/>）中描繪此山。<note>《蓬萊宿約》<ref type="biblio" target="Penglaisuyue2010">第191頁</ref>。參見本卷“導論”
                                和下文的“討論”
                            部分。</note>此圖題跋記述穿行於狼溝巨石之間的艱辛路途。他提及紀年580年和一位供養人的名字，並說明刻字或為隸書，或作楷體。</p>
                        <p>阮元（1764－1849）刊行於1797年的《山左金石志》首次更為詳盡地記載崗山刻經，蓽路藍縷，開一時之光。此書崗山條目起首將整座山的刻經斷代為580年，隨後提及雞嘴石三處刻經，但未全文著錄，也沒有確定佛經名稱。關於《入楞伽經》，他只提到了兩段節文，即崗山B7號和崗山B30號。他著錄了崗山B7號九個字中的八個，但讀法順序有誤；崗山B30號則只錄起始四字，不過註明巨石的尺寸，以及位置在崗山後方。阮元熱衷區分書體，他將雞嘴石刻石均歸為八分書，崗山B30號刻石為正書，而崗山B7號刻石則“書兼篆隸”。<note>《山左金石志》<ref type="biblio" target="Shanzuojinshizhi">第14486a頁</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>段松苓（1745－1800）《山左碑目》前有清嘉慶元年（1796）自序，但直到清宣統元年（1908）才整理刊刻。此書只沿襲阮元之見。<note>《山左碑目》<ref type="biblio" target="Shanzuobeimu">第14844a頁</ref>。 </note>
                        </p>
                        <p>曾與阮元共事的孫星衍（1753－1818）自編石刻目錄《寰宇訪碑錄》（清嘉慶七年［1802］序刻本），其中記崗山的四段刻經，書體為正書，並註明其紀年。<note>《寰宇訪碑錄》<ref type="biblio" target="Huanyufangbeilu">第19873b頁</ref>。</note>但這些信息並未出阮元所言之外。</p>
                        <p>清道光十四年（1834），董純修、馬星翼纂的《鄒縣志稿》提及崗山五處刻石，即崗山B28號、崗山B29號、崗山B31.2號，以及均刻有“菩薩自在”的崗山B28號和崗山A5號。該書作者未覺察兩件刻石實為同一篇刻經段落，即崗山B28號刻經。另外，此書誤以為崗山未見紀年和題名。<note>《鄒縣志稿》<ref type="biblio" target="Zouxianzhigao">第469頁</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>數十年後，李佐賢（1807－1876）在《石泉書屋金石題跋》中作出更加全面詳盡的紀錄。他列舉了崗山十三段刻經，其中十段是《入楞伽經》經首序文小字本和大字本。李氏完整地抄錄了其中五段刻經，但沒有認識到兩個版本之間的區別，而混為一組。</p>
                        <p>不過，李佐賢是第一位以正確的閱讀順序記錄刻經的學者，糾正了阮元此處之誤。他亦記錄刻石的相對位置，但未理解刻經段落的整體順序。李佐賢還提到十六個他認為未完成的零散刻字。<note xml:id="LiZuoxian11_zh">李佐賢的第一至三段對應雞嘴石刻經（崗山E和D1號，以及C1和C2號）。他的第四段對應崗山A5號，部分抄錄。他的第五段對應崗山B24號，抄錄完整。他的第六段對應崗山B31.2號，抄錄完整。他的第七段對應崗山A3號，部分抄錄。他的第八段對應崗山B7號，抄錄完整。與阮元不同的是，他從左至右逐行閱讀，並且明確提到了這一點。他的第九段對應崗山A4號，抄錄完整。但出人意料的是，他沒有記錄同一石上的崗山A3號。他的第十段對應崗山B30號，部分抄錄。他的第十一段對應崗山B25號，部分抄錄。李佐賢記行格作四行八字，但沒有意識到右邊尚有一部分磨蝕的刻銘，原先為八個字，其中三字至今仍可辨認。這說明李佐賢未親自踏訪刻經處。他的第十二段對應崗山B26號，抄錄完整。之後是六個散落的字，李氏稱之為“不成段之殘字”，這六字可能是吳式芬所記刻於六塊岩石上的單字。他的第十三段對應崗山B28號，部分抄錄。之後是十個散落不成段的字，一如吳式芬所記，對應於成對刻在五塊岩石上的字。李佐賢在按語中感慨“鄒縣古刻，各著錄家罕有錄其文者。惟《山左金石志》收錄，而又多挂漏。”見《石泉書屋金石題跋》<ref type="biblio" target="SQSW">第14195b－14196a頁</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>吳式芬（1796－1856）《金石彙目分編》一書的著錄同樣精準。他列舉了大字本和小字本刻經節文，凡24種。他當時尚可見到今已佚失的崗山B6號刻石和崗山B17號刻石的一部分。<note>《金石彙目分編》<ref type="biblio" target="Jinshihuimufenbian">第21153頁</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>汪鋆（1816－1884－）的《十二硯齋金石過眼錄》前有清同治十三年（1875）自序。他僅著錄了崗山B30號刻經，並稱：“孫星衍《寰宇訪碑錄》載岡山刻經四種，此刻何属，不能肊定。”<note>《十二硯齋金石過眼錄》<ref type="biblio" target="Shieryanzhaijinshiguoyanlu">第7856b頁</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>繆荃孫（1844－1919）的《藝風堂金石文字目》前有清光緒二十四年（1898）自序，刊行於光緒三十二年（1906）。他列出五段刻經：三段小字本（崗山A4、A3和A5號），一段大字本（崗山B30號）和一段所謂“佛經二十一行”。<note>《藝風堂金石文字目》<ref type="biblio" target="Yifengtangjinshiwenzimu">第19552b頁</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>陸增祥（1833－1889）《八瓊室金石補正》廣為人知，有民國十四年（1925）刻本。此書崗山條目先記雞嘴石刻銘，完整轉錄題名和紀年（崗山E號），以及三個佛名（崗山D1號）。他摘錄了崗山C1和C2號這兩段佛經節文，依舊沒有確定是哪一部佛經。他摘錄了《入楞伽經》小字本的兩段經文（即崗山A4和A5號）和大字本的十段經文。<note>這些節文順序如下：崗山B30號，崗山B25號（缺第一部分），崗山B26號，崗山B24號，崗山B18號（“重”），崗山B17號（僅“俱”字），崗山B16號和崗山B27號（“種”）。此外，陸增祥還列出了“常”和“間”兩個單字。“俱”字原本是崗山B17號的一部分，惜已佚失。刻有“間”字的刻石（本為崗山B6號的一部分）同樣如此，不過北京中國國家圖書館保存了帶有此字的一張拓片。另一字陸氏錄為“常”，字徑一尺，可能是對“岩”字（崗山B19號）的誤讀，此字高30釐米。<!--倒過來看時，“岩”字與“常”字彷彿，特別是“山”的第一筆很長，容易誤作“常”字的最後一筆。--></note>他提到阮元《山左金石志》僅著錄了上述一處刻經段落，即崗山A5號，依據拓片題簽，阮元推測所參考的拓片應當出自崗山，並稱“俟再訪詢”。<note>《八瓊室金石補正》<ref type="biblio" target="Baqiongshijinshibuzheng">第4364b－4365b頁</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>時任山東地方官的孫葆田（1840－1911）所提供的信息量前所未有。他出版於1911年的《山東金石志》，收錄了存世的27處《入楞伽經》大字本刻經節文中的13處，並逐一對之全文轉錄。除崗山B29號之外，這些刻經段落均在東邊的山谷中。此外，他還記錄了今已失佚的五個刻字。它們構成了崗山B6號刻經段落的一部分。刻本依原石行格上版。他撰寫的崗山條目從B28號刻經段落入手，並以此刻石為基準描述其他刻石的位置，尤其是與雞嘴石和崗山B7號刻經巨石的關係。由於未考訂經文內容，所以孫葆田不了解釋讀這些刻石所應採用的順序。他已經注意到崗山A5號的刻字比其他刻經段落的小，但沒有意識到崗山刻有同一種刻經的兩個版本。他著錄的刻經段落中有五個字今已不詳。<note>孫葆田著錄刻石按如下順序：崗山B28號，B25號，B24號，B30號，A3號，D3號，A5號，A4號，B31.2號，B26號，“聞”字（或許是對已失佚的B6號刻經中“閒”字的誤讀。此刻又如上所述，僅存拓本，藏北京中國國家圖書館），崗山B27號，B7號，B29號，“成”字（此字曾在B6和B20號刻經，二石均失），崗山B23號，B31.1號，D2號（僅一個佛名），“光共明”三字，“一諾”二字（或許是對崗山B10號“一時”二字的誤讀）。見《山東金石志》<ref type="biblio" target="Shandongjinshizhi">第9248a－9251b頁</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>法偉堂（1843－1907）的《山左訪碑錄》刊刻於清宣統元年（1909年），同樣只是引用阮元《山左金石志》。<note>《山左訪碑錄》<ref type="biblio" target="Shanzuofangbeilu">第9089a頁</ref>。</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>綜上所述，可以對金石學家的相關研究做大致的梳理。阮元確立了寫作標準，他撰寫的條目先記紀年，並著錄行格、尺寸，判定書體。後來的作者無不熟知他的著作並遵循他的著錄體例，有的僅從其說，有的增補其書，轉錄更多刻銘，更加關注刻石的空間關係。
                                    但是，所有的金石學家均未辨別經文內容，並不了解刻石的正確順序。最早確定刻經經名的是道端良秀。此後，20世紀的很長一段時間未取得更多的學術進展。1991年，山東省石刻藝術博物館前館長王思禮和訓練有素的考古學者賴非率先完成了全部崗山刻經的轉錄工作，<note>王思禮和賴非<ref type="biblio" target="Wang_Lai1991b">第445－454頁</ref>。</note>隨後在1997年、<note>見安廷山 <ref type="biblio" target="AnTingshan1997">第51頁</ref>。</note>2000年<note>見賴非<ref type="biblio" target="LaiFei2000a">圖版見第226－234頁，錄文見第301－303頁</ref>。</note>和2007年<note>見賴非<ref type="biblio" target="LaiFei2007">第127－144頁</ref>。</note>陸續發佈了更多有關崗山刻經的研究成果。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>張總<space n="2"/>雷德侯</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>刻銘</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>銘文總數</head>
                        <p>崗山刻有六個佛名（崗山D號），三段佛經節文（崗山A號、崗山B號、崗山C號）和一則題記（崗山E號）。</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>佛名</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>崗山D1至崗山D4號</head>
                            <p>雞嘴石北側有三個重要的佛名：釋迦文佛（釋迦牟尼較不常見的一種譯名）、弥勒尊佛、阿弥阤佛（崗山D1.1號、崗山D1.2號、崗山D1.3號）。最後一個佛名又見於附近一塊較小的岩石（崗山D3號）上。
                                    釋迦文佛乃現在賢劫之佛，其後是未來佛<?cb?>彌勒佛，他將在遙遠的未來降臨於世並成佛。在此對彌勒佛的稱謂選用的是“當來彌勒尊佛”或“當來下生彌勒尊佛”的縮寫。彌勒佛的這些稱謂幾乎僅見於懺悔儀式中。<note>出現上述三個稱呼的儀式文本中最為人所知者是《受菩薩戒儀》（R，第105冊:
                                        第1－9頁），傳統認為由慧思（515－577）所作。不過，梅弘理（<ref type="biblio" target="Magnin1979">第117－128頁</ref>）找到充足的證據，駁斥了9至10世紀的日本目錄中宣稱慧思為作者的斷言。</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>不同於世間的釋迦牟尼和彌勒尊佛，阿彌陀佛可謂超脫之佛，他不論過去還是現在都居於遙不可測的西方淨土內。刻於雞嘴石北側的這一佛名統攝著該石東側和南側所刻的《觀無量壽佛經》。<note>《觀無量壽佛經》T#365,
                                    12:
                                340c29－341a10。</note>此經中釋迦牟尼佛教導韋提希王后，如何觀想西方的阿彌陀佛淨土。因此，刻鑿於雞嘴石的這三個佛名將過去和未來的世界編織在一起，經過無數的佛國，直至永恆的西方樂土。</p>
                            <p>雞嘴石旁的另一巨石上刻有“大空王佛”（崗山D2號）。此佛名不見於任何一部佛經，但在山東數座山上都有刊刻。<note>對此佛名的討論參見《中國佛教石經·山東省》第一卷<ref type="biblio" target="Shandong_1">第60－63頁</ref>。</note>崗山D4.1號的“大”字有可能是另一個“大空王佛”的第一個字。崗山D4.2號的第二行看來並不指任何特定的佛，而僅僅讀作“一切佛”。這一名字表明崗山的佛名反映了普遍的大乘信仰。</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>溫狄婭</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>佛經</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>崗山A1至崗山A5號；崗山B1至崗山B31.2號</head>
                            <div>
                                <p>刻在崗山的主要的佛經節文出自菩提留支<note>北印度僧人菩提留支（亦稱菩提流支；活動於508－535年。他與唐代僧人菩提留支同名）活動於北魏時期的洛陽，是6世紀最重要的譯經者之一。他的譯作包括《金剛般若經》（T#236）、《無量壽經論》（T#1524）和《十地經論》（T#1522）。《無量壽經論》極大影響了中國淨土宗，而《十地經論》對於中國北方十地師論學派的形成至關重要。</note>譯的《入楞伽經》經首序文，<note>《入楞伽經》T#671,
                                        16: 514c7－18。</note>這篇序文在崗山被刻了兩次。</p>
                                <p>《入楞伽經》在中古時期有三個漢文譯本。<note>眾所周知，《歷代三寶紀》多有不可靠之處，其中提到了一個已經佚失的早期譯本，四卷本，曇無讖（385－433）所譯（T#2034,
                                        48: 84b7）。可信的《開元釋教錄》（T#2154, 55:
                                        629b11）也將之列出，但只列在歷史部分，稱其為《楞伽經》四卷。鑑於這一譯本未在僧祐（445－518）所著的更早的目錄《出三藏記集》中列出，有理由懷疑它是否存在過。</note>現存最早的譯本是四卷的《楞伽阿跋多羅寶經》，<note>《楞伽阿跋多羅寶經》T#670,
                                        16:
                                        479a－514b。</note>譯者為求那跋陀羅（394－468）。他的譯本受到早期禪宗大師的推崇，認為該譯本是菩提達摩傳給其弟子慧可（約485－574以後）的佛經，是合於此傳承的唯一經文。菩提留支部分參考了求那跋陀羅的譯本，翻譯了《入楞伽經》十卷。<note>《入楞伽經》T#671,
                                        16:
                                        514c－586b。</note>最後一個譯本為實叉難陀（652－710）的《大乘入楞伽經》七卷本。<note>《大乘入楞伽經》T#672,
                                        16: 587a－640c。</note>
                                </p>
                                <p>這三個譯本中的經首序文差別甚大。菩提留支的經首序文是最詳盡複雜的一個。他不僅描述了說法地點和與會者，還在菩薩和比丘的會眾中增加了“古昔諸仙、賢、聖”，處於“重巖屈曲，處處皆有仙堂、靈室、堪窟”中。這種描寫給菩提留支的經首序文增加了濃郁的中國韻味，尤其是展現了一個理想化的天堂景象：花園香樹，微風吹拂，妙音繚繞。</p>
                                <p>這一精緻的景象描述不見於《入楞伽經》的另兩個譯本。在求那跋陀羅的經首序文中，僅簡略地提及講經之山：</p>
                                <quote>如是我聞：一時佛住南海濱楞伽山頂，種種寶華以為莊嚴，與大比丘僧及大菩薩眾，俱從彼種種異佛剎來……<note>《入楞伽經》T#670,
                                        16: 480a17－19。</note>
                                </quote>
                                <p>求那跋陀羅對山的簡短描述“種種寶華以為莊嚴”，似乎是菩提留支大幅擴充的譯文本的基點。更晚的實叉難陀譯本則完全沒有對山加以刻畫：</p>
                                <quote>如是我聞：一時佛住大海濱摩羅耶山頂楞伽城中，與大比丘眾及大菩薩眾俱。<note>《大乘入楞伽經》T#672, 16:
                                        587b15－16。</note>
                                </quote>
                                <p>如此，菩提留支譯文中對楞伽城摩羅耶山極樂性質的描述實際上是一段衍文，後來被實叉難陀加以修訂和刪除。因而，菩提留支譯本中疑為衍文的段落始於“彼山種種寶性所成”，終於“古昔諸仙賢聖思如實法得道之處”。<note>《入楞伽經》T#671,
                                        16:
                                        514c9－15。</note>菩提留支的譯文以“如是我聞：一時婆伽婆住大海畔摩羅耶山頂上楞伽城中”開篇，比照實叉難陀的版本，後接“與大比丘僧及大菩薩眾……”<note>《入楞伽經》T#671,
                                        16: 514c7－8和514c15。在研討小組的討論中，葛利尹（<foreign xml:lang="en">Eric
                                            Greene</foreign>）指出了這一處衍文。</note>將會更加自然。書丹者在崗山A5號“與”字前（<ptr target="GS_A5.jpg"/>）和崗山B25號該字後（<ptr target="GS_B25.jpg"/>）所留的空可能表明，他們知道這是一處衍文。抑或，崗山B25號中的空白也可能是為了對“大比丘僧”及後面的“大菩薩”表示敬意而留。</p>
                                <p>這段衍文分佈在崗山上沿途的岩塊巨石之上，從原來靠近狼溝底部而今佚失的崗山B4號延伸至靠近西部高地中央的崗山B25號。因而這段經文的大部分刻在廣闊區域內的諸多石塊上，這包含著一個理想化、神聖化的中國場景描述，這個景象令人聯想起漢譯淨土經文中的表述，例如長、短篇版《無量壽經》。</p>
                                <p>這段衍文後，經文接著讚美了前來集會的菩薩摩訶薩埵的成就。三個現存的譯本的措辭再次有所不同，但這次的差異不是在內容，內容描述的都是菩薩引導和轉化眾生的非凡能力。一如大字本崗山B30號和崗山B31.2號中所描述的，他們掌握了“五法、［三］自性、［八］識、二種無我”，這對經文本身的內容作了一個預先的展示。</p>
                                <ab>
                                    <abbr>柏剛<space n="2"/>溫狄婭</abbr>
                                    <p/>
                                </ab>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <p>
                                    <anchor xml:id="consciousnesses_zh"/>崗山B30號刻經節文刻於倒數第二塊大石上，它證實了“識”字的釋讀，該字並不見於該經的所有版本。《中華大藏經》在《金藏》的基礎上複製了菩提留支的譯本，包含有此字，但註明《高麗大藏經》再雕版中無此字。<note>《入楞伽經》ZH#169,
                                        17:
                                        630c1－2。</note>的確，在以《高麗大藏經》再雕版為基礎的《大正新脩大藏經》中不含此字。不過《大正新脩大藏經》的腳註中提到了另外三個含該字的《大藏經》版本。<note>《入楞伽經》T#671,
                                        16: 514, 註15。</note>
                                </p>
                                <p>“識”字的釋讀無疑是正確的，因為它是該經枚舉的五法、自性、諸識、二無我的一部分，對於整個經文段落的理解至關重要。求那跋陀羅和實叉難陀的漢譯本也含有此字。<note>求那跋陀羅譯本作：“於五法、自性、識、二種無我，究竟通達。”<space/>T#670,
                                        16: 23－24。實叉難陀譯本作：“其諸菩薩摩訶薩，悉已通達五法、三性、諸識、無我。”<space/>T#672,
                                        16: 17－18。</note>
                                </p>
                                <p>實叉難陀其譯文甚至提到“諸識”。這個複數的“識”在實叉難陀的註疏者、唐代學僧法藏（643－712）<note>《入楞伽心玄義》T#1790,
                                        39: 425c25－27。</note>和宋代的寶臣（生卒年不詳）<note>《注大乘入楞伽經》T#1791, 39:
                                        435a28－b1。</note>看來，<?cbraw?>等同於“八識”。寶臣還進一步解釋五法、自性、諸識、二無我這四個術語即“四妙門”。菩提留支譯本<note>《入楞伽經》T#671,
                                        16:
                                        559b22－25。</note>完整列舉了“八識”。明代兩位註疏者蒐集了全部三種《入楞伽經》漢譯本，將“自性”解為“三自性”，將“識”釋作“八識”，並將之全部列出。<note>《楞伽阿跋多羅寶經參訂疏》X#332,
                                        18: 5a4－6。《楞伽阿跋多羅寶法經精解評林》X#333, 18:
                                        68b22－25。</note>“八識”學說十分重要，因為它後來成為東亞佛教中早期瑜伽行派的基本教義之一。<anchor xml:id="consciousnesses_end_zh"/>
                                </p>
                                <p>不僅如此，《入楞伽經》還和傳為真諦（499－569）所譯但極有可能是在中國編造而成的《大乘起信論》，<note>《大乘起信論》T#1666,
                                        32: 575a－583b。</note>一起促進了中國大乘佛教如來藏思想的形成。</p>
                                <ab>
                                    <abbr>溫狄婭</abbr>
                                </ab>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>崗山C1至崗山C2號</head>
                            <p>崗山上刻的第二段佛經節文是《觀無量壽佛經》<note>《觀無量壽佛經》T#365, 12:
                                        340c29－341a10。</note>的經首序文，此經據稱由中亞僧人畺良耶舍（383?－442?）於424年譯就。經文講述了頻婆娑羅王的故事，他被自己的逆子阿闍世囚禁，因王后韋提希的忠貞不渝方得苟活。從此，他求佛陀庇護，受持八戒。所刻經文於此結束。這段經文陳述了大逆不道、琴瑟調和、自我犧牲，以及對佛教義理的篤信，是交代佛說《觀無量壽佛經》緣起的一部分。在此經中，應王后韋提希之請，佛陀開示十六種觀想，以使人得以往生無量壽佛所居的西方淨土。《觀無量壽佛經》在中國影響巨大，是淨土宗的主要經典之一。崗山選刻的節文強調俗人居家授戒的修行，<note>如今的淨土宗儀式中，俗人先發菩薩願，然後再進行阿彌陀佛淨土觀想修行仍很普遍，見周文廣<ref type="biblio" target="Jones2004"/>。</note>
                                該刻經可能針對在家信衆宣講，以鼓勵其支持該地區的佛教信仰。</p>
                            <p>歸於譯者畺良耶舍的譯經還有《觀藥王藥上二菩薩經》。<note>《觀藥王藥上二菩薩經》T#1161, 20:
                                    660c－666b。</note>據慧皎（497－554）於519至553年間編撰的《高僧傳》，畺良耶舍是著名的觀想大師。<note>《高僧傳》T#2059,
                                    50:
                                        343c－344a。</note>他口述譯經，中國僧人筆錄。一如漢文佛經中常見的，《觀無量壽佛經》四字一句，中國讀者無疑樂於接受這一文體。<note>船山徹對佛教經文漢譯時所用的策略作了分析，見船山徹<ref type="biblio" target="Funayama2013">第196頁</ref>。</note>
                            </p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>柏剛</abbr>
                            </ab>
                            <p/>
                            <p>道端良秀將崗山上所選擇的兩部佛經稱為一個不同尋常的組合，不過在他看來，這是由於一個特殊的歷史境況造成。<note>道端良秀<ref type="biblio" target="Michihata1972">第19－28頁</ref>。</note>他認為《觀無量壽佛經》中的國王被他的兒子投入牢獄等死，其命運指的是在北周滅佛期間佛教遭受的威脅。而王后在這一毀滅性的災難中開啓了一條出路，她將丈夫救出監牢，使兒子皈依佛教，並喚出阿彌陀佛淨土的種種景象。而《入楞伽經》則以佛陀和來自他方佛土的菩薩們的絕妙集會轉化了崗山，使之成為歷經滅佛之後，正法再次得以傳承的處所。</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>雷德侯</abbr>
                            </ab>
                            <p>《觀無量壽佛經》無梵文本和藏文本傳世，此經很可能作於中亞或中國本土。《觀無量壽佛經》屬於觀想類佛經，這類經典反映了“觀”（冥想）在5世紀上半葉逐漸流行。然而崗山所刻節文隻字未提觀想，而是佛陀向王后韋提希諭示十六觀卷端的一部分。</p>
                            <p>此經首序文在雞嘴石書丹上石之時，《觀無量壽佛經》仍鮮為人知。後世被奉為淨土宗宗師之一的曇鸞（476－542）是率先系統性探討此經的學僧之一，他的《無量壽經優婆提舍願生偈註》<note>《無量壽經優婆提舍願生偈註》T#1819,
                                    40:
                                    826a－844b。</note>是對世親的《無量壽經優波提舍願生偈》<note>《無量壽經優波提舍願生偈》T#1524,
                                    26:
                                230c－233a。</note>所作的註疏。世親的這一文本通常稱《往生論》。曇鸞奠定了念誦阿彌陀佛名號而得救渡的信仰。</p>
                            <p>對這部佛經更深入的學理探討始於淨影慧遠（523－592）為此經所撰的《觀無量壽經義疏》。<note>《觀無量壽經義疏》T#1749,
                                    37:
                                173a－186b。</note>此經的其他眾多註疏本隨後陸續完成，均出自當時的飽學僧人。《觀無量壽佛經》後來被尊為“三經一論”之一，日本淨土宗的教義即依據於此經論。</p>
                            <p>不同於《入楞伽經》經首序文節文，崗山刻經中的《觀無量壽佛經》經首序文與木刻雕版印刷的傳世版本幾乎完全一致。僅一字有異，但在此於義無礙。</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>溫狄婭</abbr>
                            </ab>
                            <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="Gangshan_Ost_Cliff_Übersicht.jpg">
                                <head xml:lang="zh">崗山，狼溝；2002年拍攝</head>
                                <head>Mount Gang, Wolf Gorge; photograph taken in 2002</head>
                                <graphic url="Shandong_Band_2/Gangshan_Ost_Cliff_Übersicht.jpg" height="120mm"/>
                            </figure>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>歷史題記</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>崗山E號</head>
                            <p>雞嘴石北側有一則供養人題記。前六個名字中有三位比丘，一位比丘尼，兩名俗人信衆，這些名字應該與“大象二年七月三日”（580年7月29日）紀年有關聯。後兩個名字可能與內有坐佛的圓形像龕直接相關，因為相鄰的這兩位供養人中的一位冠有“像主”的稱謂。這個觀想佛像浮雕是整座山上唯一的圖像元素，它左邊的“石經”二字可能是後來作為一種註明添加的。“石經”二字同樣也見於崗山B8號刻經第一行下方。</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>溫狄婭</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>刊刻技法</head>
                        <p>崗山刻經採用的刻法與山東其他刻經址的刊刻技法沒有區別。從筆道橫斷面分析，可分四種刻法：一、“U”形刻法；二、“V”形刻法；三、“雙鈎”刻法；四、“凵”形刻法。詳情參見鐵山部分的相關描述。 </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>賴非</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>書體</head>
                        <p>
                            <anchor xml:id="style_zh"/>崗山刻經為楷書。《入楞伽經》大字本出自一人之手，而《入楞伽經》小字本、《觀無量壽佛經》及題記由其他若干書家書丹。《入楞伽經》大字本用筆的起、收、轉、折皆以方筆，有些字結體或方或縱，上疏下密。每個字都個性鮮明，風格獨特別具，甚至帶有詼諧感。《入楞伽經》小字本、《觀無量壽佛經》及題記用筆方圓兼施，略顯生硬，結體或密或疏，率性而為，但個性不定。</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>賴非</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <p/>
                        <p>崗山上刊刻的《入楞伽經》有小字本和大字本之分，其書法特徵有助於推斷其間年代先後。小字本無界格、無紋飾，諸如崗山A2號（<ptr target="GS_A2.jpg"/>）、崗山A3號（<ptr target="GS_A3.jpg"/>）、崗山A5號（<ptr target="GS_A5.jpg"/>）。大字本刻字置雙線界格之內，有的在上邊框的外側還飾以花紋，崗山B27號（<ptr target="GS_B27_rba_d017295.jpg"/>）、崗山B30號（<ptr target="GS_B30_rba_d017312.jpg"/>），以及巨石上的崗山B28號刻經（<ptr target="GS_r_B28_part_DSC2978.JPG"/>；<ptr target="GS_B28_rba_d017307.jpg"/>）便是如此。對照崗山A5號與崗山B28號刻經，其經文多有相同之處，而大字本的筆畫更明晰，結體更精緻，其刻字之用心和製作之複雜，無不表明年代較小字本晚。</p>
                        <p>從地形上來看，相對於雞嘴石刻經《佛說觀無量壽佛經》的書法，上述相對年代乍看上去有些抵牾。漢唐數百年間，由隸而楷漸次演變，路徑不一，推動了書法的進展。這兩種字體的字結體有異，即筆畫的數量和位置不同。它們在結構的均衡和運筆上也有差別。6世紀時，楷書尚處發展階段，直到唐代初期才臻完善。<note>多位學者闡明了這幾個世紀中書體轉變的各個層面。
                                    其中包括盧慧紋鉅細靡遺的研究（<ref type="biblio" target="Lu2003"/>），她在對洛陽北魏石刻的探討中綜合了政治和風格的分析。 倪雅梅（<ref type="biblio" target="McNair2012"/>）考察了中央和地方之間引人入勝的交流。還可參見韓文彬（<ref type="biblio" target="Harrist2008"/>）多處精準到位的描述。 </note>
                        </p>
                        <p>藉由上述書法史背景，《觀無量壽佛經》（崗山C1號；<ptr target="GS_r_C1_part_G7S92048.JPG"/>；<ptr target="GS_C1.jpg"/>；<ptr target="GS_r_C2_total_Ar11.jpg"/>；<ptr target="GS_C2.jpg"/>）以及佛名和題記（崗山D號和崗山E號；<ptr target="GS_r_D-E_part_DSC3092.jpg"/>）較之《入楞伽經》大字本似乎有所進步。《入楞伽經》大字本保留了舊有的用筆特徵。舉諸崗山B7號刻經段落，“照”字左偏旁寫作圓圈中間加一點（<ptr target="GS_B7_rba_d017310.jpg"/>；<ptr target="GS_B7_rba_d017310.jpg"/>，第二行第三字）；而崗山C號至崗山E號未見這種古樸的寫法。阮元歸類此段佛經“書兼篆隸”，或許起因於此。崗山B1號“羅”字的偏旁“糸”寫作兩個疊加的三角形，這正是隸書特有的寫法（<ptr target="GS_B1.jpg"/>，第六行第一字）。就書寫風格而言，《入楞伽經》大字本趨於保守，有隸書筆意。譬如崗山B1號和崗山B25號（<ptr target="GS_B1.jpg"/>；<ptr target="GS_B25.jpg"/>），字形多呈扁方。崗山B7號刻經中“山”字的兩個短豎畫向外斜出（<ptr target="GS_r_B7_total.jpg"/>，第三行第三字），同樣的例子見於崗山B1號（<ptr target="GS_B1.jpg"/>，第六行第三字），字的結體因此略顯扁方，深思熟慮。雞嘴石刻經《觀無量壽佛經》則未採用這樣的處理方法，“山”字的筆畫短而直（<ptr target="GS_C1.jpg"/>，第一行第十五字）。</p>
                        <p>《觀無量壽佛經》刻字有楷書的特徵，每字在方形界格之內；捺畫不像《入楞伽經》大字本有意拉長。《入楞伽經》大字本的書丹者偏好渾圓的小點，有時遊戲且有效地帶有尖鋒，諸如“菩”字（崗山B28號；<ptr target="GS_B28_rba_d017307.jpg"/>，第四行第二字）、“竟”字（崗山B31.2號；<ptr target="GS_B31.2_rba_d017309.jpg"/>，第三行第二字）。他的書法結體巧妙而大膽，“楞伽”二字堪為範例（崗山B2號；<ptr target="GS_B2.jpg"/>），不愧為用筆大師。</p>
                        <p>不過，《入楞伽經》小字本和大字本刻字偏於守舊的書風並不表明其年代更早，或許只是出於擬古而已。刻經所採用的古老書風，尤其是大字本用筆之複雜極有可能是有意為之，用以顯示莊嚴之感。山東省境內有大字摩崖刻經的洪頂山（564）、鐵山（579）和葛山（580）刻銘中已有使用隸書先例，此書體在當時是一種古風的體現。</p>
                        <p>古今學者可能都囿於阮元的舊說，把崗山所存的一個紀年加諸整座山的銘刻，因而從未具體地探討斷代的問題，而是傾向於將包括《入楞伽經》小字本和大字本在內的所有刻經，都定為580年。不過，不同的銘文之間看來存在著時間上的先後順序，書法分析也支持上文基於地理位置所得出的相對年代次序。因此，年代順序應該是這樣的：狼溝盡頭顯著的雞嘴石上的刻經最早，是580年小字刊刻的《佛說觀無量壽佛經》。同時或稍後在其附近加刻了佛名。其後不久，在三塊岩石上刊刻了《入楞伽經》小字本，書風較前者更保守。最後是《入楞伽經》大字本，字體古風洋溢，遍及全山，雄心可鑒。</p>
                        <p>崗山刻經不僅非同時所為，而且應當出自信奉不同教義的僧團。刊刻《觀無量壽佛經》者信從淨土教義。雞嘴石北面上的“阿彌陀佛”與“釋迦牟尼佛”相互毗鄰，這或許可以視為信仰重心從釋迦牟尼向阿彌陀佛的轉移，這一點已見於6世紀的佛教。<note>見塚本善隆<ref type="biblio" target="Tsukamoto1974_76">第2冊:
                                    第254－265頁和第436－448頁</ref>。</note>如前所述，《入楞伽經》備受原始禪宗和早期瑜伽行派的尊崇。“大空王佛”是雞嘴石附近的佛名之一，未見諸佛教經典，但在山東各地刻銘中凡十五見。“空”，是般若波羅蜜類佛經的核心概念，此類佛經節文大量見於山東其他刻經址。<note>有關討論，見《中國佛教石經·山東省》第一卷<ref type="biblio" target="Shandong_1">第60－61頁</ref>。</note>“一切佛”，此稱呼並不常見，彷彿在祈求同處崗山的不同僧團，無論協作還是競爭，應當和睦相處，眾志成城。<anchor xml:id="style_end_zh"/>
                        </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>雷德侯</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="en">
                <head>Mount Gang</head>
                <div>
                    <head>Space</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Location</head>
                        <p>Mount Gang <foreign xml:lang="zh">崗山</foreign> is unique among the sites
                            in Shandong, because three sutra passages are engraved here across
                            single stones, boulders and cliffs along a path ascending the mountain.
                            The mountain lies at the northern edge of Zoucheng City <foreign xml:lang="zh">鄒城</foreign> (map, fig. <ptr target="Zoucheng_2013_02_21e.jpg"/>), with an east-west extension of
                            1.2 km and a north-south extension of 0.7 km. The peak is at an altitude
                            of 235 m above sea level. The slope east of the peak drops into the
                            so-called Wolf Gorge (Langgou <foreign xml:lang="zh">狼溝</foreign>),
                            which is up to 85 m wide and opens toward the east. Following natural
                            erosion, the gorge has filled up with large and small boulders and
                            debris.</p>
                        <p>The foot of the mountain, at the lowest point of the gorge, is at an
                            altitude of 110 m above sea level. Geographically, the gorge is situated
                            116.969° east and 35.426° north, WGS84. This equals 497250 E (easting)
                            and 3920200 N (northing), UTM zone 50S.</p>
                        <p>The inscriptions on Mount Gang are distributed along the eastern gorge
                            and on a plateau close to the peak (map, fig. <ptr target="Gangshan_Karte.jpg"/>). As they are carved over many rocks
                            and cliffs, the inscriptions face various directions. </p>
                        <p>Not more than 1.5 km to the southwest of Mount Gang are the south-facing
                            inscriptions of Mount Tie <foreign xml:lang="zh">鐵山</foreign>. Although
                            the mountains are well within each other’s line of sight, the
                            inscriptions are not. Mount Jian <foreign xml:lang="zh">尖山</foreign> is
                            located 4.8 km to the east-northeast of Mount Gang. The inscriptions on
                            Mount Jian, which have now been destroyed, would not have been visible
                            from Mount Gang either.</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>TS</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Topography and Spatial Grouping</head>
                        <p>Five distinct groups of inscriptions were carved at Mount Gang:</p>
                        <list>
                            <item>A: The opening passage from the Bodhiruci translation of the
                                        <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Sutra of Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                                    </hi> (<hi rend="italic">
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkāvatāra-sūtra</foreign>
                                    </hi>, <hi rend="italic">Ru Lengqie
                                        jing </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">入楞伽經</foreign>)</title> in
                                small characters (GS A1–GS A5);</item>
                            <item>B: Another, longer version of the opening passage from the
                                Bodhiruci translation of the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Sutra of
                                        Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                                    </hi>
                                </title> in large characters (GS B1–GS
                                B31.2);</item>
                            <item>C: The opening passage of the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Sutra
                                        Spoken by the Buddha on the Contemplation of the Buddha of
                                        Immeasurable Life</hi>
                                </title> (<hi rend="italic">Fo shuo
                                    guan wuliangshou fo jing </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">佛說觀無量壽佛經</foreign>, GS C1–GS C2);</item>
                            <item>D: Some Buddha names (GS D1–GS D4);</item>
                            <item>E: A Colophon (GS E).</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The passage from the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Sutra of Arrival in
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                                </hi>
                            </title> is
                            engraved twice. Neither version is placed consecutively on one complete
                            surface; both are spread out over many rocks. Version B in large
                            characters is parceled out over 31 cliff walls and boulders, covering
                            much of the mountain (GS B1–GS B31.2). Version A in small characters is
                            more confined and found on five separate rock faces (GS A1–GS A5; see
                            map, fig. <ptr target="Gangshan_Karte.jpg"/>). </p>
                        <p>The devotees start their journey over the mountain in the east, at the
                            entrance to Wolf Gorge. There, the first text segment of version B (GS
                            B1) is cut onto a cliff. After reading it, they continue on to the next
                            inscribed boulder. As they wind their way through the rugged terrain,
                            clambering over random piles of rocks, the devotees pass inscriptions GS
                            B2 to GS B19. They thus ascend the entire gorge as far as Chicken Beak
                            Rock (Jizuishi <foreign xml:lang="zh">雞嘴石</foreign>), the boulder with
                            the most striking shape on the <hi rend="nh">mountain</hi>. It can be
                            seen from afar. This rock carries a number of inscriptions, including
                            the opening passage of the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the
                                    Contemplation of the Buddha of Immeasurable Life</hi>
                            </title>
                            (GS C).</p>
                        <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="_DSC2997.jpg">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">崗山A4號因山體滑坡而移動的巨石；2007年拍攝</head>
                            <head>Boulder, showing inscription GS A4, moved by a landslide;
                                photograph taken in 2007</head>
                            <graphic url="_DSC2997.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>Beyond Chicken Beak Rock, but still in the eastern area, a ridge carries
                            inscriptions GS A1 and GS A2. These are the beginning segments of the
                                <hi rend="nh">slightly</hi> shorter version A of the passage from
                            the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Sutra of Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                                </hi>
                            </title>. Then the terrain opens into a
                            rising amphitheatre, with more inscriptions, GS A3 to GS A5, and GS B21
                            to GS B31.2. The distance, as the crow flies, from the first inscription
                            in the east to the last inscription in the west, amounts to only 159.7
                            meters. Yet the winding path through difficult terrain is much longer
                            and climbs from 169 to 234 meters above sea level. The last stone of the
                            longer version of the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Sutra of Arrival in
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                                </hi>
                            </title> is close
                            to a path that goes directly to a Daoist temple. Although this temple
                            was only founded in Ming times, there may have been an earlier one on
                            the same site. Here, an irregular flight of steps leads down the
                            southern side of the mountain back to the city of Zoucheng.</p>
                        <p>The scattered segments of version B are thus divided by the topography
                            into two separate groups, one to the east of the prominent Chicken Beak
                            Rock (fig. <ptr target="GS_sc_eastern_gorge_comm.jpg"/>), and one to the
                            west (map, fig. <ptr target="Gangshan_Karte.jpg"/>). The content of the
                            engraved text is equally divided into two parts. The first part
                            describes in evocative language the entrancing scenery of Mount Malaya
                            (Moluoye Shan <foreign xml:lang="zh">摩羅耶山</foreign>) where the Buddha
                            once preached the sutra. The second part conjures up the <hi rend="nh">preaching</hi> scene itself, with a great assembly of monks as well
                            as bodhisattvas who have arrived from various other Buddha-lands of the
                            cosmos.</p>
                        <p>The southern side of Wolf Gorge, where the path along the inscriptions of
                            version B begins, is shown in figure <ptr target="Gangshan_Ost_Cliff_Übersicht.jpg"/>. Trees in the background
                            give an impression of the massive scale of the rocky cliffs. On the
                            eastern side of the initial section—the side facing the viewer—is the
                            first segment, GS B1, with the first sentence of the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Sutra of Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                                </hi>
                            </title>. It directs the reader’s
                            attention to Mount Malaya in the city of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā
                                </foreign>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">楞伽城</foreign>, by the shore of the
                            great ocean, where the Buddha once dwelt and preached. The characters
                            are encased by a double grid of thin lines. Remarkably, the text is
                            written from left to right. It follows the direction, by which the
                            reader enters the gorge.</p>
                        <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="GS_sc_jizuishi_G7S92029.jpg">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">雞嘴石；2005年拍攝</head>
                            <head>Chicken Beak Rock; photograph taken in 2005</head>
                            <graphic url="GS_sc_jizuishi_G7S92029.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>Earthquakes and landslides have shifted quite a number of boulders and
                            stones during the last fifteen centuries. Many in the eastern gorge have
                                <hi rend="nh">rolled</hi> down, piling up at its center, where they
                            form a frozen waterfall of stones. Some boulders have <hi rend="nh">fallen</hi> in such a way that the inscriptions engraved on them
                            are now hidden from view. Thus five segments of the text can no longer
                            be found. In other cases, the carved characters are almost buried, but
                            they have, nonetheless, been discovered. The short segments, GS B2 and
                            GS B3, are engraved on such boulders. They have rolled down and in their
                            new position are beyond the lower edge of GS B1 (fig. <ptr target="GS_sc_eastern_gorge_comm.jpg"/>). The three characters of
                            segment GS B4 are among those that are now lost from view. They may have
                            been engraved on one of the boulders lying in the foreground. It is
                            today impossible to recover the rocks carrying these characters.</p>
                        <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="Geier_Brehm_bw.jpg">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">黑白禿鷲；《布雷姆的動物生活• 動物界概覽》 Brehm, Pechuel-Loesche, and
                                Haake 1892，第 452頁。來源：www.BioLib.de</head>
                            <head>Rüppell’s Griffon Vulture (<hi rend="italic">Gyps
                                rueppellii</hi>). After Brehm, Pechuel-Loesche, and Haake 1892, p.
                                452. Source: www.BioLib.de</head>
                            <graphic url="Geier_Brehm_bw.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>As with GS B1, the two characters of section GS B5 are also placed on the
                            rock wall, but further back on another part, facing north, and high up
                            beneath a ledge sprouting grass. Because it is too dangerous to climb
                            up, rubbings of the characters have never been taken. Yet even the solid
                            rocky cliff has not resisted the course of time. Large boulders have
                            broken off. Thus, the whereabouts of the eight characters of segment GS
                            B6 again remain unknown, and the characters GS B7 are found on the rear
                            side of a heavy angular boulder seen in the center of the figure <ptr target="GS_sc_eastern_gorge_comm.jpg"/>. It is likely that this
                            chunk of rock fell from the cliff behind, where an overhanging
                            triangular ‘roof’ has lost the rock below it. This segment also carries
                            double grid lines. Possibly the sections on the cliff of Wolf Gorge all
                            had a grid, while those carved on single boulders did not. As a result
                            of the various changes in the topography, the original course of the
                            path can no longer be<!-- securely--> reconstructed. But as the
                            inscribed text is transmitted in the printed Buddhist canon, its full
                            content and the sequence of the segments are known.</p>
                        <p>Another long segment, GS B8, is the last one to be engraved on the
                            vertical cliff wall. It faces east (fig. <ptr target="GS_r_B8_total_KA23.JPG"/>). The characters are again placed
                            in a double grid, and the passage, like all the others so far, is read
                            from left to right, corresponding to the direction of the ascent through
                            the gorge.</p>
                        <p>On the same rock, but on its northern side, is segment GS B9. With it
                            begins the series of ten middle- or small-sized rocks that each carry
                            only one single character (GS B11, GS B12, GS B13, GS B14, GS B15, GS
                            B16, GS B18, GS B19), and, in one case, two (GS B10). None of these
                            characters has a grid. From this series, which ends with GS B19, only
                            four characters are missing (GS B17). These may have been carved on four
                            separate rocks or stones. </p>
                        <p>As the devotee ascends through the canyon and reads the text about Mount
                            Malaya, he can envision himself reaching a place where “gems are strewn
                            together, sparkling and illuminated with a fiery brilliance.” He,
                            himself, senses how “light breezes blow, rustling the branches and
                            moving the leaves,” and he himself smells the “hundreds and thousands of
                            wondrous fragrances,” and listens, as “hundreds and thousands of
                            wondrous tones all at once sound together.” Mount Gang thus becomes a
                            Chinese Mount Malaya. This phenomenon is well-known in religious art. It
                            is known as <hi rend="italic">translatio loci</hi>, translocation of a
                            site, whereby a site from one area is recreated at another.</p>
                        <p>The following long passage of twenty characters (GS B 20) is again one of
                            those that has not been found. It must have been situated between stone
                            GS B19 in the eastern gorge and boulder GS B21 on the western plateau.
                            It remains unknown, <hi rend="nh">whether</hi> these twenty characters
                            were originally distributed over single stones along the gorge, or
                            whether they formed longer text segments on cliffs or larger boulders.
                            The missing passage talks about layered cliffs, which “twist and turn,
                            there are everywhere halls of transcendents and numinous abodes,
                            innumerable grottoes and caves formed of masses of gems.” Thus, it is
                            equally unclear, whether the evocation of the transcendents’ halls and
                            numinous abodes is still part of the ascent to the mountain, or belongs
                            already to the second part of the text on the western plateau, which
                            opens up beyond Chicken Beak Rock. There, the sutra continues by evoking
                            the assembly to which the Buddha once preached.
                            <!--At this place and point in time, the devotee comes himself into the presence of the Buddha.-->
                            Even though the historical Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign> no longer dwells in our world, as he has
                            already entered <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">parinirvāṇa</foreign>
                            </hi>, the devotee is able to join, at
                            this place and point in time, “a great gathering of monks and a great
                            multitude of bodhisattvas, all of whom, from the various kinds of
                            Buddha-lands of the other quarters [of the cosmos] had arrived
                            together”. Being himself a participant of that assembly, the believer is
                            taught by the bodhisattvas, who, being “completely endowed with
                            incalculable samadhis of mastery [giving] supernatural power [...]
                            swiftly go around converting.” In due course, the participant will
                            understand their teachings; he will become a bodhisattva himself and,
                            ultimately, attain Buddhahood. </p>
                        <p>This second part of the sutra passage is spread over ten rocks and
                            boulders. Here, the texts read from right to left, corresponding to the
                            direction, in which the path now leads the pilgrim.<note>GS B21 can be
                                read from left to right and from right to left, GS B22 is missing,
                                GS B23 is engraved from top to bottom. Only from GS B24 onward can
                                there be no longer any doubt about the direction. </note> The rocks
                            on the plateau have moved less and are better <hi rend="nh">preserved</hi> than those in the gorge; only one <hi rend="nh">segment</hi> of five characters (GS B22) can no longer be located
                            today. The quantity of text carved on a single rock varies considerably
                            between one (GS B27) and 18 (GS B28) characters. In this solemn sphere,
                            where the assembly takes place, all texts, beginning with GS B23, are
                            now encased in a <hi rend="nh">double</hi> grid. In addition, from GS
                            B26 on, they are adorned with lotus petals and flowers, even if there is
                            only a single character as on GS B27. These lotus petals and flowers are
                            the appropriate adornments for a Buddha field (<hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">buddha kṣetra</foreign>
                            </hi>; <hi rend="italic">fotu </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">佛土</foreign>) or Pure
                            Land (<hi rend="italic">jingtu </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">淨土</foreign>), into which Mount Gang, or our world, is turned at the
                            very moment the bo­dhi­satt­vas take up their task of converting and
                            saving beings.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Halkias2013">4</ref>. His
                                remarks would apply to Mount Gang: “The conceptualization of buddha
                                fields as pure abodes, idealized locations where the buddhas
                                perpetually teach the Dharma, inspired meditators, artists, and
                                thinkers to contemplate new ways of representing and engaging with
                                their exalted forms.”</note> Only segment GS B31.1, which
                            was<!-- apparently--> not finished and abandoned, has no grid. </p>
                        <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="GS_sc_eastern_gorge_comm.jpg">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">東谷鳥瞰圖；2005年拍攝</head>
                            <head>Aerial view of the eastern gorge; photograph taken in 2005</head>
                            <graphic url="GS_sc_eastern_gorge_comm.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>Looking back over the segments of version B, it is apparent that the
                            sutra has been deliberately embedded in a wide landscape. The reader
                            cannot sit still in front of the text, as he would do in his cell in
                            front of a sutra scroll, but he has to proceed from one stone to the
                            next, following a prescribed path that leads him up and along the
                            mountain. Thus he experiences bodily how the engraved script has created
                            a sacred topography. It has transformed the entire Mount Gang into a
                            Chinese Mount Malaya, where the Buddha Dharma is still present and
                            preached perpetually.</p>
                        <p>Version A of the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Sutra of Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                                </hi>
                            </title> is engraved in
                            small characters. It is much more compact than the longer version B and
                            confined to only five separate rock faces at three sites (GS A1–GS A5;
                            see map, fig. <ptr target="Gangshan_Karte.jpg"/>). They are situated in
                            a central region of the mountain, between the eastern and western parts
                            of version B. The first two passages, GS A1 and GS A2, appear, as
                            already mentioned, on a cliff below a ridge, 21 meters above Chicken
                            Beak Rock. The next two passages, GS A3 and GS A4, are engraved on one
                            boulder lying some 65 meters further up, and the last passage, GS A5, on
                            another boulder, is yet 20 meters higher. That boulder is seen in figure
                                <ptr target="GS_sc_path_DSC2960.JPG"/>, lying in the foreground. The
                            texts of versions A and B are identical up to the characters <hi rend="italic">sanmei</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">三昧</foreign>
                            (sama­dhis; fig. <ptr target="GS_r_A5_part_G7SB8241.JPG"/>). The text of
                            version B continues <hi rend="">thereafter</hi> for another 23
                            characters, including two characters on the discarded segment GS B31.1
                            (see p. <ptr type="infra" target="endofGSB"/>).</p>
                        <p>Chicken Beak Rock presents the pilgrim with another <hi rend="italic">translatio loci</hi>. Its name seems to derive from its unusual
                            shape. Especially when seen from afar, the upper stone resembles the
                            beak of a bird (frontispiece and fig. <ptr target="GS_sc_jizuishi_G7S92029.jpg"/>). We do not know when the
                            name came into use; it does not occur in traditional epigraphic
                            literature. In 1911, the local epigrapher, Sun Baotian <foreign xml:lang="zh">孫葆田</foreign> (1840–1911), talks about Chicken Claw
                            Rock (Jizhaoshi 雞爪石).<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Shandongjinshizhi">9253</ref> and below, Discussion.</note> In Chinese, Chicken
                            Beak exudes an auspicious aura, because the homophone <hi rend="italic">ji</hi> can be understood as “chicken” <foreign xml:lang="zh">雞</foreign> and as “good fortune” <foreign xml:lang="zh">吉</foreign>. Yet, at a sacred Buddhist site, the name sounds
                            somehow profane and out of place. Indeed, it is likely, that the unusual
                            rock formation reminded the sixth century Buddhist monks of another
                            bird, namely a vulture, and thus of the renowned Vulture Peak in India
                                (<foreign xml:lang="sa">Gṛdhrakūṭa</foreign>). It is transliterated
                            in Chinese as Qi­she­jue Shan <foreign xml:lang="zh">耆闍崛山</foreign>, but
                            also known as Numinous Vulture Mountain (Lingjiu Shan <foreign xml:lang="zh">靈鷲山</foreign>), or simply Numinous Mountain (Ling Shan
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">靈山</foreign>). Chicken Beak Rock may
                            originally have carried one of those names. </p>
                        <p> The Indian Vulture Peak is located near the City of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Rājagṛha </foreign>(modern Rajgir), in the ancient
                            state of Magadha, about 50 kilometers northeast of modern Gaya. It was
                            the Buddha’s preferred site when preaching sermons. He taught several
                            Mahayana sutras there, among them the celebrated <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Lotus Sutra</hi>
                            </title>. Yet, whereas in India
                            the resemblance<?cb?> between the inconspicuous Vulture Peak and a
                            vulture is not obvious, the rock on Mount Gang, with its spectacular
                            upper stone jutting out horizontally, does indeed recall the shape of a
                            vulture (fig. <ptr target="Geier_Brehm_bw.jpg"/>). Even the two rocky
                            blocks below resemble the typically richly feathered feet of the
                            bird.</p>
                        <p>Additional, and even more forceful arguments are the texts, GS C–GS E,
                            that are engraved on the rock. The opening passage of the <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Visualization of the Buddha of
                                Immeasurable Life</hi>, in relatively small characters, begins on
                            the eastern side (GS C1) of the rock and continues on its southern side
                            (GS C2). This sutra was another one of those that the Buddha preached on
                            Vulture Peak, as one learns in the opening sentence: “Thus have I heard:
                            At one time, the Buddha was on Mount <foreign xml:lang="sa">Gṛdhrakūṭa</foreign>, near the city of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Rājagṛha</foreign>, with a great gathering of 1,250 monks and
                            32,000 bodhisattvas, with the Prince of the Law, <foreign xml:lang="sa">Mañjuśrī</foreign>, as their leader” (figs. <ptr target="GS_r_C1_part_G7S92048.JPG"/> and <ptr target="GS_C1.jpg"/>).
                            The name Vulture Peak (Qishe­jue Shan <foreign xml:lang="zh">耆闍崛山</foreign>), is thus inscribed onto Chicken Beak Rock
                            itself.</p>
                        <p>On the northern side of the rock, three Buddha names are found in
                            slightly larger characters: Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign> (Shijiawen fo <foreign xml:lang="zh">釋迦文佛</foreign>), Buddha Honored Maitreya (Mile zun fo <foreign xml:lang="zh">弥勒尊佛</foreign>), and Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> (Amituo fo <foreign xml:lang="zh">阿弥阤佛</foreign>, GS D1.1–GS D1.3; figs. <ptr target="GS_r_D-E_part_DSC3028.jpg"/> and <ptr target="GS_D1.jpg"/>).
                            The adjacent colophon (GS E) contains the names of six signatories
                            (figs. <ptr target="GS_r_D-E_part_DSC3092.jpg"/> and <ptr target="GS_E1.jpg"/>). They take the place of the “great gathering
                            of 1,250 monks” that, as the sutra tells us, came together at Vulture
                            Peak to listen to the Buddha. Buddha Maitreya and Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> join in, as do four more Buddhas,
                            whose names are seen on the rocks lying nearby: Buddha King of Great
                            Emptiness (GS D2), another Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> (GS D3), All Buddhas (GS D4), and possibly the
                            remnants of another name of Buddha King of Great Emptiness (also GS D4).
                            Their engraved names bring the Buddhas to the assembly. They will,
                            together with <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni’s</foreign> name, endure
                            on the hard rock through the ages and guarantee that the teachings,
                            which were first promulgated on Vulture Peak at a specific historic
                            moment, will continue to be heard in perpetuity.</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>LL, CW</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <figure rend="center" xml:id="ChickenRock">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">雞嘴石（點擊鼠標左鍵並移動可切換視角）@TODO:Does this get rendered in
                                the print version too?@</head>
                            <head>Chicken Beak Rock (left click and move mouse to change viewing
                                angle)@TODO:Does this get rendered in the print version too?@</head>
                            <graphic height="384" rend="flash" url="movies/SCHNABELFELS_640.swf" width="512"/>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Place Name</head>
                        <p>Mount Gang is known by various names. It is sometimes called Northern
                            Mount Gang <foreign xml:lang="zh">北崗山</foreign>, and sometimes Great
                            Mount Gang <foreign xml:lang="zh">大崗山</foreign>. Mount Tie has been
                            named Southern Mount Gang <foreign xml:lang="zh">南崗山</foreign>, and, for
                            this reason, Mount Gang is also called Rear Mount Gang <foreign xml:lang="zh">後崗山</foreign>. The <hi rend="italic">Gazetteer of Zou
                                County</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Zou Xian zhi</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">鄒縣志</foreign>, revised by Lou Yijun <foreign xml:lang="zh">婁一均</foreign>) in the fifty-fourth year of the Kangxi
                            era (1715), states: “Northern [Mount] Gang has stones which stand erect
                            like stelae.”<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Zouxianzhi1715">301</ref>.</note> The <hi rend="italic">Geographical Records of Zou
                                County in Shandong</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Shandong Zou Xian dili
                                zhi</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">山東鄒縣地理志</foreign>, revised by Zhang
                            Piju <foreign xml:lang="zh">張丕矩</foreign>) of the Republican era reads:
                            “On the ridge of Rear Mount Gang are 24 sites carved with [<hi rend="nh">characters</hi>] of the Northern Qi dynasty.”<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Zouxianjiuzhihuibian1986">25</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>LF</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <!--p>The present name of the Chicken Beak Rock seems to derive from its
                            unusual shape. Especially when seen from afar, its upper stone resembles
                            the beak of a bird (figs. <ptr target="GS_sc_jizuishi_G7S92029.jpg"/>, <ptr target="GS_r_C1_total_G7S92039.JPG"/>).
                            We do not know when the name came into use. It does not occur in the traditional epigraphic
                            literature. The local epigrapher, Sun Baotian, in 1911, talks about a
                            Chicken Claw Rock (<hi rend="italic">Jizhaoshi </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">雞爪石</foreign>). In Chinese, Chicken Beak exudes
                            an auspicious aura, because the homophone <hi rend="italic">ji</hi> can
                            be understood as “chicken” <foreign xml:lang="zh">雞</foreign> and as
                            “good fortune” <foreign xml:lang="zh">吉</foreign>. Yet at a sacred
                            Buddhist site, the name sounds somehow profane and out of place. Indeed,
                            it is likely, that the unusual rock formation reminded the sixth century
                            Buddhist monks of a vulture, and thus of the renowned Vulture Peak in
                            India (<foreign xml:lang="sa">Gṛdhrakūṭa</foreign>). It is
                            transliterated in China as Qishejue shan <foreign xml:lang="zh">耆闍崛山</foreign>, but also known as Numinous Vulture Mountain
                            (Lingjiushan <foreign xml:lang="zh">靈鷲山</foreign>), or simply Numinous
                            Mountain (Lingshan <foreign xml:lang="zh">靈山</foreign>). Chicken Beak
                            Rock may originally have carried one of those names.</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>LL</abbr>
                        </ab-->
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Time</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Related Monasteries</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>The Eastern Monastery of Mount Gang</head>
                            <p>It has been suggested that there was a monastery at the foot of Wolf
                                Gorge, provisionally called the Eastern Monastery of Mount Gang.
                                Here we find open ground, surrounded by mountains on three sides.
                                The trees on the mountains are luxuriantly green; the spring water
                                at the foot of the mountain gushes; and in the distance, fields and
                                villages stretch to the horizon. It is a beautiful place, at once
                                secluded and quiet, but still open to the world.</p>
                            <p>This environment fits the conventions for selecting sites for
                                monasteries during the Northern dynasties, for example on Mount Tai
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">泰山</foreign> and on Mount Yi <foreign xml:lang="zh">嶧山</foreign>: A secluded and quiet place, but not
                                too far away from human settlements; water at the foot of the
                                mountain; flat and cultivable land.</p>
                            <p>If there was a monastery nearby, it is likely to have been close to
                                the beginning of the path leading up Wolf Gorge. The wide space
                                directly east of the gorge would have been an appropriate site for
                                such a monastery (fig. <ptr target="GS_sc_G7S93333.JPG"/>).</p>
                            <p>Since 1990, this area has been repeatedly explored. However, as the
                                ground has been broken up over a long period to supply a brick
                                factory, no remains have been discovered here to date.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Evening Glow Monastery</head>
                            <p>Another monastery, which is sometimes thought to have been the center
                                for the monks who carried out the carving on Mount Gang, is Evening
                                Glow Monastery (Wanzhao Si <foreign xml:lang="zh">晚照寺</foreign>),
                                located at a northwestern pass of Mount Gang. The site is surrounded
                                by mountains to the east, south and north, with the result that
                                sunlight can first be seen after midday, hence the name.</p>
                            <p>The monastery must have been ancient. Its remains cover an area of
                                approximately 7,000 square meters. A western section was destroyed
                                when a reservoir was built in the 1960s. Villagers reported that
                                large quantities of bricks and tiles were excavated there. A high
                                platform, visible at the eastern part of the site, would have
                                supported buildings and halls. The excavated rectangular bricks with
                                coarse rope pattern and round tiles for the eaves, decorated with
                                lotus motifs, indicate that the monastery may have been built in the
                                Sui or early Tang dynasties. It was not occupied after the Song and
                                Yuan period. Some fragments of pottery from these times have been
                                excavated at the site, but ceramics from later periods are rare.</p>
                            <p>It is possible that Evening Glow Monastery was established by moving
                                another religious community, perhaps that of the hypothetical
                                Eastern Monastery of Mount Gang. Indeed, given the configuration of
                                Mount Gang and the sequence of the engraved stones, it seems likely
                                that the monks, who engraved the sutras, came from a monastery east
                                of the mountain.</p>
                            <p>Although Evening Glow Monastery is also quite close to the stone
                                inscriptions of Mount Gang, the Buddhist stone sutras were probably
                                not carved by the monks from this monastery, which lies to the
                                northwest beyond the last segment of the inscription GS B.</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>LF</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Related Persons</head>
                        <p>Among the inscriptions on Mount Gang there is only one colophon. The
                            north side of Chicken Beak Rock carries the following names: “Second
                            Son. Monk (<hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">bhikṣu</foreign>
                            </hi>) Huihui, and Nun (<hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">bhikṣuṇī</foreign>
                            </hi>) Fahui. Monk Daocheng,
                            Seng’an, Tang Zhang. The image donor Chao Sihe, the wife of Wei Chuanzhu
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">二郎。 比丘惠暉 。 比丘尼法會。 比丘道成、 僧岸、 唐章。 像主朝 思和，
                                韋傳竹妃。</foreign>” (GS E, fig. <ptr target="GS_r_D-E_part_DSC3092.jpg"/>).<note>Chao Sihe may have chosen the story about the virtuous and
                                pious Queen <foreign xml:lang="sa">Vaidehī</foreign>. She must have
                                been one of the many resourceful woman patrons, who were so
                                successful in creating the wealth of Buddhist monuments in
                                China.</note> These names were carved together with the date, July
                            29, 580, and the two characters “Stone Sutra,” as well as the three
                            Buddha names “Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign>, Buddha
                            Honored Maitreya, Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign>” (GS
                            D1, fig. <ptr target="GS_r_D-E_part_DSC3028.jpg"/>). The date and the
                            name of “Monk Daocheng” were carved in two parallel columns and have to
                            be read together. “Seng’an” and “Tang Zhang” are carved in smaller
                            characters. In addition, a small roundel contains a Buddha figure in
                            relief.</p>
                        <p>The two versions of the beginning of the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Sutra
                                    of Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                                </hi>
                            </title> and the passage from the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Contemplation of the Buddha of
                                    Immeasurable Life</hi>
                            </title> differ in calligraphic style and
                            layout. Thus we can conclude that the Mount Gang inscriptions were
                            executed by two or more groups of monks. But these groups appear to have
                            had no relation to the more active group around Seng’an Daoyi <foreign xml:lang="zh">僧安道壹</foreign> (fl. 562–579). Furthermore, among the
                            many surviving colophons of the Seng’an Daoyi group, which name clerics
                            and lay people, there is no overlap with the names at Mount Gang. The
                            monks, nuns, and lay people named on the north side of Chicken Beak Rock
                            must have had a close relation to the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Sutra on
                                    the Contemplation of the Buddha of Immeasurable
                                Life</hi>
                            </title>. They represent the groups that make up a Buddhist
                            community: monks (<hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">bhikṣu</foreign>
                            </hi>), nuns (<hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">bhikṣuṇī</foreign>
                            </hi>), and lay believers, male
                            and female (<hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">upāsaka</foreign>
                            </hi> and <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">upāsikā</foreign>
                            </hi>).</p>
                        <p>The colophon at Mount Gang suggests that clerics and lay believers joined
                            forces. The colophon is very short and cannot compete with the genealogy
                            of the Kuang <foreign xml:lang="zh">匡</foreign> and Wei <foreign xml:lang="zh">韋</foreign> families mentioned in the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Stone Hymn</hi>
                            </title> at nearby Mount Tie, and
                            the slightly more distant Mount Jian. Nonetheless, it is evident from
                            Mount Gang that, during the Northern dynasties, the Buddhist religion
                            reached all social strata of society, from the imperial house down to
                            the common people. While Seng’an Daoyi was sponsered by the Kuang and
                            Wei families, the carving at Mount Gang manifests the achievement and
                            thoughts of monks and the common people.</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>ZZ</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Dating</head>
                        <p>The only date on Mount Gang is found on the northern side of Chicken Beak
                            Rock. It reads: “Third day of the seventh month in the second year of
                            the <hi rend="italic">daxiang</hi> era (July 29, 580).” However, it is
                            unlikely, that the five inscription groups A–E on Mount Gang were
                            produced at the same time according to one master plan. They differ from
                            each other in content, format, and calligraphic style. It is not
                            possible to determine definitively the relative chronology, but informed
                            assumptions can be made, based on topography and calligraphy.</p>
                        <p>All five segments of the <hi rend="italic">Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                            </hi> version A fill only a small
                            circumscribed area. The two cliff walls above Chicken Beak Rock and the
                            two boulders in the western area lie within the perimeter of the much
                            more extended area marked by the boulders of the <hi rend="italic">Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                            </hi> version B
                            (map, fig. <ptr target="Gangshan_Karte.jpg"/>). It is reasonable to
                            suggest that the more confined version A came first and was later
                            dwarfed by a more extensive and more elaborately carved second version,
                            rather than the other way around. Along the same lines of reasoning, it
                            would appear that the inscriptions on the singular Chicken Beak Rock are
                            even earlier than the first <hi rend="italic">Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                            </hi> version. This highly visible
                            stone almost begs to be engraved. Earlier cliff inscriptions of sutra
                            passages in Shandong are also found on conspicuous rock faces that can
                            be seen from a distance, as on Mount Yi (564), Mount Culai (570), or on
                            neighboring Mount Tie (579). The Buddha names on the stones next to
                            Chicken Beak Rock may have been carved in the same period as those on
                            the rock itself or slightly later. According to this scenario, the
                            chronology indicates an expansion of a sacred space in stages. The first
                            stage was a sacred site, Chicken Beak Rock. This was enlarged into the
                            sacred area of version A, followed by the still larger area covered by
                            version B.<note>For further discussion of the relative chronology based
                                on stylistic grounds see below pp. <ptr type="infra" target="style style_end"/>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p> The question now arises as to how the anchor date of July 29, 580, fits
                            into the historical events of the period. Three years earlier, in 577,
                            the Northern Qi dynasty, whose territory included present-day Shandong,
                            had been subjugated by its neighbor to the west, the Northern Zhou
                            dynasty. On June 21, 574, its Emperor Wu <foreign xml:lang="zh">武帝</foreign>(r. 559–578) launched a persecution of Buddhism. He
                            died on June 21, 578, and his son and successor, Emperor Xuan <foreign xml:lang="zh">宣帝</foreign> (r. 578–579), immediately reversed the
                            most severe anti-Buddhist measures. If the above relative chronology is
                            correct, the inscriptions on Mount Gang would have heralded a new period
                            of triumph of Buddhism.<note>For the Buddhist persecution see <ref type="biblio" target="Shandong_1">27–30</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>LL</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Research History</head>
                        <p>In the late eighteenth century, epigraphers began to take note of the
                            inscriptions on Mount Gang. The early field archaeologist, Huang Yi
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">黄易</foreign> (1744–1802), included a sketch
                            of the mountain in his album of 1797, <hi rend="italic">Illustrations of
                                Enquiries into Stelae Around Mount Dai</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Dailu
                                fangbei tu </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">岱麓訪碑圖</foreign>; fig. <ptr target="Huang_Yi_Gangshan.jpg"/>).<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Penglaisuyue2010">191</ref>. See also Introduction
                                above, and Discussion below.</note> In the colophon to his own
                            painting, he describes the arduous route in between boulders and rocks,
                            by which he approached the hill along Wolf Gorge. He notes the date 580
                            and the name of one donor, and he alerts the reader to a difference
                            between engraved characters in clerical and those in regular script. </p>
                        <p>In his pioneering <hi rend="italic">Epigraphic Records of Shandong</hi>
                                (<hi rend="italic">Shanzuo jinshi zhi </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">山左金石志</foreign>) of 1797, Ruan Yuan <foreign xml:lang="zh">阮元</foreign> (1764–1849) makes a first attempt at a fuller
                            description of the engravings on Mount Gang. He begins his entry by
                            assigning the date 580 to the entire mountain and then mentions the
                            inscriptions on the three sides of Chicken Beak Rock. Yet, he does not
                            record the full text, and he does not identify the sutra. Of the <hi rend="italic">Sutra of Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                            </hi>, he only mentions two segments, GS B7 and
                            GS B30. He records eight of the nine characters of GS B7, but in the
                            wrong sequence. Of GS B30, he only records the first four characters,
                            yet he gives measurements of the boulder and says that it is lying at
                            the rear of Mount Gang. Ruan Yuan is always keen to label calligraphic
                            styles. So he classifies all inscriptions on Chicken Beak Rock as being
                            carved in symmetric clerical script (<hi rend="italic">bafen
                                </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">八分</foreign>). In GS B30, he recognizes
                            standard script (<hi rend="italic">zhengshu </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">正書</foreign>), and in GS B7, a combination of seal script and
                            clerical script (<hi rend="italic">zhuanshu </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">
                                篆書</foreign> and <hi rend="italic">lishu </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">隸書</foreign>).<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Shanzuojinshizhi">14486a</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Duan Songling <foreign xml:lang="zh">段松苓</foreign> (1745–1800), in his
                                <hi rend="italic">List of Stelae in Shandong</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Shanzuo beimu </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">山左碑目</foreign>), preface
                            1796, but edited and published only in 1908, merely repeats Ruanʼs
                                    findings.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Shanzuobeimu">14844a</ref>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Sun Xingyan <foreign xml:lang="zh">孫星衍</foreign> (1753–1818), who worked
                            together with Ruan Yuan, says in his list of stone inscriptions,
                                    <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Record of Enquiries into Stelae in the
                                    Whole World</hi>
                            </title> (<hi rend="italic">Huanyu fangbei lu
                                </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">寰宇訪碑錄</foreign>, preface 1802), that
                            four passages from sutras, written in standard script, can be seen on
                            Mount Gang and he gives the date.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Huanyufangbeilu">19873b</ref>. </note> This information
                            does not go beyond what Ruan Yuan had said.</p>
                        <p>In their <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Draft of the Gazetteer of Zou
                                    County</hi>
                            </title> (<hi rend="italic">Zou Xian zhi
                                gao</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">鄒縣志稿</foreign>) of 1834, Dong Chun
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">董純</foreign> and Ma Xingyi <foreign xml:lang="zh">馬星翼</foreign> say that there are five engraved stones,
                            and they mention GS B28, GS B29, GS B31.2, and two inscriptions reading
                            ‘bodhisattvas mastery’ (GS B28 and GS A5). However, Dong and Ma were
                            unaware that two of their excerpts refer to the same segment, namely GS
                            B28. They further mistakenly claim that a date and signatures are
                            lacking on the mountain as a whole.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Zouxianzhigao">469</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>A few decades later, Li Zuoxian <foreign xml:lang="zh">李佐賢</foreign>
                            (1807–1876) gives a more complete and detailed account in his <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Colophons to Epigraphica from the Stone Well
                                    Studio</hi>
                            </title> (<hi rend="italic">Shiquan shuwu jinshi tiba
                                </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">石泉書屋金石題跋</foreign>). He enumerates 13
                            inscriptions on Mount Gang. Ten of these are segments of the two
                            versions of the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Sutra of Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                                </hi>
                            </title>. For five of the
                            segments, he transcribes the complete text, but he does not recognize
                            that there are two versions and treats them as one set. Yet Li Zuoxian
                            is the first epigrapher to record the columns in their proper sequence
                            and he corrects Ruan Yuan on this point. He also notes the relative
                            spatial <hi rend="nh">positions</hi> of the inscriptions, but he does
                            not understand the overall sequence of the segments, and he mentions 16
                            scattered characters from segments that he thinks are
                                    unfinished.<note>
                                <anchor xml:id="LiZuoxian11"/>Li Zuoxian’s
                                segments 1 to 3 are inscriptions on Chicken Beak Rock (GS E and GS
                                D1, GS C1 and GS C2). Li’s segment 4 corresponds to GS A5, with a
                                partial transcription. Li’s segment 5 corresponds to GS B24; he
                                gives a complete transcription. Li’s segment 6 corresponds to GS
                                B31.2, with a complete transcription. Li’s segment 7 corresponds to
                                GS A3, with a partial transcription. Li’s segment 8 corresponds to
                                GS B7, with a complete transcription. Unlike Ruan Yuan, Li reads the
                                columns correctly from left to right, and he mentions this
                                explicitly. Li’s segment 9 corresponds to GS A4, with a complete
                                transcription. Surprisingly, however, Li does not record GS A3 on
                                the same boulder. Li’s segment 10 corresponds to GS B30, with a
                                partial transcription. Li’s segment 11 corresponds to GS B25, with a
                                partial transcription. Li counts eight characters in four columns,
                                not recognizing the partly effaced portion on the right, with
                                originally another eight characters, of which three are still
                                clearly legible today. This indicates that Li Zuoxian did not visit
                                the actual site. Li’s segment 12 corresponds to GS B26; he gives a
                                complete transcription. Then follow six fragmented characters,
                                which, in Li’s words, “do not form a segment”, but which are
                                probably the same as those recorded by Wu Shifen as carved on six
                                single stones. Li’s segment 13 corresponds to GS B28, with a partial
                                transcription. Thereafter follow ten scattered characters not
                                forming a segment, which correspond to the characters carved in
                                pairs on a total of five stones, as Wu Shifen records. In his
                                concluding remarks, Li Zuoxian regrets that epigraphers, who
                                recorded engravings at Zou County, hardly ever transcribed the text,
                                and that even Ruan Yuan, who recorded some segments in his
                                        <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Epigraphic Records of
                                    Shandong</hi>
                                </title>, did not succeed in giving a full report.
                                    <ref type="biblio" target="SQSW">14195b–14196a</ref>.
                            </note>
                        </p>
                        <p>In his <hi rend="italic">Categorized Edition of an Assembled Catalog of
                                Epigraphica</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Jinshi huimu fenbian
                                </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">金石彙目分編</foreign>), Wu Shifen <foreign xml:lang="zh">吳式芬</foreign> (1796–1856) is equally precise. In 24
                            entries, he lists segments of versions A and B. He was also able to see
                            the now lost stone GS B6 and part of the lost GS B17.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Jinshihuimufenbian">21153</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Wang Jun<foreign xml:lang="zh"> 汪鋆</foreign> (1816–1884–) in his <hi rend="italic">Record of Epigraphica that Passed Before my Eyes in
                                the Twelve Ink Stones Studio</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Shi’eryan zhai
                                jinshi guoyan lu </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">十二硯齋金石過眼錄</foreign>),
                            with a preface of 1875, only records the text of GS B30. He says that
                            the four sutra segments, which according to Sun Xingyan are on Mount
                            Gang, cannot be identified.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Shieryanzhaijinshiguoyanlu">7856b</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p> Miao Quansun <foreign xml:lang="zh">繆荃孫</foreign> (1844–1919) in his
                                    <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">List of Epigraphic Characters from the
                                    Yifeng Hall</hi>
                            </title> (<hi rend="italic">Yifengtang jinshi
                                wenzi mu </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">藝風堂金石文字目</foreign>, preface
                            1898) lists five segments: Three inscriptions from version A (GS A4, GS
                            A3, GS A5), one from version B (GS B30), and a sutra in 21
                                    columns.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Yifengtangjinshiwenzimu">19552b</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>In his well-known <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Supplementary Corrigenda to
                                    the Epigraphica of Eight Gems Studio</hi>
                            </title> (<hi rend="italic">Baqiong shi jinshi buzheng </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">八瓊室金石補正</foreign>, published in 1925), Lu Zengxiang <foreign xml:lang="zh">陸增祥</foreign> (1833–1889) begins his entry on Mount
                            Gang with the rubbings of the inscriptions on Chicken Beak Rock. He
                            transcribes in full the names of the signatories, with the date (GS E),
                            as well as the three Buddha names (GS D1). Of the two segments of the
                            sutra, GS C1 and GS C2, he quotes the beginning and the end, but, as
                            usual, he does not identify the text. From version A of the <hi rend="italic">Sutra of Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                            </hi>, he quotes two segments (GS A4 and GS A5)
                            and, from version B, ten segments.<note>In the following sequence: GS
                                B30, GS B25 (without the first part), GS B26, GS B24, GS B18 (<hi rend="italic">zhong </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">重</foreign>), GS
                                B17 (only the character <hi rend="italic">ju </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">俱</foreign>), GS B16, GS B27 (<hi rend="italic">zhong </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">種</foreign>). In addition, Lu
                                Zengxiang lists two single characters, <hi rend="italic">chang
                                    </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">常</foreign>, and <hi rend="italic">jian</hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">間</foreign>. The stone with the
                                character <hi rend="italic">ju </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">俱</foreign>, which was formerly part of the segment GS B17, is
                                now lost. The same is true for the stone with the character <hi rend="italic">jian</hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">間</foreign>,
                                formerly part of GS B6. However, a rubbing of this character has
                                survived and is in the National Library of China in Beijing. The
                                character with a diameter of one foot, which Lu reads as <hi rend="italic">chang </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">常</foreign>, is
                                probably a misreading of the character <hi rend="italic">yan
                                    </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">岩</foreign> (GS B19), which measures
                                30 cm in height.</note> He notes that Ruan Yuan records only one
                            segment of the above, namely GS A5, but that the rubbings, which he
                            consults, must come from Mount Gang, because the labels on them say so.
                            Only a future visit can bring certainty, he notes.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Baqiongshijinshibuzheng">4364b–4365b</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>The local offical, Sun Baotian <foreign xml:lang="zh">孫葆田</foreign>
                            (1840–1911), surpasses all earlier authors with the amount of
                            information he offers. In his <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Epigraphic
                                    Records of Shandong</hi>
                            </title> (<title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Shandong jinshi zhi </hi>
                            </title>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">山東金石志</foreign>) of 1911, he records 13 of 27 surviving inscription
                            segments of version B of the <hi rend="italic">Sutra of Arrival in
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                            </hi>, and he transcribes
                            each of them in full. All but one (GS B29) of these segments are located
                            in the eastern gorge. Moreover, he records a total of five characters
                            that are missing today. They formed part of segment GS B6. His layout on
                            the printed page reproduces the numbers of columns and characters in
                            each column. He begins with GS B28 as the most imposing segment. Then he
                            goes on to describe the position of all other stones in relation to this
                            stone, as well as in relation to Chicken Beak Rock, and to the boulder
                            GS B7.</p>
                        <p>However, like all others before him, Sun fails to understand the
                            sequence, in which the stones have to be read, because he does not
                            recognize the sutra text. Although he observes that the characters of GS
                            A5 are smaller than those of other segments, he does not realize that
                            two versions of the same text are carved on Mount Gang. He records five
                            characters in passages whose whereabouts are no longer known
                                today.<note>Sun Baotian treats the stones in the following sequence:
                                GS B28, GS B25, GS B24, GS B30, GS A3, GS D3, GS A5, GS A4, GS
                                B31.2, GS B26, character <hi rend="italic">wen </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">聞</foreign> (probably a misreading of <hi rend="italic">jian</hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">閒</foreign> of the
                                lost segment GS B6, of which a rubbing, mentioned above, has
                                survived in the National Library of China in Beijing), GS B27, GS
                                B7, GS B29, character <hi rend="italic">cheng </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">成</foreign> (the character occurs in GS B6 and GS
                                B20, which are both lost), GS B23, GS B31.1, GS D2 (only one Buddha
                                name), the three characters <hi rend="italic">guang gong ming
                                    </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">光共明</foreign>, and the two
                                characters <hi rend="italic">yi nuo </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">一諾</foreign>, probably a misreading of GS B10, ‘<hi rend="italic">yi shi </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">一時</foreign>’.
                                    <ref type="biblio" target="Shandongjinshizhi">9248a–9251b</ref>.
                            </note> His detailed description was a major advance on those of his
                            predecessors. </p>
                        <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="GS_sc_B28_G7S93160_1.jpg">
                            <head xml:lang="zh">崗山B28的《入楞伽經》節文片斷；2005年拍攝</head>
                            <head>Carved segment GS B28 of the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Sutra of
                                        Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                                    </hi>
                                </title>; photograph taken in 2005</head>
                            <graphic url="GS_sc_B28_G7S93160_1.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                        <p>Fa Weitang <foreign xml:lang="zh">法偉堂</foreign> (1843–1907), in his <hi rend="italic">Record of Enquiring into Stelae in Shandong</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Shanzuo fangbei lu </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">山左訪碑錄</foreign>), published in 1909, again, only quotes Ruan
                                    Yuan.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Shanzuofangbeilu">9089a</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Looking back at the writings of the traditional epigraphers, we can trace
                            a steady development. Ruan Yuan set the standard. He begins with the
                            date; he records the numbers of columns and measurements, and he is
                            definite on calligraphic styles. All later authors are familiar with his
                            writings and follow his scheme; some merely quote him, but others
                            improve on his work by adding more <hi rend="nh">passages</hi>, and by
                            giving more attention to the spatial dimension. None of the traditional
                            epigraphers, however, understands the correct sequence of the engraved
                            stones, because they do not recognize the sutra text. The first to
                            identify the sutra passages on Mount Gang was <foreign xml:lang="ja">Michihata Ryōshū </foreign>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">道端良秀</foreign>.
                            In 1991, Wang Sili, the former director of the Shandong Stone Carving
                            Art Museum in Jinan, and Lai Fei, a trained archaeologist, were the
                            first to give a complete transcription.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="Wang_Lai1991b">445–454</ref>.</note> More transcriptions
                            followed in 1997,<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="AnTingshan1997">51</ref>.</note> 2000,<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="LaiFei2000a">plates 226–234, transcription
                                301–303</ref>.</note> and 2007.<note>
                                <ref type="biblio" target="LaiFei2007">127–144</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>ZZ, LL</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Inscriptions</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Inventory</head>
                        <p>At Mount Gang six Buddha names were carved (GS D1–GS D4), three sutra
                            passages (GS A1–GS A5, GS B1–GS B31.2, GS C1–GS C2), and one historical
                            inscription, the colophon GS E.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Buddha Names </head>
                        <div>
                            <head>GS D1–GS D4</head>
                            <p>On the north side of Chicken Beak Rock are the names of three
                                prominent Buddhas: Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign>
                                (in the less usual transcription Shijiawen fo <foreign xml:lang="zh">釋迦文佛</foreign>), Buddha Honored Maitreya (Mile zun fo <foreign xml:lang="zh">弥勒尊佛</foreign>), and Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> (Amituo fo <foreign xml:lang="zh">阿弥阤佛</foreign>; GS D1.1, GS D1.2, GS D1.3). The last name is
                                also found on a smaller boulder nearby (GS D3). Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign>, the historical Buddha of our
                                world-age, is thus followed by the future Buddha Maitreya, who will,
                                in the distant future, also descend to our world and attain
                                Buddhahood. The appellation chosen here for Maitreya is an
                                abbreviation for “Buddha Honored Maitreya of the Future” (<hi rend="italic">danglai Mile zun fo </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">當來彌勒尊佛</foreign>) or “Buddha Honored Maitreya Attaining Rebirth
                                Below in the Future” (<hi rend="italic">danglai xiasheng Mile zun fo
                                    </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">當來下生彌勒尊佛</foreign>). These forms of
                                Maitreya’s names are found almost exclusively in the context of
                                repentance rites.<note>The most well-known among the ritual texts in
                                    which the above three appellations occur is the <title>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Ceremony for Bestowing the Bodhisattva
                                            Precepts</hi>
                                    </title> (<hi rend="italic">Shou pusajie yi
                                        </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">受菩薩戒儀</foreign>, R 105: 1–9),
                                    traditionally attributed to Huisi <foreign xml:lang="zh">慧思</foreign> (515–577). However, <ref type="biblio" target="Magnin1979">117–128</ref> found sufficient evidence
                                    to reject the alleged authorship of Huisi claimed in Japanese
                                    catalogs of the ninth and tenth centuries.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>By contrast with <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign> and
                                Maitreya, who are the two great Buddhas of our world, Buddha
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> may be called a
                                transcendental Buddha. He has always been and is right now residing
                                in his Buddha-field, the Pure Land in the West, which lies at an
                                unfathomable distance to the west of our world. This name on the
                                north side of Chicken Beak Rock complements the passage from the
                                        <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Contemplation of the
                                        Buddha of Immeasurable Life</hi>
                                </title> (<title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Guan wuliangshou fo jing</hi>
                                </title>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">觀無量壽佛經</foreign>, T#365, 12: 340c29–341a10) on the
                                east and south sides of this rock. For, in this sutra, Buddha
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign> is about to instruct
                                Queen <foreign xml:lang="sa">Vaidehī</foreign> on how to visualize
                                the Pure Land of Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign> in
                                the west. The three Buddha names carved on Chicken Beak
                                    Rock—<foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign>, Maitreya, and
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign>—thus weave together
                                our past and future worlds across billions of Buddha-lands to the
                                timeless Land of Bliss in the west. </p>
                            <p>Another boulder close to Chicken Beak Rock has “Buddha King of Great
                                Emptiness” (Da kong wang fo <foreign xml:lang="zh">大空王佛</foreign>)
                                written on it (GS D2). This precise name does not appear in any
                                scripture of the Buddhist canon, but was hewn into the rocks of
                                several Shandong mountains.<note>For discussion of the name see <ref type="biblio" target="Shandong_1">82–87</ref>.</note> The
                                character “great” (<hi rend="italic">da </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">大</foreign>) of GS D4.1, seems to be the beginning of another
                                “Buddha King of Great Emptiness.” The second <hi rend="nh">column</hi> of GS D4.2 does not seem to refer to any particular
                                Buddha at all, but simply reads “All <hi rend="nh">Buddhas</hi>.”
                                This name suggests that the Buddha names on Mount Gang reflect
                                Mahayana beliefs in general.</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>CW</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Sutra Passages</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>GS A1–GS A5; GS B1–GS B31.2</head>
                            <div>
                                <p>The main text passage, carved twice, was taken from the
                                    introduction of the <title>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Sutra of Arrival in
                                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                                        </hi> (<hi rend="italic">
                                            <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkāvatāra-sūtra</foreign>
                                        </hi>
                                    </title>,
                                            <title>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Ru Lengqie jing
                                        </hi>
                                    </title>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">入楞伽經</foreign>) as
                                    translated by Bodhiruci<note>The north Indian monk Bodhiruci
                                        (Putiliuzhi <foreign xml:lang="zh">菩提留支</foreign> or
                                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">菩提流支</foreign>; fl. 508–535—not
                                        to be confused with the Bodhiruci of Tang times), active
                                        during the Northern Wei dynasty <foreign xml:lang="zh">北魏</foreign> (386–534) in Luoyang <foreign xml:lang="zh">洛陽</foreign>, was one of the most
                                        important <hi rend="nh">translators</hi> of the sixth
                                        century. Among his translations are the <hi rend="italic">Diamond Sutra</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Jingang bore
                                            jing</hi>
                                        <foreign xml:lang="zh">金剛般若經</foreign>, T#236),
                                        the <hi rend="italic">Treatise on the Sutra of Immeasurable
                                            Life</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Wuliangshou jing
                                            lun</hi>
                                        <foreign xml:lang="zh">無量壽經論</foreign>, T#1524),
                                        which greatly influenced the <hi rend="nh">doctrines</hi> of
                                        Pure Land thought in China, and the <hi rend="italic">Treatise on the Sutra of the Ten Stages</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Shidi jing lun</hi>
                                        <foreign xml:lang="zh">十地經論</foreign>, T#1522), a text central to the
                                        formulations of the Ten Stages movement in northern
                                        China.</note> (T#671, 16: 514c7–18).</p>
                                <p>The <title>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Sutra of Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                                        </hi>
                                    </title> was
                                    translated into Chinese three times during the medieval period.
                                        <note>The notoriously unreliable <hi rend="italic">Record of
                                            the Three Jewels in Successive Dynasties</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Lidai sanbao ji </hi>
                                        <foreign xml:lang="zh">歷代三寶紀</foreign>, T#2034, 48: 84b7)
                                        mentions as lost an early translation in four scrolls by
                                            <foreign xml:lang="sa">Dharmakṣema</foreign> (Tanwuchen
                                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">曇無讖</foreign>, 385–433). The
                                        authoritative <hi rend="italic">Kaiyuan Era Catalogue of
                                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni’s</foreign>
                                            Teachings</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Kaiyuan shijiao
                                            lu</hi>
                                        <foreign xml:lang="zh">開元釋教錄</foreign>, T#2154,
                                        55: 629b11) also lists it, but only in the historical
                                        section, where it is named the <hi rend="italic">
                                            <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign> Sutra in Four
                                            Scrolls</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Lengqie jing
                                            sijuan</hi>
                                        <foreign xml:lang="zh">楞伽經四卷</foreign>).
                                        Given that this translation is not listed in the earlier
                                        catalog by Sengyou <foreign xml:lang="zh">僧祐</foreign>
                                        (445–518), the <hi rend="italic">Compilation of Notes on the
                                            Issuing of the Tripitaka</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Chu
                                            sanzang jiji </hi>
                                        <foreign xml:lang="zh">出三藏記集</foreign>), we are justified in wondering whether it
                                        ever existed or not.</note> The earliest extant translation,
                                    consisting of four scrolls, is known as the <hi rend="italic">Precious Sutra of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkāvatara</foreign>
                                    </hi> (<hi rend="italic">Lengqie
                                        abaduoluo baojing </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">楞伽阿跋多羅寶經</foreign>, T#670, 16: 479a–514b). Its translator
                                    was <foreign xml:lang="sa">Guṇabhadra </foreign> (Qiunabatuoluo
                                        <foreign xml:lang="zh">求那跋陀羅</foreign>; 394–468). His work
                                    was honored by the early Chan masters, as being the version
                                    Bodhidharma (<foreign xml:lang="zh">菩提達摩</foreign>) gave to his
                                    disciple Huike <foreign xml:lang="zh">慧可</foreign> (ca. 485–ca.
                                    574–), as the only text appropriate for the tradition. Bodhiruci
                                    based his translation in part on <foreign xml:lang="sa">Guṇabhadra’s</foreign> work. This second translation ranges
                                    over ten scrolls and is named the <hi rend="italic">Sutra of
                                        Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                                    </hi> (<hi rend="italic">Ru Lengqie jing </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">入楞伽經</foreign>, T#671, 16: 514c–586b). The final
                                    translation, in seven scrolls, belongs to <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śikṣānanda</foreign> (Shichanantuo <foreign xml:lang="zh">實叉難陀</foreign>, 652–710). This work is known as the <hi rend="italic">Mahayana Sutra of Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                                    </hi> (<hi rend="italic">Dasheng ru Lengqie jing</hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">大乘入楞伽經</foreign>, T#672, 16: 587a–640c).</p>
                                <p>The introduction to the sutra reads quite differently in the
                                    three translations. Bodhiruci’s introduction is the most
                                    detailed and elaborate one. Instead of merely naming the place
                                    of the sermon and the members of the assembly, he embarks on a
                                    lyrical description of a landscape populated by “transcendents,
                                    worthies and saints of old”, who “pondered the true Law” in
                                    “numinous abodes, innumerable grottoes and caves formed of
                                    masses of gems.” This description adds a strong Chinese flavor
                                    to Bodhiruci’s introduction, which is best characterized as a
                                    presentation of an idealized, paradisical landscape with flower
                                    gardens, fragrant trees, light breezes and wondrous tones.</p>
                                <p>This elaborate landscape is not found in the other two
                                    translations of the <hi rend="italic">Sutra of Arrival in
                                            <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                                    </hi>. In <foreign xml:lang="sa">Guṇabhadra’s</foreign> introduction, the
                                    mountain where the sermon took place is mentioned only
                                    briefly:</p>
                                <quote>Thus have I heard: At one time the Buddha dwelt by the shore
                                    of the southern ocean on the peak of Mount <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>, [a mountain] adorned with all
                                    manner of gems and flowers, along with a great <hi rend="italic">
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">bhikṣu-saṅgha</foreign>
                                    </hi>,
                                    and a great multitude of bodhisattvas, who had arrived together
                                    from the various kinds of Buddha-lands of the other quarters [of
                                    the cosmos]...<note>T#670, 16: 480a17–19: <foreign xml:lang="zh">如是我聞：
                                            一時佛住南海濱楞伽山頂，種種寶華以為莊嚴，與大比丘僧及大菩薩眾，俱從彼種種異佛剎來。</foreign>
                                    </note>
                                </quote>
                                <p>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Guṇabhadra’s</foreign> short
                                    characterization of the mountain as “adorned with all manner of
                                    gems and flowers” seems to have been the point of departure for
                                    the considerable expansion found in Bodhiruci’s text. The later
                                    translation by <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śikṣānanda</foreign>,
                                    however, does not characterize the mountain at all. It simply
                                    says:</p>
                                <quote>Thus have I heard: At one time the Buddha dwelt by the shore
                                    of the southern ocean on the peak of Mount Malaya in the City of
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>, along with a great
                                        <hi rend="italic">
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">bhikṣu-saṅgha</foreign>
                                    </hi>, and a great multitude of
                                        bodhisattvas.<note>T#672, 16: 587b15–16: <foreign xml:lang="zh">如是我聞：一時佛住大海濱摩羅耶山頂楞伽城中，與大比丘眾及大菩薩眾俱。</foreign>
                                    </note>
                                </quote>
                                <p>It seems as if the passage on the paradisical nature of Mount
                                    Malaya in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign> in Bodhiruci’s
                                    translation is in fact an interpolation that was later taken out
                                    again in the revision by <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śikṣānanda</foreign>. The suggested interpolation starts
                                    with “a mountain formed of all manner of things of gem-like
                                    nature” <foreign xml:lang="zh">彼山種種寶性所成</foreign> and ends with
                                    “sites, where transcendents, worthies, and saints of old
                                    pondered the True Law and attained the Way” <foreign xml:lang="zh">古昔諸仙賢聖思如實法得道之處</foreign>.<note>T#671, 16:
                                        514c9–15.</note> The first sentence in Bodhiruci’s
                                    translation, starting with “Thus have I heard: At one time the
                                    Bhagavat dwelt by the shore of the great ocean, on the peak of
                                    Mount Malaya in the City of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>”, would have continued more naturally with
                                    the character <hi rend="italic">yu </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">與</foreign> (along with) in the phrase “along with a great
                                        <hi rend="italic">
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">bhikṣu-saṅgha</foreign>
                                    </hi> [gathering of monks], and
                                    a great multitude of bodhi­sat­tvas...”,<note>T#671, 16:
                                        514c7–8: <foreign xml:lang="zh">如是我聞：一時婆伽婆住大海畔摩羅耶山頂上楞伽城中</foreign>, to be continued
                                        with T#671, 16: 514c15: <foreign xml:lang="zh">與大比丘僧及大菩薩眾……</foreign>. In discussion with the research
                                        group, Eric Greene pointed out this interpolation.</note> by
                                    analogy with <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śikṣānanda’s</foreign>
                                    revision. The empty space which the carvers left before the
                                    character <hi rend="italic">yu </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">與</foreign> in segment GS A5 (fig. <ptr target="GS_A5.jpg"/>) and after this character in segment GS B25 (fig. <ptr target="GS_B25.jpg"/>) might indicate that they were aware
                                    of the interpolation. The space in GS B25 may also have served
                                    as an honorific space for the great <hi rend="italic">
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">bhikṣu-saṅgha</foreign>
                                    </hi> and the
                                    bodhisattvas that follow. </p>
                                <p>On the rocks and boulders at Mount Gang, the interpolation
                                    extends from the lost section GS B4, originally located close to
                                    the foot of Wolf Gorge, to the<!-- large--> boulder GS B25 close
                                    to the center of the western plateau. Thus the larger part of
                                    the text passage carved on many stones over a wide area consists
                                    of a description of an idealized, sacred Chinese landscape that
                                    echoes formulations found in Chinese translations of Pure Land
                                    texts, such as the longer and shorter <hi rend="italic">
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sukhāvatīvyūha-sūtras</foreign>
                                    </hi>. </p>
                                <p>After the interpolation, the text continues with praise of the
                                    achievements of the <hi rend="italic">
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">bodhisattva-mahāsattvas</foreign>
                                    </hi>, who arrived to
                                    join the assembly. Again, the three extant sutra translations
                                    differ in the wording, but this time not in the content, which
                                    describes the bodhisattvas’ extraordinary abilities in guiding
                                    and converting living beings. Their mastery of “the Five <hi rend="italic">Dharmas</hi>, [Three Kinds of] Intrinsic
                                    Nature, [Eight Kinds of] Consciousness, and the Two Kinds of
                                    No-self”, as described in the last text segments GS B30 and GS
                                    B31.2 of the large character version B, gives a preview of the
                                    contents of the sutra itself. </p>
                                <!--p>The <title>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Sutra of Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                                        </hi>
                                    </title> has been influential in many schools of Chinese Buddhism. The
                                    early Chan tradition honored the version in four scrolls by <foreign xml:lang="sa">Guṇabhadra</foreign>,
                                    which was thought to be
                                    the very same that was handed down by Bodhidharma to his
                                    disciple Huike <foreign xml:lang="zh">慧可</foreign>, as the only
                                    text appropriate for the tradition.</p-->
                                <ab>
                                    <abbr>PC, CW</abbr>
                                </ab>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <p>
                                    <anchor xml:id="consciousnesses"/>The text segment GS B30, carved
                                    on the penultimate boulder, corroborates the reading of the
                                    character <hi rend="italic">shi </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">識</foreign>, consciousness, which is not found uniformly in
                                    all editions of the Buddhist canon. The <hi rend="italic">Chinese Edition of the Buddhist Canon</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Zhonghua da zangjing </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">中華大藏經</foreign>), which reproduces the
                                    Bodhiruci translation on the basis of the Jin canon (Jinzang
                                        <foreign xml:lang="zh">金藏</foreign>), includes this
                                    character, but notes that the edition of the Second Goryeo Canon
                                    omits it.<note>ZH#169, 17: 630c1–2.</note> And, indeed, the
                                    modern <hi rend="italic">
                                        <foreign xml:lang="ja">Taishō</foreign>
                                    </hi> edition, which is based on the Second
                                    Goryeo Canon, does not have the character. However, the <hi rend="italic">
                                        <foreign xml:lang="ja">Taishō</foreign>
                                    </hi>
                                    apparatus names three other editions of the canon in which it
                                        appears.<note>T#671, 16: 514, note 15.</note>
                                </p>
                                <p>There is no doubt that the reading of the character <hi rend="italic">shi </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">識</foreign> is
                                    correct, as it is essential to the understanding of the entire
                                    text passage, which is part of an enumeration including the Five
                                        <hi rend="italic">Dharmas</hi>, the Intrinsic Natures, the
                                    Consciousness(es), and the Two Kinds of No-self. The
                                    translations by <foreign xml:lang="sa">Guṇabhadra</foreign> and
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śikṣānanda</foreign> also contain
                                    this character.<note>
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">Guṇabhadra</foreign>
                                        (T#670, 16: 23–24) has: “They mastered completely the Five
                                        Dharmas, [Three Kinds of] Intrinsic Nature, [Eight Kinds of]
                                        Consciousness, and the Two Kinds of No-self. <foreign xml:lang="zh">於五法、自性、識、二種無我，究竟通達。</foreign> ” <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śikṣānanda</foreign> (T#672, 16: 17–18)
                                        has: “All these <hi rend="italic">
                                            <foreign xml:lang="sa">bodhisattva-mahāsattvas</foreign>
                                        </hi> had already
                                        completely mastered the Five Dharmas, the Three Kinds of
                                        Intrinsic Nature, the [Eight Kinds of] Consciousnesses, and
                                        the [Two Kinds] of No-self. <foreign xml:lang="zh">其諸菩薩摩訶薩，悉已通達五法、三性、諸識、無我。</foreign>” </note>
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śikṣānanda</foreign>, in his translation,
                                    even speaks of “consciousnesses” (<hi rend="italic">zhu
                                        shi</hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">諸識</foreign>). These plural
                                    consciousnesses have been identified as Eight Consciousnesses
                                        (<hi rend="italic">ba shi</hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">八識</foreign>) by <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śikṣānanda</foreign>’s commentators, the Tang scholar-monk,
                                    Fazang <foreign xml:lang="zh">法藏</foreign> (643–712; T#1790, 39:
                                    425c25–27), and the Song commentator, Baochen <foreign xml:lang="zh">寶臣</foreign> (dates unknown; T#1791, 39:
                                    435a28–b1). Baochen furthermore explains that the four terms,
                                    Five Kinds of Entities, Intrinsic Natures, Consciousnesses, and
                                    Two Kinds of No-self, refer to the Four Wonderful Gates (<hi rend="italic">si miaomen </hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">四妙門</foreign>). A full list of the Eight Consciousnesses is
                                    given further on in Bodhiruci’s translation of the sutra (T#671,
                                    16: 559b22–25). Two Ming commentators, who collate all three
                                    Chinese translations of the <hi rend="italic">Sutra of Arrival
                                        in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                                    </hi>, explain the
                                    Intrinsic Natures as Three Kinds of Intrinsic Natures, and the
                                    Consciousnesses as Eight Kinds of Consciousnesses and list them
                                    all (X#332, 18: 5a4–6 and X#333, 18: 68b22–25). The doctrine of
                                    Eight Consciousnesses is important, because it became one of the
                                    basic teachings of the Yogacara School in East Asian
                                        Buddhism.<anchor xml:id="consciousnesses_end"/>
                                </p>
                                <p>Together with the <hi rend="italic">Awakening of Mahayana
                                        Faith</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Dasheng qixin lun</hi>
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">大乘起信論</foreign>, T#1666, 32: 575a–583b),
                                    allegedly translated by <foreign xml:lang="sa">Paramārtha</foreign> (Zhendi <foreign xml:lang="zh">真諦</foreign>, 499–569), but most likely composed in China,
                                    the <title>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Sutra of Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                                        </hi>
                                    </title> was,
                                    furthermore, instrumental in the formation of <hi rend="italic">
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">tathāgatagarbha</foreign>
                                    </hi>
                                    thought in Chinese Mahayana Buddhism.</p>
                                <ab>
                                    <abbr>CW</abbr>
                                </ab>
                                <figure rend="center" n="figure" xml:id="Dia_ZDF_Gangshan_001.jpg">
                                    <head xml:lang="zh">崗山B31.2號，崗山朝山之路上最後一塊刻經石；2000年拍攝。漢堡<foreign xml:lang="en">ZDF</foreign>提供</head>
                                    <head>GS B31.2; last carved stone of Mount Gang’s path taken by
                                        devotees; photograph taken in 2000. Courtesy ZDF,
                                        Hamburg</head>
                                    <graphic url="Dia_ZDF_Gangshan_001.jpg"/>
                                </figure>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>GS C1–GS C2</head>
                            <p>The second sutra passage carved on Mount Gang is the opening passage
                                of the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Contemplation of the
                                        Buddha of Immeasurable Life</hi>
                                </title> (<title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Guan wuliangshou fo jing </hi>
                                </title>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">觀無量壽佛經</foreign>, T#365, 12: 340c29–341a10),
                                purportedly translated in 424 by the Central Asian monk, <foreign xml:lang="sa">Kālayaśas </foreign>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">畺良耶舍</foreign> (Jiang­liang­ye­she, 383?–442?). It tells the
                                story of King <foreign xml:lang="sa">Bimbisāra</foreign>, who was
                                imprisoned by his unfilial son, <foreign xml:lang="sa">Ajātaśatru</foreign>. Queen <foreign xml:lang="sa">Vaidehī’s</foreign> unwavering loyalty kept him alive, and
                                    <foreign xml:lang="sa">Bimbisāra</foreign> then took refuge in
                                the Buddha, accepting the Eight Precepts. Here the carved text
                                breaks off. The passage, a straightforward narrative of extreme lack
                                of filial piety, moving conjugal love and self-sacrifice, and
                                devotion to the Buddhist teaching, is part of the tale that provides
                                the reason why the Buddha preached the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Contemplation of the Buddha of Immeasurable
                                        Life</hi>
                                </title>. Granting Queen <foreign xml:lang="sa">Vaidehī’s</foreign> request, the Buddha, in this sutra, teaches
                                Sixteen consecutive Visualizations that ensure rebirth in the Pure
                                Land of the West, where the Buddha of Immeasurable Life dwells. The
                                        <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Contemplation of the
                                        Buddha of Immeasurable Life</hi>
                                </title> gained immense
                                influence in China and constitutes one of the main scriptures of
                                Pure Land Buddhism. The passage selected on Mount Gang emphasizes
                                the practice of bestowing the precepts on lay people;<note>In
                                    contemporary Pure Land rituals, it is still common for lay
                                    people first to take the bodhisattva vows before they engage in
                                    visualization practices of the Pure Land of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign>; see, for example, <ref type="biblio" target="Jones2004"/>.</note> it probably
                                addressed the latter in order to encourage support for the Buddhist
                                faith in the region. </p>
                            <p>The translator, <foreign xml:lang="sa">Kālayaśas</foreign>, is also
                                credited with the translation of the <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the
                                    Contemplation of the Two Bodhisattvas, the Medicine King and the
                                    Superior Physician</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Guan yaowang yaoshang
                                    er pusa jing </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">觀藥王藥上二菩薩經</foreign>,
                                T#1161, 20: 660c–666b). According to the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Biographies of Eminent Monks</hi>
                                </title> (<hi rend="italic">Gaoseng zhuan </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">高僧傳</foreign>, T#2059, 50: 343c–344a) compiled by Huijiao
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">慧皎</foreign> (497–554) sometime between
                                519 and 533, <foreign xml:lang="sa">Kālayaśas</foreign> was a famous
                                master of meditation. His translations were made orally, and he had
                                them written down by Chinese monks. As is common in the Chinese
                                translations of Buddhist texts, the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Sutra
                                        on the Contemplation of the Buddha of Immeasurable
                                    Life</hi>
                                </title> is cast in four character phrases, a style
                                that no doubt made it appealing to Chinese readers.<note>Strategies
                                    in the translations of Buddhist texts into Chinese are analyzed
                                    in <ref type="biblio" target="Funayama2013"/>, 196.</note>
                            </p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>PC</abbr>
                            </ab>
                            <p>
                                <foreign xml:lang="ja">Michihata Ryōshū </foreign>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">道端良秀</foreign> has called the choice of the two
                                sutras on Mount Gang an unusual combination, which he explains,
                                however, through the particular historic circumstances.<note>
                                    <ref type="biblio" target="Michihata1972">19–28</ref>.</note> He
                                suggests that in the <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Contemplation of
                                    the Buddha of Immeasurable Life</hi> the fate of the king, who
                                is thrown into prison by his son and left to die there, refers to
                                the threat to Buddhism during the persecution under the Northern
                                Zhou. Yet the queen opens a way out of this devastating calamity by
                                saving her husband from prison, converting her son, and evoking the
                                promises of <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha’s</foreign> Pure Land.
                                The <hi rend="italic">Sutra of Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                                </hi>, on the other hand, with its fabulous
                                assembly of the Buddha and the host of bodhisattvas from other
                                Buddha-lands, turns Mount Gang into a place, where, after the
                                Buddhist persecution, the True Law is transmitted again.</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>LL</abbr>
                            </ab>
                            <p>No Sanskrit or Tibetan equivalent can be found for this text, which
                                was probably compiled in Central Asia or China proper. The
                                        <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Contemplation of the
                                        Buddha of Immeasurable Life</hi>
                                </title> belongs to a larger
                                group of visualization sutras that reflect the growing popularity of
                                    <hi rend="italic">guan </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">觀</foreign>,
                                meditation, in the first half of the fifth century. However, the
                                passage carved at Mount Gang does not mention any meditation at all,
                                but is part of the narrative framing the Buddha’s teaching of the
                                Sixteen Visualizations to Queen <foreign xml:lang="sa">Vaidehī</foreign>.</p>
                            <p>When the introductory passage was carved on Chicken Beak Rock, the
                                        <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Contemplation of the
                                        Buddha of Immeasurable Life</hi>
                                </title> was not yet well
                                known. Tanluan <foreign xml:lang="zh">曇鸞</foreign> (476–542), who
                                was later canonized as one of the patriarchs of Pure Land Buddhism,
                                was one of the first to discuss the text systematically when he
                                wrote a commentary on Vasubandhu’s <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">Sukhāvatīvyūhopadeśa</foreign>
                                    </hi>
                                </title> (<hi rend="italic">Wuliangshou jing youbotishe yuansheng ji </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">無量壽經優波提舍願生偈</foreign>, T#1524, 26: 230c–233a).</p>
                            <p>Vasubandhu’s text is commonly known as the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Treatise on Rebirth</hi>
                                </title> (<hi rend="italic">Wangsheng lun </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">往生論</foreign>). In
                                his <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Commentary on the Verses on the Vow for
                                        Rebirth of the Treatise on the Sutra of Immeasurable
                                        Life</hi>
                                </title> (<hi rend="italic">Wuliangshou jing <hi rend="nh">youpotishe</hi> yuansheng ji zhu </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">無量壽經優婆提舍願生偈註</foreign>, T#1819,40: 826a–844b),
                                Tanluan laid the foundation of belief in the salvific power of
                                reciting <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha’s</foreign> name. </p>
                            <p>Deeper scholarly interest in this sutra began with Jingying Huiyuan’s
                                    <foreign xml:lang="zh">淨影慧遠</foreign> (523–592) <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Commentary on the Meaning of the Sutra on the
                                        Contemplation [of the Buddha] of Immeasurable
                                    Life</hi>
                                </title> (<hi rend="italic">Guan wuliangshou jing yishu
                                    </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">觀無量壽經義疏</foreign>, T#1749, 37:
                                173a–186b). Many more commentaries followed, written by the most
                                learned monks of their time. The <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Sutra on
                                        the Contemplation of the Buddha of Immeasurable
                                    Life</hi>
                                </title> was later celebrated as one of the “three
                                sutras and one treatise” (<hi rend="italic">san­jing yilun
                                    </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">三經一論</foreign>), on which the
                                Japanese Pure Land school founded its teachings.</p>
                            <p>Contrary to the passage from the <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Sutra of
                                        Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                                    </hi>
                                </title>, the introductory passage from the
                                        <title>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Contemplation of the
                                        Buddha of Immeasurable Life</hi>
                                </title>, as carved on Mount
                                Gang, is almost identical with the version transmitted in the
                                woodblock printed editions. Only one character differs, but in this
                                case without any change in the meaning.</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>CW</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Historical Inscriptions</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>GS E</head>
                            <p>A donor’s colophon has been carved on the northern side of Chicken
                                Beak Rock. The first six names of three monks, one nun and two
                                laypeople are thought to relate to the date, July 29, 580. The last
                                two names may be directly connected to the small image of the
                                roundel with the seated Buddha, for the title of one of the two
                                adjacent donors is “image donor.” This meditating Buddha figure in
                                relief is the only iconic element on the entire mountain. The two
                                characters <hi rend="italic">shijing </hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="zh">石經</foreign> (stone sutras) to its left may have been added
                                later as some form of commentary. The same two characters stand
                                below the first column of section GS B8.</p>
                            <ab>
                                <abbr>CW</abbr>
                            </ab>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Carving Techniques</head>
                        <p><!--As on many of the inscribed mountains in Shandong Province, several-->Four
                            carving techniques were employed here:
                            <!--They fall into four categories:-->
                        </p>
                        <list type="ordered">
                            <item>U-shaped carving,</item>
                            <item>V-shaped carving,</item>
                            <item>Double-outline carving,</item>
                            <item>Rectangular U-shaped carving.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>See also the description for Mount Tie. </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>LF</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Style of Calligraphy</head>
                        <p>
                            <anchor xml:id="style"/>The inscriptions at Mount Gang were carved in
                            regular script (<hi rend="italic">kaishu </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">楷書</foreign>). The <title>
                                <hi rend="italic"> Sutra of Arrival in
                                        <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                                </hi>
                            </title> in large
                            characters (version B) was written by one person, while the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic"> Sutra of Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                                </hi>
                            </title> in small characters (version
                            A) as well as the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Contemplation of
                                    the Buddha of Immeasurable Life</hi>
                            </title> and the colophon
                            were written by other calligraphers. The strokes of the characters of
                            the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Sutra of Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                                </hi>
                            </title> in version B have angular
                            beginnings, endings, twists and turns. Sometimes single characters fit
                            into a square and sometimes into a vertical rectangle. Their upper part,
                            where the balance point of the character is situated, is rather loose.
                            The lower part is rather more dense. Each individual character is
                            distinctive, with a unique style and even a touch of humor. The
                                    <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Sutra of Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                                </hi>
                            </title> in small
                            characters (version A), as well as the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Sutra on
                                    the Contemplation of the Buddha of Immeasurable
                                Life</hi>
                            </title> and the colophon, both present angular and round
                            brushstrokes. The brushwork appears slightly stiff. Some characters are
                            dense, some loose, but no matter how spontaneous they are, they still
                            lack individual flavor.</p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>LF</abbr>
                        </ab>
                        <p>The calligraphy supports the relative chronology of the two versions of
                            the <hi rend="italic">Sutra of Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                            </hi>. The small characters of version A have no
                            grid and no ornamentation, as on GS A2 (fig. <ptr target="GS_A2.jpg"/>);
                            GS A3 (fig. <ptr target="GS_A3.jpg"/>); GS A5 (fig. <ptr target="GS_A5.jpg"/>). The large characters of version B, however,
                            are encased in rectangular fields in a grid of double lines and, in some
                            instances, surmounted by flowery ornamentation, as on GS B27 (fig. <ptr target="GS_B27_rba_d017295.jpg"/>), GS B30 (fig. <ptr target="GS_B30_rba_d017312.jpg"/>), and the magnificent rock GS B28
                            (fig. <ptr target="GS_r_B28_part_DSC2978.JPG"/>; fig. <ptr target="GS_B28_rba_d017307.jpg"/>). When comparing figures <ptr target="GS_A5.jpg"/> and <ptr target="GS_B28_rba_d017307.jpg"/>,
                            which in part show the same text, it appears that the strokes in version
                            B are sharper, and the composition of the characters is more deliberate.
                            This ambitious and elaborate execution suggests a later date for version
                            B.</p>
                        <p>A comparison with the calligraphy of the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Sutra
                                    on the Contemplation of the Buddha of Immeasurable
                                Life</hi>
                            </title> on Chicken Beak Rock, however, seems at first
                            glance to contradict the relative chronology that the topography
                            suggests. The thrust of development in these centuries, between the Han
                            and the Tang dynasties, was the gradual and ramified metamorphosis of
                            clerical script (<hi rend="italic">lishu </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">隸書</foreign>) into regular script (<hi rend="italic">kaishu
                                </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">楷書</foreign>). Characters in the two
                            scripts differ in their construction, that is the number and position of
                            strokes. They also differ in their compositional balance and the
                            execution of strokes. The regular script reached maturity only in the
                            early Tang dynasty.<note>Several authors have illuminated aspects of the
                                calligraphic transformations in these centuries. Among them are the
                                meticulous studies by <ref type="biblio" target="Lu2003"/>, who
                                combines political and stylistic analysis in her treatment of stone
                                engravings of the Northern Wei in Luoyang, and <ref type="biblio" target="McNair2012"/>, who thematises the fascinating exchanges
                                between center and periphery. See also the pungent descriptions in
                                    <ref type="biblio" target="Harrist2008">passim</ref>.</note> In
                            the sixth century the process was still ongoing.</p>
                        <p>In this overall scheme, it appears that the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Sutra on the Contemplation of the Buddha of Immeasurable
                                    Life</hi>
                            </title> (GS C1; fig. <ptr target="GS_r_C1_part_G7S92048.JPG"/>; fig. <ptr target="GS_C1.jpg"/>; fig. <ptr target="GS_r_C2_total_Ar11.jpg"/>; fig. <ptr target="GS_C2.jpg"/>), as well as the accompanying Buddha names and
                            the colophons (GS D and GS E; fig. <ptr target="GS_r_D-E_part_DSC3092.jpg"/>), are more advanced than the
                                <hi rend="italic">Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                            </hi> version B, which retains old fashioned
                            typological features. In segment GS B7, for example, the left hand
                            element of the character <hi rend="italic">zhao </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">照</foreign> is written as a circle around a point
                            (fig. <ptr target="GS_r_B7_total.jpg"/>; fig. <ptr target="GS_B7_rba_d017310.jpg"/>, 2/3). This archaic detail never
                            occurs in inscriptions GS C–GS E. It must have been the reason why Ruan
                            Yuan categorized the calligraphy of this passage as a combination of
                            seal script and clerical script. The silk radical in the character <hi rend="italic">luo </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">羅</foreign> of segment
                            GS B1 is formed by two superimposed triangles, a typical feature of
                            clerical script (fig. <ptr target="GS_B1.jpg"/>, 6/1). Stylistically,
                            too, version B exudes a conservative, clerical flavor. The fields for
                            the characters tend to be oblong, for example in GS B1 and GS B25 (fig.
                                <ptr target="GS_B1.jpg"/>; fig. <ptr target="GS_B25.jpg"/>). In GS
                            B7 the two small vertical strokes of the character <hi rend="italic">shan </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">山</foreign> lean outward (fig.
                                <ptr target="GS_B7_rba_d017310.jpg"/>, 3/3), as they do in GS B1
                            (fig. <ptr target="GS_B1.jpg"/>, 6/3). This treatment results in
                            slightly oblong, sophisticated compositions, which are never seen in the
                                    <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Contemplation Sutra</hi>
                            </title> on
                            Chicken Beak Rock. There, the strokes of the character <hi rend="italic">shan </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">山</foreign> are short and vertical
                            (fig. <ptr target="GS_C1.jpg"/>, 1/15).</p>
                        <p>In the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Contemplation Sutra</hi>
                            </title>, the
                            characters are inscribed in an imaginary grid of square fields, typical
                            of regular script. The strokes that point diagonally to the lower right
                            tend to be less drawn out than they are in the <hi rend="italic">Arrival
                                in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                            </hi> version B. The
                            calligrapher of this version has a penchant for small round dots,
                            sometimes with a pointed tip, which he uses playfully and effectively,
                            as in the characters <hi rend="italic">pu </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">菩</foreign> (GS B28; fig. <ptr target="GS_B28_rba_d017307.jpg"/>,
                            4/2) or <hi rend="italic">jing </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">竟</foreign>
                            (GS B31.2; fig. <ptr target="GS_B31.2_rba_d017309.jpg"/>, 3/2). He is a
                            master of the brush, who can create felicitous and daring compositions,
                            as with the two characters <hi rend="italic">lengqie </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">楞伽</foreign> (GS B2; fig. <ptr target="GS_B2.jpg"/>).</p>
                        <p>However, the more conservative style of the two versions of the <hi rend="italic">Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                            </hi>
                            sutra does not necessarily suggest that these are more archaic; they may
                            just be archaistic. Their ancient style and, in particular, the
                            sophisticated execution of version B may well have been chosen
                            intentionally to add dignity to the large-size characters. Other large
                            character inscriptions on the Shandong mountain cliffs, Mount Hongding
                            (564), Mount Tie (579), and Mount Ge (580), had set precedents in the
                            use of clerical script, which in those times already had an antique
                            flavor.</p>
                        <p>Authors, both traditional and modern—possibly still under the spell of
                            Ruan Yuan, who assigned the one surviving date to the entire
                            mountain—have not explored the chronological problem in detail, but have
                            tended to date all inscriptions, including the two versions of the <hi rend="italic">Sutra of Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                            </hi>, to 580. There seems to be, however, a
                            temporal sequence among the different inscriptions, and the analysis of
                            the calligraphy supports the relative chronology suggested above on the
                            basis of the topography. The chronology now appears thus: the highly
                            visible, unusually shaped Chicken Beak Rock at the end of Wolf Gorge was
                            the first stone to be engraved in 580 with a sutra text in small
                            characters. At the same time, or soon thereafter, Buddha names were
                            added in the vicinity. The three rocks with the <hi rend="italic">Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                            </hi> version A,
                            in small characters, followed not much later in a more conservative
                            calligraphic style than that of the first inscriptions. Finally, the
                            most ambitious effort resulted in a second version of the <hi rend="italic">Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                            </hi>
                            sutra in large characters, carved in a spectacular archaistic script and
                            spread out over the entire mountain.</p>
                        <p>It might well be that the various inscriptions on Mount Gang were not
                            only produced at different times, but also by groups of monks favoring
                            different doctrines. The engravers of the <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Contemplation Sutra</hi>
                            </title> sympathized with the Pure Land
                            teachings. The name of Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign>,
                            which is positioned next to the name of Buddha <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign> on the northern side of Chicken Beak Rock, may
                            be an indication of the shift in emphasis from <foreign xml:lang="sa">Śākyamuni</foreign> to <foreign xml:lang="sa">Amitābha</foreign>,
                            which has been observed in sixth century Buddhism.<note>See <ref type="biblio" target="Tsukamoto1974_76">2: 254–265 and
                                    436–448</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>The <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">Sutra of Arrival in <foreign xml:lang="sa">Laṅkā</foreign>
                                </hi>
                            </title> by contrast was, as mentioned
                            before, favored by the proto-Chan and early Yogacara movements. “Buddha
                            King of Great Emptiness”, one of the Buddha names near Chicken Beak
                            Rock, is not found in the canonical scriptures, but the name appears 15
                            times on the Shandong Mountains. “Emptiness” (<hi rend="italic">kong
                                </hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="zh">空</foreign>) is the central concept in
                            the <hi rend="italic">
                                <foreign xml:lang="sa">Prajñā­pāramitā</foreign>
                            </hi> literature, from which the Shandong
                            monks carved numerous passages at other sites.<note>See the discussion
                                in <ref type="biblio" target="Shandong_1">82–84</ref>.</note> The
                            unusual invocation “All Buddhas” seems to conjure up unity among the
                            different groups who collaborated or competed amongst each other on
                            Mount Gang.<anchor xml:id="style_end"/>
                        </p>
                        <ab>
                            <abbr>LL</abbr>
                        </ab>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>