<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Zacchetti2016a" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://sueyling:sueyling@data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/webdav/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo lang="en">
        <title>Notion and Visions of the Canon in Early Chinese Buddhism</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <!-- <titleInfo lang="zh">
        <title>眾經目録</title>
    </titleInfo>-->
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Zacchetti 2016a</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" lang="en" ns2:href="#zacchetti_enzh" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="en" type="family">Zacchetti</namePart>
        <namePart lang="en" type="given">Stefano</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">左</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">冠明</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>The “inclusive nature” of the Chinese canon refers to the trans-sectarian character of the texts, which “were generally considered and treated as part of a <hi rend="italic">single</hi> textual body.” (p. 82) That lead to hermeneutical techniques like “doctrinal classification” 判教. Chinese <hi rend="italic">Āgama</hi>s “are, as a group, an entirely Chinese invention.” (p. 83) 
        Zongmi 宗密 (781–841) thought the four versions of the <hi rend="italic">Āgama</hi>s constitute the stage of the "Lesser Vehicle" 小乘.
        The “conservative nature” of the Chinese canon refers to the preservation of multiple translations of the same scriptures, which adds a historical dimension to the canon. Example: the seven Chinese translations (Han to Song) of the <hi rend="italic">Aṣṭasāhasrikā Prājñāpāramitā</hi> 
        The “classical” Chinese canon attained its definitive form and sctructure in 730 with the <hi rend="italic">Kaiyuan shijiao lu</hi> by Zhisheng 智昇.
        The <hi rend="italic">Chu sanzang ji ji</hi> (T.2145) by Sengyou 僧祐 (445–518) is the result of the first “historiographical outpouring” under the Southern Liang dynasty. It refelcts “ideas and expectations of early sixth-century Jiangnan cultivated clergy” (p. 85) and it contains some precious early sources (prefaces, colophons, commentaries).
        Patterns of influence in early translations: “For some early Chinese commentaries, An Shigao’s translations (or at least some of them) worked as a de facto “micro-canon.” (p. 88) Zacchetti gives an example from the first half of the third century preface to the commentary <hi rend="italic">Yin chi ru jing zhu</hi> 陰持入經註 (T.1694), a commentary on An Shigao’s <hi rend="italic">Yin chi ru jing</hi> 陰持入經. “there is little doubt that ast least some of these [early] texts were soon seen and utilized as a single corpus—that is, as a canon in a nutshell.” (p. 88)
        “these early commentaries were in effect based on a certain “micro-canon” (p. 89)
        “Another exegetical practice typical of early Chinese Buddhism ... is that of the “synoptic editions,” as Zürcher calls them.” (p. 89)
        Visions of the canon: “... we want a canon to be “pure,” ... we want it to be “complete” ” (p.89)
        “Buddhist scriptures were introduced in China piecemeal” (p. 90). Dao’an regretted that the canon was incomplete. Buddhist texts are in principle big, and larger is better, see <hi rend="italic">Da zhidu lun</hi> (T.1509, 25: 756a26–b6): The version of the Prājñāpāramitā kept in the palaces of the Nāga and Asura kings are long, because the lifespan of the deities is long, and the force of their memory strong.
        The Indian Tripitaka paradigm is finally refelcted in the <hi rend="italic">Kaiyuan shijiao lu</hi>. In early scriptures, “the classification of canonical scriptures in twelve classes, or divisions (<i ren="italic">aṅga</i>), is already mentioned.” (p. 91) =&gt; the Dharma in twelve classes was produced after Ānanda’s recitation; this is a mythical depiction of the Buddha and his teaching.
        It is the “archetype ... of a topos that occurs frequently in early Chinese discourse on canonical scriptures, particularly in the initial portion of prefaces” (p. 92) =&gt; “the narrative of the canon”, “...thus suggesting the <hi rend="italic">idea</hi> of a whole canon even during the early phase of Chinese Buddhism, when the <hi rend="italic">reality</hi> of actually available translated scriptures, still few and fragmentary, was certainly very different.” (p. 92)
        “The “the narrative of the canon” figures with particular prominence in Daoan’s prefaces” (which are preserved in <hi rend="italic">Chu sanzang ji ji</hi>, T.2145) (p. 92)
        “no author earlier than Daoan uses <hi rend="italic">sanzang</hi>” (p. 92)=&gt; the Tripitaka “became part of the Chinese discourse on the canon essentially with Daoan.” (p. 93)
        the “Tripitaka paradigm” (the notion of a complete canon) “was rather something of a polestar, a powerful force that led Daoan into a relentless search for canonical scriptures ... and the quest for its completeness was a constant leitmotif in his surviving works.” (p. 93)
        the <hi rend="italic">Chu sanzang ji ji</hi> preserves more than 60 glosses by Daoan (安公云), most of them “on scriptural classification, in which Daoan sought to match one or more translations to a specific Indian canonical subdivision.” (p. 93) The most intriguing of these categories is <hi rend="italic">fangdeng</hi> 方等 (<hi rend="italic">vaipulya</hi>), and this is “a category belonging to the list of twelve divisions of canonical scriptures.” (p. 93) Daoan adopted it from the “twelve divisions” in order to find a place for classifying Mahayana scriptures. In his catalogs, “Daoan made use of certain Indian traditional categories to produce what was, in effect, a highly imaginative and rather “Chinese” notion of the canon.” (p. 96)
        Daoan used the <hi rend="italic">vaipulya</hi> category “as an attempt to integrate Mahayana texts into the <hi rend="italic">tripiṭaka</hi>/<hi rend="italic">āgama</hi> paradigm.” (p. 96)
        “That each translated scripture was part of a whole— a notion voiced in so many early prefaces through the “narrative of the canon”—was probably the most important legacy in this area inherited from the Indian tradition.” (p. 97)
        Daoan’s use of <hi rend="italic">vaipulya</hi>: “this embryonic but eventually succesful attempt to integrate Mahayana sutras into the Tripitaka framework” (p. 97)
        “the close relationship between the birth of the canon and the process of bringing Buddhism under the control of the state, in full swing during the sixth century, especially in North China.” (p. 103, footnote 57) =&gt; AN EXPLANATION FOR THE BIRTH OF STONE SUTRAS AS WELL? 
        
    </abstract>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#Wu_Chia2016" type="host">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>Spreading Buddha’s Word in East Asia: The Formation and Transformation of the Chinese Buddhist Canon</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>monographic</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>81</start>
                <end>108</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>