<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="ZhangZong2013a" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo transliteration="pinyin">
        <title>Beixiangtang shiku kejing dong de Fo dian jisong he Fo ming</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="zh">
        <title>北響堂石窟刻經洞的佛典、偈頌和佛名</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo lang="en" type="translated">
        <title>The Engraved Buddhist Sūtra, Gāthas, and Names of Buddhas at Northern
            Xiangtangshan</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Zhang Zong 2013a</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#zhangzong" type="personal">
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="family">Zhang</namePart>
        <namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="given">Zong</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">張</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">總</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>After an overview of research done on the southern cave at Northern Mount Xiangtang,
        Zhang Zong first describes where inside and outside this cave inscriptions are located. The
        "Sutra cave" 刻經洞 of Northern Mount Xiangtang is a classical stūpa cave 塔形窟: The main chamber
        主窟 (cave 2) has a porch 前廊 in front. It can be entered through a middle gate 拱門 that is
        flanked by two guardian figures 力士. The porch is formed by four pillars, which makes a porch
        three bays wide. On the pillars rests the roof 頂簷 of the porch, which is made of stone but
        imitates wooden architecture. On top is the stūpa dome 覆缽 embellished by palmette-shaped
        acroteria 山花蕉葉 and crowned by a chattra 塔刹 composed of a lotus from which three precious
        pearls (cintāmaṇi) 摩尼寶珠 sprout. Part of the inscriptions (including those on the pillars)
        might be later than Tang Yong's project. The protective stone wall in front of the cave was
        built under the Qing. Next to the central cave opening of the stūpa dome, a stele dated to
        1736 (qianlong 1) was erected that reports about its construction (發石券三間). Zhang Zong gives
        transcriptions, and, if possible, reconstructions of all the inscribed texts (see also
        Texte/Hebei/Xiangtangshan/Bei Xiangtang/BeiXiangtangShanPräsentation1.pptx), followed by an
        analysis of their doctrinal context. 
        On the reconstructed passage from the Nirvana Sutra
        (T.374, 12: 411b28-411c1) carved on the pillar south of the cave entrance he notes that the
        exact wording is different from the transmitted canonical version. It is a slightly altered
        text that nevertheless reflects the essence of the original source. (p. 83) The same kind of
        phenomenon can also be observed at Mount Honggu, where in front of the Verses in Praise of
        the Buddha 讚佛偈 taken from the Virtuous Conduct Chapter 德行品 of the <hi rend="italic">Sutra of
            Immeasurable Meaning</hi> (T.276, 9: 384c29–385b21), an extra line was carved that
        contextualizes the verses (Verses spoken in one voice by 80,000 bodhisattva-mahāsattvas in
        praise of the Dharma body of the Great Being ( mahā-puruṣa) 大莊嚴菩薩摩訶薩八萬法身大士等同聲偈讚). The
        characters “佛言” carved at Mount Jian in front of JS 12 serve the same purpose. Another
        example is found at Mount Sili: 過去諸佛、未來諸佛、今世十方諸佛亦因是咒，得阿耨多羅三藐三菩提 (Sili 3; Shandong 1, p.
        421-425). At Xiaonanhai, the "Buddhāvataṃsaka Verse" 華嚴經 is created on the basis of T.278,
        9: 441b24-c14: 盧捨那佛惠無尋，此佛曾來此室，是故此地最吉祥 (CW: MR does simply not quote the verse as inscribed on
        the wall. And Zhang Zong is wrong here. The verses can be traced to T. 278, 9: 441b26–27; 441c13–14; 434c22–23; 434c27–28, with a switch from Kanakamuni Buddha to Vairocana Buddha!).
        The reconstructed passage from the Nirvana Sutra (T.374, 12: 411b28-411c1) carved
        on the pillar south of the cave entrance epitomizes the core content of this sutra,
        "一切衆生悉有佛性." This statement also forms the basis for the upcoming Pure Land movement. (p. 84)
        The calligraphy reveals that the date of August 2, 803 (真元十八七月一日) on the same pillar was
        added later. 
        
        (p. 85) The appearance of the name of Amitābha Buddha on the south pillar among
        the names of the 25 Buddhas (T.440, 15:159c15–161c7) might be connected to the carving of the Verses on the Vow for Rebirth 願生偈 from the commentary (upadeśa 優波提舍) on the Sukhāvatīvyūha 无量壽經 ascribed to bodhisattva Vasubandhu 婆藪槃豆菩薩 on the southern outside wall of the porch. And the appearance of this name is also an indicator that the group of 25 Buddha names has no connections to the Three Levels movement. 
        
        
        The Buddha name 南无帝寳幢摩尼勝光如來 (also T.440, 14: 120b5 南無諦寶幢摩尼勝光佛; T.441, 14: 200c4-5) on the west side of the south pillar is taken from 《佛說千佛因緣經》T.426, 14: 70c21-24：「第二比丘久已成佛，號帝寶幢摩尼勝光如來，十號具足；若有四眾聞彼佛名，五體投地，歸依頂禮，即得超越七百萬億阿僧祇劫生死之罪。」 The "quote" equivalent to T.426, 14: 70c17–21 following the Buddha name is a re-wording and abbreviation of the original sutra text. Yet instead of venerating the Buddha by prostration, the carved text recommends "whole-heartedly invoking the name 至心稱名" of this Buddha, which also reflects Pure Land impact. However, this result is achieved not be invoking Amitabha, but by invoking the 25 Buddha names for repentance. The same name appears on the Mujing Si Stele dated to 571, titled : Guanyin Sutra Stele of the Seven-Tier Stone Stupa  七級石浮圖觀音經碑. Mujing Si and its donors may possibly be connected to the pillar texts at the southern cave. Therefore, this stele might offer a possible date for the pillar texts. Mujing Si may also have had some impact. After all, it is known that Emperor Wenxuan died at Mujing Si after illness (p. 86)
        pp. 87-88: On the verse on the west side of the same pillar: T.353, 12: 217a24–25: a verse spoken by Queen Śrīmālā just before the Buddha manifests in front of her (see T.874, 17: 960b6, "發十大受願讚歎如來，如來則現"). As already noted by LiYuqun1997, 475, note 20, this verse also appears in 七階佛名經 (a Tang manuscript) as part of Sanjiejiao repentance rites. But it originates in the Śrīmālā Sutra (T.353), where it forms a couple together with the next verse: 《勝鬘師子吼一乘大方便方廣經》〈1 如來真實義功德章〉：「如來妙色身，　　世間無與等；
        　無比不思議，　　是故今敬禮。　如來色無盡，　　智慧亦復然；一切法常住，　　是故我歸依。」(CBETA 2025.R1, T12, no. 353, p. 217a24-27). It is a metaphor for the advent of the Buddha, which was later used in a wide liturgical context, also in 集諸經禮懺儀 (T.1982). It is particularly connected to the act of  "praising the Buddha" (tan Fo 嘆佛). In Dazhusheng Ku, a 嘆三寶偈言 is carved (title for a longer passage, starting with 如來定慧無邊際， 神通廣大妙難思。相好光明超世網。。。), praising the Buddha, Dharma, and Sangha.
        In sum, the verse T.353, 12: 217a24–25 does not necessarily denote a Sanjie context, as it is much earlier. There are only two early manuscripts of the 七階禮: B8318 is dated to 675 (上元二年), and B8326 is dated to 667 (乾封二年), yet both of them are lacking the beginning and the end of the text, and do thus not preserve this verse. Rather than the Southern Cave pillars, the repentance text at Dazhusheng Ku might count as prototype for the 七階禮, although this text lacks the 25 Buddha names (but these are carved nearby...). 
        p. 89: Zhang characterizes the overall  program of the texts once carved on the four pillars as a "repentance text of seven roster of Buddha names" 七階佛名禮懺文 that is different from, and earlier than the eponymous Sanjie text.
        p. 89: The 3 names carved next to cave 1 (弥勒佛, 師子佛, 明炎佛) are Buddhas 5-7 in the Sutra of the Names of the Thousand Buddhas of the Present Worthy Eon 現在賢劫千佛名經, (T.447, 14: 376a23–24). They follow after Sakyamuni in the present eon. Sakyamuni is the fourth Buddha of this eon.
        The prājñāpāramitā spell 般若咒讚 (般若波儸蜜是大明呪，无上明呪，无等等明呪) flourished only after Xuanzang's (alleged) translation of the Heart Sutra (T.251, 8: 848c17-18: 般若波羅蜜多是
        大神咒、是大明咒、是無上咒、是無等等咒). This spell is also carved at Mount Sili. It was taken from one of Kumarajiva's Prājñāpāramitā Sutra translations (at Mount Sili the short version). A different formulation is known from the 《高王觀世音經》at T.2898, 85: 1425b9-12: 南無摩訶般若波羅蜜。是大神呪。南無摩訶般若波羅蜜。是大明呪。南無摩訶般若波羅蜜。是無上呪。南無摩訶般若波羅蜜。是無等等呪。It was carved on a stele dated to 559 (東魏武定八年)河南禹縣杜氏造像碑 (rubbing also in Chicago Field Museum) that was only discovered in 2005.
        Emperor Wucheng 北齊武成 (r. 561-565) had a crush on the longer version of the Prājñāpāramitā Sutra: T.2110, 52: 508a7-8: 《辯正論》卷3〈2 十代奉佛篇(四-四)〉：「大寧元年創營寶
        塔。脫珍御服並入檀財。轉大品經月盈數遍。」Zhang Zong assumes a connection between the emperor's frenzy and the carving of the prājñāpāramitā spell 般若咒讚.
        p. 91: Zhang Zong analyses the addenda "歸命真覺藏識海" and "稽首常住大寳海" in a way similar to Kuramoto2016a. Zhang Zong suggests that these addenda might be traces of a Dilun repentance rite that is even earlier than the Pure Land repentance rites.
        The style of the carvings of 大空王佛，寳火佛，無垢佛 is very different from the other inscriptions. It is the style of the Shandong carvings. 寳火佛 (no. 7) and 無垢佛 (no. 11) both belong to the 35 Buddhas. Li Fei once suggested that the carvings of the 10 epithets, the 12 classes of scriptures and all Buddha names are from Seng'an Daoyi's hand. But the Dilun content of the addenda does not support this view.
        p.93-95: Zhang Zong mentions other stone texts of Buddha names (Yungang, Longmen, Dazhusheng Ku, Bahui Si, Leiyin Dong, Lingyan Si...) The earliest stele with Buddha names is the Songyang Si stele 嵩陽寺 dated 535 東魏太平二年 (see WangJingquan2009, 145-152). He indicated combinations of rosters (53 names + 35 names + 7 names etc) for each of these sites in his conclusions (p. 96)
        Verses: p. 97-98 discuss 無量義經讚佛偈 in the inner cave (102 x 7 characters), p. 98-99 discuss the 無量壽經論 Verses on the Vow for Rebirth 願生偈. 
        The text of the 讚佛偈 is supposedly close to another 讚佛偈 found at T.360, 12: 267 (80 x 4 characters). Zhang Zong names other occurrences of the 無量義經讚佛偈, in particular those carved on the two steles at Baoshan Lingquan Si (Huayan bahui bei 華嚴八會碑 and Lou Rui Stele). The verses on this stele represent the entire program of the Avatamsaka that was preached in seven places and nine assemblies. The 無量義經讚佛偈 verses on this stele are not complete (35 of the 102 lines are missing, unfinished?). There are two deviations from the canonical text.
        pp. 99-100: There have been at least three phases of construction: the inner cave 1; the porch with the Vimalakīrti-nirdeśa, which is the first part of Tang Yong's carvings, and everything post-Tang Yong. The corridors on which the Vimalakīrti-nirdeśa was carved are not symmetrical: the southern corridor measures 563 cm, and the northern 466 cm. The size of the walls of these corridors were carefully planned to house the entire Vimalakīrti-nirdeśa. The sequence of the four sutras is just as indicated in the Tang Yong stele text: Vimalakīrti-nirdeśa, Srimala-sutra, Sutra on Bo, and the Maitreyavyakarana. 
        p. 101: The protagonists of all of the four sutras carved are laypeople, that cannot be coincidence. The Sutra on Bo narrates that a pregnant woman once falsely accused the Buddha of being the father of her child. Thereupon the Buddha told the story of one of his former incarnations as minister Bo. After governing the country for 10 years, he was denounced by four other officials and the wife of the ruler and dismissed. After invention of the people, his case was re-examined and he was rehabilitated.
        p. 102: Tang Yong was dismissed from office in 570 (武平元年), but redeemed later. However, it is not known how long his supension lasted. The highest title he ever held, Prince of Jinchang 晉昌王, was bestowed upon him between wuping 3-5 (572-574). The Tang Yong stele calls him 晉昌郡開國公. Two years for the carving of the Vimalakīrti-nirdeśa (568-570), about two more for the other three sutras.
        p. 103: Zhang Zong basically agrees with Xie Zhenfa 2006 that the selection of the Bo jing was satirizing the court during the final years of the dynasty, when the circle around Lady Lu Lingxuan (who had entered the palace as a slave when her husband Luo Chao was executed for plotting rebellion) rose in power. [According to Dien, She was the wet nurse of Gao Wei (Houzhu; r. 565-577) and a friend of his mother, Empress Hu. She adopted a royal concubine, nee Mu, as a protegee and made her empress. From 572, Lady Lu and her son were in control of the court.] 
        Under the reigns of Wucheng (Gao Zhan, r. 561-565/569) and Gao Wei (Houzhu; r. 565-577), Tang Yong's position was even higher than under Emperor Wenxuan (Gao Yang, r. 550-559). 
        
        
        
        
    </abstract>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="Beixiangtangshiku_kjd_kgbg" type="host">
        <titleInfo lang="zh">
            <title>北響堂石窟刻經洞：南區1、2、3號窟考古報告</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>monographic</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>79</start>
                <end>114</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>