<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Zhou_Sun2024" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    
    <titleInfo lang="en">
        <title>Reconstructing a Pagoda-Temple of 5th-Century Dunhuang</title>
    </titleInfo>
   
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Zhou and Sun 2024</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#zhouzhenru" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">周</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">真如</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#sunyihua" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="zh" type="family">孫</namePart>
        <namePart lang="zh" type="given">毅華</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>This is a theoretical reconstruction of "the prototypical pagoda-temple" (fo ta miao 佛塔廟) mentioned in Jinshu, juan 97: Qiu1ci2. Kucha. 龜茲國　　龜茲國西去洛陽八千二百八十里，俗有城郭，其城三重，中有佛塔廟千所。人以田種畜牧爲業，男女皆翦發垂項。王宮壯麗，煥若神居。 
    Men and women both cut the hair that hangs down to the neck. 
    The digital reconstruction is based on a mural in Mogao Cave 257 of the Northern Wei period (386–534), one of the earliest Dunhuang murals that represents an architectural frame around the Buddha image. A hall (housing a Buddha image), flanked by two <hi rend="italic">que</hi> 闕 (muzi men 母子們) towers, is depicted frontally. The gable roof of this hall seems to have a miniature pagoda on top. Xiao Mo thought this to be an artistic imagination (as a heavy brick building would not be placed on top of a wooden hall). Sun Ruxian already suggested that this image shows an architectural hybrid of the Chinese hall, the <hi rend="italic">que</hi> gate-tower, and the dome-shaped stupa. Zhou Zhenru now created a digital 3D-model of this hybrid building, in which she suggests that the stupa stood behind the temple hall in a separate courtyard. The stupa dome thus towers above the gable roofed hall. The Buddha icon is supposedly located below the stupa dome, as the curtains above the icon indicate an interior ritual space surrounding the Buddha icon. There is supporting archaeological and literary evidence.  
        "As for the layout of a square-stupa centered quadrangle, the ancient pagoda temples
        in Xinjiang provide reliable archaeological evidence." (Rawak Temple in Niya; ancient city of Jiaohe in present-day Turfan)
        "Although the exterior dome of the central stupa is not preserved in archeological sites,
        textual resource provides insight. A Record of Buddhist Monasteries in Luoyang (Luoyang
        qielan ji 洛陽伽藍記) by Yang Xuanzhi (fl. 547), a memorial of Buddhist temples in
        the late Northern-Wei capital city Luoyang, narrates how a Khotan king built a pagoda temple:..."</abstract>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#" type="host">
        <titleInfo lang="en">
            <title>Newsletter of the International Institute of Asian Studies (IIAS)</title>
        </titleInfo>
       
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <detail type="volume">97</detail>
            <!--<detail type="no"></detail>-->
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>14</start>
                <end>15</end>
            </extent>
            <date>2024</date>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>