<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Zouxianjinshixuzhi" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd"><titleInfo transliteration="pinyin"><title>Zouxian jinshi xuzhi</title></titleInfo><titleInfo lang="zh"><title>鄒縣金石續誌</title></titleInfo><titleInfo lang="en" type="translated"><title>Sequel to the Gazetteer of Zou County: Epigraphy</title></titleInfo><titleInfo lang="zh" type="abbreviated"><title>鄒縣</title></titleInfo><titleInfo type="reference" displayLabel="Zouxian jinshi xuzhi"><title>Zou­xian jin­shi xu­zhi</title></titleInfo><name xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#qiantai" type="personal"><namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="family">Qian</namePart><namePart transliteration="pinyin" type="given">Tai</namePart><namePart lang="zh" type="family">錢</namePart><namePart lang="zh" type="given">枱</namePart><namePart type="date">Qing dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm>author</roleTerm></role></name><abstract>Concerning Mount Tie, Qian Tai mentions two texts carved "on the rock neighboring the
        north side of Mount Tie northwest of the city". One is the sūtra text, which is according to
        Qian Tai written in clerical script and consists of 18 columns, with 68 characters each (in
        fact there are only 17 columns, with about 58 characters each). He then gives a brief
        description of the other text on the cliff (the Stone Hymn) without naming the title. He
        defines the calligraphy as clerical script, gives a short summary of its contents, and
        transcribes the poem at the end of the text. Furthermore, transcriptions of the colophons
        "to the east" and "to the south of the rock" are given.
        On Mount Yi: “At stone sutra cave 石經洞 at Mount Yi 繹山is carved: 文殊師利白佛言, one section in 7 column with 14 characters each, 
        which is the same as the inscription by Wei Zishen at Dafoling 大佛嶺. Just the same, there is a signature. At the end of the 
        line the 11 characters 囗囗太保家客邑主董弥陀 are written, also in lishu. Therefore, it should have been carved at the same time. 
        The denomination yizhu 邑主 is the same as that found on stelae from the Sui dynasty. Even though it is undated, it can be 
        assigned to someone from after the Northern Wei dynasty.”
        On Mount Gang: In his Sequel to the Gazette of Epigraphy in Zou County (Zouxian jinshi xuzhi 鄒縣金石續誌) of 1893, Qian Tai 錢枱 records 
        four sections of the Lankāvatara sutra version B, and mistakenly claims that date and signatures are lacking on the mountain as a whole.(LL)
    </abstract><physicalDescription><extent><detail type="fascicle">1</detail></extent></physicalDescription><originInfo><dateOther>Completed 1892</dateOther></originInfo><relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#SKSLXB" type="host"><titleInfo transliteration="pinyin"><title>Shike shiliao xinbian</title></titleInfo><titleInfo lang="zh"><title>石刻史料新編</title></titleInfo><originInfo><issuance>monographic</issuance></originInfo><typeOfResource collection="yes"/><part><detail level="1" type="series"><number>3</number></detail><detail level="2" type="volume"><number>26</number></detail><extent unit="page"><start>131</start><end>141</end></extent></part></relatedItem></mods>