<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Zuercher1982b" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo lang="en">
        <title>Perspectives in the Study of Chinese Buddhism</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Zürcher 1982b</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#zuercher" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="en" type="family">Zürcher</namePart>
        <namePart lang="en" type="given">Erik</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>p. 164: "...Chinese Buddhism in its totality: a tiny clerical establishment is working
        at imperial order in a handful of top-level official monasteries; they are charged with the
        production of texts, obviously as a magical protection for state and dynasty; the production
        of those texts is to some extent regulated; their inclusion into the Canon (apparently an
        imperial prerogative) certainly is. The texts are subjected to clerical censorship under
        imperial supervision... All this takes place in an extremely narrow circle, both socially
        and geographically." p. 165: "...our picture of Chinese Buddhism as a historical phenomenon
        is not merely unbalanced, it is distorted beyond all proportions...." It was carried on by a
        very small, highly literate élite within the clergy; their theories and teachings
        represented Buddhism at its highest level of sophistication; they were closely linked up
        with the worldly establishment, notably the imperial court." p. 167: "In A.D. 510 there was
        an ascetic monk in Yingchou 郢州 (present-day Wuhan), named Miao-kuang 妙光, .... He preached an
        apocryphal text, no doubt pretending to have "received" it, entitled "The Sūtra of the
        Adornment of Sarvajñata and his Family" sa-p’o-jo-t’o chüan-shu yen-ching 薩婆若陀眷屬嚴經, and he
        soon was surrounded by a large crowd of devotees. The text itself apparently also functioned
        as a sacred object: written on a screen and covered with red silk gauze, it was venerated
        with offerings of incense and flowers." (T#2145, 55:40b24-c12) p. 169: "The translation of
        scriptures--one of the central elements in the Great Tradition--is of course a highly
        meritorious work that benefits all those who take part in it, as well as its sponsors, but
        it is described in rather down-to-earth terms. Chinese versions are "produced" (ch’u 出);
        they are in no way supernaturally revealed, or found in mountain caves." p. 172:
        "...hagiography is not just fantasy...It is the hyperbolic expression of existing ideals and
        attitudes."</abstract>
    <relatedItem xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#JournalRoyalAsiaticSociety" type="host">
        <titleInfo xml:lang="en">
            <title>Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society of Great Britain and Ireland</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <titleInfo lang="zh">
            <title/>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <detail type="no">
                <number>1</number>
            </detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>161</start>
                <end>176</end>
            </extent>
            <date>1982</date>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>