<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Radich2012" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo lang="en">
        <title>Immortal Buddhas and Their Indestructible Embodiments. The Advent of the Concept of <hi rend="italic">Vajrakāya</hi>
        </title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Radich 2012</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#radich" type="personal">
        <namePart type="family">Radich</namePart>
        <namePart type="given">Michael</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>Radich studies doctrines that "eventually propose that the Buddha is completely immortal, and that his immortality is reflected in
        his embodiment in an utterly indestructible substance (Skt. vajra, Ch. jin’gang 金剛, “adamant”)."
        Pāli canonical antecedents indicate that the Buddha has the power to life an extraordinary long life and that he has voluntary control over his earthly lifespan. He also has the power to decide at will when he will die.
        Early Mahāyāna texts develop the ideas of a Buddha’s immortality in three phases. First, extreme longevity, but only for cosmically remote Buddhas; second, around the time of Dharmarakṣa, Buddhas in general are exempt from parinirvāṇa; and third, with Dharmarakṣa’s translation of the Lotus, the
        idea of the actual immortality of Śākyamuni appears and becomes common.
        Nattier points at a passage in the earliest versions of the the Larger Sukhāvatīvyūha (T.362 by Lokakṣema, and its revisison, T.361 by Zhi Qian) which says that the chain of Buddhas will stop with Avalokiteśvara’s successor, Mahāsthāmaprāpta, who will not enter parinirvāṇa, but will endure forever.
        Moreover, T.362 and T.361 present the length of the lifespan of Amitābha in a way that it becomes difficult to distinguish from complete immortality. Certainly, by Dharmarakṣa’s time (the middle of the third century), the idea is current that a Buddha, or Buddhas in general, do not in fact enter parinirvāṇa.
        The first apparent ascription of immortality to Śākyamuni in Dharmarakṣa’s Lotus (T.263; ca. 286), in the "Lifespan" chapter. "... it seems clear that Śākyamuni himself is in fact immortal, and his apparent parinirvāṇa is a docetistic show."
        Quotation T.263, 9: 113c20-23: [In reality] it is an immensely long time since I attained buddhahood and realised saṃyaksaṃbodhi; [my] lifespan is immeasurable; [I = the Tathāgata (Skt.)] endure forever, and do not become extinct (壽命無量常住不滅度; aparimitāyuṣpramāṇas tathāgataḥ sadā sthitaḥ; aparinirvṛtas tathāgataḥ).
        An explosion of new ideas about immortality in the Chinese record around 400 C.E.:
        Various dedicated chapters on longevity in Mahāyāna scriptures: 
        Chapter four "On Long Life" of the (Mahāyāna) Mahāparinirvāṇa-mahāsūtra (MPNMS)
        Chapter 2, “The Measure of Life of the Tathāgata,” of the Sūtra of Golden Light (Suvarṇabhāsottama-sūtra, first translated into Chinese by *Dharmakṣema 曇無讖 [385–433]; T.663)
        The Śūraṃgamasamādhi-sūtra T.642 (translated into Chinese by Kumārajīva [344–ca. 413, active as translator 401–ca. 413]) also features a short section
        on extreme longevity.
        These examples show that around 400 C.E., the idea that Śākyamuni is potentially, virtually or actually immortal is now common.
        
        The body like adamant 如金剛, 若金剛, 猶金剛 etc.): Already attested in “Inscription of Senavarma” (first half of the first century C.E.), which characterises relics as “final body” (*āntimaśarīra) and a “mass of vajra” (*vajrasaṃghaṇa). Also attested in Lokakṣema, Zhi Qian, and Dharmarakṣa. However, the body like adamant in these texts is associated with qualities other than permanence and immortality, namely, purity, freedom from sickness, and strength.
        
        The advent of vajrakāya (jin’gangshen 金剛身 = *vajrakāya) in the Chinese record ca. 400 C.E.
        Chapter five of the MPNMS: “On the Adamant Body” 金剛身品, which is dedicated entirely to the “adamant body,” and which Shimoda Masahiro identifies as “the core chapter” of the entire proto-MPNMS. 
        T.375, 12: 623b5-8: Kāśyapa professes that he will “henceforth regard the Tathāgata’s body as the eternal dharmakāya, the body of peace and bliss (安樂之身) … Yes, indeed, the Tathāgata’s Dharma-Body is adamant and indestructible.”
        
       p. 264: One of the claims the MPNMS makes about its own virtues as a text is that the “ground” and the people wherever the MPNMS is disseminated are adamant
        or like adamant (T#375, 12: 638c25-27). 
        
        Elsewhere the sūtra says of itself that it is like a vajra treasure, perfect and without blemish (T#375, 12: 624c26-28).
        MPNMS thus identifies the absolute immortality of the universal Buddha with a particular understanding of his embodiments. The apparently earthly
        body, about to die in the mise-en-scène of the text, is merely a docetistic show; the Buddha’s true embodiment is the dharmakāya; and this dharmakāya is an “adamant body” (*vajrakāya) and utterly indestructible. 
        A complex of very similar ideas is also found in the Mahāmegha-sūtra T387, also translated by *Dharmakṣema – unsurprisingly, given the extremely
        close links between the Mahāmegha and MPNMS. In one passage, the Buddha is asked how aspirants can attain the “adamant dharma body” (金剛法身 *vajradharmakāya);
        In the Golden Light Sūtra (like MPNMS and the Mahāmegha, translated by *Dharmakṣema), the doctrine of the Buddha’s infinite lifespan is linked to a denial of the reality of relics (dhātu), which are shown to be a mere expedient.
    </abstract>
    <relatedItem xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#JIABS" type="host">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>Journal of the International Association of Buddhist Studies</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <date>2012</date>
            <detail type="volume">34,2011</detail>
            <detail type="no">1–2</detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>227</start>
                <end>290</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>