<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Radich2019" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo lang="en">
        <title>Reading the Writing on the Wall: ‘Sengchou’s’ Cave at Xiaonanhai, Early Chinese
            Buddhist Meditation, and Unique Portions of *Dharmakṣema’s <hi rend="italic">Mahāparinirvāṇamahāsūtra</hi>
        </title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Radich 2020</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#radich" type="personal">
        <namePart type="family">Radich</namePart>
        <namePart type="given">Michael</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>p. 518: In this study, I aim to achieve a more adequate reading of elements drawn from MPNMS in the programme of Sengchou’s cave, as a case
        study in what I regard as a more adequate method for the treatment not just of this cave, but of such questions in general. Because my aim is thus
        methodological, I will take pains at relevant points to contrast my method and the resulting interpretations with those in the prior scholarship characterised
        above. The principal elements of the method I propose, against that of earlier analyses, are simple. First, I treat direct citations from
        MPNMS as allusions to the larger contexts in which those citations are embedded, and I therefore read closely the more extended narratives or
        passages constituting those contexts. Second, I then examine these multiple contexts for resonances in theme and content, and the ways that they
        might work in concert to create larger patterns of meaning. In the service of this model methodological exercise, I will largely restrict myself only to references to MPNMS in Sengchou’s cave, even
        though the cave includes elements from a number of other texts.11 This study therefore makes no pretence of proposing a full re-reading of the
        cave as a whole.
        p. 531: As the above summary shows, despite the fact that it calls itself “the four bases of mindfulness,” and was known as such to posterity,
        the meditative curriculum laid out in this MPNMS passage is anything but a representative instance of the practice usually known by that name.
        Rather, it is highly idiosyncratic (spezifisch, eigenartig), for a number of reasons.
        p. 535: Despite its name, it only features one of four constituents of the classic “four bases” meditations – the meditation on
        the body (kāyagatānusmṛti). ... Key concerns in the meditation as laid out in MPNMS are the impurity of the ordinary body, the motif of death, the impossibility of finding anything
        worthy of the label “self” (*ātman), visions of light and of Buddhas, and mental preparation to willingly undergo physical suffering in traversing the bodhisatva path.
    
    Verses accompanying two jātaka reliefs from MPNMS (T374 (XII) 450a16 and 451a1.) and Da zhidu lun (T.1509.25: 87c11-12). 
    p. 538: All conditioned things 行 are impermanent; Of their nature, [they] come into existence and go out of existence [become extinct] 滅;
    They come into existence and go out of existence, and when they have gone out of existence, The calm of [their] extinction 滅 is bliss.
    諸行無常/是生滅法/66生滅滅已/寂滅為樂.
    p. 539: In both T7 and the Saṃyuktāgama, the verse functions as an epitome of the Dharma, recited  at the very brink of the Buddha’s passing into final extinction (in T7, by
    the Buddha himself; in the Saṃyuktāgama, by Śakra – precisely as in the present MPNMS episode).
    p. 540: In particular, the MPNMS version is unique in giving a verse specifically from the Buddha’s deathbed (the parinirvāṇa scenario) as the epitome of the Dharma that is worth dying
    for. In the MPNMS retelling, then, the message of the jātaka is that a devoted bodhisatva was, is, or should be prepared to sacrifice his life for
    the tiniest sliver of the Dharma – but the Dharma in a specific inflection.
    p. 549: I contend that it is significant, therefore, that the references to MPNMS in the programme of Sengchou’s cave fall, in Dharmakṣema’s text,
    respectively: in Fascicle 10 (second verse in dedicatory inscription, Element  4); Fascicle 12 (Sengchou’s “four bases of mindfulness” meditation,
    Element 1); Fascicle 14 (jātaka on “giving up the body for a single verse of the Dharma” – and partner jātaka from MPPU – Element 2);
    Fascicle 20 (verses from Ajātaśatru’s redemption); and Fascicle 22 (second verse in dedicatory inscription).103 In other words, these references
    bracket the entirety of the discrete “Five Practices Section:” the two verses in the inscription occurring just before and after it, and the other
    citations evoking significant high points in its content and drama.
    p. 551: This example already captures more than one dimension of the way I believe the allusions in the Sengchou cave must have worked – principally,
    the way a single verse could suffice to evoke an entire scene or drama.
    p. 552: When a culture lives so intimately with a text like MPNMS, audiences can also be expected not only to recognise individual episodes or items
    of content; they also know the sequence of the content, and this knowledge is something else allusion can play on. In this light, I believe that
    the five loci from MPNMS cited at Sengchou’s cave, constituting as they do major high points in the dramatic arc of the “Five Practices Section,”
    would conjure up, to a mind steeped in the text, the “Five Practices Section” in its entirety, and epitomise it.</abstract>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#JIABS" type="host">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>Journal of the International Association of Buddhist Studies</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <date>2020</date>
            <detail type="volume">42, 2019</detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>515</start>
                <end>632</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>