<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Rhi2006" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo lang="en">
        <title>Fasting Buddhas, Lalitavistara, and Karuṇāpundarīka</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Rhi 2008</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <abstract>Rhi examines some textual parallels for fasting Buddha images from Gandhāra. He notices that in an early group
    of accounts of the Buddha’s life (T. 184, 3:469b-470a, T. 185, 3:476c-477a, T. 186, 3:511a-512a) there is no negative remark at all on austerities.
    This is most clearly in the Puyaojing (T. 186, translated by Dharmaraksa in 308), the earliest extant Chinese translation of the Lalitavistara.
    The Bodhisattva’s austerities are presented as if an expedient to deliver heretics who devote themselves to harsh or bizarre asceticism; and it is a great expedient.
    "... it appears that the account of the austerities in the Lalitavistara was transformed in later versions, or, much less likely, that Dharamraksa’s translation
    reflects an unorthodox regional tradition. In any case, what we have seen clearly suggests the presence of a separate tradition where the Bodhisattva’s austerities
    were never perceived in a negative spirit, which obviously parallels the glorified representations of the austerities from Gandhāra."
    In the Karuṇāpundarīka the positive spirit for the austerities continues in an even more prominent form. The austerities "are exalted as one of the major acts performed
    by the Buddha to deliver living beings and almost as the greatest of them." Karuṇāpundarīka: "... living beings achieve diverse benefits from seeing the austerities 
    of the Buddha." darśana: ritual viewing
    </abstract>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#rhi" type="personal">
        <namePart type="family">Rhi</namePart>
        <namePart type="given">Juhyung</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <relatedItem xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#JIABS" type="host">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>Journal of the International Association of Buddhist Studies</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>continuing</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <date>2008</date>
            <detail type="volume">29</detail>
            <detail type="no">1, 2006</detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>125</start>
                <end>153</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>