<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Robson2010" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd">
    <titleInfo lang="en">
        <title>Buddhist Sacred Geography</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <titleInfo type="reference">
        <title>Robson 2010</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#robson" type="personal">
        <namePart lang="en" type="family">Robson</namePart>
        <namePart lang="en" type="given">James</namePart>
        <role>
            <roleTerm>author</roleTerm>
        </role>
    </name>
    <abstract>Pre-Tang Chinese Buddhist sacred geography
        … the ways that monasteries, ordination platforms, and stupas became constituted as sacred sites…
        “sacred geography”: a domain spotted with places imbued with special natural or numinous features that could bring one into the presence of the Buddha, as well as aid one’s practice or assist in one’s salvation.
        “religious geography”: What places became centers of Buddhist practice? Where and when were religious institutions founded? How … can early Buddhist history be read from a geographical perspective?
        …a well organized Chinese Buddhist sacred geography did not exist in the Six Dynasties (222-589)…
        …Chinese Buddhists colonized China’s distant past by importing the presence of the Buddha (via his relics and other traces) to the early Chinese landscape.
        …how Buddhist monks began to transform the Chinese sacred landscape that they now claimed was dotted with Buddhist sites. Those transformations involved a number of strategies, including the transformation of sites already marked as sacred by other religious traditions or local cults. Therefore, given that Chinese Buddhists did not develop a uniquely indigenous form of sacred geography or establish sacred sites on uncharted terrain, the material under consideration here is organized into two main sections … The first, … refers to how sacred sites change places, moving from one place to another (India to China). The second involves the way a site might change religious affiliation over time.
        Previous scholarship … has tended to focus on … the ways that Buddhist doctrines were Sinicized.
        …the movement (or at least claims to the movement) of portable Buddha relics (including body parts: finger bones, hair, nails, teeth, and contact relics) to China. … the presence in the new locales of “traces” of former buddhas, which took on reality through the actual “discovery” of those sites.
        Relics and stupas: Stupas were the visible markers that mapped out Indian Buddhist sacred geography. Secondly, relics (and images) were portable..
        King Asoka (270-230 BC): …to spread Buddhist relics throughout Jambudvipa by erecting 84,000 stupas in a single day. Throughout the Buddhist world this story has been used to justify claims regarding the early transmission of Buddhism to their land and to link the newly discovered relics to Asoka’s relic distribution campaign.
        …stories about the discovery of “new” relics on or underneath the Chinese soil—what Hubert Durt has referred to as a form of “archaeologia sacra”—began to proliferate.
        Those sources chronicle the precipitous rise between the 4th and 6th centuries of lists of sites claiming the miraculous discovery of relics, stupas, and images connected with previous buddhas of the distant past or with King Asoka and his offspring.
        As Koichi Shinohara has noted, the Daoxuan lüshi gantong lu (T#2107) “consists of exchanges about a number of sites in China where ancient images and stupas are kept. In these exchanges, gods instruct Daoxuan on the cosmic histories of these sites, images and stupas in China”.
        The Renshou relic distribution campaign: …at precisely the same time—noon on the 15th day of the tenth month of 601, a date which corresponds with the Daoist festival day known as the “lower prime” (xiayuan 下元).
        Relics, … were imported and disseminated for politico-religious reasons at the same time that they signified a network of sacred sites…
        …impressions of the Buddha’s footprint or handprint.
        … the Fayuan zhulin and Guang hongming ji reveal that this tradition of finding Buddhist footprints continued and a number of new Buddhist footprints were discovered—through miraculous signs—during the early Tang dynasty.
        …the Foshou yan 佛手嚴 (Buddha hand cliff) on Lushan is recorded in the Record of Lushan (Lushan ji 廬山記), and a rubbing from a stele with a map of Huashan 華山also has an image of the Buddha’s handprint high on a cliff face.
        Obviously, not all Buddhst sites were connected with the interment of relics, but Chinese sources reveal a shift from an emphasis on the traces of the Buddha to an emphasis on the traces of eminent monks.
        Mountains in Buddhism and Buddhism in mountains.
        Was the Buddhist veneration of sacred mountains in China developed from (or modeled on) an Indian prototype of Buddhist sacred geography? … it is nonetheless safe to say that at the time Buddhism began to make its way into China there were no organized sets of Buddhist sacred mountains in India, where Buddhist sacred geography was primarily keyed to sites associated with the life story of the Buddha and the distribution of his relics. Buddhist mountain cults were not therefore part of the vast arsenal of concepts, doctrines, and beliefs that came along with Buddhism to China.
        …there were early claims that some Indian sites were in fact relocated to China. We find, for example, that a number of different numinous mountains in China—such as Mount Lu—were compared to Vulture Peak (Gādhrakūta) in India, the important site where the Buddha preached. Many other mountains in China were named Lingjiu shan 靈鷲山, the traditional transliteration of Gādhrakūta, or Vulture Peak.
        Suffice it to say that the intimate relationship between Buddhism and mountains—especially “sacred” mountains—is primarily a Chinese development, which quickly moved to Korea and Japan.
        In addition to converting various local mountain spirits, Chinese Buddhists also attempted to assimilate and convert a special category of mountain spirits, namely those of the five sacred peaks. Although these five peaks would come under Daoist control during the Tang dynasty due in large part to the successful lobbying efforts of Sima Chengzhen 司馬承禎 (647-735) at court, we know that Buddhists established themselves on those peaks quite early….
        Elsewhere I have demonstrated how the five peaks figured importantly in an imperial edict issued by Sui Wendi that stipulated “the construction of a Buddhist monastery at the foot of each of the five sacred peaks and other famous mountains in each province and manors (tianzhuang 田莊) also be established” in order to provide a means of support for the new institutions. The five sacred peaks are also found prominently at the head of the list of sites that received the Buddha relics as part of the Sui emperor’s Renshou relic distribution campaign, which also included the building of Buddhist monasteries that housed the eminent monks dispatched to serve as propagators of the Dharma.
        
        …the submission of the deity of Taishan, Guang hongming ji, T 2103, 52.215b27-c11.
        Another site with a storied Daoist history that later attracted Buddhist monks was Zhongnan shan…
        Buddhists were not just attracted to sites with rich Daoist histories, they also converted sites marked as especially sacred within Daoism.
        Recent research on the establishment of Wutai shan as a key node in Chinese Buddhist sacred geography has noted that pre-Buddhist sacred sites on the mountain were reinterpreted by the incoming Buddhists. The examples of changing sites at Wutai did not (as far as I am aware) involve the conversion of built structures into monasteries, but might best be described as the conversion of the mental and physical landscapes.
        …”in the last year of the Daye reign period (617) (of the Sui dynasty), an imperial edict was issued that decreed that nine Daoist palaces (gong) were to be transformed into Buddhist monasteries and monks were to be ordained.” (T 2060, 50.581c13.)
        Conclusions
        Although Chinese Buddhists employed a number of techniques to institute a sacred geography, such as the spreading of relics and stupas and the narrative re-contextualization of a number of sites to include the presence of past buddhas, we also find that the chroniclers did not shy away from celebrating the vestiges of a site’s accrued history.
        Buddhists did not (at least initially) propose an entirely new vision of sacred geography, but were primarily drawn to sites already marked as sacred: alighting at sites of local spirits, mountains listed in the Baopuzi, on the five sacred peaks, and at sites with Daoist histories. … the transformed sites … many remained under Buddhist control, while others reverted to Daoist control or were subsequently converted into neo-Confucian academies 書院.</abstract>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <relatedItem xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="host" ns2:href="#LagerweyLü2010">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>Early Chinese Religion. Pt. 2. The Period of Division (220-589 AD)</title>
        </titleInfo>
        <originInfo>
            <issuance>monographic</issuance>
        </originInfo>
        <part>
            <detail type="volume">
                <number>2</number>
            </detail>
            <extent unit="page">
                <start>1353</start>
                <end>1397</end>
            </extent>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
</mods>