<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="Robson2008" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3     http://data.stonesutras.org:8080/exist/servlet/db/schema/mods-3-0.xsd"><titleInfo lang="en"><title>Signs of Power: Talismanic Writings in Chinese Buddhism</title></titleInfo><titleInfo type="reference"><title>Robson 2008</title></titleInfo><name xmlns:oXygen2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" oXygen2:href="#robson" type="personal"><namePart lang="en" type="family">Robson</namePart><namePart lang="en" type="given">James</namePart><role><roleTerm>author</roleTerm></role></name><abstract>James Robson 2008:
        Signs of Power: Talismanic Writing in Chinese Buddhism
        
        131: “Indeed, there is a large corpus of Buddhist manuscripts in which, like the Greek magical papyri discussed by Jonathan Z. Smith, “the chief ritual activity...appears to be the act of writing itself....” 
        133: “Sinply put, talismans and texts that include talismanic script have heretofore remained all but invisible to scholars of Chinese Buddhism since they have traditionally understood them to be 
        of a Daoist provenance...”
        134: “The entry on amulets and talismans in J. Z. Smith’s Dictionary of Religion includes a subheading on talismans in Chinese religion that reflects more recent general knowledge. 
        The entry reads: “Amulets and talismans are used in Taoism and in folk practices primarily for healing and protection..... Talismans .... may also be worn on one’s person or mounted on a wall.”
        “It is not only modern Western scholars that have emphasized the exclusive Daoist use of talismans and depicted Buddhists as being categorically opposed to them. This same perspective is 
        found in standard Japanese-language Buddhist reference works.”
        135: “talismanic writing” (fushu 符書, Jpn. fushō)
        “Pioneering early French sinologists like Max Kaltenmark, Robert des Rotours, and others have detailed how the original meaning of the character for “tally” (fu符), referred to two halves of an 
        object,...that were
        136:split down in the middle and inscribed on the back. ”
        Anna Seidel emphasized that talismans were not invented by nor the sole prerogative of Daoists, but rather they emerged out of Han dynasty imperial treasure objects.”
        “As many scholars of Chinese scripts have noted, it was believed that the earliest forms of writing in China were not used to transcribe human speech but, rather, preceded it and were signs 
        that reflected the hidden powers of the universe and were used to “communicate with the spirits.”
        138:”Since written traces were at root “patterns” (wen 文) originating in nature they controlled what they represented through their potent spiritual power.” 
        “Talismans were sacred images that mirrored the forms of the primordial energies at the inception of the world and were therefore imbued with a spiritual power drawn from an ability to share 
        in the essence of the thing it names or represents.”  
        THE VISIBLE AND THE INVISIBLE: SEEING BUDDHIST TALISMANS
        140: “Zhiyi’s use of talismans and seals”: evidence in the Discourse on the Profound Meaning of the Lotus Sūtra (Fahua xuanyi 法華玄義) T.#1716, 33.804a5-7
        “The absence of studies and references to the Buddhist uses of talismans is connected to ... a perduring tendency to erect rigid partitions between Buddhism and Daoism, and the refusal to 
        recognize shared practices (particularly those that have been classified as being of a “magical,” and therefore denigrated, character) between those two traditions.”
        “...talismans...do appear with some frequency  ... in Buddhist texts that
        141: have been conventionally identified as esoteric or proto-Tantric.” 
        “There are a number of recent studies regarding the Buddhist cult of the book and the way that Buddhist texts functioned like talismans, rather than as mere repositories of doctrinal teachings 
        that were meant to be read.” 
        142: “...the use of seals was not only present in Daoist sources, but that they were also pervasive in Buddhist sources, and the same can be said of written talismans. We now have some foundational 
        studies on talismans found in Buddhist sources by Gao Guofan 高國藩, Xiao Dengfu 蕭鄧福, Jean-Pierre Drège, and Christine Mollier....”
        143:”In spite of the claims by some scholars that these talsimans are evidence of the existence of Tantric or proto-Tantric Buddhism in China,  ... the use of charms, spells, and talismans are found 
        within mainstream Buddhist texts and cannot be limited to any one lineage or tradition within Buddhism.”
        “The following sources offer one vantage point from which to view how ..... talismanic writing became a shared practice that is found within Buddhism and Daoism.”
        144: “the Dhāranī Sūtra of Ātavaka, General of Demons (Azhapoju guishen dajiang shangfo tuoluoni jing 阿吒婆句鬼神大將上佛陀羅尼經), dated to the first half of the sixth century” (T#1238, 21)
        146:”...this talisman ... is written in standard script that is all completely visible and may (if this text is true to its date) suggest that Buddhists initially wrote talismans in standard script before 
        adopting the esoteric talismanic script that is common in contemporary Daoist texts and ... Buddhist talsimans found in later sources.”
        Dhāranī Sūtra of Jāngulī, The Poison Woman, Spoken by the Buddha (Foshuo Changjuli dunu tuoluoni zhoujing 佛說常瞿利毒女陀羅尼咒經 (T#1265, 21)
        147: “Then follows another talisman that, like the Ātavaka talisman, is written in standard script. The talisman says: “Ritual seal of Jāngulī; Jāngulī cures the hundred envenomations! Kill and bind! 
        Enchant and bind! Apprehend, goddess! Svāhā!” The text notes that the talisman can either be written in vermilion on paper and carried on one’s person to repel all demonic pneumas (鬼氣guiqi), 
        or it can be written in vermilion ink on paper and swallowed to get rid of stomach ailments. These talismans contain a mixture of standard and talismanic script, could be used internally 
        as well as externally, and function like an official written order or command.”
        “The canonical Buddhist text that includes the richest account of talismans to be worn (pei佩) or ingested (fu服) is Nāgārjuna’s Treatise on the Five Sciences (Lungshu wuming lun 龍樹五明論), compiled perhaps as early as the sixth century”...
        149: “In this text, as in others, astrological knowledge is all important...”
        “In the Secret Magical Techniques of the Ten-Thousand Loves of Mañjuśrī and Yamāntaka (Manshushili yanmandejia wanai mishu ruyi fa 曼殊室利煙曼德迦萬愛祕術如意法)..., a text attributed to Yixing一行 (683-727), 
        the Chan monk who later became Śubhākarasimha’s disciple, there is also a set of two talismans that are labeled “earth talisman” and “heaven talisman.”
        150:”...the closest (in form) to pre-Daoist and Daoist talismans is the star talismans found in the Sūtra Spoken by the Buddha on prolonging Life by Worship of the Seven Stars of the Northern Dipper 
        (Foshuo beidou
        151: qixing yanming jing 佛說北斗七星延命經).” (T#1307)
        “Another short text in the Taishō canon that combines text and talismans is the Rules for the Diviner’s Board of the Holy Deity of Mirth (Sheng huanxitian shifa 聖歡喜天式法). (T#1275) 
        Robert Duquenne has shown that this curious text is an amalgamation of Chinese and Indian astral images. ... This text contains a wide variety of Indian and Chinese elements, 
        including Hindu deities, Sanskrit “seed syllables” (bīja), mudrās, talismans, and the familiar injunction “quickly, quickly, in accordance with 
        153: the statutes and ordinances.”
        “Finally, the richest text for visual representations of talismans in the Taishō canon  is the Scripture on the Rites of the Vajra-Being of Impure Traces [Ucchusma] for 
        Exorcising the Hundred [Demonic] Transformations (huiji jingang jin baibianhua fa jing 穢跡金剛禁百變化法經)”. (T#1229)
        154: “Edward Davis has noted that there was “no better example of Daoist influence on Tantric Buddhism” than in the texts of the early followers of Ucchusma’s cult.  
        While this may be true, we will see .... that ... establishing a clear direction of influence—from Daoism to Buddhism—is not as straightforward as one might expect.”
        BUDDHIST TALISMANS IN DUNHUANG MANUSCRIPTS
        155: “...there are at least fifty Dunhuang manuscripts that include Buddhist talismans or describe the production of talismans, but no longer include the images.”
        British Museum, Stein Painting #170  “is a particularly fascinating example of the mixing of text, talisman, and iconography”
        158: “This talisman emphasizes the dual attainment of supramundane goals (visions of Buddhas and removal of sins) along with more mundane attainments (magical powers and admiration of others):”
        “The Sūtra of the Seven Thousand Buddhas Spirit Talismans Spoken by the Buddha (Foshuo qiqian fo shenfu jing 佛說七千佛神符經, hereafter Seven Thousand Buddhas Spirit talismans) 
        (T#2904)... is a fragmentary text included in the Taishō Buddhist canon that is exclusively focused on the explication of a series of written talismans (fu) but is also found in varying 
        states of preservation among the Dunhuang manuscripts.” 
        161: “While it is not surprising to find the Northern Dipper invoked in this text, ... it is interesting that the next asterism that is invoked is known to us primarily from Daoist texts 
        as the Three Platforms (Santai 三臺). The Three Platforms refers to a collection of six stars (though our text mentions only five) that are all within the constellation Ursa Major.”
        163: „These written talismans all appear to be a mixture of “repeated script” (fuwen 復文) and composite graphs.”
        “... the Seven Thousand Buddhas Spirit Talismans was not simply a text composed in China but has an almost verbatim copy in the Daoist canon.”
        165: “There are three texts listed in the Catalogue of Scriptures Authorized by the Great Zhou (695) with names that are nearly identical to the Seven Thousand Buddhas Spirit Talismans.” BUT
        “...it appears that the extant Daoist version of this text may postdate the eleventh century...”
        166: “...it is still  noteworthy that while there are many surviving Dunhuang versions of the Buddhist Seven Thousand Buddhas Spirit Talismans, ...there are no early extant versions of the 
        Daoist The Marvelous Classic Spoken by the Great Lord Lao for Extending One’s Life.”
        “... there was in all likelihood a popular template in circulation that was altered and applied to both Buddhist and Daoist ends.”
        167: CONCLUSIONS
        “By the Tang (at the latest), talismans and talismanic script also began to appear in Chinese Buddhist texts, where they served to repel the noxious and impel the desired. Why, however, 
        did the compilers of the Chinese texts begin to incorporate talismans written in an esoteric Chinese script when Indian Siddham script, which was already quite popular in China due to its 
        perceived magical properties, could have been used to the same effect?”
        169: “Previously held views about a “pure” or rational Buddhism also lead to the occlusion (perhaps even systematic erasure) of Buddhist talismans in scholarly writing on Chinese Buddhism.”
        
        
        
    </abstract><relatedItem xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns2:href="#HistoryofReligions" type="host"><titleInfo><title>History of Religions</title></titleInfo><originInfo><issuance>continuing</issuance></originInfo><part><date>November 2008</date><detail type="volume">48</detail><detail type="no">2</detail><extent unit="page"><start>130</start><end>169</end></extent></part></relatedItem></mods>